<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_AS_45-96_Ts_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1696" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.1696</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>11-12</numero>
        <annee>2017</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="1688">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            Mises en désir de Tanger dans les guides touristiques imprimés : formes latentes et transgressives
        </original>
        <traduction lang="es" source="1704">La atracción de Tánger a través de las guías turísticas impresas: formas latentes y transgresivas</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Sanoussi" prenom="Anas">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_AS_45-98_Ms_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1688" lang="fr">Mises en désir de Tanger dans les guides touristiques imprimés : formes latentes et transgressives</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                PhD in geography, EIREST, Université Paris 1 Panthéon-Sorbonne 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Tangier and the cultivation of desire in the print travel guides: latent and transgressive forms</titre>
    <resume>
        This article examines the different ways in which the city of Tangier is presented as a site of erotic experiences in the three large collections of print travel guides (Guide Vert, Guide Bleu and Lonely Planet) published in France after Moroccan independence (1956-2010). Heteroeroticism, which was deemed appropriate in the West’s promotional discourse on destinations with a colonial culture, no longer responds to the demands of a hypermodern touristic public in search of a more reflexive and creative experience. The figure of the artist passing through Tangier emerges as a central aspect of the touristic discourse in the contemporary travel guides, serving as a viaticum to the reader. In particular, the Lonely Planet, whose discourse championed homoeroticism from its very earliest French editions, allows us to understand the modalities of the cultivation of desire in relation to certain components of the touristic imagination of Tangier. 
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourism isa domain of choicefor the circulation of the erotic imaginations of places and erotic desire since it incites people to see and be seen, it produces a fantasy activity within the context of an individual’s travel plans and it results in relations between the visitor and the visited. In its attempt to make a travel destination desirable, touristic discourse can resort tothe use of symbols that associate touristic motivation with commercial sex (Kinnaird and Hall, 1994; Beaulieu et al., 2003).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We define the eroticisation of aplace as a type of </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">cultivation of desire in relation to </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(and through) a touristic imagination that responds to sexual </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">desire. What therefore are the activators of anerotic desire that is specific to different places? Do they respond to the same dimorphisms (female/male) as human sexuality?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Exoticism, a notion that has been largely deconstructed in the field of tourism studies, describes a process that leads to the </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">cultivation of desire in relation to</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> far-off places and persons (Staszak, 2008). It is based on such elements as the de (re)contextualisation of the characteristics and foreignness of other places and populations and leads to the construction of a condescending and fascinated gaze on alterity. The links perpetuated between exoticism and eroticism in the wake of colonialism have connected race with gender and placed the body of the other at the disposal of ‘white’ male desire. We will endeavour to show that eroticism as the </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">cultivation of desire </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">is able todispense with exoticism. Eroticism does not seek to mediatise a relationship where the dominator and dominated are predefined on the basis of race, class or gender. Rather, its aim is primarily to create desire between two sexualised entities. However, some psychoanalytical studies (Stoller, 1984) agree that hostility (that is, the desire to humiliate, hurt, cause pain) is one of the main constituents of erotic arousal. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Crépault (2007) defined some laws of eroticism that can be easily transposed to touristic storytelling and discourses for an understanding of some of the processes implemented to activate erotic desire. Crépaultcited the need to simultaneously integrate new elements with scenario repetitions through rituals (for example, to reach the destination) as well asthe need for affective detachment through the presentation of the destination as an object of desire that has been discharged of its affective qualities, population and problems with a view to removing the tourist’s guilt and allowing them to experience the pleasure more easily. The most intense cultivations of desire </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">are those that are the most transgressive, those that play with danger or run the risk of ethical drift. The touristic imagination is presented as an ‘intermediate area of experience’</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> or ‘a symbolic third space’ (Amirou, 1995) in order to reduce the distance between the tourist and the place visited. In this context, the eroticisation of touristic locations should be integrated into this mediatisation, most notably through a compromise with exoticism. Howdoes the touristic imagination, through its capacity to go beyond the object represented, manage to dilute sometimes shameful </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and even unspeakable desires in other representations in order to maintain a destination’s appeal? </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To study the processes of and variability within the eroticisation of locations, we draw on the case of the city of Tangier and its touristic imagination such as it is expressed in contemporary print travel guides. Often compared to global Mediterranean cities like Naples and Alexandria (Dodi, 2010), which have fascinated and deeply moved writers and artists the world over, Tangier is the subject of a profusion of images resulting from these traveller accounts. Both during and after its international status, Tangier was indeed one of these sexual heterotopias (Berliner, 2010), where Western moralistic laws and customs were irrelevant and the repressed desires and practices of the Western coloniser were made welcome. Hence, the travelling artist figure has been a strong invariant in the touristic imagination of the city in post-independence print editions of the guides. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The first part of this article focuses on gaining an understanding of the origins of the erotic rhetorical devices used in the contemporary touristic discourse of three travel guides published in French (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guide Bleu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guide Vert</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">LonelyPlanet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">), dating from Tangier’s independence (1956) onwards. To grasp their ideological, aesthetic and political foundations, it was necessary to examine themfrom the perspective of the representations of Tangier contained in the fictional and poetic imaginations of the city. This intertextual approach consisted in comparing the touristic discourse with the narratives from the travel guides plus other forms of expression (artists’ practices through travel journals, artistic works) in order to take into account the transfer of values in operation between them. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The diachronic approach adopted here hasrevealed significant homoerotic content, which was mobilised exceptionally and ephemerally (up to 2010) to cultivate desire in relation to Tangier in the first editions of the</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> on Morocco, published at the beginning of the 1990s. This explicitly expressed homoeroticism was not mentioned in the contemporary tourist guides analysed in this study (up to 2010) despite the survival of some furtive, emblematic twentieth-century homosexual imagination references, symbolised mainly by the Beat Generation writers who passed through Tangier.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The second part of the article draws out the discursive processes that sexualised and homoeroticised Tangier in the first editions of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely </span></em><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in an attempt to reactivate the amenities ofthe homosexual destination dating from the end of its international status to the 1960s. While this destination’s life cycle was doomed to end at the same time as the colonial and literary project that had generated it, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">combined visibility/invisibility registers that were characteristic of an ‘antimonde’ space (Brunet, Ferraset Théry, 1992</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Despite local and official constraints (sociocultural and legislative), thistravel guide exploited the situation of decline and isolation that the city found itself in to highlight its clandestine and illegal practices (including homosexuality and prostitution) to interested readers. As such, we also need to understand the economicand political realities that were limiting or fostering the cultivation of desire in relation to Tangier and which were positioning their nature. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Two key phases can be identified in our corpus of the post-independence editions of the three travel guides, corresponding to the political and urban transformations that mark the touristic territory’s history. One is Tangier’s independence, which led to economic impoverishment and marginalisation. The second is the enthronement of King Mohammed VI, which marked a renewed interest in Tangier and its urban regeneration. We will review the part that Tangier’s development during the 2000s played in the disappearance of blatant homoeroticism from the discourse as it adapted to the changes in touristic demand for a more reflexive and creative experience.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">1 - The erotic gallery of images of the city in the discourses of the contemporary print travel guides</section>
        <section niveau="h2">Heteroeroticism and female sexualisation </section>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The touristic discourse in the print guides published post-independence (from 1960 onwards) is full of metaphors (white city, muse, object of desire, etc.) that personified Tangier as a sexual female. By repeating the city’s attributions, Tangier was assimilated to a muse and even to an object of desire, thus attracting artists at the end of the 19</span><sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">th</span></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> century. The perennial references (from the very first post-independance editions) to </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Eugene Delacroix’s</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> arrival in Tangier in 1832 (in a Maghreb that was still closed to the West) became the principal representation ofthe city’s traditional function to inspire. These references to Delacroix launched an ongoing ‘saga’ in the travel guides, recounting the story of the city that was the destination of great artists. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The female sexualisation of Tangier in the form of metaphors with erotic connotations thus borrowed from the poetic language of the famous artists that had passed through the city for more than two centuries. The images of the city that the artists produced were decontextualized as part of an exoticism that was specific to the touristic imagination of the promotional discourses. The aim was to attribute traits to the object of discovery that were limited to feminisation, sexualisation, passivity and westernisation (Baider et al., 2004)</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The allegories of ‘the white city’ (fig. 1) and ‘the pearl of the Strait’, for example, which feature heavily in the contemporary guides’ touristic discourses, are combined with representations relating to purity, virginity, sobriety and generosity in order to reference elements linked with possession and accessibility that are typical of the sexualisation of destinations (Pritchard and Morgan, 2000). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The cultivation of desire in relation to a place is based on reducing it to its alterity and making it available to the tourist by offering it up to their desire for appropriation. In this respect, the touristic discourse heteroeroticises the relationship with the destination suggested to the tourist on the basis of a feeling of conquest, appropriation and even consumption, thus likening the destinationto a person (often female) or an object. This erotic approach is magnified by the denunciatory idea that assimilates tourism to prostitution (first mentioned as a third-world rhetorical figure), which has been identified as a research avenue worth exploring within the contexts of its relationships with patriarchy and imperialism (Graburn, p. 83 cited by Staszack, 2015). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The heteroeroticism of Tangier has its distant roots in its geostrategic situation (fig. 2) and its ability to fuel the appetites of the various occupations it has undergone during its history. In the travel guides, a column entitled ‘object of desire’</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> acts as a reminder of the times the city </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">has been forced to make itself available to its occupiers. Today, however, with the colonisation period in the past, the feat of sublimating sexual desire into artistic creativity is reserved for certain travellers only, namely those who manage to follow in the wake of the artists’ experience. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Autoeroticism and nostalgia</section>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Paradoxically (depending on the postcolonial interpretation given to it), this heteroeroticism in the contemporary discourses (which manifested in the female personification of Tangier from the very first French editions of the travel guides and touristic brochures on the city) ended with the introduction of international status and territorial neutrality for Tangier in 1923. The element of possession (the city was shared between several Western powers) is conveyed in Prosper Ricard’s explicitly sexualised paraphrase in the 1930s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guides Bleus</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The city that belongs to everyone</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’. The almost ‘scientific’ presentation in the publications from 1930 to 1950 of a city that combined tradition and modernity is based on maps and a list of amenities inviting the tourist to visit the whole city, including those districts newly built by the colonisers. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Heteroeroticism, particularly that mobilised through the artists and their poetic imaginations, was not to re-emerge until the post-independence editions. The ‘golden age’ (e.g. </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guide Bleu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2007) described the pivotal period in the city’s history (during its international status) and structured the space and time represented in the discourse. In short, it conferred authenticity on the locations and guided touristic practices. This was a ‘golden age’ when only the idyllic aspects of a bygone time and space were revealed. It was a period of prosperity, artistic creativity, cosmopolitanism, tolerance, freedom and partying.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This temporally undefined past, which was punctuated with the artists that had passed through the city and marked by its international period, is referred to in a nostalgic tone, which grows with each edition. It manifests in a gradual increase in the number of references to artists and in the marking of locations (regardless of whether or not they had since closed or were no longer accessible) that were laden with the imagination of this past. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Within the heteroeroticism context, the nostalgia is presented as a form of exoticism that cultivates desire in relation to the city’s former colonisation civilisation. However, this nostalgia, above all, demonstrates a frustration stemming from the fact that the erotic promises littering the contemporary discourse (conveyed by the many references to the artists) were being confronted with the everyday routines of the ‘real’, in other words those of a fast-developing city.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The myth of Tangier, such as it was mobilised by the contemporary fantasy and touristic discourses, is made up of heterogenous forms of language (fictional, historical, biographical, etc.), which reveal the destination’s seductive powers and ways to access it as well as a variety of erotic preferences. The erotic experiences suggested to the reader are configured, first, through the values of attributions to the artists referenced by the guides (illustrated through a destination experienced and/or retranscribed by these artists) and, second, through the reader’s own personal sensibility and knowledge of the artists in question and their works. This process (which involved the tourist’s individual imagination through the use of poetic word borrowed from/associated with the famous artists to the detriment of any useful erudition) was common in the publishing world producing these travel guides in the 1990s (Rauch, 2007). It allowed the guides to either move beyond or renew exoticism and rebuild the concept of the cultural visit by offering alternatives to the monumental vision of the city.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">At the end of the 1990s, we see new references to American artists beginning to emerge in the discourse of the travel guides on Tangier. The artist who received the most attention was Paul Bowles</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, whose death in 1999 was marked by a text boxentitled ‘A chapter closes’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guide Vert</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Michelin, 1999). This space has been reserved ever since for short mentions of his life in Tangier, his role as a greeter to the literary city, his work, and his friendships and romantic relationships with the Moroccans, which led him to produce his artistic works. Bowles understandably became the symbolic resident of this ‘international Tangier’. He represented this other around which the cultivation of desire was constructed, the charismatic leader of the ‘authentic’ tourist experience. Although the imagined nostalgia was now fed into the tourism imagery for marketing purposes and while it contributed to perpetuating the colonialist and orientalist imaginations on developing countries (Echtner and Prasar, 2003), it pertains here to a de-exoticisation, since the other is a Western self (embodied by Bowles) who is valorised as the ideal to strive for. This approach involved deference rather than condescendence, revealing a hybrid (or cosmopolitan, according to the myth) identitythat went beyond the oppositions between the here and the elsewhere. Exoticism is almost emptied of all meaning here.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although they go beyond exoticism, the two eroticising processes presented above can also be easily applied to a destination with a colonial past. Heteroeroticism was readily expressed in the domination/submission relationships favoured by colonialism whereas autoeroticism is expressed in a relationship to self, where the other is integrated only after it has been appropriated. However, from the point of view of the colonial perspective adopted here, it should be noted that these eroticism approaches suggest a relationship that is too fusional for a discourse that is supposed to be addressed to the white Western male. Since this discourse is sanitised in advance, however, what other latent eroticisations does it conceal through its reference to the myth of Tangier and its artists? Are there other erotic stages capable of constructing a cultivation of desire within the framework of the touristic imagination?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">The artists’ antifusional relationships with places: transgressive eroticisations of Tangier</section>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The answer to these questions can be found in the genealogy of the images produced within the context of artistic creation to eroticise Tangier but which were not integrated as such into the touristic discourse. While the discourse in the contemporary travel guides gives the impression that the paradigmatic relationship (following in the footsteps of the artists) with the destination is quite fusional, or almost anerotic in the sexual sense of the word, the artists’ travel journals and their artistic output reveal that the fusional and antifusional</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> relationships with the place and its inhabitants were often correlated. As Staszak (2003) showed for Gauguin, the artists’ geographic displacement was also a bodily experience, implying a sexual adventure that could lead to artistic creation. Pouillon (2008) described Delacroix and Matisse in Tangier as ‘caricatures of tourists’ (and even, in Delacroix’s case, as a ‘sex tourist’), explaining that their visits were limited to looking at the postcard landscapes and attending official receptions with no attempt to understand the lives of the indigenous Muslims. Before Eros could have been completely sacrificed in sublimation for the benefit of the travelling artists’ creative output, he would first have been nurtured on the </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">relations of hostility and domination emanating from the precolonial tensions or from the hegemonic colonial context. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Other travel narratives</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (most notably that of Dumas</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) followed in the wake of Delacroix’s travel journal. They described the climate of hostility that prevailed during the artists’ stays and the inhospitality of a city that was so close to Europe (two hours from Gibraltar and Algeciras) and the gateway to a still mysterious Orient. The stereotype of a population made up of redoubtable or miserable Barbaric men</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and veiled, subjugated women and of a city and its beautiful, although difficult to access</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, countryside fed (along side the orientalist paintings) the seeds of a discourse that was to serve the colonial propaganda. However, the presence of foreign consuls guaranteed security, support and shelter for visitors.The Jewish community in Tangier allowed painters access to female models and gave them a behind-the-scenes look at Moroccan culture and traditions (fig.3) (Arama, 2006). This particular cultivation of desire can be described as allo-eroticisation (as opposed to the autoeroticism described above) because the gratification of desire came from an external, foreign object and because it had to be preserved as such despite the urge to reveal it. The hostility was intense, and it guaranteed that the external object was preserved intact. In his travel narrative entitled ‘In Morocco’, Loti, who arrived in Tangier in 1889, was clearly already suffering from the tourist’s paradox (Urbain, 1991) when </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">he reported a large tourist presence</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. On his departure, he expressed his desire to hide this world away, which he was sorry to see open up: ‘Oh shadowy Maghreb, remain walled in, impenetrable to anything new for a long time to come. Turn your back on Europe and stay immobilised in the things of the past’ (In Morocco, 1890, cited by Peltre, 2003, p. 91). The appropriation of a European memory of the city marked by the illustrious painters that had passed through it began to emerge with the erasure of the characteristic features of the Moorish city by twentieth-century cosmopolitanism. In the French travellers’ writings</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn13" id="bodyftn13">13</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the singularity of Tangier within Morocco lay in a pessimistic discourse that established that Tangier had lost its identity (Tatin-Gourier, Amahjour, 2008). Exoticism only regained its meaning in Tangier through the lens of nostalgia. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Later on, at the very start of Tangier’s international status, the accounts from tourists (fig.4) and journalists</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> passing through the city reveal a high level of prostitution involving Moorish, Jewish and Muslim women as well as boys from Tangier, often housed in brothels. Postcards from the Lévy &amp;amp; Neurdein Réunis collection (considered to be the most important iconographic source on the Maghreb), which were published in the period 1913-1932</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, used photographs of these prostitutes (fig. 4 and 5) to illustrate the oriental women. The postcards also mention an over-representation of children (fig. 6), which implies an extension of the age </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">range of the ‘young boys’ cited in the literature who had been integrated into the sex market at the time. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Up until at least the 1960s, Tangier was a sexual, and more specifically homosexual, tourism hotspot for nineteenth-century writers. With its international status, the city offered all the ingredients of a space in which writers could fuel their fantasies, create amoral, mystical, sexual or syntactic revolution (the most famous manifestation of which was the cutup technique that William Burroughs experimented with in his novel </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Naked Lunch</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) and find inspiration (for example, through drugs or diverse and forbidden sexual practices</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> or</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> byindulging in a hedonistic </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">lifestyle</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn17" id="bodyftn17">17</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and meeting eccentric figures). American literature, with Bowles, Gyson, </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Williams, Vidal, Capote, Sontag and Burroughs at its helm, was part of a collective movement that led to the emergence of the Beat Generation.</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This was a counter culture </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">that flaunted its rejection of conventional, puritanical America. It became crystallised through a new form of travel that was part of a rite of avoidance </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Amirou, 1995) in relation to the sites and cultures visited. Influential artistic works and biographical literature</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> attest to the homoerotic and autoerotic potential of Tangier and to the ‘situational disinhibition’ </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Eiser and Ford, 1995) produced there, whichpermitted sexual practices and excesses that were forbidden elsewhere, including the practicenow classed as paedophilia (Caraës, Fernandez, 2003). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Homoeroticism contributed to providing the ‘heterotopic’ qualities of both the location and the literature produced there </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Albert and Kober, 2013), that is, of the geographic and literary ‘other’ spaces, where gazes distanced from the world were shaped by a hegemonic setting in which transgressive practices and desires could be confessed (gambling, prostitution, freedom, homosexuality). This heterotopia was the expression of a utopia that had been created by the city’s residents and the travellers who, fleeing the world, found themselves in Tangier sharing hedonistic values and a search for freedom and looking to unburden themselves of the norms established by society. Autoeroticism provided this heterotopia with a poetic licence to combine the qualities of a utopia of escape and individual satisfaction with those of a revolutionary utopia. </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Hence, Tangier became a ‘sanctuary in which everyone is sheltered from all interference’</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn19" id="bodyftn19">19</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We can deduce from this that the discourse in the contemporary print travel guides was sanitised of certain transgressive eroticisations because they were linked to embarrassing aspects of and taboos in the Tangier memory.The Burroughs example, however, is a reference that, although discreet in the most recent editions, represents a way of travelling. It carries latent values that the shrewd reader can decipher to feed his or her imagination. The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which uses Burroughs as its main reference up until 2005 by establishing a parallel between its description of Tangier during this period (1995-2005) and Burroughs’fictional city of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Interzone</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> to help pave the way for a gay destination, seems to be an interesting case study for drawing out the elements of the cultivation of desire </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">presented by homoeroticism and the key features of the touristic experience that it involves. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">2 - The latent and transgressive meaning of homoeroticism in the cultivation of desire in relation to Tangier through the cycle of a gay destination in the discourse of the Lonely Planet travel guides (1995-2005)</section>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Adopting a different and more assertive approach than the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guides Bleus</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guides Verts</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the first editions of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1995 proposed a touristic discourse that suggested an off-the-beaten-track adventure, an extreme experience even, which was enhanced by the danger that lay in wait for the tourist. This element of danger, which came from the other (that is, the indigenous population), had a strong presence and took an active stance in the discourse. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Homoeroticism incorporates a high level of hostility (especially when it comes from the other), which leads to the hypersexualisation of a location. This process responds to the need, as a homosexual reader, to position oneself as an object of desire. From our postcolonial point of </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">view, this type of discourse opens the door to the enclave of masochism and gives this touristic gaze that always presents itself as ‘male’a ‘female’ sexuality. This is one reason why we describe homoeroticism as transgressive.The other is that homosexual practices had to remain hidden and secret</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn20" id="bodyftn20">20</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in keeping with Morocco’s Arab-Muslim culture and because Tangier was under the Makhzen and its legislation.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The social invisibility of homosexuality manifested in an ephemeral and diffuse touristic geography of homoeroticism in Tangier. Nevertheless, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, despite a prohibitive local context and at the risk of threatening its very existence, had to deploy visibility strategies for the reader in order to mark, or identify, the meeting places and forbidden homosexual prostitution practices promised in the discourse. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Faced with having to establish this double transgression, both at the local sociocultural level and in relation to Western referents, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’s touristic discourse had to fulfil an image production function through discursive and figurative descriptions. Hence the guide reconstructed the city space as an ‘antimonde’. Like the heterotopia of international status, the reconstruction of this type of space had to enter into the spatial strategies implemented to resist dominant powers, which also ensured regulation and social reproduction.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A gay destination revived</section>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">After independence, Tangier, which was still cut off from the main national trade routes, suffered the loss of its internationally oriented trade functions. The city was marginalised following strained political relations with the central power under Hassan II. Tangier’s isolation in relation to the rest of Morocco and its openness to foreign markets promoted an illegal economy, which grew significantly in the principal cities of the Tangier Peninsula. The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> highlighted these clandestine activities, which included smuggling and a cannabis economy: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thriving drug trafficking industry (which has seen the involvement of an increasing number of South American drug barons dealing in cocaine), also a rise in people trafficking, many coming from sub-Saharan Africa</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn21" id="bodyftn21">21</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1995). In the very first French </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">edition of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1995), this transgressive and politically subversive economic situation in Tangier was exoticised within the context of a political exceptionality that Tangier ultimately always benefited from: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tangier is a unique city, not really Moroccan and not really from elsewhere. A city like nowhere else in the world</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’. The qualities of Tangier, which was perceived as a sanctuary (Boone, 1995), were brought in line with contemporary public taste in the ‘History’ column presented by the guide: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The legend of international celebrity continues. A haven for refugees, exiles, bankers and artists and a hotspot for homosexuals and paedophiles</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, pp. 95, 98). During Tangier’s international status, prohibitions had been flouted without incurring any excessive social or penal sanctions, and this tolerance with regard to non-compliance with the rules or the commonly accepted morality in Morocco continued in this unsupervised, cut-off, post-independent city. It was a space that had been abandoned to market forces, where the order of values had been disrupted, as modelled in the behaviours and practices of the city’s residents: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Money is the lifeblood of the city. From the shoeshiners to the rich and powerful, everyone is chasing it</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Introduction, 1995). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The presentation of distance from the moralistic world and the recourse to homosexual spatialities has but one aim, which is to localise a ‘sexscape’ </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Brennman, 2004), where the colonial stereotypes (which the sex tourist needs to manage their experience) are ultimately reactivated. Unlike the dissenting power of the twentieth-century literary heterotopia, Tangier as an ‘antimonde’ becomes both a black hole of the black economy and a sexual outlet for a leisure society in which relations of cultural hegemony are perpetuated. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Stereotypes linked to the indigenous population and places are highlighted through the use of metonymy from the very first French edition of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. In the Introduction, Tangier is replaced by the ‘interzone’. This hyper-homo-sexualised city allows the discourse to reproduce similar situations and then to indicate the sites specific to homoerotic practices. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Petit Socco, a small square that is still as effervescent as it was during the ‘international Tangier’ era, is identified in the guide’s discourse as a location that is emblematic of young Moroccan male prostitution. Attributing a touristic practice proposed by the guide’s discourse (which is to sit at a table in the central café in the Petit Socco) to the practices of Burrough’scharacter introduces a soliciting scene prompted by a young indigenous male. Through its reference to the novel, the discourse absolves itself (as does the tourist) of any responsibility regarding the suggestion. The sex tourist is even invited to pursue the encounter right through to the deed since Le Fuentes, which </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">‘at the end of the 19</span></em><sup><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">th</span></em></sup><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> century, (…) was one of Tangier’s luxury hotelshas [now] become a brothel</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Lonely Planet, </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">1995</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These pensions, where the bedrooms are ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">like homeless shelters</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ and‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">as cramped as prison cells</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet, 1995</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">), are the most frequently mentioned places on the guide’s touristic map of the medina. The pension tourist is then invited to visit the hammams, which are ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">quite handy given the rarity of hot water in many of the pensions</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1995). This is yet another homosociability space par excellence promoting intimacy between the tourists and the indigenous population.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Generally speaking, the indigenous population referred to in the discourse comprises constantly active men and young boys who are trying to establish a commercial relationship andare playing with ‘numbers’</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn22" id="bodyftn22">22</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tangier harbours the cleverest swindlers and pickpockets in the country (…) you will be welcomed by a cohort of polyglot friends and guides. Expect to hear the most folkloric of stories</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1995). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">The eulogy of the city’s disorder and decline: the latent meaning of homoeroticism in the cultivation of desire in relation toTangier</section>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the very first editions of the French </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> published prior to the 2010s (before the enthronement of Mohammed VI and the announcement of the ‘soft spot’he had for Tangier), the discourse took outhe heterosexual referents, not to produce values linked to possession </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and accessibility (which are a less obvious choice to highlight in a post-independence Morocco) but to capitalise on values linked to insecurity and inhospitality. These first editions of the French </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> open with a warning to the tourist about the continuous harassment they will be subjected to: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The harassment from the polyglot touts soondrives tourists away. But after a few days, they mostly leave you in peace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet, </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">1995).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The space thus presents heterotopic qualities that limit access to it and create a space that is conducive to male enclaves. The discourse in the guides published up until the 2000s excludes women (both the tourists and those indigenous to Tangier) from public and private places</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn23" id="bodyftn23">23</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The reasons for this are the male pre-eminence in public places in Morocco and the lack of security: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The spatio-temporal setting outlined by the discourse in the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of a city in decline and abandoned by both sides (that is, by both the Moroccan state and the foreign residents, including the artists who have either left or gone missing) revives the qualities of a space that is subversive and dangerous but which is also falling into disuse and decline. Hence, the famous old periods and locations for partying and ostentatious display are described in the past tense as they have given way to sad, deserted places. The characters who have stayed on are ageing, just like the locations: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Despite Tangier’s central role in a global black economy and the growth that resulted from it, the city did not develop. It was merely a central hub for the flow of goods, and it suffered an urban lethargy once its black economy activities declined:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From the colonial point of view, homoeroticism as an erotic preference can be interpreted in this discourse as a rejection of a defence system. The homosexual spatialities that go hand in hand with a male hypersexualisation of the location reveal an anxiety and malaise in a mythologised city that was changing. The sadness that accompanied the decline gave way to nostalgia in the discourses of the 2000s. Unable to access the record of decline to describe the evolving urban reality, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guide Vert </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">marked a heterochrony in the 2000s that froze the sites and landscapes in an outdated and abandoned state and the city’s inhabitants in a state of expectation. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The sanitisation of the homoeroticism discourse that accompanied Tangier’s touristic development, which was managed by the central power in the 2000s, reveals a correlation between an imagination of the decline, disorder and urban decay, on the one hand, and homoeroticism as a cultivation of desire, on the other. From the 2000s onwards, with the city’s economic and touristic renewal, the discourse in the guides gradually sanitises the homoeroticism by suppressing any references to Tangier’s past that are linked first with paedophilia (in 2001) and then with homosexuality (in 2010). From the 2000s onwards, references to the figure of Burroughs, a key element in the homoeroticisation of the discourse on the city in the 1990s, is diluted with other references. The presentation of the city as the interzone and any comparators stops in 2005. The opening of the space up to women is expressed relatively with the upscale in security concretised in the introduction of a tourist squad, first mentioned in the 2007 edition:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The implementation of security measures was part of an operation to drive the dropouts and touts out of Tangier and eradicate prostitution: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The vast majority of touts that have given Tangier a bad reputation have been driven out</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2010). Since 2010, the nature of the locations and the tourist facilities proposed by the guides definitively emphasises quality, comfort and hospitality. The tourist map for the medina shows a predominance of cultural sites, artisan shops, art galleries, restaurants run by foreign investors and guest houses and luxury hotels (Dar Nour, HôtelMamora, etc.). As a result, the city has a welcoming quality, which has been restored by the transport and accommodation infrastructures. The sites, characters and practices that once compromised the sleek image of a developing city have disappeared and been </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">replaced by a cultural tourism gentrification</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion  </section>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The touristic discourse in the print guides makes use of a rich reserve of images and poetic representations to cultivate desire in relation to Tangier. The city has always aroused a yearning in artists and travellers and liberated eroticisms. The discourse is consolidated around this stereotyped image of the artist, which suggests repetitive scenarios of accessing and visiting the city where the traveller manages to merge with the destination. Hence, the erotic rhetorical devices used in the contemporary travel guides’ discourse are developed on the basis of famous artists’ accounts of their creative trips in Tangier in the 19</span><sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">th</span></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and 20</span><sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">th</span></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> centuries.The artists as emblems give this cultivation of desire and particularly this eroticisation content all its richness and power. A whole range of erotic preferences emerges when we return to the sources behind the construction of these figures, when we decipher their original </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">meaning and when we examine the avenues they open up for readers in coproducing their destination imagination.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The discourse’s eroticisation of locations represents a type of cultivation of desire that constructs a discourse on alterity. It constructs attractiveness in the contemporary promotional discourses while moving beyond the hierarchies identified by gender and postcolonial studies. Indeed, eroticisation is able todisperse with class and race relations, retaining only gender-related differences. Nevertheless, eroticisation can also lead toethical excesses of the reduction and availability of the other that are much more extreme than would be the case with exoticism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The eroticisation of a place can demonstrate a group’s need at a particular time in its history to forcibly claim ownership of a new territory, to cultivate its own desire and to ultimately construct a new social project. In the past, literature has been a dominant ideological force that has imposed transgressive eroticisations and transformed Tangier into a receptacle of repressed desires from a group of Western artists. This homoeroticism was especially perpetuated in the touristic discourse of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">through the valorisation of a subversive spatiality because it opposed the neoliberal injunction to cities to develop, open up, sort themselves out, makes themselves visible and integrate with the rest of the world. Later, in the contemporary discourses and in the sanitisation of the discourse following an increase in regulations and the domestication of the touristic space, homoeroticism was halted and replaced by autoeroticism, which places the onus back on the reader’s imaginational capacity to form their own eroticisations and even to create new ones.In a globalised world where asperities tend to disappear, the erotic desire in contemporary discourses autoregulates by responding more to ludic and cultural activities than to sexual or psychoaffective needs.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Amirou R., 1995, Imaginaire touristique et sociabilités du voyage, Paris, PUF.</reference>
        <reference>Appadurai A., 2001, Après le colonialisme. Les conséquences culturelles de la globalisation, Paris, Payot.</reference>
        <reference>Arama M., 2006, Delacroix, Un voyage initiatique : Maroc, Andalousie, Algérie, Paris, Non-Lieu.</reference>
        <reference>Baider F., Burger M., Goustos D. (dir.), 2004, La communication touristique. Approches discursives de l’identité et de l’altérité, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Barthes R., 1970, Mythologies, Paris, Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Beaulieu  I., Joseph J. L, 2003, « Tourisme, sexualité et érotisme dans quelques romans contemporains », Téoros, 22-1, 44-50.</reference>
        <reference>Berliner D., 2011, « LuangPrabang, sanctuaire Unesco et paradis gay », Genre, sexualité &amp; société, n°5.</reference>
        <reference>Bernardie-Tahir N. (dir.), 2008, L’autre Zanzibar, Géographie d’une contre- insularité, Paris, Karthala.</reference>
        <reference>Black P., 2000, « Sex and travel : Making the links », das Clift S., Carter S. (dir.), Tourisme and Sex : Culture, commerce and coercition, Pniter, London, New York, chap. 15.</reference>
        <reference>Bonnet V., Kober M., Zekri K. (dir.), 2013, Lire les villes marocaines, Paris, l’Harmattan, Itinéraires.</reference>
        <reference>Brennan D., 2004, What’s Love Got to Do with It ? Transnational Desires and Sex Tourism in the Dominican Republic, Durham, Duke University Press.</reference>
        <reference>Bronislaw B., 1984, Les imaginaires sociaux. Mémoire et espoirs collectifs, Paris, Payot.</reference>
        <reference>Brunet R, Ferras R, Thery H., 1992, Les mots de la géographie. Dictionnaire critique, Paris, Reclus, La documentation française.</reference>
        <reference>Burroughs W., 1991 (1989), Interzone, Paris, Christian Bourgois.</reference>
        <reference>Crépault C., 2007, Fantasmes, l’érotisme et la sexualité (Les), Paris, Odile Jacob.</reference>
        <reference>Dodi C-A, 2010, Villes invisibles de la méditerranée, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Dumas A., 2006, Le Véloce ou Tanger, Alger et Tunis, Lyon, Palimpseste, Collection : Singuliers.</reference>
        <reference>Echtner C, Prasad M., 2003, « The context of Third World tourism marketing », Annals of Tourism Research, 30(3), 660­82.</reference>
        <reference>Fernandez J., Caraës M-H., 2003, Tanger ou la dérive littéraire. : Essai sur la colonisation littéraire d’un lieu, Espaces méditerranéens.</reference>
        <reference>Goffman, E., [1963]1975, Stigmate, Paris, Minuit.</reference>
        <reference>Goulemot J-M., 2008, « Peintres à Tanger au début du siècle », in Tatin­Gourier J-J., Amahjour R. (dir.), Imaginaire et mémoire de Tanger, 1880-1956 (textes réunis), Tours, université François Rabelais.</reference>
        <reference>Gravari-Barbas M., Graburn N., 2012, « Imaginaires touristiques », Via@tourismreview, n°1 Les imaginaires touristiques.</reference>
        <reference>Houssay-Holzschuch M. (dir.), 2007, « Antimondes : Espaces En Marge. Espaces Invisibles », Géographie et Cultures, n°57.</reference>
        <reference>Kinnaird, Vivian H., Derek R. Hall, 1994, Tourism : A gender Analysis, Toronto, Chichester, JhonWiley.</reference>
        <reference>Peraldi M., 2007, « Économies criminelles et mondes d’affaire à Tanger », Cultures &amp; Conflits, n° 68, 111-125.</reference>
        <reference>Pritchard, A., Nigel M., 2000, « Privileging the male gaze gendered Tourism landscapes ? » Annals of tourism Research, vol. 27, 884-905,.</reference>
        <reference>Rautenberg M., 2004, « Les « communautés » imaginées de l’immigration dans la construction patrimoniale », Les Cahiers de Framespa, n°3.</reference>
        <reference>Rebucini G., 2011, « Lieux de l’homoérotisme et de l’homosexualité masculine à Marrakech », L’Espace Politique, n°13.</reference>
        <reference>Said E, Culture et Impérialisme, 2000 [Culture and Imperialism, 1993], (trad. Paul Chemla), Fayard/Le Monde Diplomatique.</reference>
        <reference>Said E., 1980, L’Orientalisme. L’Orient créé par l’Occident, Paris, Le Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Schneider P., 1990, Matisse au Maroc, Paris, Adam Biro, 26.</reference>
        <reference>Staszak J-F., 2008, « Qu’est-ce que l’exotisme ? », in Le Globe. Revue genevoise de géographie, tome 148, 7-30.</reference>
        <reference>Staszak J-F, 2012, « L’imaginaire géographique du tourisme sexuel », L’Information géographique, N°2, Vol. 76, 16-39</reference>
        <reference>Staszak J-F, 2003, Géographies de Gauguin, Paris, Bréal.</reference>
        <reference>Staszak J-F, 2015, « Tourisme et prostitution coloniaux : la visite de Bousbir à Casablanca (1924-1955) », Via@ Tourismreview, n°8 .</reference>
        <reference>Stoller R. J., 1984, Sex and Gender: The Development of Masculinity and Femininity, Karnac Books.</reference>
        <reference>Rauch A., 2007, « Les guides, une manière d’être dans la ville touristique : visiter Florence avec le Baedeker, le Guide Autrement et le Routard », in Knafou R., Mondes urbains du tourisme, Paris, Belin.</reference>
        <reference>Tatin-Gourier J-J., Amahjour R., 2008, Imaginaire et mémoire de Tanger, 1880-1956, Tours, Université François Rabelais.</reference>
        <reference>Twain M., 1867, Voyage des Innocents : un pique-nique dans l’ancien monde, Paris, Payot.</reference>
        <reference>Urbain J-D., 1991, L’idiot du voyage : Histoires de touristes, Paris, Plon.</reference>
        <reference>Webography: </reference>
        <reference> http://www.mbctimes.com/francais/top-10-des-villes-les-plus-sexy-du-monde-2</reference>
        <reference> http://www.frommers.com/destinations/morocco/642777</reference>
        <reference>http://www.routard.com/guide_dossier/id_dp/7/num_page/5.htm</reference>
        <reference>Corpus of print guides:</reference>
        <reference>Guides Bleus. (1965, 1969). Maroc, author Boulanger R, Paris, Hachette.</reference>
        <reference>Guides Bleus. (1973, 1975, 1978). Maroc, authorFauvel JJ, Paris, Hachette.</reference>
        <reference>Guides Bleus. (1987). Maroc, authorBarbey A. (ed.), Paris, Hachette.</reference>
        <reference>Guides Bleus. (1999, 2000, 2003). Maroc, authorsBosio S, Férin D, de Panthou P, Paris, Hachette. 269 p.</reference>
        <reference>Guides Bleus. (2002). Maroc, authorBoyer C. (ed.), Paris, Hachette, 511 p.</reference>
        <reference>Guides Bleus. (2008, 2012). Maroc, authorPujo N. (ed.), Paris, Hachette.</reference>
        <reference>Guide vert Michelin. (1949, 1950, 1954). Maroc, Paris, Services de Tourisme Michelin, 219 p. </reference>
        <reference>Guide vert Michelin. (1974). Maroc, Manufacture Française des Pneumatiques Michelin. </reference>
        <reference>Guide vert Michelin. (1976, 1978, 1982, 1985, 1988). Maroc, Paris, Pneu Michelin, Services de Tourisme. </reference>
        <reference>Guide vert Michelin. (1995, 1997, 2001). Maroc, Manufacture Française des Pneumatiques Michelin. </reference>
        <reference>Guide vert Michelin. (2001, 2003, 2007, 2010, 2012, 2014). Maroc, Paris, Michelin, traveledition. </reference>
        <reference>LonelyPlanet. (1995). Maroc, guide de voyage. Authors: Simonis D, Crowther, G [trans. byThérèse de Cheriseyand Anne Dechanet], 3rd ed., Paris, LonelyPlanet. </reference>
        <reference>LonelyPlanet. (1998). Maroc, guide de voyage. Authors: Linzee F, Talbot D, Simonis D, [partially translated from English byMiadi F andPrunier C], 3rd ed., Paris, LonelyPlanet. </reference>
        <reference>Lonely Planet. (2001). Maroc. Authors: Fletcher M, Connolly J, Linzee F. et al., 4th ed., Paris, LonelyPlanet.</reference>
        <reference>Lonely Planet. (2005). Maroc. Authors: Hardy P, Vorhees M, Edsall H, 5th ed., Paris, Lonely Planet.</reference>
        <reference>Lonely Planet. (2011). Maroc. Authors: Bainbridge J, Bing A, Clammer P et al., 8th ed., Paris, Lonely Planet.</reference>
        <reference>Lonely Planet. (2014). Maroc. Authors: Clammer P, Bainbridge J, Hardy P et al., 9th ed., Paris, Lonely Planet.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">This and all subsequent quotations from French sources in this text have been translated into English.</note>
        <note id="2">A concept invented by Brunet denoting all negative, marginal and informal spaces marked by isolation and dissimulation.</note>
        <note id="5">This is the title of a historical column in the Guide Vert. In the Guide Bleu (2012), the title is ‘jouet des convoitises arabe’ (a plaything of Arabian desires). The most famous historical anecdote is that Tangier was presented as a dowry by Catherine of Braganza to Charles II on their marriage in 1661. This is one example of the legends (including those from Greek mythology) that reinforce the city-as-object metaphor.</note>
        <note id="6">Reference to this artist was highlighted in the Guide Vert. Bowles’ death in 1999 ended the saga first introduced in the Guide Vert (published that same year) with a text box entitled ‘A Chapter Closes’. Since the 2000s, the Lonely Planet and the Guide Bleu have also included a text box dedicated to Bowles’ life and activities in Tangier.</note>
        <note id="7">Crépault (2007) explained that Eros thrived, on the one hand, on hatred, suffering and destruction and, on the other, on feelings of love and tenderness. He believed that fusional fantasies circulated more freely in the female than the male imagination, which found them threatening. The male antifusional imaginations could, however, conceal fusional fantasies (especially in their orgasmic phase). </note>
        <note id="8">Delacroix, Dumas and Mark Twain, who stayed in Tangier in 1832, 1846 and 1867, respectively, all reported the need for the visitor to be escorted in the city and to be welcomed by an intermediary who could introduce them to local daily life. </note>
        <note id="9">Dumas relayed his first impressions on disembarking the Véloce in 1846: ‘This morning, you leave a friendly country, and this evening, you arrive in a hostile one. These fires that you see have been lit by a race that is completely the opposite of your own, the mortal enemy of your person, which has done it no wrong and which has no intention of ever doing so. The cries, finally, are those of ferocious animals, unknown in the land you have come from and which, just like the lion in the Scripture, will be looking for someone to devour. Set foot on this land and if you escape the animals, you will not escape the men. Why? Because this land is separated by a body of water that is seven leagues from the next land, because it is close to one quarter of a degree from the equator and finally because it is called Africa and not Spain, Italy, Greece or Sicily’ (p. 327). </note>
        <note id="10">A number of travellers mobilised this stereotype on account of the population’s hostility towards them, including Charles Didier (1844), Edmondo De Amicis (1876), Henri de la Martinière (1887). </note>
        <note id="11">Twain wrote in his travel narrative: ‘Here is a city that is full to bursting, enclosed by a massive stone wall that is more than a thousand years old.’</note>
        <note id="12">‘In the main street, which we have to cross, there are some Spanish boutiques, some French and English posters, and mixed in with the crowd of burnous are alas! some gentlemen in safari hats and young lady travellers with their sunkissed cheeks. But it makes no difference. Tangier is still very Arab, even in its commercial districts’ (Loti, 2000 (1890), p. 24). </note>
        <note id="13">In reference to Henri Amic’s work ‘Le Maroc. Hier et aujourd’hui. Deux voyages, 1920-1924’ (Paris, Calman-Lévy, 1925).</note>
        <note id="14">We refer here to the work of Salardenne (1932), who travelled to Tangier in 1930 to report on the prostitutes in what he called the ‘Moroccan Babylon’. He described the Jewish prostitutes who would ‘solicit’ bare-breasted in the streets of Tangier. A Lévy and Neurdein postcard (fig. 4) sent by a tourist in the 1930s shows a similar ‘Jewish Moor’prostitute.</note>
        <note id="15">The Dictionnaire des Orientalistes Français gives the date (1913) that the company Lévy et Fils was bought by Emile Crété, who had also taken over Neurdein. The amalgamation was called Lévy &amp; Neurdein Réunis, which subsequently became the Compagnie des Arts Photomécaniques in 1932. </note>
        <note id="16">In his letters to Allen Ginsberg, Burroughs (1990) related his experiences of paedophilia, his nights in seedy bars, his decline into the world of drugs and his journey to the depths of hell.</note>
        <note id="17">In The Dogs Bark, Capote writes: ‘Magnificent beaches. Extraordinary stretches of sand as soft as caster sugar, and big breakers. And – if you like this sort of thing – the nightlife, while neither particularly innocent nor especially varied, goes on from dusk till dawn. Which, when you consider that the majority of people take a siesta that lasts the whole afternoon and that very few of them dine before ten or eleven at night, is not too abnormal. (…) It is quite alarming how many travellers have disembarked here just for a short stay and then settled, and the years have just slipped by. Because Tangier is a harbour. It wraps around you. It is a place sheltered from time. The days slide off you without you even noticing them, like splashes of foam from a waterfall’ (Back-translated from the French [1977, p. 151-152]). He subsequently told the story of the party on Sidi Kacem beach, which lasted until dawn and during which he (and his companions) slept on the beach.</note>
        <note id="18">Burroughs William, Letters to Allen Ginsberg: 1953-1957, New Jersey, Full Court Press, 1982; Lapassade Georges, Le bordel Andalou, Paris, L’Herne, 1971; Barthes Roland, Incidents, Berkeley, University of California Press, 1992; Barthes, New Critical Essays; Capote Truman, Answered Prayers, London, Hamish Hamilton, 1986; Paul Morand, Hecate and her Dogs, London, Pushkin, 2009.</note>
        <note id="19">‘Tangier is a very gossipy city, and all the members of the foreign colony inevitably know one another. But that’s it. Neither the laws nor public opinion threaten individual freedom… Tangier is sanctuary in which everyone is sheltered from all interference’ (Back-translated from the French) (Letters to Allen Ginsberg: 1953-1957, William Burroughs, New Jersey, Full Court Press, 1982).</note>
        <note id="20">Article 489 of Morocco’s penal code criminalises homosexuality, or any sexual act between two men. </note>
        <note id="21">This and all subsequent quotations from the French editions of the Lonely Planet have been back-translated from the French.</note>
        <note id="22">This expression is used in reference to Burroughs’ Interzone, where the author describes the cultivation of desire (described as numbers) in which the Tangier (Interzone) inhabitants operate to make contact with the visitors and get some money off them. </note>
        <note id="23">When they are present, they are mundane dancers or prostitutes during their spare time. The tourists passing through Tangier are famous artists who are identified sexually (‘homosexual artists’). </note>
    </notes>
</article>