<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_BR_22-143_Fo_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1028" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.1028</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>3</numero>
        <annee>2013</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="1023">
            De l’aménagement des circuits à la réinterprétation des lieux visités : invention d’un espace-temps touristique en pays lobi burkinabè
        </original>
        <traduction lang="it" source="1033">Itinerari e luoghi visitati tra organizzazione e reinterpretazione: creazione di uno spazio-tempo turistico nei villaggi lobi di Burchina Faso</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Royer" prenom="Bertrand">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_BR_22-134_Db_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1023" lang="fr">De l’aménagement des circuits à la réinterprétation des lieux visités : invention d’un espace-temps touristique en pays lobi burkinabè</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Bertrand Royer is a PhD candidate at the Centre de Recherches et d’Études Anthropologiques (CREA) in Lyon. He is finishing a thesis on the turning of heritages in the South-Western region of Burkina Faso into tourism. He is the author of several articles and conference papers on the topic. He teaches ethnology as lecturer at the University of Lyon 2, École Nationale d’Architecture in Saint-Étienne and at Instituts de Formation en soins infirmiers. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>From the organizing of tours to the reinterpretation of visited places: Invention of a touristic space-time in the Lobi country of Burkina Faso</titre>
    <resume>
        In the Lobi country of Burkina Faso,the development of tourismset within the framework of the local heritagesculpts a regional scheme in the mode of “to do – to see”. From the museum to the villages, the exchanges amongst protagonists appear more and more formal and standardized. However, each particular situation slightly reveals the margins of action and the experimentations in progress. By focusing the analysis on the reinterpretation of the visited places, we will see how a space-time of the tourist encounter can be invented in the context of an emerging cultural tourism.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In Burkina Faso, touristic cultural events are mainly occasional orbiennial in conjunction withthe major thematic manifestations in Western Africa such as the Pan-African Film Festival in Ouagadougou, the National Week of Culture, the Atypical Nights of Koudougou, the Yeleen festival at Bobo Dioulasso, etc. In promotional documents relative to the organization of a tour of the national territory, activities in parks, reservations and the wide Sahelian spaces to the north which are all commonly liked with hunting and visual tourism being presented. At the nexus of these two different forms of tourism, the one promoting an urban and festive experience and the other offering the discovery of the wilderness, a type of rural tourism is developing in a niche outside of this double categorization. In the South-Western Burkina Faso, in and around the town of Gaoua, tourist visits are not punctuated with festivals, shows, or with the moments of euphoria and joy characteristic to the more common type of touristic experience. Even if no major event justifies the purpose of the trip, these are not contemplative tours either, that would only promote a panoramicappreciation of vast wastelands, horizons or natural surroundings. By encouraging visitors to discover the Africa of villages, of agricultural lifestyles and of peasant craftsmanship, rural and community-based tourism in Burkina Faso requires another type of “tourist gaze” (Urry, 1990), an organization, and specific activities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the pursuit of positioning correlated destinations and activities, which are the images and imaginary contexts employed to make the South-Western region of Burkina Faso attractive ? From the ”dialogue of cultures” to the “encounter with peoples”‘, we will see that the imaginary world of the “authentic” African village is at the heart of the promotional rhetoric. Supposedly preserved from the devastating effects of the productive urban “over-modernity” of “non-places” and non-sense (Augé, 1992), some villages of the “Lobi country” are thus presented as ideal cultural islets for ethical tourism. By going through a “‘return to what’s real” (Bensa, 2006), in the spatio-temporal context of organized visits, the ethnographical enquiry bringsto light a local scenography comprised of both tourism and local heritage, the amalgamation of which defines a </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">tour</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of the “Lobi country”. Issued from micro and macro social logics, these itineraries imply in fact a touristic reconfiguration and a selection of places, linked together by a route. The study of this regional scheme facilitates the understanding of the conditions in which the touristic exchanges take place, bearing in mindthe ethic of an encounter, no longer just on the scale of cultures or of peoples, but in terms of the participants : the tourists, the guides and the villagers.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">From rural tourism to ethnictourism: The Tour of the Lobi</section>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In rural areas, the touristic strategy consists ofmaking attractive, not especially a monument or a highly symbolic place</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, but a whole territory thanks to its recognition (Amirou, 2005) due to the glorification of its cultural particularities and its inhabitants. For the current Burkinabe culture and tourism minister, “in a country where eighty per cent of the population lives in the country side […], the national political option for tourism is first of all a tourism that makes for a discovery of the uses and habits of Burkina”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Through this perspective, the touristic and cultural phenomenon is decentralized. It leaves the big cities and spreads in the provinces and sub-regions, to the edges, on each side, and even beyond the borders between states. For their holiday destinations, tourists and travel agencies are less and less targeting a whole national territory, but rather one or several single regions. During their stays in West Africa, tourists don’t visit Mali, Burkina Faso, Ghana, etc, but rather the “Dogon country”, the ”Touareg country”, the “Senoufo country”, the “Ashanti country”, etc. Rather than speaking of a real competition or of a ranking among these “territories”, depending on their excellence as destinations, tourists and travel agencies are more interested in an “entity recognized by its mark and its image” (Bédard, 2011).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Images of the encounter and of the African village</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Located at the border between Ghana and the Ivory Coast, the South-West of Burkina Faso is little urbanized and mostly populated by people living on food-producing agriculture (millet, sorghum, yams…). The different cultural minorities considered as “native”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> are gathered since the colonization and the first ethnographical enquiries, under an appellation, with strong “‘mythopoetic” intonations, (Ciarcia, 2002) : the “peoples of the Lobi branch” (Labouret, 1931). Perceived as an “authentic” destination, the ”Lobi country” is, according to the ministry of culture, very suitable for a tourism that favors “the encounter between peoples”.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mobilized both by public authorities and private promoters, this “encounter” model, especially when it concerns “the peoples” in their whole, creates a clear cut distinction between the visitors and the visited, and as a consequence, mediation modalities that can’t be found in the same manner within an urban context. Outside cities, tourism in Africa is becoming an “ethno tourism”, nourished and shaped by the exotic images of a cultural elsewhere. The authors of the travel guide </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Le petit Futé</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> consider, for instance, that a ”visit to small Lobi villages offers one of the most fascinating “ethnic” experiences in Burkina Faso. […] The encounter is often authentic and touching […]” (Ausias and Labourdette, 2011, p. 255). Tourist rhetoric of the otherness entertains the idea that there are radically different sociocultural universes, and that their discovery can be approached as an entertainment. The content of the visits is then oriented towards aspects that are supposed to be the most traditional of the local society or societies and the “African village” becomes the reference model in terms of tour content. Like in rural tourism in France and in Europe, villager communities turn into “objects of desire” (Rautenberg et al, 2000 &amp;amp; Laferté and Renahy, 2003) and the African campaigns turn into the reference scales of a new ethnic tourism. Reinforced by the fact that none of them has become a destination per se, the “Lobi villages” of the South-Western Burkina have become in many aspects, in promotional rhetoric, the archetypes of a primitive Africa (Amselle, 2010), still untouched on the cultural level. The vitality of their animist beliefs and the resistant and independent spirit of the South-Western people, have turned into marketing points and are presented as guarantees of an authentic intercultural encounter. The touristic promotion of rural Africa reinforces the idea of the African village as a “timeless entity, the existence of which is not affected by history” (Amselle 2010, p. 99). These representations support the idea of locked and protected places where the visitor could enjoy an “exotic dreaming” (Jolly, 2007), not only accessible through the radio, museums</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> or virtually anymore (Cros and Mégret, 2011) but made accessible through organized travel. For the tourist industry, the notion of “village” offers the geographical references necessary to any local, but also the cognitive and sociological references that allow the visit to be anchored in the reality of the visited places. Concerning tourism development in rural areas, that notion corresponds to the carnal and material envelope that gives flesh to the promotional rhetoric.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the global and competitive field of organized travel, the village evokes imagery shared at the same time by tourists, travel conceptualizersand travel agencies. For the concerned villagers, however, if there really is a villager area, its visit, be it of a touristic nature or otherwise, is a laborious undertaking, or can even be unthinkable. In the “Lobi country”, the notion of Di (translated by the term </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">village</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) “is not based on a topographical criterion, like in Europe […] There is no central square or common house” (Meyer, 1981, p. 19). Dwellings are far from one another and function in a more or less autonomous way, “it is not possible for a stranger, whether Lobi or European, to see where a village stops and where the next one starts.” (Meyer, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ibid</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). However, when visitors go to Dihoute Palenfo’s family, according to each of the protagonists, the tourists are not visiting the yard of one craftsman among others, but Tambili, the sculptors’ village. Then, continuing their itinerary, the groups will stop successively in several particular places that have become, for the needs of tourist staging, the village of women basket weavers, the village of women potters, the village of the soothsayer</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. As Anne Doquet and Olivier Evrard accurately point out, “tourism induces much new discussion of places and it is really based on the glorificationof the particular that becomes self-justified […]” </span>(Doquet and Evrard, 2008, p. 12).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">From the selection to the valorization of places: Tourist routes</section>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">As we are going to see, there really is a “recreation of places” (Franklin, 2008) made by and for the visitor, but the appearance of these few familial dwellings on the international tourist scene has not happened ex nihilo. Their fame and the legitimacy of the tourist services that are offered there are the result of a historical process of selection and of the patrimonialization of elements considered to be the most significant of the local identity.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Without lingering here on the external and internal dynamics that are integral to the formationof the Lobi heritage (Royer, 2012), my purpose is to question not so much the content and the plural values of what is staged, but rather the staging itself, in its touristic and “communicational” (Cohen, 1989) dimension. On the regional scale, this staging shapes a “spatial decorum” that “has to do with theater” (Raffestin, 1986, p. 15), and within which each visited place becomes the support of a particular representation of the otherness. The touristic staging of identities and of territories requires that the actors of the tourism identify the places where the cultural productions associated with traditional objects and craftsmanship will be presented. Made attractive by promotional endeavors, practices such as sculpture and divination are raising a growing touristic interest. This external sight locally contributes to the emergence and the differentiation between places (Gravari-Barbas and Violier, 2003, p. 13), or even to their ranking within a hierarchy. More visible than others, these places are accessible to audiences, classified as tourist places and linked together by a route. From the urban center to rural peripheries, the route followed by visitors is being written as a regional draft, a touristic scenography on the classical model of “to see- to do”.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Before considering the role of the actors and spectators of this staging, the study of the routes in regard to their spatio-temporal characteristics, sheds light on the conditions in which the encounters and tourist exchanges occur. Within this regional scheme of the welcoming and orienting of the visitors, the little town of Gaoua–the headquarters of catering and accommodation in the region, becomes a little tourist center, from which the tour of the Lobi country is organized. With its two hotels and its museum, Gaoua is indeed a starting and arrival point for groups of visitors who are making a stop-over in the “Lobi country” and who rarely stay more than two nights. Their guides program one or two daily excursions and tourists “do” the “Lobi country” in a few hours, before following their way towards Banfora, to the East in the “Gouin country” or more to the North in the region of Tiebele, in the “Kassena country”. Contrarily to “alternative” forms of cultural and community-based tourism (Chabloz 2006, for Burkina) in the “Lobi country”, tourists are just passing through. They prefer crossing to staying, and that locally generates a rather strict management of the tourist space-time. It is cut in sequences, with stop-overs and times of systematic stopping, first at the museum, and then in the surrounding localities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Most of the routes start indeed with the museum of Gaoua. Dedicated to “the South-Western civilizations”, the museum is an important anchorage point for the legacy discourse. Inside the building, where photos and ethnographical objects are exhibited, the touristic exchange takes the shape of a data transfer, from a transmitter (the guide) to a recipient (the audience). Shaped on the model of “telegraphic communication” (Winkin, 2001, p. 27), the speech of the guides is explicitly didactical, sometimes scholarly and often technical and historical. It belongs to what Selwyn (1996) calls “cold authenticity”, that is to say that the value of that speech largely depends on the quality of the knowledge learnt by the visitor. If it remains operational within the exhibition rooms, this exchange does not fully satisfy the expectations of the visitors, and in their “quest” to rupture the veil of staged authenticity (Mac Cannell, 1976), they aspire to more proximity with the local populations. Many tourists are looking for a “warm authenticity” (Selwyn 1996), that is not specialized and museographic anymore but based on the intensity of the sensations experienced by the visitors during the touristic encounter. That is why the exhibition rooms are in fact only a sort of introduction to the visit that will continue outside the museum, in the “villages” located around Gaoua. These visits “outside the walls” serve to present artifacts and techniques (craftsmanship, divination) that are still in use in the local context and are thus made or used regularly amongst the populations. From the center towards the outskirts, from the museum to the villages, the touristic route is infused with things seen and heard during the exhibition and the progression of the visit follows the same model as the progression of the museum</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Accompanying guides who are native to the region indeed offer to have the tourists “discover” a masculine activity : sculpture, two feminine activities : pottery and basket weaving, and a religious activity : divination.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The familial yards concerned are living spaces, transformed into “legendary spaces” and mobilized for the “emplotment” of territories (Urbain, 2010, p. 104). They are located a few kilometers away from Gaoua, close to the main traffic roads ; that makes the passage of tourists and of their guides, who most of the times go there with a car, easier. These places have no heritage status in the strict and juridical sense of the word. As a result, these are not “museum villages”, but the arrival of a guide and of “his” tourists instantly transforms familial yards into some sort of museum annexes. As soon as a group arrives, craftsmen introduce, in the frame of an exhibition that could be qualified as temporary, their collection of statues, stools, canes, pots, baskets, etc. The tourists – who, let’s not forget that fact, are only there for a few minutes – are sometimes embarrassed about the “fuss” they provoke. Benches or stools are freed for them and set in front of the objects, which are disposed in the most attractive way possible. The objects are made in the same fashion as the ones in the museum, but at the craftsman’s, the exchange is not about knowledge, historical or ethnological knowledge but artifacts that have become mercantile goods. For the sculptors, the potters or the basket weavers, tourism is assimilated to objects sale, circulation, and status change. Traditionally made for being used or destined to a cult, sometimes source of power and distinction, baskets, potteries or wooden sculpted objects are apprehended, in a tourist situation, as hand-crafted or artistic items that, following a mercantile transaction, will become souvenirs.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">From the place to the links: The tourist staging as mediation</section>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The study of routes shows that the exchanges between visitors and visited happen in a scenic space filled with imagination and framed with a device that is both technical and strategical. Often, the tourists themselves are aware of this staging, and depending on their degree of responsiveness, they may or may not support the work of the providing villagers, but also of the work of the accompanying guide who is playing the role of a “stage director” (Doquet, 2005). Pretences, tricks and shams (Baudrillard, 1985) are at the heart of the touristic activity and of the development of cultural identities. Does tourism in so far induce turning traditions into folklore or a”disneylandization” (Brunel, 2006) of cultures ? Don’t these stagings rather classify as a mediation work to enable the creation of a visit consensus ? The theatrical metaphor is particularly fertile</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, not only because it helps identifying the “give to see”, but also and mostly because it supposes an interest in what happens backstage, out of the field of organized visits. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">From the ritual object to the mercantile object: New uses of sculpture</section>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The villages of craftsmen involved in touristic activities are in fact little family yards, the members of which somehow appear as “prepared” to adopt a certain type of behavior during visits. Before and after the tourist encounter per se, the providing villagers, the guidesand also the travel conceptualizerscollaborate amongst themselves and consider the places depending on certain goals.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In Tambili, even if the yard of the sculptor DihountePalenfo has become over the years an almost unavoidable place of passing for all categories of visitors, the exchange of objects often replaces the exchange of words. Dihounte and his three sons only rarely communicate with the tourists ; they only set the prices of their respective production. While facing the tourists, once the women and children have presented the objects for sale, the involvement of the sculptors in the exchange or their “interactional performance” (Goffman, 1973, p. 41) seems limited. Most of the time, during the ceremonial of the visit, they continue their work while the guide carries out the comments and the bargaining about objects and photo shots. Despite some nonchalance and a lack of direct relation with tourists, these craftsmen are however those in the region who sell the highest number of objects to visitors, who have become customers. What is special about Dihounte Palenfo’s yard ? This tourist success seems to be linked not only with the originality of the pieces that are manufactured there, but also with the history of Dihounte’s life and the conditions in which his knowledge and savoir-faire have been transmitted to him.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In Dihounte Palenfo’s family, the men are initiated to sculpture (Bognolo, 1997, and Bosc, 1999) produce wooden objects made for different usesall year round. The artifacts that are offered to tourists stand alongside, following very precise rules which are elaborated with care, those made to serve in a cult. Even when he makes profane tourist objects, the activity of the sculptor remains a religious activity, that forces him to follow some ritual constraints, especially to be able to sell or exchange his objects securely, that is in accordance with his </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thila</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> ; his tutelary spirits. The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thila</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of the sculptor, who are themselves materialized under different forms and disposed according to precise codes, dictate a certain amount of interdictions that can vary from one sculptor to another. For craftsmen, this aspect is not at all secondary and partly explains that despite the high number of sculptors in the region, very few are directly and openly involved in a mercantile and regular exchange with the tourists.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">At Dihounte Palenfo’s, if during the visits, the organized sale of sculptures takes a formal and consensual character, it is because he has the same </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thil</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (plural </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thila</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) and thus the same interdictions as SikireKambire, one of the first sculptors of the regions to have done custom works for the colonial administrators (Labouret 1931, p. 188). The sculptor Sikire Kambire, whose pieces are today installed not only at the places of soothsayer-healers but also in private and public collections worldwide, has formed Dihounte Palenfo and transmitted to him, after the three major steps of the initiation, the recipe of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thel-thii</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> ; the medicine that protects sculptors. “The fetish that I have today comes from Sikire. […] This fetish has authorized the work with the whites. That’s why I am continuing on the same direction and I sell to tourists”. Dihounte Palenfo and those that he has initiated (Wolomite Sie Palenfo, Takite Kambou…) are acting in the continuity of SikireKambire. Through their daily practice and their work with the tourists, they are somehow keeping alive the memory of the one who was a pioneer in the exchange with foreigners and European collectors.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">When briefly considering temporalities and legacies particular to the trajectory of a sculptor and his family, we can understand better why DihountePalenfo’s yard is a place open to visits. The place is however shaped in a way that the exchange between visitors and visited is limited to the purchase of objects. Tourists do not have access to the sacrificial altars located outside and inside the house. During their visit, they don’t learn anything about Dihounte’s religious activities. The visit consensus stops at the sale of object and the exchange is particularly limited when it comes to the beliefs and practices that direct the making, the exchange and the ritual use of the wooden sculpted objects. In these conditions, while the tourist demand is more and more oriented towards the immaterial exchange of beliefs and values, and less and less towards the purchase of desecrated tourist artifacts, other experiences are organized, in other places, more favorable and set for that kind of exchange.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Tourist encounters and immaterial exchanges</section>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In their quest of authenticity and of “conversion to Africanity” (Chabloz, 2009), tourists are often critical towards this staging and this bargaining game around performances, places or objects that are often perceived as inauthentic. For many of them, especially when they are occidental tourists, the interest of this route lies elsewhere, at their ultimate stop-over at a soothsayer-healer. Even if, within the framework of the visit, shamanic or initiatic tourism (Chabloz, 2009 for Gabon) is unable to answer to the new demands, some religious dignitaries are willing to play the game of touristic staging. Thanks to their collaboration with guides, and after having consulted their </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thila</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, they will give an original character to their work, adapting it to the situation.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sib Tagialte, “the fetishist of Kampti”, a man widely recognized and consulted in the region for the power of his “medicines”, has been opening for a few years his </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thildu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the chamber of spirits, to visitors and their photo and video cameras. That place, located inside the dwelling, is dark and narrow ; statuettes, pots and other various objects are covered with sacrificial blood, which soothsayers use to “feed” (Cros, 1990) the spirits. The morphological characteristics of the place make it poorly suitable for a group visit ; it is thus individually or by couple that visitors enter the sacred space. Partly respecting the ritual, tourists take their shoes off and enter in the darkness backwards. The chamber of spirits is not a comfortable place, and visitors squat or sit on small stools. The smell of blood, muck and a general staleness, mixed with the emanation of the alcohol offered to divinities, sometimes sicken tourists.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Whether seen asmystical, unsettling, or just plain worrisome, the passing of the door of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thildu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> arouses the widest array of comments. That place of cult that ends our tour of the Lobi is reinterpreted in a touristic way, to satisfy the immense desire of encounter and otherness that most tourists feel. By looking from the material towards the immaterial, from the visible towards the beliefs, this step of the route makes the savoir-faire livelier, more attractive, or even more interactive in the eyes of the participants, when for instance some tourists participate in real divination sessions. Thanks to the setting of his yard and of his </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thildu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Sib Tagialte seems to fulfill the goals of the touristic encounter. However, his approach remains individual and marginal. The other places of cult, plentiful in the region, are ruled by different codes from a village, a family or one practitioner oranother. Each </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">thildu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> has its own characteristics and very few are open to tourist visits. The question of the opening of an intimate and sacred place to tourism relies not only on the organization of tours on a global scale, but also on the sometimes difficult negotiations between the soothsayer, the guides, the tourists and the ancestors.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the way back, tourists systematically ask many questions to which, out of experience, accompanying guides often answer in an indirect way. Depending on their degree of competence, they build up narrative strategies to dodge sensitive subjects such as initiatory secrets, religious taboos or witchcraft, all the while entertaining the tourists’ imagination around the world of invisible and supernatural. These exchanges between the guide and his clients sometimes continue in the vehicle, at the hotel, sometimes in the evening around drinks or a meal. These informal times of exchange, set outside of the strict framework of the organized visit, are privileged moments in the understanding of the meaning of the touristic staging. The oral discourse of the guide weaves links between the different steps of the visit ; it transcends places and sets a leading thread for the whole route.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Through the study of touristic imaginations and stagings, the ethnologist perceives that this notion pertains to “native categories” (Cravatte, 2009) and its meaning varies depending on the groups, the relations they entertain and the circumstances. For some scholars, once they open to tourism, places of visit lose some “authenticity”. The mercantile character of the encounter is indeed often perceived as a mercantilization of cultures in favor of the personal interests of people suspected of “cheating” the tourists.In these conditions, the touristic activity remains subject to numerous criticisms, coming from the local populations, from specialists in local cultures such as heritage officers, ethnologists or scholarsand from the tourists themselves. However, if the inception of tourism is really the occasion of a mercantilization of knowledge and savoir-faire, the touristic practices and the welcoming of the visitors also work as a great indicator of the immaterial values that surround the ethnographical and vernacular heritage. Beyond the objects themselves, the materials, the arts and crafts used in their making, the exchanges between visitors and visited and the reciprocal interactions and questionings offer a platform for the interpretation of beliefs, habits, rituals,practices and representations in the social and religious life of the dwelling populations. In this context, the quality of the encounter and its “ethic” lays on the relational intensity, the degree of reciprocity and the feeling of a mutual satisfaction between protagonists rather than on the peculiar value of the exchanged objects.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Amirou R., 2005, « Imaginaire de la mondialisation et reconnaissance culturelle », in Amirou R., Bachimon Ph., Malezieux J. (dir.), Tourisme et souci de l’Autre. En hommage à Georges Cazes, Paris, l’Harmattan, pp. 61-86.</reference>
        <reference>Amselle J.-L., 2010, Rétrovolutions. Essais sur les primitivismes contemporains, Paris, Stock.</reference>
        <reference>Auge M., 1992, Non-lieux. Introduction à une anthropologie de la surmodernité, Paris, Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Auzias D., Labourdette J.-P., 2010, Le Petit Futé Burkina Faso 2010-2011, (4ème Edition), Paris, Nouvelle Edition de l’Université.</reference>
        <reference>Baudrillard J., 1985, Simulacres et simulation, Paris, Galilée.</reference>
        <reference>Bédard F., 2011, « L’excellence des destinations », Téoros, vol. 30, n° 1, [ http://teoros.revues.org/1225 ].</reference>
        <reference>Bensa A., 2006, La fin de l’exotisme. Essais d’anthropologie critique, Toulouse, Anacharsis.</reference>
        <reference>Bognolo D., 1997, « Djetò ! Fais attention ! », Journal des africanistes, 67/1, pp. 123-133.</reference>
        <reference>Bosc J., 1999, « Les sculpteurs et leurs génies. Approche ethno-esthétique de la statuaire lobi », l’Homme, n° 151, pp. 75-100.</reference>
        <reference>Brunel S., 2006, La planète disneylandisée. Chronique d’un tour du monde, Auxerre, Sciences Humaines Edition.</reference>
        <reference>Chabloz N., 2006, « Vers une éthique du tourisme ? Les tensions à l’œuvre dans l’élaboration et l’appréhension des chartes de bonne conduite par les différents acteurs », Autrepart, pp. 45-62.</reference>
        <reference>Chabloz N., 2009, « Corps et âmes. Conversions touristiques à l’africanité », Cahiers d’Etudes africaines, vol. XLIX (1-2), n° 193-194, pp. 7-26.</reference>
        <reference>Chabloz N., 2009, « Tourisme et primitivisme. Initiations au bwiti et à l’iboga (Gabon) », Cahiers d’Etudes africaines, vol. XLIX (1-2), n° 193-194, pp. 391-428.</reference>
        <reference>Ciarcia G., 2002, « L’ethnofiction à l’œuvre. Prisme et images de l’entité dogon », Ethnologie comparée, n° 5, [http://alor.univ-montp3.fr/cerce/revue.htm].</reference>
        <reference>Cohen E., 1989, « “Primitive and Remote” Hill Tribe Trekking in Thailand », Annals of Tourism Research, 16, pp. 30-61.</reference>
        <reference>Cravatte C., 2009, « L’anthropologie du tourisme et l’authenticité. Catégorie analytique ou catégorie indigène ? », Cahiers d’Etudes africaines, vol. XLIX (1-2), n° 193-194, pp. 603-619.</reference>
        <reference>Cros M., 1990, Anthropologie du sang en Afrique, Paris, l’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Cros M. et Mégret Q. (dir.), 2011, Net et Terrain. Ethnographie de la n@ture en Afrique, Paris, Editions des Archives contemporaines.</reference>
        <reference>Doquet A., 2005, « La mise en scène d’une Afrique authentique », Programme de recherche en cours, Institut de Recherche pour le Développement, IRD/Mali, [http://www.mali.ird.fr/activites/misescene%28anne%29.htm].</reference>
        <reference>Doquet A. et Evrard O., 2008, « Introduction. Tourisme, mobilités et altérités contemporaines », Civilisation, vol. 57, n° 1-2, pp. 9-22.</reference>
        <reference>Fieloux M., Lombard J. et Kambou-Ferrand J.-M. (dir.), 1993, Images d’Afrique et Sciences sociales. Les pays lobi, birifor, dagara, Paris, Karthala/Orstom.</reference>
        <reference>Goffman E., 1973, La mise en scène de la vie quotidienne, Paris, Editions de Minuit.</reference>
        <reference>Gravari-Barbas M. et Violier Ph. (dir.), 2003, Lieux de culture. Culture des lieux, Rennes, Presses Universitaires de Rennes.</reference>
        <reference>Jolly E., 2007, « Rêveries exotiques sur les Dogon », l’Homme, n° 182, pp. 187-241.</reference>
        <reference>Kambou-Ferrand J.-M., 1993, « Être lobi, ça se mérite », in Fieloux M. et al (dir), Images d’Afrique et Sciences sociales. Les pays lobi, birifor, dagara, Paris, Karthala/Orstom, pp. 538-544.</reference>
        <reference>Labouret H., 1931, Les tribus du rameau lobi, Paris, Institut d’Ethnologie.</reference>
        <reference>Laferte G. et Renahy N., 2003, « “Campagnes de tous nos désirs”… d’ethnologues », l’Homme, n° 165, pp. 225-234.</reference>
        <reference>MacCannell D., 1976, The Tourist, A New Theory of the Leisure Class, Berkeley-Los Angeles- London, University of California Press.</reference>
        <reference>Meyer P., 1981, Kunst und Religion der Lobi, Zürich, Museum Rietberg.</reference>
        <reference>Price S., 2007, Paris Primitive. Jacques Chirac’s Museum on the Quai Branly, Chicago-London, University of Chicago Press.</reference>
        <reference>Raffestin C., 1986, « Nature et culture du lieu touristique », Méditerranée, vol. 58, n° 58, pp. 11-17.</reference>
        <reference>Rautenberg M., Micoud A., Bérard L. et Marchenay Ph., 2000, Campagnes de tous nos désirs, Paris, Edition de la Maison des Sciences de l’Homme.</reference>
        <reference>Royer B., 2009, « Les exciseuses lobi entrent au musée provincial du Poni (Burkina Faso) » in Behbahani S. (dir.), Ce genre qui dérange, Paris, Téraèdre, pp. 23-37.</reference>
        <reference>Royer B., 2012, « Le fil d’Ariane du Patrimoine. Du musée ethnographique de Gaoua au site UNESCO de Loropéni (Burkina Faso) », Géographie et Culture, à paraître.</reference>
        <reference>Royer B., 2011, « Patrimoine Mondial de l’Unesco et mise en valeur des ruines de Loropéni. Du site classé aux sites en ligne », in CROS Michèle et MEGRET Quentin (dir.), Net et Terrain. Ethnographie de la n@ture en Afrique, Paris, Edition des archives contemporaines, pp. 93-119.</reference>
        <reference>Selwyn T. (ed.), 1996, The Tourist Image : Myths and Myth Making in Tourism, London, Johm Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</reference>
        <reference>Urbain J.-D., 2010, « Lieux, liens, légendes », Communications, n° 87, pp. 99-108.</reference>
        <reference>Urry J., 1990, The Tourist Gaze : Leisure and Travel in Contemporary Society, London, Sage.</reference>
        <reference>Winkin Y., 2011, Anthropologie de la communication, Paris, Seuil.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">About the classification of a site of the region at the Unesco World Heritage, cf. Roger (2011).</note>
        <note id="2">Interview conducted on December 29th 2009 in Ouagadougou.</note>
        <note id="3">The “Lobi country” includes different sociolinguistic groups, including the Lobi per se, the Birifor, the Dagara, the Djan, the Tuni, the Pougouli and the Gan. For a synthetic work on these societies located on both sides of the borders between Burkina Faso, Ivory Coast and Ghana, cf. Fiéloux et al (1993).</note>
        <note id="4">Like the images and promotional speeches that are spread on the Internet (Royer, 2011), ancient ritual artifacts exposed in museums of primitive art convey and entertain the “illusion” (Price, 2007) of a primordial authenticity. Exhibited as an “invitation to travel”, the few Lobi statuettes, that are installed in darker corners of the Quai Branly museum dedicated to divination in Africa, feed in their own way the tourist fantasies of an “imaginary “Lobi country”” (Kambou-Ferrand, 1993, p. 542).</note>
        <note id="5">Other routes are available and other tourist places are given a tourist reinterpretation, but within the frame of this article, I am studying in a non-exhaustive manner one of the classical tours, taken by most tourists.</note>
        <note id="6">The permanent exhibition is based on a division into three spaces respectively dedicated to different sectors of activity and types of objects: a room for women, a room for men and a room for cults. On the matter of the genre of the Gaoua museum, cf. Royer (2009).</note>
        <note id="7">About Dogon and Malike societies from Mali, Anne Doquet is coordinating an IRD (Institut de Recherche pour le Développement) titled “The staging of an Authentic Africa”.</note>
    </notes>
</article>