<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_CMPNAMT_56-84_Pl_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/597" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.597</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>7</numero>
        <annee>2015</annee>
    </meta>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Moura de Paulo" prenom="Carla">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="pt_CMPNAMT_56-88_Pl_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/610" lang="pt">Políticas públicas e experiências locais de turismo de paisagens : o exemplo do Pantanal</publication>
                <publication id="es_CMPNAMT_55-93_Pl_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/604" lang="es">Políticas públicas y experiencias del turismo local de los paisajes : el ejemplo del Pantanal</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                PhD in Environmental Science, PROCAM, Universidade de São Paulo 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Aparecida de Mello-Théry" prenom="Neli">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="pt_CMPNAMT_56-88_Pl_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/610" lang="pt">Políticas públicas e experiências locais de turismo de paisagens : o exemplo do Pantanal</publication>
                <publication id="es_CMPNAMT_55-93_Pl_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/604" lang="es">Políticas públicas y experiencias del turismo local de los paisajes : el ejemplo del Pantanal</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Geographer, Associate Professor, EACH, PROCAM, Universidade de São Paulo 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Public policies and local experiences of landscape tourism : the example of Pantanal</titre>
    <resume>
        This article analyses public policies and local experiences of tourism in Brazilian Pantanal through environmental approach using geographical categories of analysis. It is structured on four items that address tourism policy, its organization and governance, its relations with environmental policy represented by territories of environmental conservation, analysing the role of these Pantanal policies in multiple scales. To analyse the roles undertaken by Pantanal policies on Pantanal complex it became necessary to give some elements that characterizes it. Thus, considering tourism policy in its territorial aspect, our objective is to highlight relations between transformations in Pantanal region as it turned itself into a tourist destination and actions of public policies in their multiple administrative scales that can influence the process.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            We take as assumption that tourism has a strong potential to bring about changes in territories, at times conducting to geographic spaces restructuring so that tourism policy may be classified as a territorial vector, building (or not) perceived relations. Our environmental approach, besides this aspect, favours tourism carried out in conserved natural environments, mainly as private reserves of environmental protection. However, although as a strategy from tourism policy, this kind of activity is not authorized by managing agencies of environmental policy in full protection unities of conservation such as national parks.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            Obviously policies should be coherent. However, one notices difficulties of articulation between objectives, guidelines and strategies of national, international and also regional policies. How do they address their different issues so that a nationwide concern may be also a reflection of local yearnings ?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            To understand the governance instruments of policies and public action and check out how much they consider the advancement in knowledge and the wishes of actors involved in the elaboration and operationalization process is one of our concerns as we analyse local policies and experiences.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            Pantanal experience is our case study (Paulo, 2011), since several places in the context of this great biome are considered tourist destinations and, as such, promote visible transformations in landscapes and neighbouring cities. But why we choose Pantanal ?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            Because Pantanal is one of the world’s largest wetlands and stretches for approximately 160,000 Km2 through Brazilian, Bolivian and Paraguayan territories, although it is mostly – almost 90 % – in the States of MatoGrosso and MatoGrosso do Sul (CI, 2003). Its scenic beauties, the large number of fauna and flora’s diversity are elements that increasingly attract regional, national and international tourists.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            Pantanal complex is part of Alto Paraguai Hydrographical Basin, with a territorial extension of 361,666 km2 in its Brazilian part, occupying 38.21 % of its total area (PCBAP2, 1997). ParqueNacional do Pantanal (Pantanal National Park), that is a RAMSAR ranch and some Private Reserves of Natural Heritage are situated within this complex and are tourist destinations.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Policies of Tourism and the territories of environmental preservation</section>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            In 2002,Embratur/Ministry of Tourism carried out a diagnosis on the issue that moves billions of Reais per year, for by that time there were forecasts of accelerated growth for this segment, a factor that resulted in greater movement of passengers landed in the countryside of the national territory. Data from 2014 point a 4.06 % growth between 2012 and 2013. However, in the internal context, the country does not rate as a significant destination. Instead, Brazilian tourism is made with e for Brazilians.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            This diagnosis considered Brazilian situation in that year, defined a set of usual concepts nowadays within this sector and had as one of research axis tourism in national and state parks of Itatiaia (RJ), Aparados da Serra (RS), Fernando de Noronha (PE), Caparaó (MG), Foz do Iguaçu (PR), Chapada dos Veadeiros (GO), Pantanal (MT), Jalapão (TO), Manaus (AM) and Brotas (SP). Their results confirmed the influence that many of them have on their surroundings. Usually visitors and attenders are from closer regions, except PN Fernando de Noronha. To this park approximately 80 % of visitors come from south and southeast regions, while in Foz do Iguaçu the predominance is of tourists from São Paulo, Rio de Janeiro and Rio Grande do Sul and in Pantanal of residents from MatoGrosso, São Paulo and Minas Gerais. Thus the closest users reinforce the vector of territorial, local or regional dynamics. Data corroborate the influence reduced to long distance, considering that foreigners represent only 15 % of visitors in unities of conservation. In Pantanal, 80 % of foreigner visitors are European.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            The study highlighted that : i) these locations “are territorial spaces with relevant natural characteristics, legally instituted by public power, objectives of conservation and defined limits, under special administration regime, to which adequate guarantees of protection to keep natural resources in their original state are applied” ; ii) ecologic tourism has its nature in natural areas planned use with premises of social, economic and ecological sustainability, so that the approach of man with nature is mild (Mendonça, 2001 ; Sandeville Jr., 2002).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            Framed as a new business for moving billions of dollars (10.8 billion dollars in 2005), projections over 30 % per year (year of reference 1994-1995) appointed an accelerated growth of ecologic tourism in the country, according to Brazil Institute of Ecotourism, while the world average is of 20 %. Estimates that in 2005 ecologic tourism represented 15 % of the total movement (WTTC, World Travel &amp;amp; Tourism Council).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            Still according to that diagnosis, resources and natural beauties such as caves, deserts, rivers, lagoons, rapids, waterfalls, forests, mountains, canyons, wetlands, coastline, islands, plateaus, plains and biodiversity, along with cultural aspects, substantiated expectations on the promising development of ecological tourism, for approximately 90 % of interviewees showed interest in returning. The most visited parks were Itatiaia ; Fernando de Noronha ; Chapada dos Veadeiros ; Serra dos ÓrgãosandFoz do Iguaçu. It is worth mentioning, however, that the stay was relatively short – 2 days on average (Foz do Iguaçu) or 8 days at most (Fernando de Noronha, Manaus, Pantanal, Chapada dos Veadeiros and Jalapão).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            Considering only the main reasons for satisfaction, the interviewees appointed, by the order, natural beauties in ParqueNacional de Itatiaia, ParqueNacional de Aparados da Serra, ParqueNacionalMarinho Fernando de Noronha, ParqueNacional do Caparaó, ParqueNacional de Foz do Iguaçu, ParqueNacionalChapada dos Veadeiros, ParqueNacionalPortão do Pantanal, Brotas and in Manaus, besides natural beauties, the jungle, forest, river and igarapés have been added. Only for ParqueNacionaldoJalapão another reason was highlighted : the interest of tourists in returning to know better all corners of the park. The evaluation of conservation unities by users was also positive – around 80 % stated it is good – as far as these areas state of conservation is concerned.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            Thus, one of the consequences of the study was the joint elaboration of the Public Use and Ecotourism Programme in National Parks – opportunity of business, by EMBRATUR and ICMBio – Institute Chico Mendes of Biodiversity Conservation (at that time IBAMA). However, in the context of the National System of Conservation Unities law there is not yet authorization for wide circulation of people in protected territories, so that in order to be admitted as visitor in full protection unities, reasons and objectives of the visit must be approved.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Policy and Governance Structure of Tourism National Policy</section>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            Although the Ministry of Tourism has invested on Tourism National Plans between 2003-2007 and 2007-2010, and conceived them in order to make tourism an inductor of social inclusion and domestic market expansion and strengthening (characteristics that could transform the activity into a mechanism for country’s betterment) such initiatives were not analysed in the book Ten Years of post-liberal governments in Brazil : Lula and Dilma (Sader, 2013). It is worth noticing that there was just one mention to tourism when GlauberPiva includes in his text “Culture : public policies and new visibilities”, the idea that public policies cannot be reduced to assistentialist policies, therefore, far from any performance review of such policies.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
             With social tourism as main focus of Tourism National Plans, the ministry considers that the National Plan 2013-2016 consolidates the Tourism National Policy (PNT) by integrating PPA 2012/2015.Strategic orientations for the development of the activity concentrate on national and international market and stimulates the achievement of aims such as encouraging Brazilians to travel through the country ; expanding both foreign exchange generation and the arrival of foreign tourists ; increasing Brazilian tourism quality and competitivenessand preparing Brazilian tourismfor mega events. Elaborated according to federal government guidelines, the plandefines contributions of the sector for social and economic development, as well as eradication of poverty.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            Although tourism in areas of conservation and the enhancement of ecologic tourism are not explicit on PNT, it highlights regionalization as territorial and institutional approachfor planning. Within the framework of management it lays out guidelines such as participation and dialogue with society, generation of job opportunities and entrepreneurship and incentive to innovation and knowledge.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            In this sense, we consider thatParqueNacional do Pantanal Matogrossensewill continue to be one of tourist destinations, mainly because in the diagnosis, the evaluation/opinion of users are quite positive as far as these areas conservation status of aspects are concerned. Approximately 80 % of visitor opinions considered conservation status of parks visited good or excellent.It means, therefore, that the Park will continue being both an attraction centre and a vector of territorial dynamics in the region.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            In order to make initiatives and investments in the sector possible, one of PNT 2013/2016 objectives is to establish mechanisms that ensure stability and trust in relation to licences, authorizations, concessions and other State requirements for installation and operation of tourist enterprises in the country. Thus, the plan also aggregates a set of information and data that guide actions shared by the Ministry of Tourism and the sector’s productive chain in favour of Brazilian tourism. It also establishes priority actions for which it reorients public and private resources to solve sector’s bottlenecks.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            From governance point of view, the National Council of Tourism and its thematic chambers under coordination of the Ministry of Tourism and having the Secretariat of National Tourism Policies as executive secretariat gathers 70 counsellors, integrating federal government, private initiative and third sector. As most of the councils, it is a coordinating board in charge of advising the ministry of State of Tourism in the formulation and application of National Tourism Policy and plans, programmes, projects and related activities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            There are nine thematic chambers aiming at identifying and discussing specific issues capable of impacting National Tourism Policy.With the support of other internal secretariats of the Ministry, the National Secretariat of Tourism Policies helps in formulation, elaboration and monitoring of the National Tourism Policy, according to guidelines proposed and subsidies provided by the National Council of Tourism. It is up to it also implementing the model of decentralized management of tourism in its managerial and territorial dimensions, aligning actions by the Ministry of Tourism (MTur) with the National Council of Tourism (CNT), the National Forum of Secretaries and State Officials of Tourism (FORNATUR) and the Forums/State Councils of Tourism in the 27 Federal Unities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            How can this governance structure ensure greater involvement both in formulation and completion of public actions ? How concerned segments can be participants, both in elaboration and further stages of implementation ?Moreover, how to make sure that guidelines of this policy consider regional territorial dynamics ?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            Part of the answers to these questions should be based on a process of governmental transparency and dissemination of ideas. Besides the encouragement to technological innovations and the use of potential spaces and regions whose characteristics allow integration of these potentials to local development, these actions are vital to the assimilation of existing policies or to social construction of new proposals.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Characterizing Pantanal Matogrossense</section>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            Located in the heart of South America, “Pantanal Mato-Grossense includes savannah and Chaco ecosystems, besides biotic components of dry Northeast and peri-amazon region” (Ab’Saber, 2006, p. 9).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            We use the geo-system definition (Ross, 2006, p. 30) forPantanal, that is, “it is a clear and well circumscribed landscape that can be, for instance, instantaneously identified in aerial photographs” and because of connections between nature componentsand landscapes dynamics, it should be considered from a regional analysis. Geo-systems are found in constant state of change and natural dynamics. Despite natural occurrence, social and economic factors modify their spatial dimensions once they influence connections and landscapes and therefore interfere on landscapes dynamics – a very important criterion for geo-system classification. A regional-scale analysis of this great plain should consider that the natural dynamics is expressed along with social and economic dynamics in territory modification, through different forms in territory and landscape, by fronts and pioneering advancements and territory depression.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            Thus tourist activity is analysed as change promoter, that is, the one that stimulates dynamics over territory and generates consequent impacts. The relation between them – Pantanal and tourist activity–is the analysed system.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            Pantanal complex is comprised of eco-systems with great diversity and strong intra-eco-systemic connections. Pantanal plain is a wetland that has natural similar formationsthrough its entire extension. Despite environmental and also urban differences – there is great similarity as we analyse it in regional scale.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            Biodiversity arising from the interaction between different eco-systems is favoured and contributes to fauna and flora species diversity. Anta (2004) calls the attention to landscape diversity, the influence of different biomes and the mosaic of environments that are permanently or seasonally flooded, creating landscapeswith distinct characteristics throughout the year. TheSavanna penetrates the entire complex and expresses itself with great strength in central and east portions of the region. The Amazon influences mainly the north of Pantanal, while southwest portion is under influence of the Paraguayan/Bolivian Chaco.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            In this mixture of elements a factor is vital in Pantanal scenario : waters dynamics. During flood seasons, Pantanal complex receives and accumulates waters coming from several regions installed in the place, forming lagoons and permanent or temporary rivers due to low terrain inclination. This characteristic of water retention gives to the place – which would tend to be savannabecauseof low inclination –wet area characteristics. These factors create a differentiated ecologic environment, with some dynamics intrinsic to the place. One may consider that waters dynamics is the main responsible for Pantanal biodiversity. According to Resende (2008) its long life produces adaptations and survival strategies related to local characteristics, besides stimulating the occurrence of migrating fauna.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            Antas (2004) analyses the importance of Pantanal surroundings, considering that this should not be understood only by the plain but also by the influence of natural cycles that occur in plateaus and mountains that surround it, for these places send waters to Pantanal plain. Nutrients from rivers are also carried to the flooded plain, facilitating accumulation of these materials. Three distinct pulses of flood are observed in Pantanal complex : the first, caused by rivers floods, other, by local precipitation that does not receive influence of rivers, and finally, one, caused both by floods and local precipitation. Thus, seasonal variation of hydric regimes offers great variability of habitats, so that the flood pulse is a basic ecological process for biodiversity maintenance (ANTAS, 2004). Landscape diversity is also shaped by interactions with the flood pulse that occurs on the plain. Its interference on animal and vegetal communities is large and affects some plants morphology, besides contributing to biodiversity increase (SCREMIN-DIAS et al., 2011).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            Considering theses factors as essential, our challenge is to understand how Pantanal ecosystem is modified as it receives tourist activities. Or yet, how touristic activity should be seen as a generator of changes occurred within the territory studied.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Tourism in Pantanal</section>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            Brazilian Pantanal wild areas and their diversified landscapes attract domestic and foreign tourists, and become an important source of income to the place. Paulo (2011) states that the activity started to grow in early 90’s, the same way that PCBAP3 (1997)also points out a tourism growth in Brazil countryside during the 80’s, increasing between late 80’s and early 90’s. These data supported MatoGrosso Tourism State Policy (2003) contributing to the attraction of new investments, valued by the creation of an advertising campaignto disseminate the region during the 80’s. “MatoGrosso, a natural paradise waits for you” focused on selling and dissemination of natural beauties and contributed to the consolidation of touristic products and activity’s operationalization.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            A marketing and advertisement strategy – the project “Ecological Tourism” of EMBRATUR (1988) –aimed at increasing touristic flow by exploring natural beauties of the territory.At that time, touristic activity was already considered by the Federal Government a promoter of sustainable development for the region. So possibilities that Pantanal landscapes become a new economic basis for regional development are valued, although some negative aspects and problems related to lack of basic infrastructure and planning for consolidation of tourism in Pantanal have been highlighted(PCBAP1, 1997).In governmental plans, the discourse of sustainability is recurrent, without the establishment of measurable benchmarks(limitation of visits based on load capacity, supply infrastructure, sanitation and garbage destination, for instance). Advertising has served to increasingly attract tourists to Pantanal, in cities more and more precarious.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            Pantanal Matogrossense National Park and Private Reserves of Natural Heritage<a href="http://viatourismreview.com/2015/09/art3/#_edn1">[</a><a href="http://viatourismreview.com/2015/09/art3/#_edn1">]</a> (RPPN) in its surroundings are part of the environmental conservation recognized as World Heritage and Unesco Biosphere Reserve. Both the Park and RPPN Sesc Pantanal are included in the Convention of Ramsar. It is worth noting that the National Park has a management plan, in compliance with the law of the National Conservation Unit System – SNUC (law 9985/2000), in which a typology of zones is defined along with its respective use, including those destined to visitation. However, ICMBio (2014) highlights that visitation to the Park is not free yet, so it is not considered a tourist destination.It will only be possible if there is a “special licence for purposes of promotion” from the managing body. Therefore, tourism is practiced at RPPN of Eco-tropic Foundation and in other reserves of regional farms, which should also have a management plan.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            In Pantanal of MatoGrosso do Sul, the issue and the negative impacts have been both identified according to a typology of tourism and its establishments : camping, hospitality sector and fishing. The greatest problem is the lack of infrastructure and local services. Camping and ranch activities promoted physical disfigurement and areas pollution ; hospitality sector produced mainly solid waste, water, noise and environmental pollution. For lack of adequate places for waste disposal it ends up being incinerated or placed on rivers and lagoons banks and, during rain seasons, carried into them. Other worrying factors also related to hotel tourism are : untreated sewage discharged on rivers and lagoons and the intense use of generators and outboard engines that cause sound and environmental pollution. Fishing tourism has impact related to animal hunting and effects resulting of movement of motorboats, highlighting waters pollution, shoals stress and fauna disturbance. There is great accumulation of solid waste and disfigurement of riparian forests in areas with fishermen concentration. In general, the impacts of tourism expansion mean increase in consumption due to the number of visitors and that is reflected on the increase in the use of local natural resources and degradation of environmental quality.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            During the 90’s, the sewage treatment in MatoGrosso cities was practically non-existent and very few connections would take direct effluents to water bodies orETEs without operational conditions, with rudimentary pits remaining as main means for disposal. Municipalities of cities belonging toAlto Paraguai Basin left their solid waste at open dumps, on the soil or in ditches, among them, the situation of southern MatoGrosso citieswas not that different, and most of them used home pits or had incomplete sewage systems, destining part of them to watercourses. The same scenario would be repeated in the neighbour State as for solid waste. The non-existence of a Tourism Master Plan and the massive exploitation in both States hindered the organization of touristic activity, preventing it of being a vital element for local development (PCBAP1, 1997).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            After almost 20 years following the identification of problems mentioned, little has changed. Paulo (2011) states that tourism agents still need to clarify visitors about the conditions of infrastructure and difficulties found during flood and ebb seasons. Basic infrastructure necessary to touristic development and service to resident population is still insufficient. Problems related to collection and sewage treatment, distribution of treated water and activity planning in an integrated manner on several levels of public power – issues identified for years – remain unsolved.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            The table below shows basic sanitation conditions in touristic cities of Brazilian Pantanal studied by Paulo (2011)inAquidauana, Corumbá, Poconé andCáceres. Data collected in field and by IBGE – Brazilian Institute of Geography and Statistics – present local demands service capacity related to water and sewage.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            These data update information ofPCBAP (1997) about collection conditions and final destination of solid waste in cities of Alto Paraguai Basin inMatoGrosso do Sul.This Plan indicated that tourism already occurred massively in 1997, despite unsafe conditions of service to basic sanitation, a fact that has not changed over these years. The table portrays that destinations for dumps continue, in spite of demands from the National Policy of Solid Wastes (2010) and the growth of tourism in these cities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            Tourism was expected to become the most solid basis of local development, but data show that the activity has not brought positive changes. On the contrary, it only puts still more pressure on a precarious system of collection and treatment of solid wastes, thus generating more negative than positive impacts to local environment.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            Lack of infrastructure for services of tourism and resident population compromises environmental quality of this space. Tourism becomes a pressure factor that modifies the environment in many ways : through the construction of tourist developments, by paving highways and by impacts caused by execution of touristic activities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            Among construction, expansion and paving of highways, there are intense changes in Pantanal landscapes, for some highways get into wild areas and facilitate exploitation of areas previously inhospitable. In addition, they also are configured as access roads for several types of visitors, promoting predatory activities such as illegal hunting and fishing.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            Trying to highlight the evolution of tourism in Pantanal cities, the chart below points out modifying landscape aspects and potential environmental impacts that took place between 1990 and 2010, where X means that the process was identified, while 0 means non-identification.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Pantanal policies and actors in multiple scales</section>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            The lag between public policies and actions in different governmental scales is repeated in Brazilian Pantanal, promoting inefficiency and inefficacy of publicactions. This mismatch between several levels of policies management elaboration ends up becoming critical and reducing the capacity of regional development positive transformation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            In the international context, the Convention of RAMSAR (1971) aims at supporting humid areas all over the planet, so that the encouragement of protection falls on conservation of environments more appropriate to migratory and aquatic birds that depend on international efforts (BRASIL, 1996). Brazil became a signatory in 1996, committing to support and coordinate policies aimed at the conservation of humid areas and fauna and flora related to the environment. Pantanal has two Unities of Conservation considered RAMSAR sites : Reserva Particular doPatrimônio Natural SESC Pantanal andParqueNacional do Pantanal Matogrossense.To keep track of the commitments, Brazil created the National Council of Humid Zones (CNZU), comprised of 23 members of governments and civil society that elaborated 6 recommendations until 2014 (Tozato, 2014).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            In national scale, the only instrument of benefit to regional planning is old – Conservation Plan of Alto Paraguai Basin – PCBAP, produced by the federal government in 1997 and that had as result the general diagnosis of Pantanal and the definition of zoning unities with specific guidelines. Subsequently, no other in-depth study has been elaborated, so there is need of data updating.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            At the state level, the Association of Cities with Tourist Potential – AMPTUR has aimed to stimulate the sector, since 1993. A MatoGrosso State Policy of tourism was elaborated in 2013 bySEDTUR (State Secretariat of Tourism Development). Their actions try to draw closer public management and private sector and present the activity as a strong economic and social vector for the State. Decentralized management was strengthened in order to promote the participation of all tourism chain and to stimulate partnerships with regional entrepreneurs. Three strategic lines were established to ensure MatoGrossocompetitiveness in the market : strengthening of tourism structure, development of productive chain and promotion and advertisement. This policy encourages strategic areas, designed for tourism municipalisation and regionalization, but does not cite prioritized locations, and there is not yet ecological-economic zoning that may induce touristic use in specific zones.This strategy is considered as an attempt to empower municipalities and make defined actions to materialize locally.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            Still in state scale, the paving of MT-370road is classified as an action directly influenced by tourism industry, that is, a state policy to facilitate activities development in the city. In a section that links Poconés’ urban centre to the Pantanal community of Porto Cercado, where Sesc Pantanal – Hotel Porto Cercado is located, 42 kilometres were paved. This work aimed to increase visitation to this tourism enterprise, once it had an agreement between the State Infrastructure Secretariat andSesc Pantanal for fundraising (SINFRA-MT, 2010).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            Therefore, the need of infrastructure for access to the hotel stimulated the execution of the work, which reduced arrival time to the location, besides transportation logistics cost.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            In this case, tourism is identified as a fomenter factor for changing of Pantanal landscape due to paving and grounding corixos.Sinfra-MT (2010) indicates thatthe road was built with an average of 2 and a half meters above region’s level, to prevent impassability during rain seasons and enabling access to Pantanal throughout the year. Short time after paving, local residents indicated an increase in cases of wild fauna run over – an important impact to be attributed to local tourism encouragement.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            On the other hand, in MatoGrosso do Sul, MatoGrosso do Sul State Programme of Territorial Management – Lawnr. 3839/09–establishes governmental strategies for implantation of a state territorial management, focused on the Ecological-Economic Zoning (ZEE/MS). Some instruments of territorial management are mentioned as legal framework. This zoning approval is, in fact, the main objective of such legislation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            As an instrument of planning for Pantanal, the zoning establishes 10 zones, among which two stand out : Pantanal Plain Zone – ZPP and Pantanal Plain Protection Zone – ZPPP. ZPP guidelines indicate activities historically adapted to the environment, such as traditional farmed and fishing tourism, which although culturally accepted, can be harmful if not performed with due care and planning. The document highlights the importance of investments in activities that help sustainable developmentand are capable of integrating local culture, recommending cattle (historical and cultural) and tourism (MATO GROSSO DO SUL, 2009). The Pantanal Plain Protection Zone(ZPPP) can be understood as a buffer zone for Pantanal, once recommendations soil usage are less restrictive than ZPP. In this zone, agricultural use, incentive to tourism and production alternative activities (beekeeping, handicraft, floriculture, etc.) as well as creation of mechanisms for Payment of Environmental Services are all recommended (MATO GROSSO DO SUL, 2009).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            These zones are part of MatoGrosso do SulPantanal zoning and are also important for regulation of soil use in Pantanal plain, preserving its good conservation status. However, it is essential to highlight the needof a regional planning policy for the Brazilian Pantanal, capable of integrating the states of MatoGrosso and MatoGrosso do Sul, dealing with it as a unique complex that is not defined by administrative limits. For this purpose, it is indispensable to consider the true natural limits of Pantanal complex, integrating in such policy all its territorial extension. At last, the focus falls on Pantanal landscape, specifically on the definition of tourism development axis and intends to stimulate the state tourism corridor, incorporating in its layout landscapes with environmental, heritage, paleontological and archaeological values (MATO GROSSO DO SUL, 2009).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="53">
            Considering aspects of conserved natural environments restructuring – national natural parks– through dynamics and territorial policies nurtured by tourism, EMBRATUR has pointed, since the beginning of years 2000s, that there would be an accelerated growth of this segment in the country – an argument present in the diagnosis performed with users/attenders in national and state parks, once estimations previewed a growth of 30 % for the country while the worldwide average represented only 15 %. The effects of this diagnosis included partnerships between institutions responsible for the execution of both tourism national and conservation unities national policies.Simultaneously, as a way of increasing the participation of segments involved in these policies and their decentralization, the governance structure of tourism national policy was established, with the implantation of the National Council of Tourism, gathering representatives from Federal Government, private initiative and third sector.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="54">
            In addition, social-economic dynamics in regions where there is influx of tourists cause changes in territorial organization on account of new activities, infrastructure equipment and migratory processes location and especially because they specialize in territory. These dynamics also representanthropic modifications in Pantanal geo-system, which add to the constant state of natural dynamics modification.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="55">
            Brazilian Pantanal wild areas are important local income sources, and have been considered a tourist activity that promotes sustainable development.Pantanal, inscribed as World Heritage and Unesco Biosphere Reserve, is part ofthe convention of Ramsar. However, there has been a contradiction between international, national and state scales. In the states scale, tourism policies in Brazilian Pantanal reinforce this knowledge, although they highlight that infrastructure and impact conditions locally generated are an obstacle for the activity development. In contrast, nationallyICMBiostill does not consider this National Park as a tourist destination, allowing only scheduled visitations.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="56">
            Although the National Policy has as guideline the reinforcement of tourism in natural areas, this same guideline is not explicit as for the environmental conservation policy. Locally, governments ofMatoGrossoandMatoGrosso do Sul induce to the attraction of tourists, even if such dynamics is, for them, an embarrassment as it exposes the need of appropriate infrastructureboth of hotel industry and waste destination or of access to national parks.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>AB’SABER, A. N. Brasil : paisagens de exceção. O Litoral e o Pantanal Mato-Grossense. Patrimôniosbásicos. Cotia : Ateliê Editorial, 2006.</reference>
        <reference>ANTAS, P. T. Pantanal : guia de aves. Rio de Janeiro : SESC, DepartamentoNacional, 2004.</reference>
        <reference>BRASIL. DECREE nr. 1905, of May 16th 1996. It promulgatesthe Convention on Humid Zones of International Importance, especially as Habitat of Water Birds, known as Convention of Ramsar, of February 02nd1971. Brasília, 1996.</reference>
        <reference>CASTRO, I. E. de.Paisagem e Turismo.De estética, nostalgia e política. In : YÁZIGI, E. (Org.). Turismo e paisagem. São Paulo : Contexto, 2002.</reference>
        <reference>CI – Conservation International.Pantanal. Belo Horizonte, 2003.Available at&lt;http://www.conservation.org.br/onde/pantanal/&gt;AcessonSep. 13.08.</reference>
        <reference>DANTAS, M. Pulso de inundação, biodiversidade e produtividade no Pantanal. IV Simpósiosobrerecursosnaturais e Sócio-econômicosdo Pantanal. Corumbá : SIMPAN, 2004.</reference>
        <reference>MARIANI, M. A. P. &amp; GONÇALVES, H. C. Osimpactosambientaisdecorrentes das atividadesturísticas no pantanalsul-matogrossense (MS, Brasil). In : LEMOS, A. I. G. de. (Org.). Turismo : impactossocioambientais. São Paulo : Hucitec, 2001.</reference>
        <reference>MATO GROSSO. PolíticaEstadual de Turismo de MatoGrosso 2004-2013.Secretaria de DesenvolvimentodoTurismo de MatoGrosso – SEDTUR, 2003. Availableat&lt;http://www.sedtur.mt.gov.br/adm/uploads/downloads/2e624diagnostico_turismo_revisado.pdf&gt; Accesson Oct.15.2011.</reference>
        <reference>MATO GROSSO DO SUL. LAW nr.3839, of December 28th 2009. It establishesthe MatoGrosso do Sul State Programme of Territorial Management (PGT/MS) ; it approves the First Approach of MatoGrosso do Sul Ecological-Economic Zoning (ZEE/MS), and makes other provisions. MatoGrossodoSul, 2009.</reference>
        <reference>PAULO, C.M. Dinâmica territorial no Pantanal brasileiro : impactos do turismo e propostas de planejamento. 2011. 190f. Dissertação (Mestrado) – Programa de Pós-GraduaçãoemCiênciaAmbiental – PROCAM, Universidade de São Paulo – USP, São Paulo, 2011</reference>
        <reference>PCBAP1 – Plano de Conservação da Bacia do Alto Paraguai – Pantanal. AnáliseIntegrada e Prognóstico da Bacia Alto Paraguai.Ministério do MeioAmbiente, dos RecursosHídricos e da Amazônia Legal : Brasil, 1997.</reference>
        <reference>PCBAP2 – Plano de Conservação da Bacia do Alto Paraguai – Pantanal. ResumoExecutivo.Ministério do MeioAmbiente, dos RecursosHídricos e da Amazônia Legal : Brasil, 1997.</reference>
        <reference>PCBAP3 – Plano de Conservação da Bacia do Alto Paraguai – Pantanal. Sócio-economia de MatoGrosso.Ministério do MeioAmbiente, dos RecursosHídricos e da Amazônia Legal : Brasil, 1997.</reference>
        <reference>RESENDE, E. K. de.Pulso de inundação : processoecológicoessencial à vida no Pantanal. Corumbá : Embrapa Pantanal, 2008. Disponívelem&lt;http://www.cpap.embrapa.br/publicacoes/online/DOC94.pdf&gt;Acessoem 20.out.2011.</reference>
        <reference>ROSS, J. L. S. EcogeografiadoBrasil : subsídiosparaplanejamentoambiental. São Paulo : Oficina de textos, 2006.</reference>
        <reference>SCREMIN-DIAS, E. ; LORENZ-LEMKE, A.P. ; OLIVEIRA, A. K. M.The floristic heterogeneity of the Pantanal and the occurrence of species with different adaptive strategies to water stress. Brazilian Journal of Biology, São Carlos, vol. 71, n.1, p. 275-282. 2011.</reference>
        <reference>EMBRATUR. Estudosobre o turismopraticadoemambientaisnaturaisconservados.Relatório Final, FIPE/EMBRATUR/Ministério do Turismo. São Paulo, s/ed., dezembro.2002</reference>
        <reference>SADER, E. (org.) 10 anos de governospós-neoliberais no Brasil : Lula e Dilma. São Paulo, SP : Boitempo ; Rio de Janeiro : FLACSO Brasil 2013.</reference>
        <reference>SANDEVILLE JR., E. A paisagem natural tropical e suaapropriaçãopara o turismo. In : YÁZIGI, E. (Org.). Turismo e paisagem. São Paulo : Contexto, 2002.</reference>
        <reference>SINFRA – Secretaria de Estado de Infraestrutura do MatoGrosso. Pavimentação. MatoGrosso, 2010.</reference>
        <reference>TOZATO, H.C. Impactos das mudançasclimáticasnabiodiversidade das zonasúmidas :umaanálisesobrepolíticaspúblicas do Brasil e da França. 2014. Teseem co-tutela(Doutorado) – Programa de PósGraduaçãoemCiênciaAmbiental, Universidade de SãoPaulo, São Paulo, DoctoratemGéographie, Université de Rennes 2, Rennes (França), 2014.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">RPPN is a category of conservation unity established in law 9985/2000 and that is created in private area by public power. After it is created, it is impossible not to respect such determination and type of use.</note>
        <note id="2">This information was identified through bibliographical analysis, field researches and statistical data usage and its objective systematization to show landscape modifying activities stimulated by tourism. It is worth noting that some actions are common to cities, with particular attention to the launching of in natura waste in bodies of water (information obtained in interviews with employees and managers of tourism enterprises indicated the non-existence of adequate treatment).</note>
    </notes>
</article>