<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_CCAS_40-130_Gs_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6097" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.6097</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>18</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="6066">
            <traducteur nom="Mc" prenom="Anne" />
            Recul des glaciers et appréhension des changements climatiques par les acteurs touristiques locaux. Le cas de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc dans les Alpes françaises
        </original>
        <traduction lang="it" source="6132">L’arretramento dei ghiacciai e la comprensione del cambiamento climatico da parte degli attori del turismo locale. Il caso di Chamonix-Mont-Blanc nelle Alpi francesi</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Clivaz" prenom="Christophe">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_MLCCHF_11-91_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5756" lang="fr">Ré-invention des territoires touristiques : quelle transition pour les stations des Alpes ?</publication>
                <publication id="fr_CCAS_39-155_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6066" lang="fr">Recul des glaciers et appréhension des changements climatiques par les acteurs touristiques locaux. Le cas de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc dans les Alpes françaises</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Institute of Geography and Sustainability, Faculty of Geosciences and Environment, University of Lausanne 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Savioz" prenom="Alexandre">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_CCAS_39-155_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6066" lang="fr">Recul des glaciers et appréhension des changements climatiques par les acteurs touristiques locaux. Le cas de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc dans les Alpes françaises</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Institute of Geography and Sustainability 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Glacier retreat and perception of climate change by local tourism stakeholders: the case of Chamonix-Mont-Blanc in the French Alps</titre>
    <sousTitre>Peer-reviewed article</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        Climate change strongly impacts tourism activity in the Alps. In this context, how are these changes perceived by tourism stakeholders at the local level? According to the anthropological approach to climate change, the latter is characterized by a multitude of phenomena that generally remain imperceptible to our senses, and this makes understanding matters of climate all the more complicated. By studying the case of the Chamonix valley, characterized by a prominent presence of glaciers in the landscape, we seek to determine the 
extent to which the climate issue is better understood when it materializes in tangible problems such as glacier retreat, which in the eyes of local residents constitutes a visible threat to the tourist potential of the region. Our analysis shows that this is not the case and that the significant presence of glacial landscapes does not facilitate appropriation of the climatic phenomenon by local tourism stakeholders. 
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Numerous works have already underscored the important consequences of climate change for tourism activities in mountain regions (Hall </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2005; Pröbstl-Haider </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019; Scott </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012; Steiger </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2017). This is also the case in the Alps where resorts developed in particular around the practice of mountaineering, then around skiing, two activities that have been appreciably impacted over the last three decades by glacier retreat, the degradation of permafrost, and the increasing scarcity of natural snow. (Bourdeau </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2020; CLIMALPTOUR, 2013; Mourey </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019, 2020). A number of authors also underline the difficulties for decision-makers to imagine development models other than those based on the practice of skiing (Achin and George-Marcelpoil, 2013; Bourdeau 2019; Siegrist </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013; Vlès, 2019). In this context, the present article focuses on the way the local population perceives climate change and whether or not it is considered as a crucial issue requiring a fundamental shift in tourism development. This question is explored by analyzing the case of the Chamonix valley, presented in this article as the section of the valley including the municipalities of Chamonix-Mont-Blanc and Les Houches, a prime location for mountaineering and skiing characterized by a glacial landscape powerfully impacted by climate change</span>.<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Firstly, we will focus on the issue of the perception of climate change and clarify our approach. We will then describe our methodology, before presenting our field of study. Finally, we will present the empirical results of our survey of Chamonix’s tourism stakeholders, then finish by putting into perspective these results in the more general context of the connections between climate issues and tourism development. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. Perception of climate change by local populations </section>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">According to scientific research conducted by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), the phenomenon of climate change is a planetary problem linked to natural and anthropogenic dynamics that are global in nature. In a few decades, the climate phenomenon has become a major contemporary issue and has penetrated all spheres of societies, particularly in the west. It is omnipresent in the scientific world, in the media, and in public debates; it has infiltrated the economic sector as a potential threat and has finally led us to “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">question our way of “living together”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (De la Soudière and Tabeaud, 2009</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">p. 584, our translation). Faced with this major globalizing scientific narrative, the anthropological perspective proposes to understand the climatic phenomenon using local categories created by populations in defined territories (Sourdril and Garine Wichatitsky, 2019). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Its climatic manifestations, including rising temperatures, have a variety of impacts on societies around the world. Climate change is experienced differently due to unique variations of the climate in specific environments, as well as the disparity of socio-economic and cultural contexts (Crate and Nutall, 2009; Cruishank, 2006; Fiske </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2015). Over the past few years, approaches favouring local perspectives on the issue of climate change have been the focus of growing interest within the international community, notably the idea of developing measures adapted to different situations (Jurt </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2015). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mountain regions around the world, including the Alps, are particularly concerned by the effects of the climatic phenomenon. On one hand, the Alps have been diagnosed according to climate models as being very sensitive to the impacts of current changes to the climate (Beniston, 2012). In addition, tourism has been clearly identified as one of the most vulnerable sectors with respect to the biophysical consequences of climate change in mountain regions (Clivaz </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2015; Scott </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012; Steiger </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2017). In the Alpine context, changes in atmospheric processes are expressed through rising temperatures, changes in precipitation, an increase in the rain/snow limit, and a reduction in the snow cover, as well as the melting of glaciers and the degradation of permafrost (Beniston, 2012; Rebetez, 2002). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These environmental changes lead to many social changes for Alpine communities and trigger the implementation of adaptation and mitigation strategies, especially as regards management of natural resources and natural risks, hydroelectric power generation, and tourism planning. In other words, all forms of societal management and nature governance are put into question by the climatic issue. Confronted with this situation, civil society and political stakeholders present a wide range of reactions and divergent positions, a spectrum encompassing fatalism, skepticism, optimism, and denial. These different attitudes depend in particular on how the climate problem is perceived, the reception of scientific predictions, the means available to deal with ecological changes, and the future projections envisaged. While the climatic phenomenon is clearly emerging as one of the greatest challenges of these next decades for Alpine tourism regions (Clivaz </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2015), how it is understood by local populations is not necessarily crystal clear.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In this context, the political authorities and local populations would seem to be confronted less with a rejection of climate issues than with the difficulty of local appropriation of this situation: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The social construction of the climate problem still remains largely to be achieved at the local level” </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Brédif </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2015</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">,</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> p</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> 68, our translation). This characteristic stems, in particular, from the fact that the understanding of climate change exhibited by western populations is mainly inspired by scientific knowledge and its media coverage (Hulme, 2009). This may well be the expression of a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">climate globalization</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” phenomenon, prompting an annihilation of the subjective and “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the anthropological experience”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of climates (Aykut and Dahan, 2014, p. 52, our translation). Climate change is often perceived as a global, abstract, and distant phenomena, even though certain effects can be tangible in local environments (Elixhäuser, 2015). The fact that many consequences of climate change remain imperceptible to our sensorial apparatus makes understanding the phenomenon much more complex (Graef, 2017), and does not create a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">moral imperative”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Markowitz and Shariff, 2012, our translation). Finally, although they are differentiated through a spatial and temporal perspective, confusions between the notions of weather and climate are frequent and can be misleading. (Meira and Gonzalez Gaudiano, 2016; Lammel </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            With regard to these characteristics, the evolution of the cryosphere is an exception because the transformation of glacial landscapes occurs very quickly and can be measured visually on the scale of a human life. In fact, the phenomenon of glacier retreat is easily linked to climate change, as a consequence of rising temperatures: “More than many other consequences of climate change, glacier retreat also is easily understood: temperatures warm, and ice melts” (Orlove, 2009, p. 25). Starting from this characteristic of visibility, and in view of the various premises mentioned above concerning the difficulty of appropriating the climatic phenomenon on a local scale, the anthropological approach adopted in this article aims to understand its emergence, its construction, its appropriation, and its interpretation by local tourism stakeholders in a geographical context where glaciers are omnipresent, namely the Chamonix valley. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This article is thus in line with the reflections and perspectives developed by authors from the sphere of the anthropology of climate change, a sub-disciplinary field that is itself intersected by various currents. Anthropologists’ interest in climate issues is relatively recent. It emerged in the 1980s, and accelerated in the late 1990s. (Crate, 2011). Segmented into different approaches, the reflections are focused on various themes: “(…) </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">we [anthropologists] analyze climate change in terms of the human systems that generate greenhouse gases, the ways in which different groups perceive and understand climate change, its varying impact on people around the world and the diverse societal mechanisms that drive adaptation and mitigation</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Barnes </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013, p. 541). This "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ethnoclimatological</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" research (Strauss, 2018, our translation) focuses on understanding local systems for grasping and interpreting climate phenomena throughout the world. Many anthropological surveys on climate issues in mountain regions have been conducted in the Andes (Bolin, 2009; Cometti, 2015; Orlove, 2007; Rhoades </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2008;) or in the Himalayas (Devkota, 2013; Gagné, 2015; Vedwan and Rhoades, 2001), as well as in the Alps, primarily in Switzerland (Strauss, 2009, 2016), in Austria (Elixhäuser, 2015), and in Italy (Jurt </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019; Orlove </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This article has been inspired by five analytical concepts developed by Orlove, Wiegandt, and Luckman in their book </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Darkening Peaks: Glacier Retreat, Science and Society</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The approach developed by these authors is particularly relevant with regard to perspectives borrowed in our investigative work. To understand to what extent a population grasps the phenomenon of glacier retreat, they offer a reflection on the notion of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">perception</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which describes how populations think about glaciers. The notion </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">of observation</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> for its part refers to scientific descriptions based on systematic measures. Then, the idea of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">trends </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">evokes the temporal evolution of glaciers in past decades, along with their projected future. The notion of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">impacts</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> describes the consequences of glacier retreat on surrounding communities. Finally, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">responses</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> refer to measures taken, whether individual or collective, involving adaptation or mitigation (Orlove </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2008, p. 4). An analysis concerning these different concepts has enabled the aforementioned authors to demonstrate that perception of glacier retreat essentially stems from the economic and cultural context: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The editors argue that, in the end, it is the cultural and iconic power of glaciers for humans who both inhabit their presence and who live afar that will be the force to motivate action on climate change</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Crate and Nutall, 2009, p. 19). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Inspired by this approach, we propose in this article a three-step approach. Firstly, we will focus on observations and perceptions of climate change by Chamonix valley tourism stakeholders, highlighting the sensory dimension of the phenomenon because “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Visual and sensory perceptions are key elements of the folk epistemology of climate</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Strauss and Orlove, 2003 cited by Roncoli </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2009, p. 90). This level also encompasses an identification of the various impacts on the region as well as the influence of media and scientific discourse regarding the climatic phenomenon in terms of local understanding of it. In a second phase, the focus will be on interpretations of climate change, i.e. the way tourism stakeholders in the valley understand, explain, and give meaning to what is happening (Cometti, 2015; Crate and Nutall, 2009; Roncoli </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2009;). Thirdly, we will focus on responses and measures developed to confront the various consequences of the climatic phenomenon. Finally, we will discuss the results of the above-mentioned process, which seeks to understand how the climate issue is perceived by tourism stakeholders. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. Methodological specifications</section>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The methodological approach of this article is based on ethnographic survey work, which is firstly expressed by the notion of “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">being there</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Geertz, 1983). It describes an immersive and experiential objective of the field of research involving the physical and prolonged presence of the researcher at his or her place of investigation so as to develop an in-depth understanding of systems of practice and meaning (Roncoli </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2009). This research process is characterized by an inductive stance which consists in not imposing conceptual and theoretical assumptions on those participating in the investigation process. The results of this article stem from research that is part of a doctoral thesis in the completion phase, carried out by the second author under the supervision of the first. Within this framework, several months of field research was carried out in the Chamonix valley between 2016 and 2019. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This lengthy research period allowed for the creation of a network of acquaintances that made it easier to gain access to individuals, social groups, and institutions. It was also used to conduct more than 80 semi-directive interviews with scientists and economic, political, and associative stakeholders in the region. These interviews provided an opportunity to discuss and deepen our understanding of the climatic phenomenon, to identify the challenges facing the Mont-Blanc region, and the responses required to deal with the situation.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Participatory observation could also be undertaken during this inquiry, particularly during scientific expeditions, sightseeing tours, political mobilizations, and public meetings. These research activities provided an opportunity to observe how the climate issue was collectively and politically understood by the population of the valley. The time spent with researchers, guides, and environmental educators, in the mountains and near glaciers, helped us understand how changes in the mountains and glaciers were explained and interpreted. Also, by observing scientists on the Montenvers site presenting the evolution of mountain landscapes to visitors, we could see how they approached these issues with and presented them to the general public and how they linked them to the climatic phenomenon.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Finally, the inquiry brought together a significant body of written documents, grey literature, institutional reports, technical documents, and tourism promotion brochures so as to analyze the way in which the climate issue was raised and presented by the destination in question. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The coherence of our study was not built around a "community" but rather around a phenomenon, climate change, which concerns a group of individuals with divergent interests. For this article, we deliberately focused on "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">tourism stakeholders</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">," understood here as the participants in the study having a direct link with the tourism sector. Aware that in a destination such as Chamonix-Mont-Blanc, a large majority of the economic actors are associated to a greater or lesser extent with tourism activity, we have chosen those with a more direct link to the tourism sector, which in the context of the present research represents a corpus of twenty-two interlocutors, including guides, ski instructors, safety managers, tourism promotion managers, researchers involved in popularizing science, ski lift employees, hut wardens, innkeepers , and town hall officials. A large number of the selected interlocutors are from the region, and all of them without exception live in the valley year-round.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. Chamonix: a tourism and glacial valley</section>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The municipalities (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">communes</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) of Chamonix-Mont-Blanc and Les Houches had, in 2020, about 11,500 permanent residents. The two municipalities have been amalgamated since December 2009, forming the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Communauté de Communes de la Vallée de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (CCVCMB), an intermunicipal public association including the municipalities of Vallorcine, Servoz, Chamonix-Mont-Blanc, and Les Houches with a population of around 13,350 inhabitants. However, according to a tourist office employee surveyed, the valley experiences a significant seasonal variation, with more than “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">80,000 residents during winter and around 100,000 during summer</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.1</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, our translation), a fluctuation that causes specific problems in terms of the organization of society and notably as regards water or waste management. The highest point of the Alps is Mont-Blanc at 4,810 metres in altitude; in this regard, the Chamonix valley represents a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">high point</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” for Alpine tourism (Debarbieux, 2001, our translation) and a destination which has adopted a strategic positioning – that of “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">a</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">natural resource</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.1, our translation) – on the tourism market. Every year, several million tourists visit the valley to contemplate the landscapes and nature, or to venture to high altitudes. Many of them congregate in Montenvers to admire </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Mer de Glace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Sea of Ice), a spectacular glacial valley accessible by way of a rack railway. At the same time, this glacier symbolizes the impact of the climatic phenomenon on the planet as it affects the natural and landscape resources that make Chamonix-Mont-Blanc a renowned destination (Document 1). This means that resident populations of the Chamonix valley are faced with the climatic phenomenon on a daily basis and become direct witnesses without any need for sophisticated measuring tools. Because of its many glaciers visible from the villages, the Chamonix valley represents a privileged location to observe tangible consequences of the climatic phenomenon. In fact, the region is a national, even an international, symbol of the consequences of climate change. On one hand, it is regularly the subject of media coverage concerning the climate issue and, on the other, it represents a popular study area for researchers from different disciplines interested in this phenomenon.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Chamonix valley glaciers hold an important place in the history of the region, and the many anecdotes about them reveal the special relationship that the local populations have maintained with the cryosphere over the centuries. As documented by the historian Le Roy Ladurie, during the 16</span>th<span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and 17</span>th<span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> centuries the glaciers represented a major source of worry and anxiety for the valley’s inhabitants, who sought divine assistance by soliciting the religious authorities of the region (Le Roy Ladurie, 2004). Blessings and processions carried out during this period appear to have been effective in their eyes, since in the Chamonix valley, and more generally in the Alps, glaciers began to retreat as of the second half of the 17</span>th<span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> century (Le Roy Ladurie, 1967). Then, the first English travellers arrived in the region, including Windham and Pococke, who dubbed the glacier </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Mer de Glace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Sea of Ice) at the beginning of the 1740s. They were followed, a few years and decades later, by the arrival of other travellers, including mountaineers, scientists, artists, and naturalists such as Horace-Bénédicte de Saussure. Some of them developed a much more recreational relationship with the high mountains and glaciers of the Mont-Blanc region, while for others the connection was of a more contemplative nature. The first ascent of Mont Blanc, in 1786, had an international resonance, and the reputation of the site spread and attracted an ever-increasing number of visitors during the second half of the 19th century, especially with the appearance of the Grand Tour. This phenomenon of “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mont Blanc mania</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Carey, 2007, p. 504) contributed to the progressive development of Alpine tourism in the valley, whose glaciers and lofty mountain took on an increasing interest for the inhabitants and economy of the valley. Between 1860 and 1890, the municipality of Chamonix started to develop the high mountain in order to “(…) </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">increase the number of tourists</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> […]. </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To achieve this result, the municipality, and the entire population of Chamonix alongside it, had to adapt its vision of the surrounding mountain to that of the tourist clientele</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Debarbieux, 2001, p. 40, our translation). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">After the creation of mule trails, including the pathway leading to the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mer de Glace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, in the 1820s, the first tourist developments of the mountain were initiated with the construction of ten or so buildings, mountain lodges, and shelters, including the Hôtel du Montenvers (Debarbieux, 2001). Then, in spite of protests by the local population, railway projects were completed, including the Montenvers initiative, inaugurated in 1908. In fact, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mer de Glace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> glacier has represented a central tourist attraction of the destination since the 18</span>th<span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> century and continues to lure many visitors to this day: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The</span></em> <em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">rack railway still takes nearly 800,000 people to the glacier each and every year (number provided by ODIT France). Many of them get off there only to visit the Mer de Glace cave, which has been a major tourist attraction for 50 or so years</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Cayla, 2009, p. 100, our translation). According to figures provided by the Observatoire du Mont-Blanc, the Montenvers railway was Chamonix’s most visited tourist site during the 2000-2009 period, with a peak of 960,000 </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">visitors</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 2003.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> As of 2010, visits began to dwindle, with a total of 650,000 people coming to the site in 2016, and the railway surrendered its position as leader to the Aiguille du Midi cable car. However, a redevelopment and upgrading project of the Montenvers site is currently underway and should be completed by 2024; it will notably include the building of an interpretation centre focusing on glacier evolution. Those in charge of the destination are clearly integrating the theme of climate change by showcasing their "glacial heritage," </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For several decades now, the glaciers of the Mont-Blanc range have been significantly impacted by the phenomenon of climate change. This entails new risks, notably with potential serac ruptures; intraglacial, proglacial, or supraglacial lakes (Einhorn </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">., 2015; Magnin </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">., 2015; Vincent </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">., 2012); as well as with issues concerning the valley’s water management policies. In the region’s high mountain areas, this evolution disrupts the operation of recreational activities, including mountaineering, skiing, and hiking, which have to adapt both in terms of practice and seasonality (Cremonese </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019; Mourey </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019; Mourey and Ravanel, 2017; Salim </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2019). Finally, due to the omnipresence of the glaciers, </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">their retreat, </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">as a powerful visual indicator of the consequences of climate change, </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">has become part and parcel of the daily life of valley residents. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In fact, whereas in other places the impact of climate change often takes on an abstract and hardly perceptible character for the uninitiated, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">chamoniard</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> context seemed to us very singular indeed. In this valley, the climate change phenomenon is embodied, tangibly, by glacier retreat, which can be easily seen from the villages (Document 2). Given that “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The direct accessibility of glaciers to human vision has helped to make them a topic of personal and public concern</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Orlove </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2008, p. 5), it appears easier to address these issues in a place like Chamonix, where the effects of climate change are more visible because of this omnipresence / surrounding presence of ice (Strauss and Orlove, 2003; Strauss, 2003, 2012). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This observation is all the more credible given the powerful connection between the inhabitants of the valley and the Mont-Blanc range: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The special symbolic and material relationship that they [residents of Chamonix] have with this lofty glacial mountain is worth much more to them than a property deed. Mont-Blanc is more than merely one of their domains. It is an essential part of their heritage”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Debarbieux, 2001, p. 33, our translation). In summary, the Chamonix valley seems at first sight to be conducive to the development of a particular sensitivity to climate issues. People from Chamonix thus represent a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">frontline community”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Orlove, 2019) due to their proximity to tangible effects of the climatic phenomenon. In addition, strong links exist between residents and the region’s glaciers, connections of an emotional or economic nature. It is interesting to take these various elements into account because “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The representations, sense of attachment, and economic importance of mountains and glaciers contribute to shaping the way local people respond to accounts of climate change from scientists, government agencies, and other organizations</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Roncoli </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2009, p. 92)</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This situation then invites an inquiry into the relationship of residents to the climatic phenomenon as well as to their natural environment which, in constant evolution, is essential to their tourism-centred economic development strategies.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Authorities and elected officials from the valley have proven to be sensitive to the issue, as evidenced by the launching, on a voluntary basis, of a climate plan at the end of the 20</span>th<span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> century. In 2009, a territorial assessment of greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions was initiated, spearheaded by a few members of the federation of municipalities. Encouraged by a national policy supporting local initiatives to fight climate change, this assessment led to a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Plan Climat-Énergie Territorial</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (regional climate and energy plan, or PCET) in 2012, with the goal of implementing territory-wide measures to limit GHG emissions. Designed with the participation of the region’s communities and various civil society stakeholders, this climate plan was adopted voluntarily by the federation of municipalities, then by the town councils.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> By way of the PCET, the CCVCMB promoted individual measures and changes in behaviour as well as public measures, particularly in the transportation and mobility, urban planning and housing, and tourism sectors. This PCET initiative therefore represents an attempt to take ownership of the climate issue on a valley-wide scale. As such, the Chamonix-Mont-Blanc destination assumed a pioneering role in the fight against climate change in mountain areas and was able to benefit from this action by promoting it through strategic communication and by obtaining a number of official recognitions for the region itself. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. How do tourism stakeholders in the Chamonix valley perceive climate change? </section>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the previous section, we have suggested that a particular sensitivity to climate issues could develop in the Chamonix valley, especially due to the strong presence of glaciers. What is the reality in this regard? As previously mentioned, we are presenting the results of our ethnographic survey in three stages in order to answer this question.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Observations, perceptions, and identifications of the impacts of climate change</section>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">By browsing the communication channels regarding the local community’s climate plan, we noted that they regularly have recourse to a common symbolic universe, in particular pictures of glacial landscapes comparing the evolution of glaciers over time (Document 3), symbolic of the ongoing impacts of climate change in the valley (CCVCMB 2012 (a-b), 2016, 2017). This characteristic is highlighted on several occasions and represents undeniable awareness. The finding resonates with the statements made during the vast majority of interviews conducted with tourism stakeholders from the valley, who are aware of the evolution of their immediate environment. The observations are mostly visual, such as the thinning of glaciers and the transformation of mountain faces as well as the acceleration of this process over the last two decades. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Aside from the thinning of glaciers, other perceptible biophysical phenomena have been evoked, such as the shortening of the winter season; the modification of precipitation as observed in the diminishing annual snowfall; the increase in temperatures resulting in hotter summers; episodes of strong winds; and more. In interlocutors’ statements, all these elements are linked to the climate change phenomenon, even though some are not scientifically proven. This could stem from “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">climatic over-interpretation”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of perceptions of current natural phenomena in a context where the climate issue is omnipresent in the media. Other less easily observable characteristics have also been mentioned, such as the migration of certain plant and animal species or the concentration of carbon dioxide (CO</span>2<span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) levels, which may especially influence the state of forest health. This information, which is more difficult to discern without a careful environmental study, may stem from the dissemination of studies carried out by the Research Centre for Alpine Ecosystems (CREA), based in Chamonix since 1996, which examines among other things the evolution of alpine environments in the context of climate change. It may also be a product of media coverage of the phenomenon, the main source of information cited by our interlocutors. On a number of occasions, the climate issue has been combined with or mistaken for another problematized environmental issue in the valley since the early 1990s, namely air quality. In fact, the latter issue was almost systematically addressed by tourism stakeholders without prompting, serving as another illustration of the difficulty in understanding the climate change phenomenon. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Most interlocutors cite economic concerns. In fact, the difficulties for skiable areas due to the lack of snow; restricted access to certain mountain areas; the implementation of adaptation measures; safety issues, including fear of an increase in natural risks and problems of access to certain high mountain areas; the transformation of landscapes; and resource management issues represent threats likely to compromise the tourist attractiveness of the valley and thus the economic future of the entire region. More rarely, for some of the people questioned, the identified impacts related to the climatic phenomenon do not represent a major threat for the valley, currently or from a short-term perspective. Certain interlocutors stress, for example, the advantageous geographical location of the Chamonix-Mont-Blanc destination compared to a large number of other tourist resorts, which are lower in altitude and therefore more vulnerable to the effects of climate change. Some testimonials expressed a certain nostalgia for an era when glaciers reached a very low point in the valley, reflecting an emotional attachment to the mountain that is transforming before their eyes. Others, finally, relativize the effects perceived in the immediate environment and express a more global view of the phenomenon, including geographically or temporally distant consequences. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Multiple interpretations and representations of climate change</section>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Attitudes to climate change have become very politicized in recent years, and even more so since the onset of the student strike for the climate movements, starting in the fall of 2018. In the context of the Chamonix valley, although observations and perceptions of climatic consequences are, with a few exceptions, relatively homogeneous, understanding and interpreting the phenomenon may vary considerably. In order to recreate these observations and perceptions in our article, we propose to classify the different positions according to a number of “discursive registers,” which must be understood as typical ideal categories. In this sense, the “discursive registers” do not refer to categories of people but of discourse regarding the interpretation of climate change. In fact, certain interlocutors will make use of a number of registers. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These “discursive registers” stem from informal discussions and interviews conducted with Chamonix valley residents. They express specific understandings of the climatic phenomenon, its causes, and the issues related to it. Underlying them are different ideological positions and antagonistic values that are at the origin of conflicts concerning the use and representations of nature. In this context of a plurality of interpretations of the climatic phenomenon, nature becomes an issue and its use can lead to different types of confrontations, both discursive and practical. These “discursive registers” therefore crystalize through many themes, such as projects related to tourism in the valley, natural resources management, risk management, future projections for the valley’s development, the use of glaciers,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and more. These differences can cause tensions in the region, by opposing very dissimilar visions of such issues.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The first major distinction is based on the traditional opposition between “skeptical” discursive registers on one hand and “convinced” ones on the other. 1) "Skeptical" views represent only a small minority of the statements collected from tourism stakeholders interviewed and constitute, as such, a separate category. However, a few interlocutors shared a resolutely skeptical view regarding climate change, sometimes denying the existence of the phenomenon, and often denying its anthropogenic causes, while attributing the process of atmospheric warming to natural causes. The vast majority of tourism stakeholders surveyed claim to be convinced of the existence of the climatic phenomenon as well as anthropogenic responsibilities for it. However, statements by convinced interlocutors can be subdivided into different tendencies. 2) "Fatalistic" views, which express the idea that everything is already decided in advance and hence that any remedial action remains useless. This way of thinking leads to profiting from the situation while it is still possible to do so, without questioning any activity in the process. 3) "Optimistic" views, which consider that human beings have always been able to adapt to any situation and that the use of technology, in the current context of climate change, is a conceivable and relevant solution. For this reason, the tourism sector will always find solutions so as to continue its activities. 4) Finally, “alarmist” views, which propose to use the particular situation of the Chamonix valley to raise awareness, in particular among the region’s millions of visitors. Emboldened by alternative proposals, they also denounce an existing system that is struggling to question and reinvent itself. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To illustrate how these discursive registers differ, we can take the example of the link between local environmental transformations and the climate change phenomenon. All of our interlocutors acknowledge the transformation of the valley landscape, in particular due to glacier retreat. However, the explanation for this evolution is not consensual. An interlocutor who is a “skeptic” explains that the current changes are normal processes, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">part of the natural order, in a historical and natural cycle”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (E.3,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation), and thus categorically denies their anthropogenic causes. An “alarmist” interlocutor is very critical of this type of “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">simplistic and self-exonerating”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> reasoning (E.4,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation) and attacks, at the same time, reflections by “fatalists” who accept “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">warming without lifting a finger,</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” and who adhere to what the “alarmist” describes as a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">doctrine of determinism”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (E.4,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). In short, to summarize the argument of our “alarmist,” climate change is typically considered according to “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">personal, ideological, or economic interests rather than scientific reflections”</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (E.5,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). In this regard, the discourse would be guided by selfish interests that prevail over value systems. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Responses to climate change</section>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Climate change, and notably rising temperatures, lead to many biophysical changes in alpine landscapes, as we have already seen. The context calls for measures to counter the effects of climate change. In the tourism sector, these can be adaptation strategies, i.e., individual or collective initiatives designed to reduce the vulnerability of human systems. Adaptation can represent adjustment strategies when it targets the sustainability of current activities, or transformational strategies when it seeks to change the nature of practices themselves (Bonnemains and Clivaz, 2019; Simonet, 2016). The measures can also be mitigation strategies to stabilize concentrations of GHGs in order to limit such emissions. Since 2005, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Communauté de Communes de la Vallée de Chamonix</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> has guaranteed free public transportation in the valley, through a public-private partnership with the bus transport company and the French railway system (SNCF). Other transportation initiatives have been undertaken in subsequent years, including the creation of a sustainable mobility program in 2011. The adoption in 2009 of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Plan Climat Énergie Territoriale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (territorial climate energy plan, or PCET) and its 184 measures, essentially comprising mitigation measures for the reduction of GHGs in the valley, also reflects a willingness on the part of certain stakeholders to take action with respect to the climatic phenomenon. However, it became less important in the following years, because while nearly all of those surveyed had heard about this initiative during its preparatory phase, i.e., between 2009 and 2011, and subsequently when it was adopted by the authorities in 2012, very few of them could explain what had become of it in subsequent years. Finally, in 2019, the Chamonix-Mont-Blanc destination adopted a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Plan Climat Haute Montagne</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (high mountain climate plan), which only includes measures to adapt to the effects of climate change. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">When addressing these different types of measures during interviews with tourism stakeholders, we were able to observe that the “discourse registers” described above clearly crystallize the responses and measures that their proponents wish to see adopted. In other words, these issues represent sources of conflict, tension, and debate in the valley. Concerning the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Plan Climat</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the opinions of the interlocutors were clear-cut. For some of them, this voluntary initiative “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">was only intended as a marketing ploy… To obtain a sort of label signalling a virtuous destination. But behind this, there was no real initiative whatsoever</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.6,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). Other </span><a href="https://www.linguee.com/english-french/translation/interviewees.html">interviewees</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> seem to be more convinced and highlight the positive signal sent by the Chamonix-Mont-Blanc destination to other mountain territories. A guide interviewed claimed that climatic sensitivity emerged at the same time as the climate plan project, but that such concern quickly waned: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For a time, sensitivity concerning the evolution of the climate had become widespread in the valley and among residents of the region. And this also coincided with a more general awareness concerning the evolution of the permafrost. So, at that time, there were real reflections regarding the mountain range, its evolution, and activities occurring there, all of which had been highlighted along with the challenges identified by the climate plan. There were discussions concerning mountaineering itineraries, access to shelters, ski lift anchoring points, the snow cover in skiable areas, increased risk, and more. And for a while, I had the impression that everyone had a vested interest, especially the tourist industry, and that something was really going to take root in people’s mentalities... But this feeling didn’t last and since then... how can I say... With the years, the attitude has changed and people have a different relationship with all this; they say to themselves "we’ll adapt, we’ll see", and today, I have the impression that that’s about as far as they’re willing to go” </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(E.7,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Another topic that is nearly systematically raised by the interlocutors is that of artificial snowmaking. For most of the interlocutors we met, it is logical and necessary to invest in mechanical snowmaking in ski areas in order to guarantee their quality. However, the opinion of other tourism stakeholders concerning this solution is less cut and dried: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This is a subject that wonderfully illustrates the pervasive denial among valley residents with respect to climate change. We continue to invest in the installation of snow cannons while ignoring the prevailing knowledge about temperature inversions, for example… Because snow cannons are useless in hot air. This exemplifies the desire to avoid changing the model and a belief that this will be our saving grace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.8,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Despite the various critical viewpoints regarding mechanical snowmaking encountered during the survey, there is no real debate as such among Chamonix-Mont-Blanc destination stakeholders. Leaving aside the topic of mechanical snowmaking, we concluded that adaptation or mitigation measures seem relatively abstract for a large number of interlocutors. Many believe that management of the effects of climate change must be transferred to local, as well as national, public and political arenas: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">it’s up to elected officials and our minister of the environment to deal with this</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.9,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn13" id="bodyftn13">13</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). On the one hand, these people reference the global characteristics of the climate issue, and on the other, label it as a concern for the authorities rather than for ordinary citizens. Meanwhile, for others, this mode of reasoning represents a form of “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">grotesque self-exoneration</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.10,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). Finally, the least concerned believe that valley residents have always been able, since their arrival in the region, to muster a resilient spirit in the face of "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the vagaries of the environment</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" (E.11,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). For some of them, technical and technological innovations, in particular, will save the day: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">one day we will take charge of changing the precipitation and temperatures</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.11, our translation). Geo-engineering procedures, embodying the pinnacle of the "optimistic" spirit, were, however, rarely referenced during our interviews. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion: The delicate cohabitation of tourism and climate issues at the foot of Mont-Blanc</section>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although climate change had already been familiar issue in the Chamonix valley for several decades, thanks in particular to the interest of researchers and a research centre that studied the phenomenon in a localized manner, it has now been formalized in public life and in the political-administrative apparatus by the will of certain members of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Communauté de Communes</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (community of municipalities). The latter have worked on a public construction of the climate problem in an attempt to locally appropriate the issue so that its importance is recognized at the scale of the entire valley. In this process, the vision of glacier retreat has played a crucial role in educating and mobilizing residents and elected officials alike (JDPMB, 2009). However, the identification of GHGs linked to the valley’s activities has generated a set of paradoxical conundrums: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A research firm was hired to assess GHG emissions in the territory. And very quickly, we realized that 80% of all emissions were linked to travel to the valley by tourist visitors. So, what can be done based on that? We’ve got to focus on the remaining 20%… Because, in reality, 80% of emissions are out of our hands. There are, for example, agreements signed every year with China, representing that country’s commitment to send a certain number of tourists, about one million, or with India … Then there are the day trippers on a return trip from Geneva who head back home after climbing Aiguille du Midi mountain. This may be a bit of an exaggeration, but not much</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.12</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">our translation).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Hence, the first finding derived from this territorial assessment insisted on the importance of tourism as a GHG-emitting sector in the valley while underlining the difficulty of acting at the local level. Several interlocutors denounced this finding and pointed out a contradiction between tourist activity and the adoption of environmental measures by the destination: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The introduction of a climate plan within the framework of the tourism-economic model of the Chamonix valley illustrates the entire schizophrenic approach by those in charge of the destination</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.13, our translation).</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn17" id="bodyftn17">17</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> In summary, the valley situation is a straight jacket: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The problem is that there’s no economic diversity in the valley. 95% of the economy is linked to tourism, so that leaves very little wiggle room</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (E.14,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). Moreover, Chamonix is in a very stable economic situation, with a high level of tourist and financial inflow. Although some interlocutors recognize the excesses of the destination’s tourism development model, this does not lead them to question a system from which they benefit, and whose threats, in terms of temporality, seem to them to be very remote indeed.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">“</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Proposing alternative or sustainable tourism is one thing but proposing an efficient and profitable model is another. Restricting our economic development while nobody else in other sectors is making the least bit of effort would be absurd for the economy of the region and useless considering the overall situation itself. We know today that the curves will probably never change or if they do, only in several hundred years…” </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(E.14,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn19" id="bodyftn19">19</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> our translation). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Others are outraged at this type of thinking and at what has become mass tourism in the Chamonix valley. They propose alternatives which, without completely calling into question the current tourism model of the destination, propose the development of consciousness-raising activities, integrated into the current model: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, the rosy economic situation of the destination makes it difficult to question its development trajectory. It may be pointed out that these two findings, i.e. the difficulty for tourism stakeholders to consider a different development model and look beyond “business as usual” and the “limited wiggle room” for local stakeholders regarding GHG emissions that mainly stem from modes of transport used by visitors to reach the location of their stay, are similar to findings for the Swiss Alps (Clivaz </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Regarding the different biophysical changes perceptible in the environment, and therefore the issue of the visibility of the climatic phenomenon, glacier retreat is clearly the most recurring and salient phenomenon in the eyes of the tourism stakeholders surveyed. In their eyes, the glaciers have social and symbolic importance, and their retreat engenders different types of identifiable impacts. However, despite both the tangible and symbolic importance of glacier retreat in the Chamonix valley, our field survey demonstrates how difficult it is for tourism stakeholders to take ownership of the climate issue at a local level. In this sense, our case study does not confirm the hypothesis developed by Orlove and colleagues. The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Plan Climat Haute Montagne</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, adopted in 2019, confirms what we have observed: it only includes climate change adaptation measures designed above all to maintain the current tourism model. These findings resonate with the reflections of Scott, Hall, and Gössling, who assert that tourism stakeholders “(…) </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">were highly aware of the risk posed by climate change, but also highly optimistic about their capacity to negate the impacts of future climate change</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Scott </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012, p. 277). In Chamonix, the climate change issue is now of course an integral part of the communication and tourism offer of the destination, as evidenced by the current Montenvers redevelopment project which promises to showcase a new glacier interpretation centre by 2024. The fact remains that the strong presence of glacial landscapes, providing a bird’s eye view of glacier retreat, has not fundamentally changed local tourism stakeholders’ perception or understanding of the climatic phenomenon</span>.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Achin, C. and George-Marcelpoil, E. (2013), « Sorties de piste pour la performance touristique des stations de sports d’hiver », Tourisme &amp; Territoires, Vol. 3, pp. 67-92. </reference>
        <reference>Aykut, S.C. and Dahan, A. (2014), Gouverner le climat ? 20 ans de négociations internationales, Presses de la Fondation Nationale des Sciences Politiques, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Barnes, J., Dove, M., Lahsen, M., Mathews, A., McElwee, P., McIntosh, R., Moore, F., O’Reilly, J., Orlove, B., Puri, R., Weiss, H. and Yager, K. (2013), “Contribution of anthropology to the study of climate change”, Nature Climate Change, Vol. 3, pp. 541-544.</reference>
        <reference>Beniston, M. (2012), Changements climatiques et impacts. De l’échelle globale à l’échelle locale, Presses polytechniques et universitaires romandes, Lausanne. </reference>
        <reference>Bolin, I. (2009), “The glaciers of the Andes are melting: indigenous and anthropological knowledge merge in restoring water source”, in Crate S.A. and Nutall M. Anthropology and Climate Change : From Encounters to Actions, California, Left Coast Press, pp. 228-249.</reference>
        <reference>Bonnemains, A. and Clivaz, C. (2019), “Adaptation aux changements climatiques des stations de sports d’hiver dans les Alpes françaises et suisses : quel rôle pour les pouvoir publics ?”, in Gwiadtinski, L. (dir), Tourisme(s) et Adaptation(s), Actes du colloque AsTRES, Elya Editions, Paris, pp. 227-234.</reference>
        <reference>Bourdeau, P. (2019), “Winter Tourism: lost in transition? The process of transformation and inertia of the ski industry and places in the French Alps”, in Pröbstl-Haider U., Richins H. and Stefan Türk S. (Ed.), Winter tourism, Trends and challenges, CABI, Wallingford, pp. 493-508.</reference>
        <reference>Bourdeau, P., Mourey, J. and Ravanel, L. (2020), « Le changement climatique comme facteur de transformation des pratiques de l’alpinisme. Étude de cas dans les massifs du Mont-Blanc, des Écrins (France) et des Alpes Valaisannes (CH) », in Clastres P., Debons D. and Quin G. (Dir.), Gravir les Alpes du XIXe siècle à nos jours. Pratiques, émotions, imaginaires. Presses Universitaires de Rennes: Rennes. </reference>
        <reference>Bredif, H., Bertrand, F. and Tabeaud, M. (2015), « Redéfinir le problème climatique par l’écoute du local : éléments de propédeutique », Natures Sciences Sociétés Supplément, Vol. 23, pp. 65-75.</reference>
        <reference>Carey, M. (2007), “The History of Ice: How Glaciers Became an Endangered Species”, Environmental History, Vol. 12, N°3, pp. 497-527.</reference>
        <reference>Cayla, N. (2009), « Glaciers actuels et géomorphologie paraglaciaire, quelques exemples de valorisation touristique au sein de l’arc alpin », Bulletin de l’Association de géographes français, Vol. 86, pp. 96-109. </reference>
        <reference>CLIMALPTOUR, (2013), Le changement climatique et son impact sur le tourisme dans l’espace alpin. Rapport d’étude Programme espace alpin 2007-2013.</reference>
        <reference>Clivaz, C., Gonseth, C. and Matasci, C. (2015), Tourisme d’hiver. Le défi climatique. Presses polytechniques et universitaires romandes, Lausanne.</reference>
        <reference>Clivaz, C., Doctor, M., Gessner, S., Ketterer, L., Luthe, T., Schuckert, M., Siegrist, D. and Wyss, R. (2012), Adaption des Tourismus an den Klimawandel in den Alpen. Ergebnisse des Alpine Space - Projekts ClimAlpTour in der Schweiz, Schriftenreihe des Instituts für Landschaft und Freiraum, HSR Hochschule für Technik Rapperswil, Nr. 8, Rapperswil.</reference>
        <reference>Cometti, G. (2015), Lorsque le brouillard a cessé de nous écouter. Changement climatique et migrations chez les Q’Eros des Andes péruviennes. Peter Lang, Bern. </reference>
        <reference>Crate, S.A. (2011), “Climate and Culture: Anthropology in the Era of Contemporary Climate Change”, Annual Review of Anthropology, Vol. 40, pp. 175-195.</reference>
        <reference>Crate, S.A. and Nutall, M. (2009), Anthropology and Climate Change: From Encounters to Actions. Left Coast Press, California.</reference>
        <reference>Cremonese, E., Carlson, B., Filippa, G., Pogliotti, P., Alvarez, I., Fosson, JP., Ravanel, L. and Delestrade, A. (2019), AdaPT Mont-Blanc: Rapport Climat : Changements climatiques dans le massif du Mont-Blanc et impacts sur les activités humaines. Rédigé dans le cadre du projet AdaPT Mont-Blanc financé par le Programme européen de coopération territoriale Alcotra Italie-France 2014-2020. </reference>
        <reference>Cruikshank, J. (2006), Do Glaciers Listen ? Local Knowledge, Colonial Encounters, &amp; Social Imagination. UBC Press, Vancouver.</reference>
        <reference>Debarbieux, B. (2001), Chamonix Mont Blanc : les coulisses de l’aménagement. Edimontagne, Servoz. </reference>
        <reference>De La Soudière, M. and Tabeaud, M. (2009), “Introduction. Le ciel comme terrain”, Ethnologie française, Vol. 39, pp. 581-585. </reference>
        <reference>Devkota, F. (2013) “Climate Change and its socio-cultural impact in the Himalayan region of Nepal – A Visual Documentation”, Anthrovision, Vol. 1.2, pp. 1-27. </reference>
        <reference>Einhorn, B., Eckert, N., Chaix, C., Ravanel, L., Deline, P., Gardent, M. and Schoeneich, P. (2015) “Changements climatiques et risques naturels dans les Alpes. Impacts observés et potentiels sur les systèmes physiques et socio-économiques”, Revue de géographie alpine 103-2, pp. 1-33.</reference>
        <reference>Elixhauser, S.C. (2015), “Climate Change Uncertainties in a Mountain Community in South Tyrol”, in Reuter T., Averting a Global Environmental Collapse. The Role of Anthropology and Local Knowledge. Cambridge Scholars Publishing, Cambridge, pp. 45-64.</reference>
        <reference>Fiske, S.J., Crate, S.A., Crumley, C.L, Galvin, K., Lazrus, H., Lucero, L., Oliver-Smith, A., Orlove, B., Strauss, S. and Wilk, R. (2015), Changing the Atmosphere. Anthropology and Climate Change, American Anthropological Association, Global Climate Change Task Force, Washington. </reference>
        <reference>Gagné, K. (2015), When Glaciers Vanish: Nature, Power and Moral Order In the Indian Himalayas, Thèse de doctorat, Université de Montréal.</reference>
        <reference>Geertz, C. (1983), Local knowledge : Further essays in interpretative anthropology. Basic Books, New York. </reference>
        <reference>Graef, D.J. (2017), “Can We “See” Climate Change ?”, SAPIENS, Vol. 19, pp. 1-5.</reference>
        <reference>Hall, C.M. and Higham, J. (2005), Tourism, recreation and climate change. Channel View Publications, Bristol.</reference>
        <reference>Hulme, D. (2009), Why We Disagree About Climate Change. Understanding controversy inaction and oppprtunity, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.</reference>
        <reference>Jurt, C., Dulce, B. M., Vicuna, L., Huggel, C. and Orlove, B. (2015), “Local perceptions in climate change debats: insights from case studies in the Alps and the Andes”, Climatic Change, Vol. 133, pp. 511-523. </reference>
        <reference>Lammel, A., Dugas, E. and Guillen, G.E. (2012), « L’apport de la psychologie cognitive à l’étude de l’adaptation aux changements climatiques : la notion de vulnérabilité cognitive », VertigO : La revue électronique en sciences de l’environnement, Vol. 12 (1), pp. 1-16. </reference>
        <reference>Latzko-Toth, G. and Millerand, F. (2015), « Objet-frontière », in Doray, P., Sciences, technologies et sociétés de A à Z. Presses de l’Université de Montréal, Montréal, pp. 163-165. </reference>
        <reference>Le Roy Ladurie, E. (1967), Histoire du climat depuis l’an mil, Flammarion, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Le Roy Ladurie, E. (2004), Histoire humaine et comparée du climat : Tome 1, Canicules et glaciers XIIIe-XVIIIe siècles, Fayard, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Magnin, F., Brenning, A., Bodin, X., Deline, P. and Ravanel, L. (2015), « Modélisation statistique de la distribution du permafrost de paroi : application au massif du Mont-Blanc », Géomorphologie, relief, processus environnement, Vol. 21, N°2, pp. 145-162. </reference>
        <reference>Markowitz, E.M. and Shariff, A.F. (2012), “Climate change and moral judgment”, Nature Climate Change, Vol. 2, pp. 243-247. </reference>
        <reference>Meira, P. and Gonzalez Gaudiano, E.J. (2016), « Les défis éducatifs du changement climatique : La pertinence de la dimension sociale », Éducation relative à l’environnement, Vol 13, N°2, pp. 1-19. </reference>
        <reference>Mourey, J., Marcuzzi, M., Ravanel, L. and Pallandre, F. (2019), “Effects of climate change on high Alpine mountain environments: Evolution of mountaineering routes in the Mont Blanc massif (Western Alps) over half a century”, Arctic, Antarctic, and Alpine Research, Vol. 51, pp. 176-189.</reference>
        <reference>Mourey, J., Perrin-Malterre, C. and Ravanel, L. (2020), “Strategies used by French Alpine guides to adapt to the effects of climate change”, Journal of Outdoor Recreation and Tourism, Vol. 29, pp. 1-9. </reference>
        <reference>Mourey, J. and Ravanel, L. (2017), « Évolution des itinéraires d’accès aux refuges du bassin de la Mer de Glace (massif du Mont Blanc, France) », Revue de géographie alpine, Vol. 105, N°4, pp. 1-17. </reference>
        <reference>Orlove, B. (2009), “Glacier Retreat: Reviewing the Limits of Human Adaptation to Climate Change”, Science and Policy for Sustainable Development, Vol. 51, N°3, pp. 22-34.</reference>
        <reference>Orlove, B. (2007), Glacier Retreat in the Southern Peruvian Andes: Climate Change, Environmental Impacts, Human Perception and Social Response, AGU Fall Meeting Abstracts.</reference>
        <reference>Orlove, B., Milch, K., Zaval, L., Ungemach, C., Brugger, J., Dunbar, K. and Jurt, C. (2019), “Framing climate change in frontline communities: anthropological insights on how mountain dwellers in the USA, Peru, and Italy adapt to glacier retreat”, Regional Environmental Change, Vol. 19, pp. 1295-1309. </reference>
        <reference>Orlove, B., Wiegandt, E. and Luckman, B. (2008), “The Place of Glaciers in Natural and Cultural Landscapes”, in Orlove, B., Wiegandt, E. and Luckman, B., Darkening Peaks: Glacial Retreat, Science and Society. University of California Press, Berkeley, pp. 3-19.</reference>
        <reference>Pröbstl-Haider, U., Richins, H. and Stefan Türk, S. (Ed.), (2019), Winter tourism, Trends and challenges, CABI, Wallingford.</reference>
        <reference>Rebetez, M. (2002) La Suisse se réchauffe, Le Savoir suisse, Lausanne. </reference>
        <reference>Rhoades, R., Rios, X.Z. and Ochoa, J.A. (2008), “Mama Cotacahi : history, local perceptions, and social impacts of climate change and glacier retreat in Ecuadorian Andes”, in Orlove, B., Wiegandt, E. and Luckman, B., Darkening Peaks : Glacier Retreat, Science, and Society, University of California Press : Berkeley, pp. 216-225. </reference>
        <reference>Roncoli, C., Crane, T.A. and Orlove, B. (2009), “Fielding Climate Change in Cultural Anthropology”, in Crate, S.A. and Nutall, M., Anthropology and Climate Change : From Encounters to Actions, Routledge, New York.</reference>
        <reference>Salim, E., Mourey, J., Ravanel, L., Picco, P. and Gauchon, C. (2019), “Mountain guides facing the effects of climate change. What perceptions and adaptation strategies at the foot of Mont Blanc?”, Journal of Alpine Research, Vol. 107, N°4, pp. 1-15. </reference>
        <reference>Scott, D., Hall, M.C. and Gössling, S. (2012), Tourism and Climate Change. Impacts, adaptation and mitigation, Edition Routledge, New York.</reference>
        <reference>Siegrist, D., Clivaz, C., Doctor, M., Gessner, S., Ketterer, L., Luthe, T., Matasci, C., Schuckert, M. and Wyss, R. (2013), "Adaptation des alpinen Tourismus an den Klimawandel. Ergebnisse des Alpine Space Projekts ClimAlpTour in der Schweiz", in Bieger T., Beritelli P. and Laesser C. (Ed.), Nachhaltigkeit im alpinen Tourismus, Schweizer Jahrbuch für Tourismus 2012, pp. 145-158.</reference>
        <reference>Simonet, G. (2016), “De l’ajustement à la transformation : vers un essor de l’adaptation ?”, Développement durable et territoire, Vol. 7, N°2, pp. 1-17.</reference>
        <reference>Sourdril, A. and Garine-Wichatitsky, E. (2019), « Comment parler du temps qu’il fait à l’heure du changement climatique ? Petit catalogue de « Météorologie locales » », Ethnographiques.org, Vol. 38, pp. 1-18.</reference>
        <reference>Steiger, R., Scott, D., Abegg, B., Pons, M. and Hall, C. (2017), “A critical review of climate change risk for ski tourism”, Current Issues in Tourism, Vol. 22, N°11, pp. 1343-1376.</reference>
        <reference>Strauss, S. (2018), “Ethnoclimatology”, in The International Encyclopedia of Anthropology (En ligne : https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118924396.wbiea2305)</reference>
        <reference>Strauss, S. (2016), “Climate Change in Leukerbad and Beyond: Re-Visionning Our Cultures of Energy and Environment”, in Crate S.A., and Nutall, M., Anthropology and Climate Change : From Actions to Transformations. Routledge, New York, pp. 162-172.</reference>
        <reference>Strauss, S. (2012), “Are cultures endangered by climate change ? Yes, but…”, WIREs Clim Change, Vol. 3, pp. 371-377.</reference>
        <reference>Strauss, S. (2009), “Global Models, Local Risks : Responding to Climate Change in the Swiss Alps”, in Crate, S.A. and Nutall, M., Anthropology and Climate Change : From Encounters to Actions, Routledge, New York, pp. 166-174.</reference>
        <reference>Strauss, S. and Orlove, B. (2003), “Up in the Air: The Anthropology of Weather and Climate”, in Strauss, S. and Orlove, B., Weather, Climate, Culture. Berg, New York, pp. 3-14.</reference>
        <reference>Strauss, S. (2003), “Weahter Wise: Speaking Folklore to Science in Leukerbad, in Strauss S. and Orlove B., Weather, Climate, Culture. Berg, New York, pp. 39-60.</reference>
        <reference>Vedwan, N. and Rhoades, R.E. (2001), “Climate change in the Western Himalayas of India : A study of local perception and response”, Climate Research, Vol. 19, pp. 109-117. </reference>
        <reference>Vincent, C., Thibert, E., Harter, M., Soruco, A. and Gilbert, A. (2015), “Volume and frequency of ice avalanche from Taconnaz hanging glacier, French Alps”, Annals of Glaciology, Vol. 56, N°70, pp. 17-25.</reference>
        <reference>Vincent, C., Six, D. and Thibert, E. (2012), « L’évolution des glaciers alpins et les risques d’origine glaciaire », La Météorologie, Vol. 78, pp. 44-53. </reference>
        <reference>Vles, V. (2019), « Des territoires touristiques en transition, aux abords du point de bascule », in Carrere G., Dumas C. and Zelem M.C. (Ed), Dans la fabrique des transitions écologiques, L’Harmattan, Paris, pp. 75-98.</reference>
        <reference>Sources</reference>
        <reference>CCVCMB, 2012(a), « Plan Climat Énergie Territorial de la Communauté de Communes de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc. Tous concernés ! Des actions concrètes pour vivre durablement dans la vallée », Chamonix.</reference>
        <reference>CCVCMB, 2012(b), « Plan Climat Énergie Territorial de la Vallée de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc. Plan d’action », Chamonix.</reference>
        <reference>CCVCMB, 2012(c), « Plan Climat- Energie Territoriale (PCET) de la Communauté de Communes de la Vallée de Chamonix Mont-Blanc », Chamonix. </reference>
        <reference>CCVCMB, 2016, « Dossier de presse. Environnement et qualité de l’air. Combats et solutions de la Communauté de Communes – Vallée de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc », Chamonix.</reference>
        <reference>CCVCMB, 2017, « Dossier de presse. Environnement et qualité de l’air. Combats et solutions de la Communauté de Communes – Vallée de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc », Chamonix.</reference>
        <reference>Journal des Propriétaires du Pays du Mont-Blanc (JDPMB), 2009, « Un plan climat pour la vallée », N°89, Octobre/Novembre, Chamonix. </reference>
        <reference>Plan Climat Haute Montagne. 2019. S’adapter au changement climatique en montagne. Vallée de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc. </reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">The choice to focus on Chamonix-Mont-Blanc and Les Houches in this article is justified by the fact that glaciers are easily visible in these municipalities, which is not the case in Servoz and Vallorcine, the other two municipalities of the valley. </note>
        <note id="2">Interview with a tourism manager. October 2018.</note>
        <note id="3">Website of the Observatoire du Mont-Blanc – http://observatoire.espace-mont-blanc.com/indicateurs/frequentation-sites-touristiques - Visited on August 13, 2020.</note>
        <note id="4">Indeed, in France, only agglomerations with more than 50,000 inhabitants are legally obliged to develop this type of measure, while the Chamonix valley only has around 14,000 inhabitants.</note>
        <note id="5">In this sense, the glacier can constitute a “border object,” i.e. an “entity which serves as an interface between social worlds and stakeholders with different perspectives” and can thus be the subject of differentiated uses (Latzko-Toth, Millerand, 2015, p. 163, our translation). The glacier represents both a touristic landscape and a scientific object. </note>
        <note id="6">Interview with a tourism manager. April 2018.</note>
        <note id="7">Interview with a high mountain guide. May 2018.</note>
        <note id="8">Interview with a high mountain guide. May 2018.</note>
        <note id="9">Interview with a lodge warden. March 2019.</note>
        <note id="10">Interview with a tourism manager. October 2018. </note>
        <note id="11">Interview with a high mountain guide. September 2018.</note>
        <note id="12">Interview with a high mountain guide. September 2017.</note>
        <note id="13">Interview with a hotelier. November 2018.</note>
        <note id="14">Interview with a high mountain guide. Avril 2018.</note>
        <note id="15">Interview with a ski instructor. May 2019.</note>
        <note id="16">Interview with a tourism manager. October 2017.</note>
        <note id="17">Interview with a shopkeeper. June 2018.</note>
        <note id="18">Interview with a high mountain guide. May 2018. </note>
        <note id="19">Interview with a tourism marketing manager. June 2017.</note>
        <note id="20">Interview with a high mountain guide. May 2018.</note>
    </notes>
</article>