<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_EG_52-122_La_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5203" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.5203</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="5191">
            Mise en scène paysagère, représentations et pensée du paysage dans trois villages shui touristifiés du sud Guizhou (Chine)
        </original>
        <traduction lang="de" source="5228">Landschaftliche Inszenierung, Vorstellungen und Reflexionen zur Landschaft in drei touristifizierten Shui-Dörfern in Süd-Guizhou (China)</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Gauché" prenom="Evelyne">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PDPBEG_9-57_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5062" lang="fr">Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PBEGATL_58-100_Ll_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4932" lang="fr">Le paysage kitsch comme destination touristique en Asie du Sud et du Sud-Est (Chine, Vietnam, Népal)</publication>
                <publication id="fr_EG_51-122_Me_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5191" lang="fr">Mise en scène paysagère, représentations et pensée du paysage dans trois villages shui touristifiés du sud Guizhou (Chine)</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Associate Professor in Geography UMR CNRS CITERES 7324, Université de Tours 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Landscape staging, representations, and landscape thinking in three touristified Shui villages in southern Guizhou (China)</titre>
    <sousTitre>Peer-reviewed article</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        This contribution questions landscape representations amongst the Shui who live in Guizhou province (south China). This ethnic group, which has a strong specific cultural component, has seen its daily landscapes transformed by the implementation of tourist activities. The state-led growth of the tourist industry that started in rural areas during the early 1980s and reached Guizhou in the early 2000s has unfolded according to a highly standardized official scheme. Territories have been transformed drastically in order to set new landscape stages. In this context, the article highlights the way tourismification is changing the relationship between the Shui and their daily landscape, or more broadly, their milieu (to borrow the words of Augustin Berque). Tourism is now an integral part of this milieu through the hybridated representations of the landscape that have emerged from local residents, tourists, and the state. 
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            This work questions representations and “landscape thinking”<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a> among the Shui ethnic minority of Guizhou province (southern China), whose daily landscape has been transformed by tourismification. In China, after the opening of the country and the launch of international tourism as of 1978 by Deng Xiao Ping, domestic tourism was encouraged during the early 1980s as a tool for the development of poor rural regions, and now these domestic tourists, mainly Han Chinese urban middle class, represent most of such flows in the country (Taunay, 2011; Véron, 2013). Since the beginning of the 2000s, during the transformation of the outlook on rural spaces,<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a> driven by the central state and according to a uniform official template, this domestic tourism has been developing in the countryside, in particular in areas populated by ethnic minorities such as the mountain province of Guizhou (Document n°1). This development of domestic tourism in rural space is being carried out according to a very standardized official model. As a result, the areas concerned are undergoing major transformations, as reflected in a veritable staging of the landscape. In addition to its economic development role, domestic tourism also aims to build a sense of national identity (Oakes, 1998; Taunay, 2009, 2011); hence, the government's willingness to “<em>control the interpretation of sites</em>” (Leicester, 2008). Any official tourist site must thus be upgraded to the state model. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            As part of the ANR AQAPA<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a> program, this work focuses on social representations of the landscape among residents of three Shui villages, located in the <em>xian </em>(district)<em> </em>of Sandu (Document n°1), which have become, like many others, official tourism sites. In addition, it contributes to research on the ideal dimension of landscape in the societies of the South (Gauché, 2015), which is still much less studied by the social sciences than landscapes in the West, with the main and longstanding exception of A. Berque's (1995) in-depth work on Chinese "landscape civilization." Using an environmental approach, Berque defines the landscape as a cosmophany, that is to say, “the appearance of a milieu” (Berque, 2018). According to this approach, the landscape is thus a “<em>kind of cosmophany that appeared in the leisure class in the 4</em>th<em> century in China and during the Renaissance in Europe and has been widespread ever since: the landscape is neither a simple subjective projection nor a simple external object; it is a trajectory.”</em> (<em>Ibidem</em>). Through a trajectory, for certain beings, the environment <em>can</em> exist <em>as a</em> landscape. Those beings, and more broadly those societies, are thus infused with “landscape thinking:” “<em>a thought (about) the landscape; it is a thought that takes the landscape as its object. For such a thing to exist, one must be able to represent the landscape, that is to say, in particular, to represent it with a word that makes it an object of thought</em>" (Berque, 2016).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            This contribution thus aims to attempt to shed light on what may be the Shui <em>milieu </em>– the term “milieu” being used in the Berquian sense, as the relationship of a being to the environment – through an approach to their representations and their landscape thinking. Shui are an ethnic minority with strong cultural specificities, living within and in contact with Chinese “landscape civilization,” within a powerful state, and in a territory that is now 'touristified' and essentially frequented by Han Chinese tourists. In such a context, what relationships can this society have with its environment, which we consider here, via a dimension of social - and Western - geography, as its daily landscape? And how is the development of tourism (‘tourismification’) now part of this relationship?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            This singular Shui <em>milieu </em>is thus addressed through four aspects, which are considered to be its expression: 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            The highlighting of representations that Shui have of their everyday landscape, from their attention to these components<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a> and values they attribute to them.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            Their thought (on the subject)<em> </em>of the landscape (i.e. landscape thinking within the meaning offered by A. Berque, 2016), addressed through their conception of Chinese words which we have chosen to consider here: <em>fengjing</em> - among the many terms meaning landscape in Chinese, it is the one with the broadest meaning and closest to the Western sense (Escande, 2005) - and <em>shanshui</em> (which designates a landscape composed of mountains and water); the Shui language has no equivalent but Shui speakers who can speak Mandarin commonly use these words.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            An attempt to structure all of these representations through the highlighting of “model landscapes” (Luginbühl, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            Lastly, an approach of their territoriality in its transformations as a result of ‘tourismification.’ 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            This work is supported by semi-structured interviews (more than 80), carried out in July 2014 and continued in August 2016, with residents of the Shuige, Gulu, and Zenlei<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a> villages (sample composed mainly of smallholders owning between 2 and 4 mu<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a> of land, i.e. the main population group, and a few municipal council members).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            After a brief presentation of landscapes and of their staging according to state policies pertaining to the development of official tourism sites, we will address the relationship that Shui people have with the (their) landscape, leading to a highlighting of the landscape models that structure the representations. Finally, we will show how tourismification modifies the territoriality of residents. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. Landscapes and their staging</section>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Tourismified landscapes</section>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            As is typical in central and southern Guizhou province (Dan, 2005), the landscapes of these three villages of the <em>xian </em>of Sandu are made up of medium-sized mountains peaking at more than 1,500 m. Mainly limestone and shaped into cone-shaped karsts, the slopes are partially forested and valley bottoms are occupied by rice paddies on terraces surmounted by fields of rainfed crops (corn, peppers, peanuts, plum trees). Located at the foot of the mountainsides, the habitat is traditionally composed of wood structures, but since the arrival of the road in the early 2000s for the needs of tourism development, it has increasingly been built out of bricks, an initiative funded by young people having gone to work in cities in the eastern part of the country. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            As part of the Guizhou province tourism development policy (an extension of the national policy), based on a ‘catchy’ pretext - the great Shui Mao festival (one month of the Shui calendar) in Shuige (Document n°2); the “stone eggs” in Gulu (Document n°3); and the panorama of the hamlets of Zenlei (Document n°4) - these three villages have been converted into official tourism sites. like others before them. This most often means a major transformation of the landscape of the places in question. In fact, through a particular development model, the standards of which are set by the central government, tourist sites are used to build a sense of national identity, which explains why the vast majority of players in China's domestic tourist system are in collusion with the state (Taunay, 2011).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. The principles of official tourism site development</section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            In ethnic minority territories, the official upgrade is based on three principles (Gauché, 2017). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            It involves, on the one hand, highlighting the landscape of <em>shanshui</em>, emblematic of the Chinese aesthetic (painting, garden art) and spirituality, therefore of prestigious Chinese culture, i.e. showcasing aquatic elements and mountain panoramas via viewpoints, which fall within “the tradition of contemplation” (Xiang <em>et al</em>. 2017), a picturesque architectural style reminiscent of the architecture featured in the painting of <em>shanshui</em>, i.e. inscriptions by ancient famous Chinese scholars designed to reinforce the spirituality of the place. This enhancement also requires strengthening the villages’ ethnic character (“shuiification,” Gauché, 2017), reflecting the wealth of the Chinese nation: the addition of various decorative elements (Shui pictograms, paintings, architectural ornaments, fish statues<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a> placed on rooftops, etc.); the highlighting of beliefs and legends; dancing and singing shows held in large squares created for this purpose; ecomuseums. These two processes are accompanied thirdly by the modernization of the countryside (accessibility, parking, fire protection, sewage disposal, lighting, and public toilets, etc.) to adapt to the demand for comfort by Chinese tourists and to assert the role of the state in the economic development of the countryside, also aiming to lead minorities to become modern socialist societies (Véron, 2013).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            Finally, interpretive trails are created throughout the villages, enabling tourists to pass by the different <em>jingdian</em>, i.e. elements of official interest of various scales in a tourist site, all of which can be seen on a map at the entrance. These elements mainly include new constructions (ecomuseums, squares, entrance doors to tourist areas, and other contrivances); places that are meaningful for the Shui people (stones, trees, and sacred springs, votive caves); remarkable natural elements (rivers, cascades, rock walls, etc.); and emblematic places (Mao mountain in Shuige, stone eggs in Gulu, panorama in Zenlei), some of which are explained by interpretive panels.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Three villages offering a complementary differentiated offer </section>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            Although these planning principles are common to the various villages, they must nevertheless offer a different and therefore complementary range of features. The degree of transformation of village territories can thus differ depending on the stakeholders and on the economic objectives set by the state (provincial and local levels).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            Zenlei is an ancient village, whose main tourist attraction is the panorama which can be enjoyed from a viewpoint at 700 metres in altitude. Because of its picturesque architecture, the village has protected status and has received different national labels: “ethnic cultural village” in 2001; “construction of a new countryside” in 2007; “famous national tourist village” in 2015, etc. These labels allow the state to better channel the allocation of grants and the villages to gain greater visibility at the national level. Zenlei is therefore subject to various constraints, which mainly concern the architecture, which must remain in wood (with a subsidy from the <em>xian</em> and cutting permits within the strict limits of what is required). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            Conversely, Gulu, which is closer to Sandu, has experienced very significant transformations. In July 2014, tourismification was limited to the stone eggs site and the most ancient centre of the village organized around a large square set up for shows. Two years later, at the entrance of the expanded site, near the national road located 6 km away, had sprung a huge parking lot, a pagoda, around 20 <em>nonjiale</em>, and a gigantic gateway over 100 metres long containing payment stations, toilets, shops, restaurants, a giant screen promoting ethnic villages, and the first-floor offices of the public company that is the main contractor. Around 10 guides offer their services and electric shuttles take visitors to the main tourist area (stone eggs) by way of a new road built after the river was diverted, making it possible to discover new <em>jingdian </em>(paddle wheels, giant barrel symbolizing rice wine production, Shui spirit statues). The stone egg site has been fully developed, with an esplanade equipped with an artificial waterfall made more picturesque by the addition of fake rocks (Document n° 3). False wooden facades have been added above the ancient village centre. Almost all of the rice paddies have been replaced, after the villagers were expropriated, by fields of rapeseed, Chinese strawberries (<em>Myrica rubra</em>), or ponds with water lilies, to create a landscape context better corresponding to the taste of Chinese tourists. But another pharaonic project has been in progress since 2017, conducted by a private company along with the <em>xian</em>. With a mineralogical museum composed of four egg-shaped buildings, hotels, shops, leisure areas, artificial lakes, and pagodas, Gulu is destined to become a true amusement park, representative of the “disneylandification” (Brunel, 2012) of ethnic minority villages in China.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            Last but not least, Shuige is in an intermediary state. It underwent a number of transformations in 2005: a large square engraved at ground level with Shui pictograms and featuring stone Buddhas and an ecomuseum, developed at the expense of rice paddies; facades of the main wooden houses enriched by new architectural elements; wood facadism added to part of the brick houses; and an interpretive trail enabling tourists to pass by 16 <em>jingdian</em>. Confronted with the disrepair of the village, a second transformation phase unfolded in 2015, with the conversion of all the remaining wooden houses into brick houses painted pink with fake black bricks at their foundation (Document n°5). The few remaining wooden houses belonging to the poorest families were repainted in wood colour and varnished, with funding from the <em>xian</em>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            This landscape staging is now the residents’ everyday landscape. What are their representations of it?
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. The Shui and the (their) landscape</section>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Daily landscape and landscape preferences</section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            The representations that Shui have of their daily landscape have been approached through their landscape preferences<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a> and the values associated with them, addressed at the scale of “landscape components” (Béringuer, Dérioz, Laques, 1999) which structure the materiality of their living environment.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            The approach via landscape components has revealed that the landscape preferences of the Shui population are natural elements - water (rivers, springs, waterfalls), vegetation (trees, forest, flowers, grass), mountains, minerals (rocks, caves) – along with the contrivances stemming from tourism staging, including squares, gates, covered bridges, stalls, lookouts, ecomuseums, paddle wheels, statues, and more.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            The natural landscape components appear to be highly aesthetically pleasing. “<em>What I prefer are mountains, water, the natural landscape of my village, because it's a beautiful sight</em>”<em> </em>(W. Y. X,<em> </em>65 years old, peasant, Shuige<em>). </em>Beyond this aesthetic value, of scopic magnitude (as translated from the Chinese term<em> hao kan</em> used repeatedly, meaning “lovely, nice to look at”), natural elements – springs, waterfalls, caves, trees, rocks, mountains – also have a spiritual dimension<strong>, </strong>harking back to legends and beliefs of animist origin. In Shuige, peasants explain the following about sacred springs and trees: “<em>I like the two Dragon and Phoenix springs. The water from these springs is good, and we can ask them for children.</em>” “<em>Once upon a time, there were two young people who loved each other. They fell in love while singing. But their parents didn't agree. So they committed suicide on the mountain. When they died, people came to sing there. One tree is named after the girl; the other after the boy. They can grant our wishes.</em>” The mountain has a symbolic dimension, which also contributes to its aesthetization. It is associated with strength and protection, particularly via the shapes of animals that the locals perceive in its profile. In Zenlei, it constitutes the body of a tiger which protects the village and which must be respected by avoiding the construction of structures which would be poorly positioned and would displease it.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            While <a href="https://www.linguee.com/english-french/translation/contrivances.html">contrivances</a> built as part of tourism landscape staging are also aestheticized, they are especially appreciated because they are new places to socialize. “<em>I like the square very much because I can chat with friends there</em>” (W. Y. S., 41 years old, peasant working in the city, Gulu). “<em>It’s bustling</em>” (W. X. Z., 63 years old, peasant, Shuige). Shuige residents also very much appreciate “<em>the bridge near Mao mountain because we can stroll, stop, and meet friends there</em>” (W. C. X., 50 years old, peasant). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            On the other hand, agricultural landscape and built elements, the main components of people’s daily life, have never been mentioned as landscape preferences. While the habitat mainly has a functional role, wooden houses also have an identity and a spiritual value because they represent a legacy from ancestors, whose spirits are still housed therein. This spiritual dimension through a relationship with ancestors also infuses the agricultural landscape: “<em>Look at these two rice fields: do you see a difference between them?… There is a difference: look at mine, my rice is big and beautiful, while in the other field, it did not grow as well. Do you know why? I invited the ancestors into my home and put slats of wood on the door. The owner of this field didn't do so before moving into his house. That's why his field isn't nice, you see? (…) If your brother let the ancestors into his home and you didn’t, they’ll protect his rice but not yours. So you’ll have to add more fertilizer</em>”<em> </em>(W.Q., 35 years old, peasant working in the city, Shuige)<em>. </em>But the fields have above all a utilitarian value, through their nurturing function, and from this point of view enjoy a very positive representation, even if they are associated with hard work.<em> </em>They are a common feature of the landscape and as such are considered banal: “<em>I see the rice paddies every day, so I can't say whether I like or dislike them</em>” (W. Y. X, 65 years old, peasant, Shuige). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            These landscape preferences are consistent with what residents wish to show tourists. It is what they find beautiful and specific in their village territory, i.e. its natural components and <a href="https://www.linguee.com/english-french/translation/contrivance.html">contrivance</a>s which stem from staging (in particular <em>jingdian</em>), but also their intangible heritage, including beliefs, legends, festivals, dances, music and songs, Shui writing, traditional know-how (rice alcohol, weaving, festival costumes), and more. On the contrary, forests, rice paddies, and more generally the agricultural landscape are not mentioned as possible tourist attractions. In this regard, the president of the Shuige tourism association, also serving as village guide, states that he does not talk about rice paddies to tourists “<em>because rice paddies are well known commodities. Concerning agriculture, I instead present products like the alcohol made with rice and plums. I explain to them that the alcohol is produced by residents and sold at 15 yuans per ½ kg; that if the wine is a vintage brew, it costs 30 yuan per ½ litre. I explain this to them on top of Mao mountain. That's what matters. Rice paddies are part of our everyday life. I’ve never thought to mention them.</em>”<em> </em>Finally, if old wooden houses, associated with a lack of modernity, are not considered to be elements of tourist interest in Shuige or Gulu, wooden houses whose architecture has been embellished and “shuiified” (Gauché, 2017) are considered to be integral <em>jingdian </em>components<em> </em>of a complete square. In Zenlei, in contrast, the picturesque aspect of the old village is considered as its main attraction element.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            These landscape preferences, which reflect the terms of the residents’ “landscape experience” (Dérioz, 2012), partly reflect their “their landscape thinking” (Berque, 2016).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. The Shui and “landscape thinking” </section>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            Addressing representations of what in English we call “landscape,” the research focused on what this notion could represent for the Shui. While the word does not exist in Shui, certain Chinese words meaning landscape are known by the local population and spontaneously used by its members to evoke their environment. Minorities have in fact acquired a landscape culture, a <em>shanshui</em> culture in particular, through progressive acculturation in contact with Chinese “landscape civilization” (Berque, 1995), beginning in the 14th century (Escande, oral communication, Paris, March 13, 2015).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            While the word <em>shanshui</em> means for them, literally and specifically, a (nice) landscape composed of mountains and water, the term <em>fengjing</em><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a> is considered by interviewees as corresponding on the one hand to aesthetic elements, mainly natural and picturesque: “<em>The landscape </em>[fengjing]<em> is made up of nice things to see</em>”<em> </em>(Z. K., 53 years old, member of the municipal council, Gulu)<em>;” “They </em>[fengjing elements] <em>are nice trees, nice water, nice rocks. Fengjing includes the mountain, rivers, nature” </em>(Z. C. X., 60 years old, peasant, Zenlei).<em> </em>On the other hand, landscape characteristics also include cultural specificities, which residents associate with the aesthetic dimension: <em>“Landscape comprises those things which are specific to a nation.” </em>(Y. Q. X, peasant, 50 years old, Zenlei);<em> </em>“<em>It is special places. For example, places in specific nations have specific landscapes</em>”<em> </em>(W. L. R., peasant, Shuige).<em> </em>Thus, the Shui, by appropriating the Chinese terms, also appropriate the concept they refer to, into which they project their representations.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            On the basis of these values, associated with the different landscape components of their daily living space, and of their understanding of the word "landscape," around what models can we try to structure this system of representations constituting the Shui society <em>milieu</em>?
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. Three landscape models structuring these representations</section>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            According to Y. Luginbühl (1995), landscape representations are structured around "landscape models" derived from several levels of culture: a macro level or background culture, consisting of a set of common references; a local level forged by a society on the scale of its living environment; and an individual level, stemming from the individual's own culture. These different levels of culture are obviously intricately interrelated and make up a system. The narratives gathered during the interviews have enabled us to identify three landscape models that make it possible to structure and interpret, at least in part, the system of representations of the Shui population, including certain aspects of its <em>milieu</em>. We have designated these models in the following way: the animist peasant<em> </em>model, the <em>shanshui </em>model, and the <em>tourism culture model.</em> The first corresponds to the level of local culture, the other two to the macro level. While at the individual level it is emotional values (including attachment, nostalgia, and memory) that are associated with the living space and its landscape components, it is on these two levels, local and macro, that this research has focused. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. The animist peasant model</section>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            The animist peasant model is expressed on the one hand through the fact that the landscape preferences of the residents do not integrate the main elements of their daily life, i.e. habitat and cultivated fields, which are not aestheticized either, but viewed above all through their utilitarian value. On the other hand, it also results in a strong presence of spirituality in the representations that the Shui have of their daily landscape: the spirit of the ancestors and the powers of the natural elements (rocks, old trees, caves, springs). Some of these beliefs are still alive and constitute a fundamental element of their identity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            Even though they are being lost by the younger generation, songs and legends, so very important in Shui culture, are among the cultural and identity vectors of this model. Shui culture is indeed above all intangible culture: beliefs and legends, songs and dances, spoken language except for purposes of worship.<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a> Here, as in many other cultures, popular music is a tool for expressing spiritual values of nature (Sahi, 2010). Furthermore, an adept singer sparks admiration, love, or friendship. Shui songs address different topics, a few examples of which are presented in Table 1. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            Table 1: Some excerpts from Shui songs
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            In these songs, nature is simultaneously linked to love, gods, happiness, and life. Nature, beautiful and sacred, is very important in Shui culture, as is also conveyed in public discourse: “<em>All of nature is energy. It is at the origin of our life. If there weren't nature, we couldn't live</em>”<em> </em>(W. Y. Q., 64 years old, peasant, member of the municipal council, Shuige).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            In terms of macro level culture, the representations that the Shui have of their daily landscape reveal the existence of two landscape models: the <em>shanshui </em>model and the <em>tourism</em><em> culture </em>model.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Shanshui model</section>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            In the cultural background, the aesthetic appreciation that the Shui have of the landscape is inevitably influenced, to use the words of A. Berque (1995), by Chinese “landscape civilization,” qualified by the author (1989) as “<em>shanshui </em>society.” <em>Shanshui</em> (literally “mountains and waters”) is a Chinese word which took on the meaning of “landscape” in literary poetry in the middle of the 4th century (Escande, 2005; Berque, 2009). Constructed during the same period as a pictorial model (<em>shanshui </em>painting), it has become one of the emblematic elements of Chinese aesthetics and spirituality and is also the basis of Chinese garden art (Escande, 2005). It is structured around the harmony between four elements (water, mineral, buildings, and plants), between which flows a vital energy - <em>qi </em>(Izikowitz, 1987). The concept of landscape for the Shui population – as well as for other minorities such as, for example, the Hani of Yunnan (Dao, 2014) – is clearly influenced by this “artistic and aesthetic ideal of the natural world (<em>ziran</em>) specific to <em>shanshui</em>” (Escande, 2005). Hence, in the <em>shanshui </em>landscape model, as expressed by the Shui population, the landscape is aestheticized nature - mountains, waters, rocks, caves, trees - and picturesque architectural elements as present in <em>shanshui </em>paintings. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            Minorities have therefore undoubtedly been influenced by the landscape culture of Chinese civilization and its landscape thinking, even more so because this landscape model is also promoted by the state through the development of tourist sites.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Tourism culture model </section>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            For residents, this third landscape model aestheticizes and promotes the elements for tourism development. It reflects the recent evolution of representations that the Shui have of their daily landscape, of their landscape thinking, and more broadly of their <em>milieu</em>. The tourism culture model stems from two interacting elements. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            On one hand, it is the result of the landscape staging of tourist sites realized through a very particular form of landscape thinking, i.e. of the Han Chinese state, built around the fundamental notion of <em>shanshui </em>in Chinese culture and promoting through contrivances the landscape of mountains and water. This landscape thinking, in association with a promotion of the diversity of ethnic minority cultures, in this case Shui culture, and within the framework of access to modernity, is used to build a sense of national unity. Tourist sites are thus the vector of promotion of a prestigious Chinese culture associated with the superiority of the Han, the wealth of the Chinese nation, and the socialist ideal (Gauché, 2017). The landscape staging of tourist sites carried out by the state draws upon the two cultures levels (Chinese and Shui) and also participates in a disguised political project through the standardization of representations of the landscape (Taunay, 2011) among tourists and the Chinese population in general, so as to highlight the greatness of the Chinese nation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            On the other hand, this tourism culture model expresses itself through “<em>internalization of the tourist perspective</em>” (Leicester, 2008) produced within the Shui population through contact with tourists, whose perspective has been influenced by this “political landscape” (Jackson, 1984), i.e. the landscape thinking of the Han state. While young people from the villages who have gone to work in the city have often had the opportunity to visit certain tourist sites, contact with Han tourists, who have expressed to the Shui population their desire for landscapes shaped according to state standards, is helping to change the way residents look at their daily landscape. They increasingly see it from the perspective of what is of interest to tourists; the <em>jingdian</em> are now what add value to the landscape, and residents start liking and aestheticizing what tourists appreciate: <em>“Whenever there are visitors, family, or friends who come here, they enter through this door and say: ‘oh it’s pretty, so I think it's nice to show it to the tourists. And now I also think that this door is pretty</em>” (P. X., peasant, 64 years old, Shuige). What tourists do not like is also noted by residents as displeasing (a road in bad condition, a bridge damaged by a flood and not repaired…). Furthermore, the locals have integrated the official view of elements of interest for tourists (<em>jingdian</em>):<em> </em>“<em>I want to show tourists the museum, the bridges near Mao mountain, springs, all the things set up for tourism. Because there’s nothing else of interest here</em>” (W. Y., 46 years old, peasant, Shuige); “<em>When tourists come to the village, they like it when we show them jingdian, which are the places developed specifically for tourists (…). Why? Because these are real local things</em>” (Y. X., 63 years old, peasant, Zenlei).<em> </em>As such, residents are restating the official tourism promotion line when they designate the key tourist attractions of their territory, for example in Gulu, where they qualify the stone eggs site as a <em>“curiosity</em>,” a “<em>mystery of nature</em>,” a “<em>magical natural phenomenon</em>,” and “<em>unique</em>” (Meunier, 2016). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            This evolution of representations conveys “<em>another form of appropriation of rural space by the tourist perspective</em>” (Leicester, 2008). Local populations are therefore “<em>active subjects who build representations of their culture for the intention of tourists, representations based both on their own reference systems and on their interpretation of what tourists want</em>” (Picard, 2001).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            These three landscape models are closely intertwined. As pointed out by Y. Luginbühl (2012), the formation of social representations of landscapes at a local scale does not replace the macro scale assimilable as background, or vice versa. The two levels together influence representations. In today’s world, the tourist culture model makes a major contribution to structuring the system of representations that the Shui population has of its daily landscape, and whose origin is directly linked to state policies. This evolution of representations plays an important role in the acceptance by the local population of transformations of its territory and of prevailing development principles. These principles call upon both the <em>shanshui</em> landscape model<em> </em>and the spiritual value accorded to nature in the animist peasant model, which enhances the identity dimension of the Shui population, and also meets with the consensus of tourists.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. Tourism-driven evolution of residents’ territoriality </section>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            This evolution of representations is constitutive of an evolution of residents’ territoriality, emerging through the appropriation of landscape transformations, which are seen as the best way to protect Shui culture. However, contradictions arise pertaining to their relationship to the touristified territory of daily life.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Landscape transformations appropriated and in the service of protecting Shui culture</section>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            The residents of the three villages want tourism development, despite the meagre financial benefits they receive from it. In Shuige, shows, handicraft sales, and spin-offs from coach excursions organized by external agencies are managed by the village community and redistributed to residents of the tourist district, who receive 40 to 100 yuans, i.e. around 6 to 14 euros, per person per year. In Gulu, the direct spin-offs are even smaller and concern show participants and a few employees of the company managing the site, but in both cases these are people from outside the village; in fact, the villagers generally do not have the required qualifications and the few who manage to find a job work as cashiers, sweepers, caretakers, or maintenance workers. In Zenlei, the spin-offs concern only the dozen or so dancers of the rare shows organized during visits by tourist coaches.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            Tourist development is perceived very positively despite these meagre spin-offs. The new facilities created as part of landscape staging have become highly appreciated places to socialize for local residents and now constitute the main central village space. These meeting places are also used to dry corn and peppers, while ecomuseums on stilts create shaded shelters. Lookouts and covered bridges also serve as meeting places for friends or lovers, as well as sites for resting or for contemplation. Furthermore, a number of new facilities (parking, street lighting, public toilets, fire hydrants, road links, etc.) accommodate residents’ desire for modernity. The transformations caused by tourismification are thus incorporated in their daily territoriality, even more so because they are perceived as the best vector for protecting Shui culture. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            This is the effect of the structuring role of the landscape model of tourist culture on the system of representations of the local population, but also of the importance of spirituality in the animist peasant model. By all appearances, Shui culture is more intangible than tangible. However, in transforming the materiality of the village landscape, tourism development offers residents an enhancement of this intangible heritage by showcasing it through paintings, shows, inscriptions in Shui, ecomuseums, interpretation panels, and more. As such, for the Shui, tourismification materializes the intangible, a strong expression of their identity, and whether it is contrived or otherwise is of little or no importance. The Shui encourage contrivance, without realizing that "<em>the tourist product as the materialization of myths (...) kills, or at best, freezes tradition</em>"(Bachimon, 2001). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            Thus, even if they are carried out according to Chinese standards and serve to sinicize the landscape, the transformations induced by tourism development are seen by the local population as an essential vector of promotion and protection of Shui culture, and of its dissemination to the outside world, as reflected, for example, in the discourse of the population of Shuige: <em>“If there's no tourism, all of this will be lost. But if our village becomes a known tourist destination, the government will help us protect our culture</em>” (W. Y., 64 years old, peasant), and “<em>our life will be improved, so residents will stay and our culture will be better preserved</em>” (F. Q., 40 years old, village head, secretary of the Communist Party). As such, tourism enables young people to discover or to learn more about their culture. “<em>Now there are books on Shui culture for children. That’s thanks to tourism</em>” (W. Q., 35 years old, peasant working in the city). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            This explains the importance of <em>jingdian</em>, these elements of official interest for a tourist site, in representations that residents have of their everyday landscape. Moreover, the transformed landscape, thus staged,<strong> </strong>hanified, and shuiified, becomes, in their eyes, as well as in the eyes of the authorities,<strong> </strong>the heritage to be protected.<strong> </strong>Heritage is therefore not what is “authentic” and inherited from past history but what was produced by and for tourismification in order to meet the expectations of tourists and to transmit the message that the central state wishes to convey. All these transformations correspond to the expectations of Chinese tourists who, in the vast majority of cases, admire this “fake” heritage and prefer to “<em>have a modern rather than an authentic experience</em>” (Taunay, 2011). As stated by T. Leicester (2008), “<em>it is not authenticity that is valued but the embellishment of a reality through the trappings of civilization which has been, from the outset, at the heart of the concept of site in Chinese tourism</em>.” 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            While the Shui population considers tourism desirable, they are still faced with various contradictions.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Contradictions in relation to their territory</section>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            On one hand, while the principles and objectives of the state model of tourism development is broadly accepted by the population, this is not always the case regarding how such development is carried out. In Gulu, as part of the metamorphosis of the village, the <em>xian</em> acquired all the rice paddies, for compensation considered very insufficient by the population, whose main means of subsistence was snatched away. Yet residents approve of the tourism development and the planning principles on which this development is based and are resigned about the aspects that do not suit them. As it unfolds, tourismification thus reveals very unbalanced power relations, dominated by the state at all hierarchical levels confronting populations that experience a feeling of powerlessness in cases of conflicts. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            This is also reflected through the tension between the developments carried out and certain local values. In Zenlei, where the population perceives the terrain surrounding the village as a huge tiger protecting it, certain constructions, according to community members, disturb the beast. W. G. L. (54 years old, peasant) explains with regards to a stall that was set up at the height of the eye of the tiger: “<em>It's good for tourism that the state built this. But it's not good for the tiger that protects the village. But we're afraid to tell the state this. And even if we had told them, they still would have built this stall</em>.”
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            Finally, residents find themselves confronted by a contradiction between their desire for modernity and their yearning to preserve an attractive landscape for tourists. In Zenlei, most residents understand the importance of preserving the ancient wooden architecture. “<em>If we start building brick houses, it won't be nice, and tourists won't come anymore</em>,” said W. G. S. (60 years old, peasant). However, the constraints imposed by protection measures disturb community members, who want brick houses, a sign of social advancement. Despite a loosening of the protection policy in 2015 (possibility of using bricks to build a ground floor), the departure of families toward the neighbouring city of Dojiang continues. Another revealing example of this contradiction between tradition and modernity is that of Shuige. In 2015, the metamorphosis of the village from wood to brick led to a significant reduction in visitor traffic, brick houses being no more "ethnic" than the fish statues on the roofs. As a result, the municipal council proposed to rebuild a "new old village" out of wood on rice paddies next to the first one and - after having put wooden facades on the few brick houses in the tourist district in 2005, then removing them when the whole village was rebuilt in brick in 2015 - to add wooden adornments on the new brick houses again, in order to bring tourists back to the fold !
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            The Shui are now aware of the market value of their landscape (and of their culture), upon which they project their hope for social advancement and improvement of their standard of living, despite the meagre financial benefits accrued from a tourism industry which does not stem the emigration of young people to cities in the eastern part of the country.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            The landscape models structuring the representations of the population reveal certain fundamental aspects of the Shui <em>milieu</em>, hybridizing Chinese and Shui culture, representations which are today very strongly influenced by the national strategy for the development of tourist sites. The acculturation of ethnic minorities to <em>shanshui</em> culture has a long history, but through tourismification, the “cosmophany” (Berque, 2018) landscape as constructed by the Chinese state is increasingly constitutive of the relationship of the Shui to their environment. However, while the Han and Shui are in a “growing together” paradigm, from the Latin <em>cum crescere </em>(Berque, 2018), does this landscape cosmophany also exist among minorities in the same way as in the dominant culture? In the Shui population, those who do not speak Chinese lack the vocabulary to access a form of “landscape thinking.” However, through channels other than language, they are confronted with this landscape culture, and in particular <em>shanshui</em>, if only through the photos of those who have visited tourist sites, the paintings decorating the interiors of homes of the wealthiest residents, and the television series in Chinese taking place in a <em>shanshui </em>landscape, which they watch even if they do not understand what is said.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            Hence, to a varying extent, there is landscape cosmophany interference in the Shui <em>milieu</em>. This interference is no more and no less than the result of the political instrumentalization of the landscape carried out by the Chinese state through the transformation of ethnic minority villages into official tourism sites, as part of the construction of a national identity.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Bachimon, Ph. (2001), « La mise en désir des lieux ou la réinvention des lieux par le tourisme », Café Géo, No 249.</reference>
        <reference>Béringuer, Ph., Dérioz, P. and Laques, A.-E. (1999), Les paysages français, A. Colin, Synthèse, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (1989), « Position de recherche : La transition paysagère ou sociétés à pays, à paysage, à shanshui, à paysagement », Espace géographique, T. 18 No 1, Parallèles géographiques : voyages et paysages, pp. 18-20.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (1995), Les raisons du paysage : de la Chine antique aux environnements de synthèse, Hazan, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A., (2009), Des eaux de la montagne au paysage, Conférence à la Maison Franco-Japonaise, 24 September, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (2016), La pensée paysagère, Editions éoliennes, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (2018), Glossaire de mésologie, Editions Eoliennes, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Brunel, S. (2012), La planète disneylandisée : Pour un tourisme responsable, Sciences Humaines Ed.</reference>
        <reference>Dan, W. (2005), Partir ou rester : dans les montagnes du Guizhou, province du Sud-Ouest de la Chine ?, Geography thesis, Université Paris 10-Nanterre.</reference>
        <reference>Dao, M. (2014), « Mésologie chez les Hani du Yunnan », Séminaire Mésologiques, 12 December, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Dérioz, P. (2012), L’apparence des choses. Analyser les paysages pour comprendre les systèmes territoriaux, Habilitation à Diriger des Recherches.</reference>
        <reference>Droz, Y., Miéville-Ott, V., Forney, J. and Spichiger, R. (2009), Anthropologie politique du paysage. Valeurs et postures paysagères des montagnes suisses, Karthala.</reference>
        <reference>Escande, Y. (2005), Montagnes et eaux : la culture du shanshui, Editions Hermann.</reference>
        <reference>Gauché, E. (2015), « Le paysage existe-t-il dans les pays du Sud ? Pistes de recherches sur l’institutionnalisation du paysage », VertigO - la revue électronique en sciences de l'environnement [En ligne], Vol. 15 No 1.</reference>
        <reference>Gauché, E. (2017), « Mise en tourisme d’un village shui dans la province montagneuse du Guizhou (sud de la Chine) : imaginaires et instrumentalisation politique du paysage », Journal of Alpine Research | Revue de géographie alpine [Online], 105-3.</reference>
        <reference>Izikowitz, K. G. (1987), « Les jardins et le principe vital en Asie orientale », in Koechlin, B., Sigaut, F., Thomas, J. M. C., Toffin, G., De la voûte céleste au terroir, du jardin au foyer, Editions de l’EHESS, Paris, pp. 81-88.</reference>
        <reference>Jackson, J.B. (1984), Discovering the Vernacular Landscape, Yale University Press.</reference>
        <reference>Leicester, T. (2008), « Conflits et enjeux identitaires dans le tourisme rural à Yangshuo, Chine », Civilisations, No 57, Tourisme, mobilités et altérités contemporaines.</reference>
        <reference>Luginbühl, Y. (1995), Sensibilités paysagères, modèles paysagers, Rapport de recherche, Ladyss/Segesa, Ministère de l’Environnement.</reference>
        <reference>Luginbühl, Y. (2012), La mise en scène du monde : construction du paysage européen, CNRS Ed.</reference>
        <reference>Meunier, F. (2016), Les représentations habitantes du paysage face aux mutations territoriales et aux enjeux touristiques en Chine. L’exemple d’un village minoritaire shui, M1 dissertation in geography, Université de Tours.</reference>
        <reference>Oakes, T. (1998), Tourism and Modernity in China, Routledge, London.</reference>
        <reference>Picard, M. (2001), « Bali: vingt ans de recherches », Anthropologie et Sociétés, 25 (2), pp. 109-127.</reference>
        <reference>Sahi, V. (2010), “Folk Music as a Tool of Expressing the Spiritual Values of Nature”, VI Habitat Contact Forum of the Barents Euroregion, Arkhangelsk, Russia.</reference>
        <reference>Taunay, B. (2009), Le tourisme intérieur chinois : approche géographique à partir de provinces du sud-ouest de la Chine, Doctoral thesis in geography, Université de La Rochelle.</reference>
        <reference>Taunay, B. (2011), Le tourisme intérieur chinois, PUR, anthology. « Espace et Territoires ». </reference>
        <reference>Véron, E. (2013), « Les espaces ruraux touristiques dans le delta du Yangzi, entre intégration ville-campagne et développement rural », EchoGéo, No 26.</reference>
        <reference>Xiang, W., Bachimon, Ph. and Dérioz, P. (2017), « Le spectacle de plein air dans les sites paysagers remarquables des montagnes chinoises : le cas du Renard du Mont Tianmen à Zhangjiajie, entre réinvention d’une tradition et mise en tourisme  », Journal of Alpine Research | Revue de géographie alpine, 105-2.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">According to the expression used by A. Berque (2016, our translation, as are all quotations from authors cited in this text unless otherwise noted).</note>
        <note id="2">During the cultural revolution, going to the countryside was synonymous with suffering and re-education through peasant labour (Taunay, 2011).</note>
        <note id="3">AQAPA (2014-2019): “A Qui Appartiennent les Paysages en Asie ? La mise en tourisme des hautes terres en Asie méridionale : dynamiques sociales et patrimonialisation des paysages dans les campagnes à minorités ethniques,” project spearheaded by UMR CNRS 7324 CITERES of Université de Tours.</note>
        <note id="4">According to the definition of landscape component as the smallest elementary object observed at ground level (Béringuer, Dérioz, Laques, 1999); for example, house, field, forest, river.</note>
        <note id="5">The interviews were carried out in Chinese via an interpreter, with the exception of a few in Shui (with the inevitable bias of a double translation).</note>
        <note id="6">1 ha = 15 mu, 1 mu = 0.07 ha.</note>
        <note id="7">The fish has a symbolic value in Shui culture.</note>
        <note id="8">Defined by Y. Droz et al. (2009) as “a penchant (…) for certain types of landscapes.”</note>
        <note id="9">We only used these terms at the very end of the interview so as not to influence the spontaneity of their choice of vocabulary.</note>
        <note id="10">And known only to old geomancers.</note>
        <note id="11">Loose translations from Chinese or Shui into English.</note>
    </notes>
</article>