<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_EGMS_36-62_Ir_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1108" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.1108</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>2</numero>
        <annee>2012</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="1102">
            <traducteur nom="Binebine" prenom="Laila" />
            Identité, imaginaire et tourisme en pays touareg au Niger
        </original>
        <traduction lang="de" source="1112">Identität, Imagination und Tourismus bei den Tuareg im Norden des Niger</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Grégoire" prenom="Emmanuel">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_EGMS_34-57_Ir_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1102" lang="fr">Identité, imaginaire et tourisme en pays touareg au Niger</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Directeur de recherche IRD - Centre d’études africaines (UMR 194 EHESS-IRD) - 96 bd. Raspail, Paris 75006 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Scholze" prenom="Marko">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_EGMS_34-57_Ir_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1102" lang="fr">Identité, imaginaire et tourisme en pays touareg au Niger</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Goethe Universität, Institut für Ethnologie Grüneburgplatz 1, 60323 Frankfurt am Main 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Identity, imaginary and tourism in the tuareg region, in Niger</titre>
    <resume>
        This paper aims to understand the complexity of the identity questions related to tourism while discerning the different levels of identity within the visited society. This paper therefore deals with the development of tourism among the Tuareg of Northern Niger. Focusing the analysis on identity transformations observed among local actors. The authors discuss first the western imagination relative to the Sahara and the Tuareg, an element that the Tuareg have remarkably played upon to encourage regional tourism based on “Desert tourism”. Then, from an historical perspective, they study the growth of tourism in the Agadez region, while highlighting its appropriation by the Tuareg, and the identity adaptations to which this appropriation has led. Finally, the authors consider the decline of tourism, as a result of the 2007-2009 rebellion, and the presence in the neighboring Northern Mali of the Salafist brigade Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb (AQIM), which prohibits access to the region to foreigners for security reasons.The brutal halt in the tourist activity came with the decline of the Tuareg subculture that had been forged through their entrepreneurial dedication to tourism.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The influence of tourism on the host societies’cultures and identities has been a major preoccupation for anthropologists and sociologists, sometimes even geographers, ever since tourism entered the realm of these disciplines. The first research endeavours, such as those of Van den Berghe (1980) have considered the influence of this “interethnic relationship” on the local populations to be rather negative. The authors referred to concepts such as “acculturation”, which results in a process of asymmetrical cultural borrowing (Nunez, 1963 ; Nash, 2001) or “commodification”, (Greenwood, 1989) which transforms cultural traditions into commodities. The increasing number of empirical studies on tourism starting in the 1990’s has opened the way to new perspectives, this time more positive. They concern, in particular, the capacity of local actors to face this external influence. The proponents of this thought have noted the revitalization of certain cultural elements in host societies, such as handicrafts (Deitch 1989, Silverman 1999), as well as the newfound interest for the touristic exploitation of certain traditions (Van Beek, 2003 ; Kahrmann, 1995).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Other authors have shown the capacity of local actors to manage their contact with tourists in order to decrease the negative effects of their arrival, and to use tourism as potential for innovation and the enrichment of local tradition (Picard, 1990). Others still, returning to a critical stance, have shown that the confrontation with the stereotypical images brought by the tourist against the cultural reality of the visited society could lead to a radicalization of ethnic identity (Friedman, 1994) and rouse conflicts within the host society in the face of the introduction of cultural innovations (Tilley, 1997).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Beyond the observation of the local actors’ capacity for “agency” (Crain, 1996), the salient analysis here would be to seize the complexity of the identity questions linked to tourism while discerning the different levels of identity within the visited society. This article therefore deals with the development of tourism among the Tuareg of Northern Niger, focusing the analysis on the identity transformations observed among local actors. We shall begin by discussing the western imagination relative to the Sahara and the Tuareg, an element that the Tuareg have remarkably played upon to encourage regional tourism. Then, from an historic perspective, we will study the growth of tourism in the Agadez region, while highlighting its appropriation by the Tuareg, and the identity adaptations to which this appropriation has led. Last but not least, we consider the decline of tourism, as a result of the 2007-2009 rebellion, and the presence in the neighbouring Northern Mali of the Salafist brigade Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb (AQIM), which prohibits access to the region to foreigners for security reasons. We shall then see that this brutal halt in touristic activity came with the decline of the Tuareg subculture that had been forged through their entrepreneurial dedication to tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Imagination and tourism in Tuareg country</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For several long decades now, the Sahara and the Tuareg has exerted a certain fascination on Europeans, the French in particular. This fascination is reflected in a set of discourses, metaphors and stereotypical images concerning both the desert and the people who inhabit and draw from it their means of subsistence. These aspects constitute the basic elements of the tourists’ perspective and their interest in the region. This vision does not pretend to conform to any sort of reality. It is rather marked by an “aestheticization” and an idealization of the place and the people. Urry (1990, p. 1) speaks of a systematic and socially organized “tourist gaze” which highlights certain traits of a landscape, a particular place or a culture. These characteristics influence the imagination, even the emotion of the tourist, and as such condition the representation of the local reality he/she creates. This process of imaginary appropriation is a crucial structural element of Saharan tourism. It is maintained by the diffusion of images in the media and other platforms. The tourists themselves are involved in this process, because imagination is the essential reason of their decision to undertake the journey and face those stereotypical images. But what are the actual contents that determine the perception of Tuareg and the Sahara which interest us here ?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The western myth of the Sahara and the Tuareg was first forged in France, starting in the 19th century, through the influence of such early accounts of travelers like René Caillé and Henri Duveyrier. The main elements of the “myth” were then consolidated during the inter-war period, particularly through the popular Saharan novel, such as </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">L’Atlantide</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> by Pierre Benoît, published in 1920 (Henry, 1984, p. 431). From the beginning, the desert and the Tuareg were the pillars of this myth, and mutually enriched and amplified each other. Indeed, the Tuareg derive a large part of their mysterious aura from the fact that they live in the Sahara, a space that is by definition inhospitable and without resources</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Boilley, 2000).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The image of the Tuareg was heavily influenced by an historical context marked by a certain ambivalence. Until the First World War, the Tuareg were seen as fierce, sometimes cruel warriors, who oppressed the black populations of the Sahel, and subjected them to raids or even reduced them to slavery. This unflattering image may be found in René Caillé’s work. It was further reinforced by the massacre of the second mission of Colonel Flatters by Hoggar Tuareg in 1881 (Henry, 1996, p. 258). In addition to this image of a dominant people, other images of more benevolent opinions emerged, such as those of Henri Duveyrier and Heinrich Barth, who likened the Tuareg to brave and proud knights and stressed their hospitality and the noble customs of their aristocracy. However, this positive view remained very much a minority, as the fierce Tuareg resistance caused serious problems to the French colonial expansion, notably in the revolt of 1916-1917. It wasn’t until after the conquest of the Sahara and the first world war that the romantic perception of the Tuareg as a “noble savage” was solidified. It implicitly recalled the European medieval knight, and emphasized the particular status of women as well as an Islam then qualified as “gentle”. Another reason for the fascination of Europeans with Tuareg lies in the physical attraction of Europeans to the Tuareg men and women. While during the golden age of the Saharan novel (the 1920’s and 30’s) romantic relationships between Frenchmen and Tuareg women were predominant, the opposite can be seen in contemporary literature.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The myth of the Sahara and Tuareg simultaneously created an exotic counter-world to western civilization and a certain closeness, even a human and cultural complicity between Tuareg and Europeans. In the 1930’s, the Tuareg became a symbolic figure of the French colonial empire, and made their debut into touristic advertising, notably for the bus lines of the Société Algérienne des Transports Tropicaux (SATT), which linked Algeria to Niger (Bejui, 1994). In the travel guide for the Sahara, the romantic discourse on the Tuareg appears as early as 1938 (Boilley, 2000). This romantic image is reinforced in the 1970’s and 1980’s by socio-economic considerations that deplore the disappearance of nomadic life due to dramatic droughts (1973-74 and 1983-84), the triumph of modernization and globalization.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The colonial myth therefore finds itself anchored and spread in the form of richly illustrated works, novels, travel accounts, documentaries, films and exhibits which always reproduce the same stereotypes. This is true especially for the catalogues of travel agencies and tourist guides. All of them highlight images such as those of sand dunes and turban wearing Tuareg riding camels. As such, the “tourist gaze” is built upon this “natural and ethnic marker” (Adams, 1984, p. 475 ; MacCannell, 1999, p. 41) which urges and inspires tourists to undertake the journey. This impact of the imaginary appropriation of faraway landscapes or cultures can influence the very identity of the visited peoples through their interactions with tourists carrying those markers.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Northern Niger has particularly “benefited” of the mythos (Pandolfi, 2004). Tourism in Northern Niger is essentially a “desert tourism”, the main attractions of which are the sand dunes of the Tenere. There is also the Aïr massif, which offers a contrasting landscape of volcanic mountains crossed by temporary streams which give birth to lush green oases of gardens and palm groves</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The city of Agadez too presents much tourist interest : founded in the second half of the XVth century, its Sudanese architecture is perfectly preserved, with its old ochre coloured mud houses.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To this natural and historic heritage is added the human presence : the region is populated by Tuareg, who are mainly pastoralists, agro-pastoralists, caravan traders and artisans. Nevertheless, “cultural tourism” is poorly developed, even marginal. The Tuareg myth remains an essential motivation for tourists, but for most of them, the Tuareg are merely an element of the decor, rarely the main reason for the trip. A minority of visitors bothers to understand the traditional society and to comprehend the causes of its deterioration. This quest for authenticity led certain tourists to claim a degree of ethnological knowledge. It also sometimes roused a feeling of solidarity, which led to a humanitarian, even political engagement during the first rebellion (1991-95). However, this philosophy of human, humanist, humanitarian and politically engaged travel allowed these tourists to guard themselves against the harmful effects that commonly plague the activity : the point for them was to visit “in another way”, and therefore to dissociate themselves from mass tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Tourism development and assertion of identity (1968-2000)</section>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Saharan tourism in Niger was launched by Europeans (Gregoire E., 1999, repr. </span>2010). <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The pharmacist Louis Henri Mourèn in Niamey was one of the first to identify sites and realize their touristic potential. In 1968, he founded a travel agency that marked the beginning of the touristic exploitation of the Sahara in Niger. He enjoyed the support of the President of Niger, Hamani Diori, who aimed to promote that activity ; this desire was reflected in a law that allowed foreigners to set up agencies. At the same time (1974), the Italian Vittorio Gioni created Sahara-Niger after being ousted from Algeria by ONAT (Algerian National Office of Tourism). From 1974 to 1980, Sahara-Niger was the main agency to operate in northern Niger (200 visitors in 1975) after the rapid withdrawal of Louis-Henri Mourèn.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The year 1980 marked the first break : national legislation prohibited the exercise of tourism to foreigners for the sake of the “nigerianization” of the sector. The same decree withdrew its license to Sahara-Niger and gave it to Temet-voyages belonging to Mano ag Dayak. As they did in Algeria before, the Europeans gave way to the Tuareg, whom they had initiated into the business (management, hospitality and customer management, installation of bivouacs, preparing Western cuisine, etc..). This transfer took place without conflict, with Europeans even helping their former Tuareg employees to start their own agency.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With his newly obtained license, Mano ag Dayak expanded the logistical means and the staff of his agency. His charisma and sense of public relations enabled him to become the special correspondent of European agencies and to weave a web of relationships that made him the indispensable go-between for all those who had a project (tourism, film, development, etc.. ) </span>in the Agadez region. <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For five years he enjoyed a monopoly over the situation and became the figurehead of Saharan tourism in Niger. During that time, he involved for the first time his network of contacts during the drought of 1983-1984 by calling to attention the poverty of the Tuareg in the Aïr and the need to provide assistance.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In 1987, the Nigerian government made tourism a national priority ; it believed that this activity could foster local development through the creation of micro and small businesses and hence employment. More generally, it saw it as a way to reduce poverty. This commitment was reflected in the creation of the Ministry of Transports and Tourism and the adoption of measures to promote this activity. Six years later, tourism was the third source of gross income of foreign currency in the country, that is 2.5 to 3 billion CFA francs</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, just behind the uranium, agricultural and pastoral exports. In the same vein, the Ministry pushed Temet-voyage to become a veritable small business. In the late eighties, the agency had indeed accumulated a large debt due to lax management. A company in its own name, it became in 1989 a limited company with capital of 20 million CFA distributed between three Tuareg and four European shareholders. Mano ag Dayak alone owned more than half of the capital. With a loan from the International Bank of West Africa, the agency invested in the purchase of new vehicles and set up a liaison office based near Paris. Temet-voyages served 900 customers in 1986 and nearly 2000 in 1988, plus other groups travelling in the Niger River valley and the park of “W”, south of the country. Its turnover amounted to 450 million CFA francs during the 1989-1990 season ; then it fell the following year with the start of the rebellion that led to its first provisional and then final closing.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the early nineties, the Tuareg, under the leadership of Mano ag Dayak, managed to control Saharan tourism : of the ten agencies or so then in Agadez, the six foremost ones belonged to the Tuareg. However, these agencies depended on their partnership with European tour operators who sent tourists and as such achieved higher margins. By revealing their region to an already captivated audience, the Tuareg carried out an activity that suited them perfectly, the Sahara remaining for them a social, cultural as well as economic space. A careful examination of the actors at that time, however, reveals an unequal access to tourism : the Iforas, whose leading personality was Mano ag Dayak, and, to a lesser extent, the Kel Ferouane were more successful than other groups (Kel Ewey, Kel Tadele, etc.) in engaging into the profession. This hegemony also created jealousy. Some people, such as the inhabitants of the eastern edge of the Aïr (Kogo and Zagado regions) and the Bagzan massif, benefited little from tourism. They devoted themselves instead to the development of agro-pastoral products for the two areas, even though they had the most beautiful landscapes. Finally, Agadez gained more from tourism than the hinterland through the development of a series of activities and infrastructures such as hotels, restaurants, agencies and crafts which were closely linked to it. Therefore in this period, several peoplewere excluded from the tourism benefits.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, from 1980 to 1991, the Agadez region began experiencing a significant development through tourism, the latter pulling it out of its torpor. The Tuareg cleverly managed both to respond to thethe imagination of tourists and to play on their search for “authentic” adventure and their quest for the absolute. After all, they knew how to exploit the myth that they embodied in the eyes of tourists. This sympathy had turned into an unconditional adherence to their cause : during travels in the Aïr and the Tenere, the guides made visitors aware of the miserable fate of their relatives affected by the droughts of 1973-74 and 1983-84 which condemned some to exile. The NGO TUAREG, founded in 1992 by Mano ag Dayak was thus one of the first to intervene with a budget of nearly 160,000 FF in 1999. Its actions involved education, health, construction of pastoral wells, and agro-ecology. Mano ag Dayak (E. Gregoire, 2006) was also indirectly responsible for </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Grain de Sable</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, another NGO founded in 1996. From a political standpoint, when the Tuareg rebellion began (1991-1995), many former tourists supported Mano ag Dayak who easily managed to mobilize his strong network of friendships in France (politicians, journalists, organizers and competitors in the Paris-Dakar rally, etc..). He appeared as the ambassador of the Tuareg cause, committed to political dialogue and peaceful resolution of conflict, rather than as one of its military leaders. That role fell unto Rhissa ag Boula, his former accountant. In this context, a whole pro-Tuareg French lobby (Casajus , 1995 ; Bourgeot , 1992), supported the rebellion despite of their ignorance of the Tuareg “problem” ; Tuareg society was then known to them only under aspects of its folklore. The rebellion therefore had a significant international dimension (Salifou A., 1993), with Mano ag Dayak portrayed as the spokesman of the Tuareg community by the French press, whom he had rallied to his fight. He remarkably exploited the image of a community which, without outside mobilization, could disappear under the fire of the Nigerian army who was nevertheless held in check on the field. He had, however, no “traditional” legitimacy</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and no mandate to represent alone the Tuareg world, which was quite fragmented. His position on the forefront was only due to his work as a tour operator and the fame he had gained from it in France.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The year 1992 marked a second turning point : the region had for the first time a sharp drop in tourist arrivals due to the insecurity caused by the rebellion. This situation continued in 1993 and 1994 as the area was the scene of battles between Tuareg fronts and the Niger military forces. Without going into the details of the rebellion’s causes (Grégoire, 1999, repr. 2010), it should be noted that the Tuareg “problem” was born with colonization, which caused the dislocation of the political organization and the military power of the community. Niger’s independence then made it move from a dominant to a dominated position, Hausa and Djerma populations of the South seizing the state machinery because of their higher education. Underrepresented in positions of responsibility in the absence of qualified managers, Tuareg society was therefore left with no control over the new state and its political and economic choices. Coupled with a reduction of its travel space with the birth of nation-states and the deterioration of its traditional economy, this political ostracizing led the Ishumars, young Tuareg exiles in North Africa, to take up arms against the state of Niger, after having learned how to handle them in the Libyan Islamic Legion. Marked by strong identity claims, the rebellion ended with the signing of the Ouagadougou Peace agreements (April 24, 1995). Some tourism professionals considered a possible rebirth and began building a new infrastructure. Agencies kept on developing round the time of Mano ag Dayak’s death (1995) in a plane crash on his way to Niamey to negotiate with the authorities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The end of 1996 saw the return of tourists and the resuming of flights between Agadez and Paris. But the season was soon interrupted after the mugging of several groups by, to use local terminology, “uncontrolled bands”, during their tour in the Aïr. The Paris-Agadez air route was again suspended. Local agencies that had invested large sums recorded significant losses. Relying on the cantonment of former combatants to stop the action of the “uncontrolled bands”, they hoped to restart in 1997-98. Their hopes were again disappointed : in November 1997, heavy fighting at the foothills of the Bagzan Mountains, between the Niger Armed Forces and the fighters of UFRA (Union of Forces for armed resistance) and FARS (Revolutionary Armed Forces of the Sahara) cast doubts upon the peace accords of April 24, 1995. The situation only improved in the late 1990s with the signing of the Algiers Agreements and the cantonment of former combatants.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Emergence and decline of a new subculture</section>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">During the years 2000-2006 tourism saw a rebirth in the Agadez region under the leadership of Rhissa ag Boula, a former rebel leader who became Minister of tourism in the government of President Mamadou Tandja. He granted licenses to local agencies, even if they did not always fulfill the legal requirements. In practice, this meant the creation of new agencies ; 62 were identified in the sector in 2007. They then employed more than 500 guides, drivers, cooks, cameleers, accountants and watch guards. With few exceptions, their managers and their staff were nationals of various Tuareg groups of Aïr ; their directors primarily employed their own family or group members.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In general, the directors and employees of these agencies belonged to the noble social strata (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">imajighen</span></em><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) or vassals (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">imghad</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) of Tuareg society. They were also almost exclusively men. Only three companies were run by women. However, the growing number of agencies led to a gradual diversification of the social structure of the stakeholders. The disappearance of Mano ag Dayak had left a vacuum. The latter was filled, on the one hand, by his former partners and staff and on the other by new actors. As such, alongside the Iforas and the Kel Ferouane, the Kel Ewey and Kel Tadele, to which the Minister Rhissa ag Boula belongs, engaged in the industry although they had not been involved in it to the same extent before.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">After the rebellion of the nineties, we witness the resuming of European tour operators thanks to the restoration of air links between France and Agadez. The number of tourists visiting the region increased rapidly, stabilizing between 3,500 and 5,000 clients per season (Regional Direction of Tourism in Agadez</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). Given the difficulties of transportation in the region, combined with the residual insecurity due to banditry, all the European operators associated with local partners to whom they subcontracted their groups : with few exceptions, all journeys in Aïr and Tenere were then organized by local travel agencies. Individual tourism was virtually non-existent. Travel agencies organized tours of one to three weeks in Aïr and Tenere in 4×4 vehicles (65 % of all trips), by camel (30 %) or hiking (5 %) (Scholze, 2009).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Working in tourism in collaboration with European tour operators then became a true profession for the Tuareg, who in this way diversified the local economy. This was not the case in the early development of regional tourism (1970’s and 1980’s). The first Tuareg who had invested in this area were indeed being criticized by their relatives, particularly by the local aristocracy who had a tendency to regard manual labor such as mechanics, for example, as an unworthy task. They also accused the leaders of local tourism to “follow the white man” : this criticism in fact referred to a fear of neglecting the traditions and values of their community, as well as a fear to see the Tuareg convert to Christianity.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Over time, attitudes changed : it became commonly accepted that this commitment to tourism could be lucrative and did not mean abandoning traditions. This acceptance became evident in the 2000s, as many young Tuaregs came to see tourism as the revenue source that pastoralism no longer offered. Meanwhile, the pioneers of tourism who had entered the business rather accidentally, by adapting their traditional activities as cameleers, for example and through ties developed with Europeans, gradually began to abandon their nomadic lives to devote more time to their new and now dominant activity.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The work and lifestyle of these tour operators was then marked by the combination of traditional elements (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">kel eru</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> meaning “people of the past”) and modern (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">or kel azzaman</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> as “people of today”) ones. This combination was based on a process of cultural appropriation, where foreign or modern elements were integrated into the indigenous culture through a reinterpretation of these elements, thereby giving them local meaning and local value (Probst &amp;amp; Spittler, 2004). Finally, this appropriation and the change in lifestyle would operate to varying degrees according to the work performed. A cameleer of Aïr accompanying a camel tour with tourists (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">meharee</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) could easily take advantage of his traditional practices of breeding and training of camels. The modern element lied then in his interaction with tourists. As for driver-guides, they resorted to their traditional techniques of orientation in the desert, but they also had to learn to drive a car on the sand, and develop some basic knowledge of mechanics. Finally, an agency director had to reach an even higher level of appropriation by addressing the needs of a global market in promoting his products, keeping clean accounting books and offering services of high quality.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Beyond the appropriation of new technologies, skills and knowledge, we can see that, depending on the work that was performed, tourist activity had implications in different areas of ordinary life. After accompanying a group, a cameleer returned to his camp where he resumed his nomadic life. The drivers, guides and cooks lived an urban life in Agadez during the tourist season, then they returned to the Aïronce the tourists had left. Finally, a growing number of Tuareg agency directors travelled to Europe during the off season to build relationships with European tour operators. Some of them married European women and shared their lives between Niger and Europe. One can observea process of a growing spatial deployment from the cameleer tothe agency manager (from the camp to Europe) that takes advantage of new means of transport, from all-terrain vehicles to commercial airliners. This deployment was accompanied by the appropriation of new knowledge and world experience. This included an ever more intense confrontation with urban and modern life, along with a certain distancing from the traditional lifestyle and values. Yet, for all that, this confrontation did not lead those involved in tourism to demonstrate any distancing with respect to their Tuareg identity. Quite to the contrary, the Tuareg living farthest from their usual environment due to their tourism related work were most often very conservative, placing a high value on their home country and their culture. This process was also explained by the fact that their homeland and cultural identity were recognized by their visitors and were the very resource of their business. In sum, work in the agencies offered the Tuareg a “modernized” life while allowing them to remain attached to their traditions and their region. Moreover, they readily described themselves as “modern nomads”, which equated tourism with a new form of nomadism</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The symbol of this modernization was then the ownership of the Toyota 4×4 which partly replaced the camel as a means of transportation and foundation of wealth. As a result, actors attributed the word “ehare” (wealth), traditionally applied to cattle, to their cars. The owners and drivers gave camel names to their 4×4’s and the money earned carrying tourists was referred to as “camel’s milk” (akh-n-talamt).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This appropriation process, coupled with the transformation of the original identity into that of modern nomads, led to the birth of a new subculture among the local tourism operators. They shared a work ethic based on their knowledge of the trade, their mastery of the technical side, and pride supported by the admiration of tourists for them. They gladly referred to the memory of “heroes” of the trade and to a specific directory of stories and anecdotes relating to tourism. At the same time, they remained attached to their Tuareg identity and still felt like full members of their community.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">But besides these similarities, the adherents to that subculture differed from each other relative to their belonging to different Tuareg groups, lifestyles and experiences. This was not a subculture that stood together. These aforementioned travel agencies were in very strong competition. While their number had nearly doubled between 2002 and 2007, the number of tourists remained relatively stable. In fact, during these years only about fifteen agencies were well established in the area and shared the largest contingent of tourists. Their leaders enjoyed the special relationships they had built up with Western tour operators. The other agencies struggled to find customers that they solicited in hotels in Agadez or among European expats installed in Niger, working for the mines of Arlit or primarily in Niamey. By capturing the local resource, some of the main Tuareg operators became wealthy characters who influenced policy primarily at the municipal level. As a part of this emerging subculture, they began and continue building a new bourgeoisie (Bourgeot, 1992).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The involvement of the Tuareg in the agencies means not merely changing their lifestyle. It also affected their social status. They began to play an intermediary role between the public and tourists by facilitating their contact. This primarily concerns the inhabitants of the Aïr who were also eager to take advantage of tourism. Among them were blacksmiths (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">enaden</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) who manufacture silver jewelry and stone artifacts of gypsum, and their wives who made leather goods or necklaces for tourists. In this group were also </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">shasturis</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (tourist-hunters), many in the oasis of Timia. They majority of them did not belong to the class of blacksmiths, but were most often young noble men (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">imajighen</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) or descendants of former slaves (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ighawelen</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). Relations between blacksmiths and those </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">shasturis</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> on the one hand, and travel agencies on the other were often full of conflict. Having no customers on their own, artisans and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">shasturis</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> residing in the Aïr depended on agencies to sell their products to tourists ; as a matter of fact, it was the guides and drivers who ultimately decided to take the groups to one place or another.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">As for women and men of noble descent who wished to sell jewelry, pottery and basketry, their dependence on intermediaries was even stronger. They not only needed the agencies to bring to them customers, but their noble status prevented them from coming into direct and public contact with tourists : this constraint refers to obligations imposed upon them by tradition, as these were linked to the respect for values such as pride (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">asshak</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) and shame (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">takarakit</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). In this perspective, selling items to strangers at the sight of all was considered shameful by the local population. These actors therefore had an imperative need for intermediaries so they entrusted their goods to blacksmiths or </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">shasturis</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> who sold on behalf of them for a fee.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Another form of mediation was the organization of cultural events : traditional songs and dances (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">tende</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) without or with camels (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">fantasia</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). These performances were requested by agency guides and organized locally by a village intermediary. In this domain, the noble women of the villages and especially in the Aïr Oasis of Timia were very active and participated in these events as singers. At Timia, a tende for tourists was organized up to twenty times per season and was so well rehearsed it could even be spontaneously put on. This was because the people of Timia had acquired some experience in these events and because, unlike many other parts of the Aïr, traditions there had remained very much alive. Under these conditions, one wonders how the desire to preserve their ancestral traditions meshed with their value as a tourist attraction. A first answer comes to mind : since the tradition was well preserved, the people of Timia are readily able to produce such events. Although the context and the audience were different from the traditional framework, there was little change in the dances and songs performed in front of tourists or at a wedding or a baptism ; they were essentially the same. A second answer to the question posed above was the high valueaccorded by the local actors to their cultural identity. Hence for the Tuareg of Timia, it was evident that tourists came to immerse themselves in these traditions. Therefore, the touristic imagination of the Tuareg culture coincided perfectly with the perception that the host societies had of themselves. The recognition of this culture by tourists reinforced their self-esteem and local identity. Finally, unlike the situation of selling objects, noble women who participated in these events could make money without violating the principles that governed feelings of shame and pride : they acted as a group and under the rules of hospitality applied to foreigners.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Under these circumstances, the mediation of tourism contributed to the preservation of traditions. Conversely, there were areas of the mediation which contributed to a “modernization” of the villages and settlements. Tuaregs who worked for agencies introduced new goods and disseminated new knowledge about the world and ideas hitherto unknown. For young men living in the villages, tourist operators that circulated in 4×4, dressed in expensive clothes, have become a role model. However, the tourists themselves exerted little influence on the local population : most of the men of Timia continued their work as herders, caravan traders or gardeners. The tourists constituted just one source of sometimes significant extra income.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In early 2007, a new Tuareg rebellion affected the Aïr and more generally the Agadez region. As in the previous one, tourism actors played an important role in it, particularly Aghali Alambo, a former rebel and head of an agency of Agadez who became the leader of the MNJ (Niger Movement for Justice). Since then, tourism no longer resumed because it became too dangerous to send Europeans to the region. Therefore, the new bourgeoisie, keeper of the subculture born of tourism, is now suddenly deprived of its main resource and related income. Some agency managers and staff joined the rebellion, while others took refuge in Europe. But most of them stayed at home and are since unemployed or living by their wits.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In order to understand the identity issues related to the Saharan tourism in Niger, one should distinguish two levels of identity :</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">By focusing the analysis on local actors, we have seen that the tourism imaginary linked to the Sahara and the Tuareg has been a mainstay of their business. In this context, the European tour operators have subcontracted tourist groups to Tuareg partners because they offered low-cost services and knew the ground perfectly. Although the Tuaregs themselves were not the main reason for the practice of tourism in northern Niger, visitors still required that they accompany them and make them discover their region and its inhabitants. However, it is difficult to assess whether the tourist imagination was truly instrumentalized by the local actors or if there was a case of true appropriation. Does, for example, the speech delivered by Tuareg guides on the beauty of the desert, when the Sahara is traditionally regarded by the caravaneers as a source of danger, show a change of perspective due to their interaction with tourists ? Or does that discourse only show a mastery of Western stereotypes and a representation of fact, limited to the context of the exercise of tourism ? This has to be answered for each actor individually.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A second level refers to the social identity of local actors. Tuareg who have worked in agencies belonged to a particular social strata of society. They were distinguished from the nobles and their vassals in having created their own subculture and having become a kind of new bourgeoisie. Yet these actors always perceived themselves as belonging to the nomadic culture, fundamental part of their traditional collective identity. In addition, some representatives of this sub-culture played a key role in the political claims in the rebellions of the 1990s and 2007-2009.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Finally, these local actors have played an essential role for the population of the Aïr by making them take advantage of the benefits of tourism. From the perspective of cultural events, the mediation of local actors has made possible a “dialogical relationship” (Tilley, 1997) where recognition from tourists reinforced the tradition and collective identity within the villages and encampments. The valorisation of these traditions for tourism attested to the strength of cultural identity and vitality, of maintaining a self-esteem which is strong enough to toleratethe opening to appropriated innovations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">More generally, the example of Niger also highlights the fragility of any touristic activity that can collapse overnight because of a changing political climate or natural hazards. This article has highlighted the precarious economic success and accumulation that benefited, for a time, those who invested in the sector, including the Tuareg agency leaders. The rebellion of the 1990s was a disaster for them and for tourism development in northern Niger just as it was beginning to bear its fruits by providing jobs and distributing income in an area that had great need of new activities. Far from having learned the lessons of the past, the rebellion of 2007-2009 dealt a fatal blow to regional development. It is hard to imagine in the current political context how the activity could possibly resume.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Indeed, as shown by a recent issue of the journal Herodotus (Gregoire and Bourgeot, 2011), profound changes are affecting the region. Northern Niger is going through a very rough time due to the settlement of Islamic terrorist groups on its soil, the development of trafficking of all kinds (cigarettes, drugs, weapons, etc..), illegal immigration from Sub-Saharan regions on its way to the countries of the European Union and finally the competition waged between countries of the North and emerging countries to appropriate its mining and oil wealth. Thus, in the space of ten years, the Sahara in Niger became a coveted space from which tourists have been driven out. As a result, its geopolitical situation is in shambles ; cards are redistributed with no real idea of who will be dealt the best hand : the United States, for security reasons, France, for historical and economic reasons, and China are the main stakeholders of this new configuration. The “Arab Spring” also changed the situation : the fall of Colonel Gaddafi was, for Niger and Mali, a major event given the influence he exerted on the Tuareg population. Many living in Libya stood for him and took advantage of the massive distribution of weapons to rearm just as AQMI, which raises fears of a resumption of armed struggle against the Sahelian countries. This is what is happening in Mali where the National Movement for the Liberation of Azawad (MNLA) started, in mid-January 2012, its military actions in the North of the country with support from the AQMI and Tuareg movements close to it (Ansar Dine). The Niger is not (yet ?) affected by this new rebellion, but in such a context of insecurity, the recovery in tourism seems, and for a long time, unthinkable and impossible.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Adams K. M., 1984, “Come to Tana Toraja, Land of the Heavenly Kings. Travel Agents as Brokers in Ethnicity”, Annals of Tourism Research, n° 11, pp. 469–485.</reference>
        <reference>Barth H, 1857, Reisen und Entdeckungen in Nord und Central-Africa in den Jahren 1849 bis 1855, Gotha, Justus Perthes.</reference>
        <reference>Bejui D. &amp; P., 1994, Exploits et fantasmes transsahariens 80 ans de traversées sahariennes abouties ou rêvées, en auto, en camion, en train et en avion, Chanac, Éditions La Régordane.</reference>
        <reference>Boilley P., 2000, “Sahara et Sahariens. Les Touaregs dans le regard des guides de voyage” in Chabaud G. (ed.), Les guides imprimés du XVIe au XXe siècle. Villes, paysages, voyages, Paris, Belin, pp. 619–641.</reference>
        <reference>Bourgeot A., 1992, “L’enjeu politique de l’histoire : vision idéologique des événements touaregs (1990-1992)”, Politique africaine, n° 48, pp. 129-135.</reference>
        <reference>Casajus D., 1995, “Les amis français de la cause touarègue”, Cahiers d’études africaines, XXXV, n° 137, pp. 237-250.</reference>
        <reference>Crain M. M., 1996, “Negotiating Identities in Quito’s Cultural Borderlands” in Howes D. (ed.), Cross-Cultural Consumption : Global Markets, Local Realities, New York, Routledge, pp. 125–137.</reference>
        <reference>Deitch L.I., 1989, “The Impact of Tourism on the Arts and Crafts of the Indians of the Southwestern Unites States” in Smith V. L. (ed.), Hosts and Guests. The Anthropology of Tourism, Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Press, pp. 221–235.</reference>
        <reference>Dayak M., 1992, Touareg, la tragédie, Paris, Éditions Lattès.</reference>
        <reference>Dayak M., 1996, Je suis né avec du sable dans les yeux, Paris, Éditions Fixot.</reference>
        <reference>Friedman J., 1994, Cultural Identity and Global Process, London, Sage Publications.</reference>
        <reference>Greenwood D.J., 1989, “Culture by the Pound : An Anthropological Perspective on Tourism as Cultural Commoditization” in Smith V. L. (ed.), Hosts and Guests. The Anthropology of Tourism, Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Press, pp. 172–185.</reference>
        <reference>Grégoire E. &amp; Bourgeot A., 2011, “Géopolitique du Sahara”, revue Hérodote, n° 142, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Grégoire E., 1999, réimp. 2001, réed. 2010, Touaregs du Niger, le destin d’un mythe, nouvelle édition avec une postface de l’auteur (20 pages), Paris, Éditions Karthala.</reference>
        <reference>Grégoire E., 2006, “Tourisme culturel, engagement politique et actions humanitaires dans la région d’Agadès (Niger)”, revue Autrepart, n° 40, pp. 95-111.</reference>
        <reference>Henry J.R. (1984), “Romans sahariens et imaginaire français”, Baduel P.-R. (ed.) : Enjeux sahariens, Paris, CNRS, pp. 424–440.</reference>
        <reference>Henry J.R., 1996, “Les Touaregs des Français” in Claudot-Hawad H. (ed.), Touaregs et autres sahariens entre plusieurs mondes, Aix-en-Provence, IREMAN, pp. 249–274.</reference>
        <reference>Kahrmann Ch., 1995, Hoffen auf den reichen Strand, Berlin, Dietrich Reimer.</reference>
        <reference>MacCannell D., 1999, The Tourist. A New Theory of the Leisure Class, Berkeley, University of California Press.</reference>
        <reference>Nash D., 2001, Anthropology of Tourism, Oxford, Elsevier.</reference>
        <reference>Nunez T., 1963, “Tourism, Tradition, and Acculturation : Weekendismo in a Mexican Village”, Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, n° 21, pp. 347–352.</reference>
        <reference>Pandolfi P., 2004, “La construction du mythe touareg, quelques remarques et hypothèses”, Ethnologies comparées, n° 7,[http://alor.univ-montp3.fr/cerce/r7/pl.p.htm].</reference>
        <reference>Picard M., 1990, “Cultural Tourism in Bali : Cultural Performances as Tourist Attraction”, Indonesia, n° 49, pp. 37–74.</reference>
        <reference>Probst P. &amp; Spittler G., 2004, “From an Anthropology of Astonishment to a Critique of Anthropology’s Common Sense : An Exploration of the Notion of Local Vitality in Africa” in Probst P. &amp; Spittler G.(eds.), Between Resistance and Expansion. Explorations of Local Vitality in Africa, Münster, Lit Verlag, pp. 7-32.</reference>
        <reference>Roux M., 1996, Le désert de sable. Le Sahara dans l’imaginaire des Français (1900–1994), Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Salifou A., 1993, La question touarègue, Paris, Éditions Karthala.</reference>
        <reference>Scholze M., 2009, Moderne Nomaden und fliegende Händler. Tuareg und Tourismus in Niger, Muenster, Lit Verlag.</reference>
        <reference>Silverman E. K., 1999, “Tourist Art as the Crafting of Identity in the Sepik River (Papua New Guines)”, in Phillips R. B. &amp; Steiner C. B. (eds.), Unpacking Culture. Art and Commodity in Colonial and Postcolonial Worlds, Berkeley, University of California Press, pp. 51–66.</reference>
        <reference>Tilley Ch., 1997, “Performing Culture in the Global Village”, Critique of Anthropology, n° 1, pp. 67–89.</reference>
        <reference>Van Beek W. E.A., 2003, “African Tourist Encounters : Effects of Tourism on Two West African Societies”, Africa, n° 73, pp. 251–289.</reference>
        <reference>Van den Berghe P. L., 1980, “Tourism as ethnic Relations : A Case Study of Cuzco, Peru “, Ethnic and Racial Studies, n° 3, pp. 375–391.</reference>
        <reference>Urry J., 1990, The Tourist Gaze, London, Sage.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">The geographer Michel Roux (1996) distinguishes two important elements characterizing the French outlook on the Sahara. Firstly, the desert appears as a place of initiation for the Europeans tired of modern civilization. Secondly, the sand dune has become the emblematic image that represents the absolute essence of the desert landscape from an aesthetic standpoint.</note>
        <note id="2">Even if the desert dominates European imagination when it comes to the Sahara, the massifs of Hoggar and Aïr are also part of the myth. Heinrich Barth declared the Aïr to be « the Alps of the desert » (1857 : 327). This discourse persists until today.</note>
        <note id="3">1 Euro = 655,957 FCFA.</note>
        <note id="4">Some argue that the French secret service who was looking for a privileged mediator favored Mano ag Dayak at the expense of other leaders of the rebellion (Casajus, 1995).</note>
        <note id="5">Words in italics are tamajeq words, the Tuareg language.</note>
        <note id="6">The main tourist season begins in November and ends in February.</note>
        <note id="7">Local operators used to describe the journey performed with tourists with the term “awezlu” (travel) traditionally applied to the caravan.</note>
    </notes>
</article>