<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_GAMZJEVA_49-22_Is_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/teoros/2671" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <revue>Teoros</revue>
        <numero>33, 2</numero>
        <annee>2014</annee>
    </meta>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Miranda Zambrano" prenom="Gloria Amparo" email="mirandazambrano.gloria@yahoo.com.mx">
            <description>
                Researcher, Demographic and Political Studies Department, Economic-Administrative Sciences Division, Universidad de Guanajuato (Mexico), 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Vidaurri Aréchiga" prenom="José Eduardo" email="vidaurriarechiga@hotmail.com">
            <description>
                Researcher, Business Management, and Supervision Department, Economic-Administrative Sciences Division, Universidad de Guanajuato (Mexico); 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Indigenous Communities</titre>
    <sousTitre>Resisting Ecocentric Sustainability within Rural Tourism</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        Agricultural, communal, and indigenous communities, organized as ejidos,1 have for centuries shown an ecocentric and devoted relationship with Nature, humanity, and the planet, and continue to apply their values in the development of rural tourism that promotes sustainability. This is an alternative archetype to the Western development paradigm (whose universalist, one-dimensional, and egocentric viewpoint has alarming impacts to the planet and humanity). Our study addresses the expressions of resistance and preservation of natural property and heritage under the guise of rural tourism services within two indigenous communities in Mexico. Our methodology was based on “participative research-action,” where ejidatarios (members of an ejido) and elders reflected on their contribution to rural sustainability. Despite the onslaught of the Western model of global development, in the midst of the 21st century we find the expression of a strong cultural and cosmological identity that expresses a particular form of relationship, both material and spiritual, with Nature—defending and re-creating an environmentally sustainable culture through multiple strategies (encompassing tourism, land, territory, and cultural identity) in the face of the worldwide onslaught and divestment of indigenous peoples. The results of this study provide substantive and symbolic values for similar areas of study.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We address the contributions of indigenous peoples and rural farmers to the sustainability of both the environment and humanity itself in today’s world, which result from over a decade of epistemological and methodological reflections (Grupo Talpuy: 1984-1997; Miranda Zambrano, 2011; Mazabel and Miranda Zambrano, 2013; Miranda Zambrano </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">,</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">2014).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Rural areas have experienced crisis since time immemorial. There are continued tendencies for exclusion, impoverishment, and dispossession of natural and sociocultural heritage, migratory pressure, dependence and thus extinction throughout Mexico (Miranda Zambrano, 2011; Miranda Zambrano </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2014). Little has been elucidated, particularly in social sciences, natural sciences, and related fields of study, regarding the origin of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">landlocked</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">panorama. Consequently, the situation is becoming even more difficult, goods and heritage are under pressure, disputes, threats, and aggravation, by actors both external and internal.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">What are the causes and what prevents us from making substantial changes in this sector? What paradigm sustains and legitimizes the historical endurance of rural areas in the face of long-established oppression and exclusion? Where does their construction begin, how are </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> organized, recognized, valued, maintained, and how do they contribute to rural tourism?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Objectives, Methodology, and Object of Study</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We compare the management, assimilation, and appropriation processes in regard to the sustainable rural tourism projects operated by two </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">2</a></sup><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">using the sustainability paradigm. The study of the structure and management of these </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> enables us to put the two rural tourism projects into context, including aspects of local culture, community business culture, local knowledge, skills, and abilities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Our research was conducted in two agricultural </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> communities; the first in the state of Guanajuato, the Balneario Ejidal Ojo de Agua de Ballesteros (BEOAB, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ejido-</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">owned waterpark in</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ojo de Agua de Ballesteros) in the city of Salvatierra, and the second in Mexico City, the</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Parque Ejidal Eco Turístico San Nicolás Totolapan (PEESNT, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ejido-</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">owned ecotouristic park in San Nicolás Totalapan). Information was gathered </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">in situ</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in both communities, where authorities (mayor, ex-commissaries, surveillance personnel, and administrators) and a group of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidatarios</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> served as lead researchers. Expert farmers (project founders, historians, local foresters, and ecologists) also participated in the study as researchers.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Participatory observation techniques and open questions were used to design the questionnaire, in a qualitative methodology context. The interview guide contained 29 basic questions, corresponding to a study of the reality and complexity of each community studied. We included life stories with “symbolic character” where applicable, as well as the exchange of knowledge in order to carry out “farmer-to-farmer” development with social actors from both projects visiting one another.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We conducted a participatory assessment inventory to gain a better understanding of the geographic area by identifying its attributes and potential while recognizing its problems and limitations. This assessment resulted in a wide panorama, yet in this study we only analyzed a segment of the overall results. The cross-sectional study was performed sequentially between January and June 2012.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The BEOAB is composed of 900 acres of land, including a forest (with a heavy cover of flora and an important presence of local fauna), a crystalline 19-acre lagoon, 16 waterholes (thermal, with an inclination for health tourism), and agricultural land, its atmosphere is clean, and its climate temperate, among other natural attributes.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">At the heart of the Ejidal Waterpark project—a social enterprise for more than ten years—are 60 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidatarios</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> who are motivated and actively manage the park to ensure the integrity of their property and natural heritage, as the inflow of water to the waterpark depends on this. This project not only has local impacts, but it also supports the ecological preservation of ten municipalities in the area’s hinterland aside from its indirect environmental contributions to water conservation and ecological preservation of the central Mexican states of Guanajuato (southern Bajío region), Queretaro, and Michoacán.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The PEESNT has managed 2300 acres of forest thanks to 336 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidatarios </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and 15 years of work, both as a tourism business and a </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Reserva Ecológica Comunitaria</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (REC, Community </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ecological Reserve</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Its strategic importance lies in being an important part of Mexico City’s ecology as it is located within the biological corridor surrounding this large metropolitan area. It also generates water for the Federal District from the groundwater collected in this watershed. It is the principal project relating to rural community ecotourism, both at the national and Latin-American levels. It integrates various production-oriented projects within the park. The central axis for further advancing the project focuses on generating employment and income, with reinvestments in infrastructures and in providing a “better living” for all beings.</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">3</a></sup>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The problem shared by social enterprises is the threat of dispossession, collapse, and loss of property and heritage due to external pressures. In the case of the BEOAB, the clandestine poaching by </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">pajareros</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (birders) and skin collectors is tied to the illegal logging by woodsmen and the growing interest of financial capital by those interested in seizing resources, especially water, causing irreparable damage to the forest (for example, the recent installation of a Korean assembly plant a few metres away from the waterpark, and foreign companies acquiring rural land in the region).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The main problem and a rising threat faced by the PEESNT and its hinterland is the hydrological and land imbalance affecting influential areas such as Mexico City as a result of forest exploitation, erosion, soil removal, water runoff, and human encroachment from urban development policies, or lack thereof. According to data from the Special Commission for Integral Water Management, the Federal District’s water deficit will grow from seven cubic metres per second to more than 18 in just a decade, as a consequence of population growth and deforestation. Each acre of the Chichinautzin corridor, the aquifer recharge, is losing 2.5 million litres of this non-renewable resource every year </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Miranda</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Zambrano</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2011: 152).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Today, both </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> experience identity (cultural and political) resistance regarding their territory, which empowers them toward an unwavering commitment to themselves, their families, and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and, therefore, contributes to water and forest sustainability. They are learning basic and innovative skills for service and production management in the context of sustainable ecotourism. To better understand this social phenomenon, it is important to comprehend how </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> were created and what the term implies in the contemporary world of rural Mexico. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">The Ejido in the Mexican Context</section>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Upon unraveling the history of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in Mexico, the persistence of rural communities in regard to land and territory becomes clear. It shows, among other things, that when communities wish to provide services previously unexplored by them, as in the case of rural community tourism, their objectives go far beyond the tourist service itself. The background is that tourism for, and in communities is nothing but another great strategic effort in order to continue defending and entrenching their goods and natural heritage, with the support of a living identity approach in addition to an eco-socio-centric approach. The goal is to show and elevate the events that created disruption through actions and thoughts of rupture or change (Villoro, 1998: 43). Let us see why.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Mexican Revolution, between 1910 and 1920, was a period of vicious clashes between the old Porfirian bourgeoisie defending their privileges, and other social sectors, mainly </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">peasants, demanding greater participation in the distribution of national wealth.</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">4</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> In the first decade of 1900, there was a popular insurgency in Mexico due to dissatisfaction with the presidential election, tied to a movement known as </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Maderism</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which was against the reelection of Porfirio Díaz who represented the dominant power groups, the town elite, the masters and stewards of estates, whom he kept safe from the labourers, but soon the whole Republic was wrapped in the Maderist Revolution (Camacho de la Rosa, 2007: 21, in Miranda</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Zambrano</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2011). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the national context, rebels were attacked by Díaz’s government, determined to kill insurgents. The land dispute was ever incontrovertible. General Emiliano Zapata and his alternative proposal outlined in the “Plan de Ayala” was clear: the revolution will not end until the land taken from the people is returned, until every elite in every community are expelled from each village, until communities re-take their social structure, built over centuries, and until the evil ranchers and landowners are extirpated from Mexico (Miranda</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Zambrano</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2011: 107).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">After the agrarian revolution, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> was established in terms of people’s rights based on the Mexican Constitution itself as well as the Mexican Agrarian Law, involving social ownership of land. Thus, the articulation of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> results from historical and social processes that the various regions of Mexico lived through; in other words, the characteristics of previous organizational schemes, of processes of control, and political participation in the defense of the land and cultural heritage tied to it, of the progress or setbacks supported or confronted with the regional power (Mazabel and Miranda</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Zambrano</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013: 198).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Subsequently, the State granted and conceded rights to its population, as in this case, of land as social property. However society—more specifically communities or collectivities—provide a sense of practicality to the management of their lands. It is precisely at this point that ownership and social identity play a central role in the social construction of these territories (Mazabel and Miranda</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Zambrano</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the case of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> under study here, it should be remembered that the Zapatista and Pancho Villa movements had a significant impact. In San Nicolas Totolapan several Nicolaitans were among General Zapata’s personal bodyguards, and the forest (today the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ejido </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ecotouristic Park) was a hiding place hosted and supported by the people. Ojo de Agua de Ballesteros, however, supported Francisco “Pancho” Villa, a far-left leader of the revolution, on his journey through the Republic as they progressed through their lands from the municipality of Celaya (Mazabel and Miranda</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Zambrano</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013). Both territories, having obtained the designation of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, synthesize a history where processes of collective pain are exacerbated and, therefore, bear a definitive seal on their recent identity. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These facts somehow explain how integration is promoted and how the group has survived as a community, providing a certain awareness of their own identity and reinforcing attitudes of defense and combat against external groups, where the past justifies the present (Villoro, 1998: 44).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The long history of struggles over and forming roots in land and territory shows that communities and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in Mexico are incorporating multi-functionality in their agricultural activities. Thus, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">rural ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> tourism is explained as a strategic reserve, where tourism activities imply a new interpretation of their environment. These adjustments in social identity appear to lead—as one of their main consequences—to a reduction of agriculture in the area. Rather than the often-predicted demise of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> as a social identity, we are witnessing its revitalization.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In short, strategies and mechanisms of socialization exercised within the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> strengthen its resilience. The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> studied here engaged in rural tourism as well as in the defense of their property and their natural and cultural heritage.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Theoretical Lenses and the Pre-eminence of Change</section>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the academic world and outside its scope, we note the encouraging presence of a movement that aspires to contradict the Western paradigm of globalization. In particular, the need to reconsider and question the fundamental thinking (focus, direction, philosophy, and rationality) seated in “techno-centrism” and “growth mania,” which are aspects that criticize humans’ dominion over Nature that lies in egocentrism. Ecocentrists assume that Earth is inert and passive and legitimately exploitable. Human beings think of themselves as separate and superior to Nature, in the objectivized natural world that holds only instrumental value, typically quantified in monetary terms, as a resource to exploit, expropriate, and, in the lesser of cases, transform (García Miranda, 1996; Gonzáles, 2008; Miranda Zambrano, 2011).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">At the other extreme, a number of academic movements are increasingly more critical of the global impact, perhaps wanting to end the environmental chaos and threat to humanity currently at stake worldwide.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wallerstein (2004) proposed a form of conservation that is ontology-driven and anti-systematic, while Naess (1995) introduced archetypes with a sociocultural focus and concepts sustained in continentally owned epistemologies. These authors’ main merits are in highlighting the substantial differences between the egocentric eurocentrism to give way to the unveiling of paradigms from denied or invisible sociocultural sectors (based on an ecocentric paradigm). This derives from considering humans as part of the chain of life, where everything that happens to one member of the system affects another and its ecosystem at the micro, macro, and mega levels (see figure 1).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In this line we find “eco-sophy” and the deconstruction of the economy (Leff </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2005); the epistemology of the South (de Sousa Santos, 2010); the concept of “Good Living” (Albó, 2009; Quijano, 2010; Houtart, 2011; Caudillo-Félix, 2012; among others); complex and “multiversity” thinking (Morin, 1994); and the re-dignified American indigenous holistic line of thought (Toledo, 2005; 2006; Boege Schmidt </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2008; Miranda Zambrano, 2011; among others); and, more recently, the proposal of the quantic conscience economics (Pigem, 2013).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, as de Sousa Santos (2010) claims, this does not mean that we can rule out or “completely” ignore</span><strong><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></strong><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Western culture. On the contrary, through ecocentric thought, which is based on knowledge and a relational understanding of Nature and Life, we can retrieve elements of Western culture and, in the process, humanity itself. It is in the indigenous communities of Latin America—particularly Mesoamerica, the Andes, and the Amazons—that we can find a dormant underground prominence of this line of thought (see figure 1). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Indigenous Communities and Rural Tourism</section>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It is gratifying to observe a renewed conception of indigenous communities in the above panorama. Until a few decades ago, anthropology and history—led by Caso (1996), León Portilla (2001), and Levi-Strauss (1988), among others—expressed their concern about the value of these communities as they distinguished them as social actors with unparalleled and ancient idiosyncrasies, reflecting their own identities and cultures in ways differing from egocentric thinking and paradigms.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It was not until the 1990s that the works of Grupo Talpuy (1984-1997), Martínez-Alier (1992), Geertz (1994), García Miranda (1996), Lenkersdorf (1999), and others catalyzed the recognition of these communities as actors bearing a differing epistemology that stems from a cosmovision, culture, knowledge, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">corpus cognoscitivo</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and science and technology that </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">reproduce and evolve based on the sacred association with Nature and the Universe—which should be unequivocally preserved. Currently, the authors cited as leaders of the ecocentric thought mostly provided guidelines regarding the importance of time-honoured rural communities who hold the keys, codes, symbols, and secrets of sustainability. By their presence they reproduce the dynamics of inflowing energy and the substance of</span><strong><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Life</span></strong><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> where the interrelations of this creative source are manifested: constellations, plants, animals, fungi, rocks, water, soil, landscapes and vegetation, or upon physical, biological, or ecological processes such as climate or hydrological change, life cycles, flowering, fruiting, germination, breeding or reproduction periods, as well as ecosystem recovery phenomena (ecological succession) (Toledo, 2005).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the tourism field, in recent years indigenous communities have made inroads in the rural sector, as a result of a shift toward economic decentralization (CDI, 2005), in virtually trying to correct inequalities and, therefore, initiating the emergence of new tourist destinations under the pretence of redirecting the course of the excessive actions against Nature. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Experiences have often been encouraging, while others had disastrous and catastrophic impacts on both the environment and sustainability. Consequently, alternative tourism analysts appeared, in different fields such as ecotourism, ethnic-tourism, rural and experiential tourism, agrotourism, or spiritual tourism. Authors like Paré and Lazos (2003), Pera and Mc Laren (2002), Molina (2006), Santana (2006), Vigna (2006), and Miranda Zambrano (2011) have denounced their disastrous impacts on sanctuaries and live relicts that concentrate the “wise life” (biodiversity seedbeds: water, soil, flora, fauna, climate, soil microorganisms, etc.). In fact, these forms of tourism hold a hidden and threatening discourse; the neoliberal capitalistic context with its egocentric focus implies dispossession (again) of nature and cultures as a hidden purpose.</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">5</a></sup>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We cannot fail to highlight learning experiences such as that of Pueblos Mancomunados (Oaxaca), El Parque San Nicolás Totolapan (object of this study), Escudo Yahuar y Aru Macao, Misol-Ha, Agua Clara, Welib-Ha (Chiapas), or the Red de Ecoturismo de Los Tuxtlas (Veracruz).</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">6</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> At the Latin-American level, there are enriching experiences—in Peru, Panama, Costa Rica, Brazil, and Argentina—where several claim to be “paradigmatic models” (Miranda Zambrano, 2011). The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> studied fall in the latter experimental framework. What do they do to confront and stay away from neocolonialism disguised as an alternative project?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">The Vertigo of Indigenous Tourism: Communal Resistance Actions in Favour of Life and Nature</section>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> like San Nicolas Totolapan and Ojo de Agua de Ballesteros hoist rural tourism projects as an objective in the spirit </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">per se</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of service. There, the sense of cooperation and self-service of indigenous cultures funnels into the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">natural</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">spontaneous</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> flow of the business. However, at the core of such service there is a complex expression of an intimate perspective and commitment. They put all their efforts in the preservation, protection, and defense of </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">property and assets in order to continue to generate a culture favouring Life and Nature. In other words, they do not launch rural tourism projects upon the mere capitalist logic of economic growth (egocentric). The logic, justified by tourism assistance, structures and synthesizes a sequence of agricultural and environmental activities. The “common people” observe and enjoy only the external face known as “service tourism,” however when scrutinizing and looking at the behind-the-scenes actions,</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">interesting discoveries regarding the resistance in favour of these Life-giving cultures are made.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Resistance to Land Privatization </section>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Both </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> challenged the forced entry into the Programa de Certificación de Derechos Ejidales y Titulación de Solares (PROCEDE,</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Ejidal</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Property Certification and Solar Entitlement Program)</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">7</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> because it was obvious to them that it was a pitfall or slow and certain death of their heritage and communal </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidal</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> organization, and therefore was not an option. “We will fight tooth and nail and give up our own life” is the recurrent discourse, as the generation that manages today’s projects experienced in their youth the agrarian revolution of 1910 where their family members lost their lives in defending their land and territory. Zambrano (2001) believes that territorial struggles and conflicts arise when varying perceptions of ownership, dominion, and sovereignty over a space come into close contact. Meanwhile, Toledo (2005), Bartra (2008), Concheiro Bórquez and López Bárcenas (2006), and Miranda Zambrano (2011) corroborate that in a fight for land, the claim of nature and the reproduction of life are incorporated and manifested through a sustainable culture within and around it. In the same fashion, the proposal for rural tourism is nothing but a manifestation of temporary defense and preservation of heritage. Therefore there is a certain degree of correlation and agreement, and re-generation of the laws and principles of Life.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Under these circumstances, both </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> proudly and with dignity declare they had not accepted such exhortation, and would continue according to the traditional collective work forms and norms, just as it has always been since its creation. Avoiding the virtual dismantlement and the subsequent fragmentation of communal property gives them the nationwide distinction of being one of the few indigenous </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> that did not accept to enter the Program.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Poor? We Are Rich!</section>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">How does this poor-rich binomial contradiction of acknowledgment in the ecotouristic rural community management affect both </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">? It is common knowledge that to work in the area of tourism, it is necessary to </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">show in order to seduce</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> the public interested in that segment. In the case of both </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and for countless generations, the social actors have been stigmatized as </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">poor people who do not know anything and are not worth anything</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Consequently for some it is complicated to enter the tourism industry and disregard such an identity. However, upon seeing that natural goods and heritage were threatened, they imagined a completely original scenario. “My voice and my hands shook when I did my first tour, I didn’t know what to say, I thought the visitors to the forest would laugh at me, and no matter how much I pinched myself I couldn’t keep myself under control, so I almost escaped. But I had to get into it, my trees couldn’t wait anymore; people were cutting them to use as mere firewood…” [Our translation of a personal communication, 2012]</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">As both projects grew, they empowered their actors. Today when you ask, “are you poor?” you get an exploding answer to the tune of “Me, poor?! I’ve never been poor! I have my </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">forest, I am high on life, and I have more than everyone who lives in the city. We used to think we were poor, but we hadn’t yet noticed that […] we are richer than everyone!</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">[Our translation of a personal communication, 2012]</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Communities have learned to resist with a renewed look at their heritage while avoiding their dispossession under various external contentious strategies. They question the prevailing idea that if you are “poor,” then it is fair to get paid less than the market price. They know about prices, about value, and no one will take away what Zapata fought for.</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">8</a></sup>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">“We Communicate with Nature”</section>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The horizontal and cultural relationship of inter-subjectivity with Nature, and with elements subjacent to Nature, is shared in the tourism actions for both groups of social actors. In other words, the indigenous ideological cosmovision is transmitted to visitors as an educational message </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">from the heart</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Consequently, it is common for them to be motivated or, in the best of cases, form a link with Nature: “We speak with trees, water, we hug them . . . children watch us, they imitate us, that is why they never come just once, they always come back!” [Our translation of a personal communication, 2012]</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’s identity has been built on the basis of ecocentric thinking around physical assets and forest culture. Social capital is developed, leading to complex networks and social relations both internally and externally. In addition, the multiple skills and abilities of the actors involved flow with an open dialogue on sustainability issues. Visitors from the city learn to experience new feelings as they read symbols that once were unimaginable in their </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">habitus</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Among Fear and Never Trodden Paths: Safeguarding and Invigorating Natural Assets and Heritage</section>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On innumerable occasions, San Nicolas Totolapan faced uncertainty and chaos due to threatening invasions. In 1997, the community received a proposal to work on a mega project on their land, led by companies such as Coca-Cola, General Motors, and Chrysler, who considered a total of 26 projects, among which were included the installation of themed museums such as “tree museum,” “car museum,” and “bullfighting museum.” The agreement was based on a 99-year concession (Miranda Zambrano, 2011). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Zambrano (2001: 40) states that when a conflict arises there is a transition from a cultural territory to a political one, where the subjects collectively define the multiple contours of the land. In other words, we are talking about a cultural to political transition—formulated in the expressions of resistance that are summarized in the figure of the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Setting Up the Ejido Park</section>
        <section niveau="h2">Ongoing Monitoring and Multiple Actions to Protect Assets</section>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ojo de Agua de Ballesteros is known for the ongoing and strong monitoring of its heritage. The rupture with the mainstream establishment is attributable to actions by local residents who can barely read and write, who acknowledged the challenge of facing touristic presentation duties that are completely unknown to them. They made their way, they fenced springs because people kept contaminating the water with detergent, preventing it from being used for irrigation or conservation purposes. The waterpark took the heat for abrupt changes in daily practices, often facing harsh externalities. Some of the actions taken are:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Training authorities and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidatarios</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (collective landowners) during events related to the protection of natural heritage and its relationship to productive projects.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Initiatives to support municipal security and enforcement of fines to those who do not play an active role. Natural assets are watched 24 hours a day by groups of adults and young members, on a rotating basis.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Filing paperwork with forest authorities in order to fence the forest. After eight years of proposals before the Secretaría de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales (SEMARNAT, the Mexican Department of Environment and Natural Resources), they agreed to sponsor the installation of a perimeter fence surrounding the majority of the forest, therefore greatly reducing pillaging.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Fines (and in extreme cases a penalty) for those caught subtracting from, or destroying the natural heritage.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Establishment of a co-participatory project with the University of Guanajuato for the recovery of natural assets and touristic development: for recognition as a Community Ecological Reserve.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Over 30 projects, in total, have been achieved in favour of preservation, restoration, forestation, reforestation, and recovery of native species. Tourism services are optimized thanks to projects such as fish breeding, an </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> restaurant, and overall beautification of the site. People used to swim and rest at the waterpark, it is believed that they will return when they notice that the mountain is green and the water is nice and clean!</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With these actions of care and defense of the forest, springs, agricultural land, and the lagoon itself, Ballesteros generally energizes and benefits from productive activities, but its long-term vision is set on sustainability. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusions</section>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejido</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> management experience shows that a community taking on goods and wealth undeniably differs from the egocentric commercial organization we know. These tourism projects rest on a commitment to the ecological conservation and sustainability, where </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidatarios</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> express a repertoire of knowledge and skills to keep their own property, which is a central aspect of the ecocentric thought. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the rural tourism paradigm is an opportunity to continue to maintain their link with Nature and Life through multiple use of the ecosystem, the vast number of species, watershed management, water management, variations in climate, soil management, ecological zones, productive and reproductive cycles, etc. Thus, productive communities are a concrete example of the value of the reproduction of social and natural biodiversity, and of lower impacts on other communities in the country and the world. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Rural tourism is an area of environmental education for visitors where social actors show their skills and abilities and knowledge while offering experiences that dignify them as human beings. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ejidos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> are reaching out in defense of the dynamics of the energy stream and mainstay of Life where the interrelationships between the natural and the human are manifest. Nature marvels in the Human Being and humans merge into the substance of Life. Bartra (2008: 375) explains that peasants are indispensable not because “they produce cheap goods without subsidy,” but because they reproduce social and natural diversity, whose value lies in its use rather than its exchange. In short, rural tourism is a scenario that provides some security for the recovery and reproduction of ecology and sustainability.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>ALBÓ, Xavier (2009) “Buen Vivir, Desarrollo y Mal desarrollo,” Revista de Ciencias Sociales OBETS, no. 4, p. 25-40. Spain: Instituto Universitario de Desarrollo Social y Paz. Universidad de Alicante.</reference>
        <reference>BARTRA, Armando (2008) El hombre de hierro: Los límites sociales y naturales del capital, Mexico: Universidad Autónoma de la Ciudad de México, 213 p. </reference>
        <reference>BOEGE SCHMIDT, Eckart; Georgina VIDRIALES; Isabel CHAN et al. (2008) El patrimonio biocultural de los pueblos indígenas de México. Mexico: Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia, Comisión Nacional para el Desarrollo de los Pueblos Indígenas, 344 p.</reference>
        <reference>CAMACHO DE LA ROSA, Gerardo (2007) Raíz y razón de Totolapan: el drama de la guerra zapatista. Mexico: Gobierno del Distrito Federal. Centro de Estudios Antropológicos, Científicos, Artísticos, Tradicionales y Lingüísticos “Ce–Acatl”, AC / Programa de Pueblos Originarios de la Dirección General de Equidad y Desarrollo Social del Gobierno del Distrito Federal, Mexico, 110 p.</reference>
        <reference>CASO, Alfonso (1996) “Contribución de las culturas indígenas de México a la Cultura Mundial,” IN Homenaje a Alfonso Caso. Obras Escogidas, 455 p. Mexico: Patronato para el Fomento de Actividades Culturales y de Asistencia Social a las Comunidades Indígenas.</reference>
        <reference>CAUDILLO-FÉLIX, Gloria Alicia (2012) “El buen vivir: un diálogo intercultural,” Ra Ximhai, vol. 8, no. 2., p. 345-364. Mexico: Universidad Autónoma Indígena de México.</reference>
        <reference>CDI (Comisión Nacional Para El Desarrollo de los Pueblos Indígenas) (2005) Turismo comunitario. Mexico, DF. &lt;http://www.e-mexico.gob.mx/wb2/eMex/eMex_Turismo_Comunitario&gt;, accessed August 1, 2015. </reference>
        <reference>CHÁVEZ DE LA PEÑA, Jorge (2001) “¿A dónde llevan los excesos del ecoturismo? Derechos Humanos. Órgano informativo de la Comisión de Derechos Humanos del Estado de México,” Turismo Ecológico, no. 52, p. 97-98. </reference>
        <reference>CONCHEIRO BÓRQUEZ, Luciano and Francisco LÓPEZ BÁRCENAS (Editors) (2006) Biodiversidad y conocimiento tradicional en la sociedad rural. Entre el bien común y la propiedad privada. Mexico: Centro de Estudios para el Desarrollo Rural Sustentable y la Soberanía Alimentaria, Cámara de Diputados, LX Legislatura / Congreso de la Unión, Mexico, 454 p.</reference>
        <reference>DE SOUSA SANTOS Boaventura (2010) La hora de los invisibles. Sumak kawsay/buen vivir y cambios civilizatorios. Quito: Fundación de Estudios, Acción y Participación Social (FEDAEPS), p. 13-26.</reference>
        <reference>GARCÍA MIRANDA, Juan José (1996) Racionalidad de la cosmovisión andina. Lima, Peru: Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología, Serie Socio Cultural no. 3, 153 p.</reference>
        <reference>GEERTZ, Clifford (1994) Conocimiento local: hecho y ley en la perspectiva comparativa. Conocimiento local. Ensayos sobre la interpretación de las culturas. Barcelona, Spain: Paidós Básica, p. 195-262. Published in English in 2008 [trans. Alberto López Bargados] Local Knowledge. Further Essays in Interpretative Anthropology. New York: Basic Books.</reference>
        <reference>GONZÁLEZ, Octavio Francisco (2008) “Plano Cognición-Intervención: Instrumento hacia la sustentabilidad.” Conference paper presented at the XIIth Congreso Anual de Investigación en Ciencias Administrativas, Tijuana, Baja California, Mexico. </reference>
        <reference>GRUPO TALPUY, Minka (1984-1997) “Hacia el desarrollo de una ciencia andina,” nos. 11-40, Revistas de ciencia y tecnología “Minka.” Huancayo, Peru: Grupo Talpuy. </reference>
        <reference>HOUTART, François (2011) “El concepto de Sumak kawsay (buen vivir) y su correspondencia con el bien común de la humanidad,” Revista de filosofía, vol. 69, no. 3, p. 7.</reference>
        <reference>LEFF, Enrique; Arturo ARGUETA et al. (2005) “Más allá del desarrollo sostenible. Una visión desde América Latina,” Revista Futuros, vol. 3, no. 9. Available online: &lt;http//www.revistafuturos.info&gt;, accessed January 20, 2012.</reference>
        <reference>LENKERSDORF, Carlos (1996) Los hombres verdaderos: voces y testimonios tojolabales: lengua y sociedad, naturaleza y cultura, artes y comunidad cósmica. Spain: Siglo xxi, 197 p.</reference>
        <reference>LEÓN PORTILLA, Miguel (2001) La visión de los vencidos; relaciones indígenas de la conquista. Mexico, DF: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, DGSCA, Coordinación de Publicaciones Digitales, Ciudad Universitaria, 224 p. </reference>
        <reference>LEVI-STRAUSS, Claude (1988) [3rd ed. in Spanish] El pensamiento salvaje. México: Fondo de Cultura Económica. &lt;https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Especial:FuentesDeLibros/9789681609337&gt;, accessed in January 2012.</reference>
        <reference>MARTÍNEZ-ALIER, Joan (1992) De la economía ecológica al ecologismo popular. Barcelona, Spain: Icaria, vol. 60, 362 p. </reference>
        <reference>MAZABEL, Davison and Gloria MIRANDA ZAMBRANO (2013) “Apropiación del espacio e identidad social en el ejido Ojo de Agua de Ballesteros, Salvatierra, México.” IN Estudios Culturales, Demográficos y Políticos, p. 181-195. Mexico: Universidad de Guanajuato / Altres Costa-Amic.</reference>
        <reference>MIRANDA ZAMBRANO, Gloria (2011) Contribuciones de las Comunidades Rurales a la Sustentabilidad. Parque Ejidal Ecoturístico San Nicolás Totolapan, Ciudad de México. Mexico: Universidad de Guanajuato, Comisión Nacional Para El Desarrollo de los Pueblos Indígenas (CDI), Axolot México Sustentable. </reference>
        <reference>MIRANDA ZAMBRANO, Gloria; Mazabel DAVISON and Isaura ARREGUÍN (2014) “Pueblos indígenas: Prospectiva de la defensa de la Naturaleza, el Ser Humano y la Sociedad,” IN Daniel VEGA MACÍAS and David C. WRIGHT-CARR (Editors), Los pueblos indígenas en el Estado de Guanajuato: su historia, su actualidad y sus derechos colectivos. Mexico: Universidad de Guanajuato/ Pearson Los pueblos originarios en el Estado de Guanajuato. Mexico : Pearson / Universidad de Guanajuato. </reference>
        <reference>MOLINA, Sergio (2006) El posturismo: turismo y posmodernidad. Mexico: Trillas, 109 p.</reference>
        <reference>MORIN, Edgar (1994) [trans. by Marcelo Pakman from 1st ed. in French 1990] Introducción al pensamiento complejo. Barcelona: Gedisa, 176 p.</reference>
        <reference>NAESS, Arne (1995) “Politics and the Ecological Crisis: An Introductory Note. Deep Ecology for the 21st Century,” IN George SESSIONS (Editor), Deep Ecology for the 21st Century, p. 445-453. Boston: Shambhala. </reference>
        <reference>PARÉ, Luisa and Elena LAZOS (2003) “El ecoturismo comunitario y la gestión ambiental.” La escuela rural y organización comunitaria, p. 261-311. Mexico: Instituciones locales para el desarrollo y el manejo ambiental, Conacyt / UNAM. </reference>
        <reference>PERA, Lee and Deborah MC LAREN (2002) “Globalización, turismo y pueblos indígenas: lo que debemos saber de la industria más grande del mundo.” Revista Globalhoy. Available online: &lt;http://www.gloobal.net/iepala/gloobal/fichas/ficha.php?entidad=Textos&amp;id=157&amp;opcion=documento&gt;, accessed January 10, 2013.</reference>
        <reference>PIGEM, Jordi (2013) La nueva realidad: del economicismo a la conciencia cuántica. Spain: Kairós, 227 p. </reference>
        <reference>QUIJANO, Aníbal (2010) El buen vivir y derechos de la Madre Tierra: avances y propuestas hacia el mundo. Panel in the Social Las Américas forum, held in Asunción, Paraguay, August 13. FEDAEPS – Fundación de Estudios, Acción y Participación Social. Available online: &lt;http://www.fedaeps.org/spip.php?article124&gt;, accessed April 20, 2013.</reference>
        <reference>SANTANA, Agustín (2006) Turismo y antropología ¿Nuevas hordas, viejas culturas? Barcelona, Spain: Ariel Antropología, 224 p. </reference>
        <reference>TOLEDO, Víctor (2005) “La memoria tradicional: la importancia agroecológica de los saberes locales.” Leisa Revista de agroecología, vol. 20, no. 4, p. 16-19. Lima, Peru. </reference>
        <reference>TOLEDO, Víctor (2006) “Ecología, espiritualidad y conocimiento. De la sociedad del riesgo a la sociedad sustentable,” Graffylia, p, 224-228. Mexico: Programa de las Naciones Unidas para el Medio Ambiente / Universidad Iberoamericana.</reference>
        <reference>VIGNA, Ana (2006) “Los falsarios del “ecoturismo,” Grandes proyectos privados en México y Centroamérica, no. 521, Tepoztlán, Morelos, Mexico: Echoway.</reference>
        <reference>VILLORO, Luis (1998) “El sentido de la historia,” Historia ¿para qué? Mexico: Siglo XXI, p. 32-52.</reference>
        <reference>WALLERSTEIN, Immanuel (2004) Capitalismo histórico y movimientos antisistémicos: un análisis de sistemas-mundo. Mexico, DF: Akalm vol. 24, 480 p.</reference>
        <reference>ZAMBRANO, Carlos (2001) “Territorios plurales y cambios sociopolíticos y gobernabilidad cultural,” Territorio y cultura. Territorios en conflicto y cambio sociocultural, Manizales, Colombia. Grupo de Investigación Territorialidades, Departamento de Antropología y Sociología, Universidad de Caldas, Colombia, p. 19-67.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="2">After the agrarian reform and land endowments—products of the 1910 Mexican Revolution—the ejido was established as a form of rural property based on the collective use and benefit of the land.</note>
        <note id="3">The concept of “better living” is an alternative world system paradigm to the anthropocentric view of the modern Western world, which has its foundation in instrumental rationality. Its main principle is to conceive Nature and Life as sacred, where all living and non-living beings—including human beings—are part of a global community. Society and humans evolve and base their principles on eco-socio-centric values. This model is addressed further below.</note>
        <note id="4">&lt;http://www.conacyt.mx/comunicacion/revista/208/Articulos/CRM/CRM01.htm&gt;, retrieved on April 20, 2012.</note>
        <note id="5">There are cases denounced by Vigna (2006) where the Mundo Maya Project, which was supported under the label of ecotourism and protected by the Puebla Panama Plan and the International Development Bank (IDB), created ecotourism projects “to benefit the environment and communities,” but had the opposite effect. Nature is sold and exploited, exactly as it was in the Acapulco Bay, in Mexico, 40 years before, pinpointing “tourism coyotes” who buy land for low prices, extinguishing the last untouched gems on the planet (Miranda Zambrano, 2011). </note>
        <note id="6">All of them in Mexico. They have demonstrated a gradual empowerment as a social enterprise. In other words, the indigenous enterprise is strengthened by the contributions of its organization based on solidarity and cooperation and a sustainable worldview on the environment. </note>
        <note id="7">This is a political-administrative instrument used by the federal government, which was made available to agrarian groups in 1992 in order to regularize social property with the objective of providing legal certainty to land ownership, through the issuance of deeds and of the right to common use. </note>
        <note id="8">Emiliano Zapata symbolizes the Mexican Agrarian Revolution of the early twentieth century. Along with his followers, he struggled to dismiss the hacienda and political system that dominated the country’s economy, politics, and agriculture. His ideology was synthesized in the cry for “land and liberty,” which was taken up by farmers. He remains a significant historical figure and the rural insurgent movement which took up arms in the Mexican state of Chiapas in 1994 is named after him: the Zapatista Army of National Liberation (EZLN). </note>
        <note id="1">In Mexico, an ejido refers to rural lands used collectively. In the next section we address the ejido concept in terms of the historical resistance it represents in order to shed light on today’s rural tourism activities.</note>
    </notes>
</article>