<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_HV_44-33_As_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1232" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.1232</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>1</numero>
        <annee>2012</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="1227">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            Anecdotes et imaginaires touristiques
        </original>
        <traduction lang="it" source="1237">L’infimo culturale e l’immaginario turistico - L’aneddoto nelle guide di viaggio</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Vergopoulos" prenom="Hécate">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_HV_49-37_As_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1227" lang="fr">Anecdotes et imaginaires touristiques</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Hécate Vergopoulos holds a PhD in information and communication sciences. Her research focuses on tourism, and more specifically tourism mediation and travel guides. By studying a variety of devices, she aims to identify the way in which the representations of tourist values emerge and are transferred throughout culture. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Anecdotes and Tourism Imaginaries</titre>
    <resume>
        Tourism imaginaries are not rooted only in spectacular “must-see” attractions. They also founded in the realm of small cultural objects. This is proved by the prevalence of anecdotes in tourism mediation devices. These anecdotes seem inessential and yet they fully contribute to the construction of a fundamental regime of authenticity. How should we understand the dual status of anecdotes ? What are the challenges faced when institututing cultural “truth” through tiny anecdotal objects ?
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">“</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Aside from its wild processions, with their explosion of morality, the Spain of the Guide Bleu, recognises only one cultural location ; that of a tight chain of churches, sacristies, altarpieces, sculpted crosses (Family and Work), Roman gateways, naves and life-size crucifixes woven though a succession of empty spaces</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”, remarked Roland Barthes (1957, p. 123). The semiotician then went on to highlight the fact that culture, as represented through mediation, seems to be defined as the sum of monumental objects, or even a “corpus of works” to use the expression coined by Jean-Claude Passeron (1991). Ten years later, Jules Gritti made the same mistake again, studying a guide from the same collection to dissect the injunctive logic of “must-look” (1967) which as a consequence implies that which we could call “must-know”. The author again highlights the fact that tourist culture, as exhibited through mediation devices, is organised around these essential items.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourist culture, however, is not simply constructed around these “must-see” objects. It is also based on the sum of minute objects which hold great value despite their socio-cultural insignificance. Tourism thus has only one face: that of mediation and the practicality of these little objects which do not seem to have the same aura as these monumental works, but which nonetheless hold similar worth. This is the main argument put forward by this article, which will be supported using the case of one particular lowly object: the anecdote.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Anecdotes are frequently found in many objects relating to tourism mediation. Woven within the text in printed guides, evoked concisely by guides, or hidden on printed labels in exhibitions, they can go unnoticed when in fact they are an important part of mediation and, as such, they contribute greatly to tourism imaginaries. Starting from this singular discourse object as observed in one of these types of tourism mediations, that is to say in printed guides, this article will discuss a number of ways of understanding and interpreting these small cultural objects which define, more generally, the regime of miniature tourism. Our approach to anecdotes is primarily semiotic and communicative insofar as it aims to highlight the balance between values and representations – the imaginary – which accompanies the mediation of these lowly objects by analysing their written occurrences.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The anecdotes studied here were taken from a corpus of travel guides selected for their editorial diversity</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. They were chosen on the criteria of their “texture”: we are thus specifically interested in anecdotes featured in linguistic rather than iconic format, as this has already been studied, for example by Christian Moncelet in his study of photographic anecdotes (1990). We will begin by showing that the anecdotes featured in mediation devices have specificities relating to tourist anecdotes in general. We will particularly focus on the authenticity that they attempt to transmit. We will then go on to examine the way in which these discursive objects are qualified, by the devices themselves, as insignificant or inessential from a socio-cultural standpoint. Finally, we will try to better understand the ambiguity which is central to anecdotes, as they are seen to be both authentic and inessential. We will also try to identify the difficulties related with constructing the “truth” about cultures through the insignificance of these anecdotal details.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Anecdotes and Authenticity</section>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Anecdotes are a narrative form of discourse which are more often than not defined by their brevity (Huglo, 1997). Another of their particularities is that, when used in tourism, they are featured as desired objects. Juicy and spicy anecdotes slip into the ears or dance under the eyes of travellers ; they are savoured, coveted and are often brought home as souvenirs. As such, they represent both a way of making tourists travel as they are told, and a way of transmitting culture for those involved in tourism mediation. Thus, when we talk about touristic anecdotes, it is important to distinguish between, on the one hand, anecdotes as desired by tourists (in the form of souvenirs) and on the other, anecdotes as desired by the tourist devices (playing a role in the mediation process). In the following paragraphs, we will try to clarify this distinction in order to show how this desire for anecdotes, as they takes shape through mediation, questions the “depth” of the tourists’ judgment (Urbain, 2002 [1991]) which will help them to access the “authenticity” of the cultures visited (MacCannell, 1999 [1976]).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Souvenir Anecdotes and Mediation Anecdotes</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">If it can be said that anecdotes are desired by the world of tourism in general it is because anecdotes are used to facilitate narration in a great variety of tourist devices. They are extremely prevalent in online blogs, as shown in that of Miss Potin, a traveller who, after telling her own anecdotes, asks her readers to share their own</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Another example can be found on the blog Un jour, un voyage, which invites readers to post “tickets” telling their travel anecdotes, be they “imaginary, political, funny, poetic, childish or theatrical”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This said, blogs are not the only devices that desire anecdotes. Publishing companies also seem to like this type of narrative form. Publibook, for example, invites potential writers and travellers to take up their pens and write about their travels, and stresses the importance of any anecdotes people might like to share: “You have just returned from your trip, your head still full of images and your holiday diary full of notes, impressions, anecdotes and other accounts. Would you like to make that dream last, in black and white ? […] Publibook would like to help you to make that manuscript a reality” (Auzias &amp;amp; Labourdette, 2007, p. 316).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Be it for blogs or for the publishing company described above, that which is desired and thus that which can be told, are either “souvenir anecdotes” or “testimonial anecdotes”, that is to say stories told in the first person – both singular and plural – which recount one or more episodes of a personal trip. In other words, anecdotes in this respect refer to a domain of memory and follow the format of autobiographical writing. By sharing their impression of their encounters, travellers are invited to take the stage to represent themselves in the eyes of potential readers: they are thus also describing themselves by describing what happened to them.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, these testimonial anecdotes are not the only kind of anecdotes which are desired by the world of tourism. There is a second kind which play a central role in tourist mediation. They do not describe a journey which has already taken place, but rather anticipate a journey, either enticing people to leave, or used to enrich a journey which has already started. Thus, in the Guide du Routard for Scotland, under the article about visiting the Royal Yacht Britannia in Edinburgh: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To visit on board: royal apartments, but also the machine room, the crew’s quarters, the Admiral’s room (as the captain was always chosen from the admirals in the Royal Navy)… all enlivened with comments and historical anecdotes ! Here is just one for fun: the Queen always travels with five tonnes of luggage !</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Gloaguen, 2008, p. 127). Or again, in the Le Petit Futé guide to New York, in the section about the Lower East Side Tenement Museum, it is said that “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the guided tour […] is punctuates with anecdotes and captivating stories from immigrants</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Auzias &amp;amp; Labourdette, 2005 p. 274). Here we can see that experts in tourist mediation (Le Guide du Routard and le Petit Futé) place great importance on the fact that a tourist representative (the mediator of the Royal Yacht or the Lower East Side Tenement Museum) chose to include numerous anecdotes in their mediations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This type of anecdote clearly does not belong to the world of personal souvenir, but instead to the mediation process. From now on, we will differentiate between this kind of anecdote and testimonial anecdotes, by qualifying them as either mediation or historical. They are characterised by the fact that they seem to be able to provide an additional asset for tourist mediation in the sense that they hold a certain touristic and/or cultural value. They thus appear as a sort of gauge of the quality of the mediation. This would go some way as to explaining why Le Guide du Routard and Le Petit Futé alike highlight their importance when describing an attraction or tourist site.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This would also explain the fact that the tourist guides themselves like to make it known that they use a lot of anecdotes, as illustrated in the La Bibliothèque du voyageur. When presenting its route for the “tour of the USA”, it specifies: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The guide retraces the history of each of the regions visited, giving information about how to get there, making time for humorous anecdotes, painting a portrait of the local inhabitants, drawing readers’ attention to oddities off the beaten track and, when necessary, denouncing certain vulgar tourist attractions.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Collectif, 2001, p. 13). Anecdotes thus seem to add value and become a veritable selling point insofar as they provide specific information which is in some way different from those providing the history, portraits, or practical information.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To summarise, we have identified two different types of anecdote: those which stem from testimonies and those which play a role in mediation. The former have already been researched extensively, for example by Marie-Christine Gomez-Géraud &amp;amp; Philippe Antoine (2001), Alain Montandon (1990) or Dominique Jullien (1993), whereas the second have attracted considerably less attention. In the next section, we aim to give them the attention they deserve, by trying to better understand the kinds of information and the values provided by historical and mediation anecdotes.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Historical Anecdotes and Authenticity</section>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It must first be noted that it would seem that historical anecdotes are connected with the very first anecdotes which history has kept alive. The term was coined by Procopius, historian and biographer of Emporer Justinien in the 6th Century AD. The term comes from the Greek ekdotos, a verbal adjective derived from ekdidomai “to produce from outside, to publish” (Rey, 1992, p. 74) to which a privative a was added, followed by a linking n. Anekdote therefore means, first and foremost, that which has not previously been published, or “new”. Procopius used this term to designate texts which should only be published after the death of the Emperor and his wife Theodora. These texts included information about their love life, jealousy, anger, as well as conspiracies in which the imperial couple were involved. “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It was not possible,” he later wrote, “to publish [these stories] while those involved were still alive. I could no better escape the espionage which surrounded me on a grand scale, than I could escape a most horrible death if ever discovered. I could not even count on my closest relatives to keep these secrets</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.” (Procopius, 1856, pp. 3-5).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From their very origin, therefore, anecdotes have been reports evoking the world of secret, underground stories which, most often, oppose that of written history. This was confirmed by one of Procopius’ heirs, Antoine Varillas, when he wrote: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Historians almost always consider people as they were seen in public, whereas writers of anecdotes only examine them as individuals. The former believe they are relieving them of their duties, depicting them as they were in the army, or during civil unrest ; and the latter try their best to catch a glimpse of their most private affairs. The first see them in ceremony and the second in conversation ; the first attaching themselves to their actions and the second wanting to report on their inner life and participate in their personal private time. To summarise, the first is interested only in command and authority, and the second in that which occurs in secret and solitude.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Varillas, 1689 [1685], p. 4).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Anecdotes are also in some ways rather virtual: if the facts that are being reported have remained hidden until the anecdote is told, it is probably because they do not conform to the norm, and thus that they have some foreign nature, mystery and/or secret, which is precisely why they deserve our interest (Hadjadj, 1990, p. 10). Generally speaking, anecdotes carry a cultural element exactly because they oppose institutionalised knowledge. Consequently, when they are used in mediation devices, we could say that they are both a product of and contributing to the regime of touristic authenticity (MacCannell, 1999 [1978]). This is not in the sense that they certify events, but rather that they pave the way for “in-depth tourism” (Urbain, 2002 [1991]), revealing a more intimate layer of a culture: that which concerns the private life of people and places ; their truth as men, women, or spaces, in the state in which they were overlooked by the public eye and made official by knowledge institutions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In much the same way as the tales and legends analysed by Michel de Certeau, anecdotes thus do not belong to the world of “social categories which ‘write history’” and simultaneously dominate it. (1990 [1980], 43). They rather propagate informally, and their cultural trajectory along with the stories that they tell, belong to discourse and individual memory, rather than to their institutions, i.e. in the “wings” of their historical and/or contemporary nature, to use the term defined by Erving Goffman (1973 [1956]). This world of representations associated with anecdotes certainly explains why, in “cultural” guides (such as the Guide Bleu which is based on official and institutional mediation logic) anecdotes which, despite being numerous, are not identified as such. On the contrary ; in “practical” guides (such as the Routard which aims to be friendly, liberated and helpful), the tendency is to present and identify anecdotal utterances.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Anecdotes and the “Seriousness Effect”</section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The second characteristic of mediation anecdotes is that which can be referred to as the “seriousness effect”. In order to explain this expression, we must first distinguish anecdotes from that which is anecdotal, that is to say to separate stories from the values which are associated with them. In order to do this, we refer to a specific piece of research by Ruth Amossy on stereotypes. She makes a point of differentiating between discursive format on the one hand, and the representations associated with it on the other. Based on this work we will examine and justify the arguments distinguishing between anecdote and anecdotal offered below. We will then go on to clarify this second notion by highlighting the values which characterise it. Finally, we will put forward a specific definition of anecdotal as an editorial and discursive strategy used to avoid seriousness.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Anecdotes and Anecdotal</section>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In her work Les Idées reçues: Sémiologie du stéréotype (1991), Ruth Amossy explains that stereotypes must be separated from the conscience of stereotyping. As such, stereotypes or common views have existed for a long time. In Antiquity, they were valued, in the form of topos, for their rhetorical convenience, whereas today we acknowledge only their effects of extreme simplification: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The stereotype [as an object invested with negative values] is not an absolute and eternal theoretical concept, but rather a notion stemming from and designed to serve the modern era. The conscience of the stereotype is the ultimate defence drawn up by a society doomed to decline and automation. It attempts to point out danger to stop it from spreading unlawfully […]. In this sense, it can be said that stereotypes have become one of the greatest obsessions of modern times</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (1991: 11).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Stereotypes are a socio-historic, and therefore a “cultural” notion. They are built up over time and those that we know today which are pejorative and detrimental, (only) characterise our modernity and the view that they have on pre-constructed and replicable schemata. Stereotypes do not carry any morals in themselves and if, nowadays, we condemn them, this judgement is also cultural. Indeed, that is the conscience of stereotypes: the set of socio-cultural values which we attribute to the practice of stereotype production. Anecdotes must be recognised as carrying the same investment of socio-cultural values, distinguishing between, on the one hand, the discursive format, and on the other, the associated conscience or representations, thus differentiating the anecdote from that which is merely anecdotal.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Anecdotes and Socio-cultural Value</section>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With regards to that which is anecdotal, we need to digress briefly in order to better identify the issue as presented in tourism mediation devices. If we examine the case of travel guides in particular, we can see that they are presented as complex texts. They use an infinite number of writing formats (bold, italics, typographic alterations, and even images, drawings, plans, diagrams, maps, summaries, indexes, etc.). Each of these textures occupies a distinctive place and defines a text’s specific function. For example, italics are often used to designate practical information ; bold regularly indicates logical usage of the guide, i.e. a bold term in the body of the text will often also be found in the index ; titles and sub-headings are used to organise the information and make it easier to read legible and/or more visible. These works thus semiotise how tourists approach the text, in their role as readers, both cognitively and manually speaking. They visually indicate the way in which the guide should be read and the manner in which the reader/traveller will interpret the given information.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">There are a number of constants in the way in which anecdotes are semiotised by the guides. Let us examine the example of Grace Church, presented in the New York Guide Vert, of which we learn: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Originally founded by Trinity Parish in 1808, this Episcopalian church was built in 1846 by James Renwick who then went on to design the plans for Saint Patrick’s Cathedral. Remarkable for the acuity of the spire’s profile, Grace Church is a good example of Gothic Revival architecture. In 1863, the world-renowned P.T. Barnum managed to convince the rector of Grace Church to celebrate the marriage of two dwarves from his circus: Charles S. Stratton, better known as Tom Thumb, and Lavina Warren.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Brabis, 2005, p. 183). What is remarkable when reading this work (but which is difficult to grasp from this re-transcription), is first of all the fact that the anecdote about the marriage of small circus folk is here semiotised as information in the body of the text. In other words, it is not highlighted in a title or sub-heading, but is instead presented according to the logic of “normal” text. Furthermore, it is not featured in a separate paragraph but is instead included in the body of the text.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This editorial approach to the way anecdotes are handled is systematic in almost all of the travel guides. Generally speaking, anecdotes are summarised as the enunciation of simple suggestions which are added to the main body of the text without any noticeable change to the layout. At best, they are announced and identified as anecdotes using specific expressions (“as an anecdote” or “according to the anecdote”) and at worst, they are simply added or included in the main information. However, in both cases, they appear in the most “infra-ordinary” part of the text, to coin the term used by Georges Perec – and invented by Emmanuël Souchier (1998) – that is to say everything which is present in the text but which is not seen. “Infra-ordinary” more specifically characterises that which Emmanuël Souchier refers to as “editorial utterance”, that is to say the way in which the material format of the text, (i.e. the “image of the text”) is expressed at the same time as the text, from a linguistic point of view.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This approach to editing anecdotes brings us back to that which we will call the “inessential” nature of the information transmitted. This term defines a socio-cultural value and not, of course, a sociological value. We can therefore can that the “inessential” characterises a set of objects in the discourse whose status might seem ambiguous: they are secondary, but nonetheless present. They are not, however, fundamental, or they would be attributed a typographical format by which they could be recognised immediately. They are therefore neither essential, as they are not highlighted, nor are they useless as they are nonetheless present, and even recurring.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">The Anecdotal as a Strategy for Avoiding Seriousness</section>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Anecdotes thus now appear to be culturally inessential objects within the context of the exercise of tourism mediation. This socio-cultural position of an object clearly defines that which is anecdotal, raised in the previous paragraphs. Anecdotal elements, thus defined, characterise anecdotes, but also other discourse objects such as legends or rumours. Generally speaking, they carry the property of being able to rid the discourse referent of the its “seriousness effect” insofar as they are not interested in that which is “serious” but rather in something which occurs nearby.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Let us take the example from the Routard guide to Scotland, in which we find: “A little anecdote: In Perth, in 1539, the famous reformer John Knox gave the first of his incendiary anti-papal speeches” (Gloaguen, 2008, p. 237). It must be noted that John Knox (1514-1572) is considered as the founder or reformer of the Church of Scotland. However, in this extract, we are given very little information about the man himself. The focus of the information is the location in which he made his first overtly anti-papal declaration. In other words, the central importance of the information is altered by shifting the interest in the historic and emblematic character to the location in which he gave his speech. We thus obtain a piece of information which ignores the weight and historical pertinence, instead relying on adjacent information which had previously been marginalised.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With that which is anecdotal, we enter into the pleasures of superfluous details, of little treats of information opposing institutional and historical weight. This is demonstrated, among others, in the extract from the Routard cited above which, in the section about the Royal Yacht, highlights the fact that the excursion which it offers is punctuated with anecdotes, and even goes as far as providing one for the reader “for fun” (Gloaguen, 2008, p. 127). Thus, the realm of that which is anecdotal is that of little pieces of supplementary information which are for the most part inessential and which complement the cultural element, like the icing on a cake.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This suggestion is negatively supported by the following extract from a column by Quebec filmmaker Jacques Leduc. When he returned from travelling to Ramallah to direct Tahani Rached’s film (Soraida, une femme de Palestine released in 2004), he wrote a column in the cinema magazine 24 images, in which he stated: “My memories of this journey, which are all relatively recent, are not anecdotal: they are all emotional ; I’m talking about emotion as persistent as toothache, and each time I am asked to talk about it, I experience the same discomfort. The anecdotes and stories about life on-set that I get to tell when I come back are by no means anecdotal ; they are vital parts of daily life. And they can invariably be summarised by the arbitrary measures taken by the Israeli army in its occupied country, Palestine” (2005). If the filmmaker refuses to see the anecdotal nature of his journey, it is because for him the term refers to that which is frivolous, or unimportant. This thus confirms that the anecdotal is positioned within a strategy of avoiding the seriousness of the information in the sense that it is indeed essential.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Producing Discourse</section>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We have seen how, anecdotes aim to penetrate the authenticity of cultures by making known that which occurs “in the wings.” They simultaneously impose themselves as discourse objects characterised by their socio-cultural insignificance. Here, is there not a paradox between wanting to establish truth within miniscule details ? Why does tourism choose this approach ? We shall aim to provide answers to these two questions in the following paragraphs, firstly by examining the ambiguous status of those who tell anecdotes, who must both know how to identify the utterance and to remove themselves from it in order to render the stories accessible to others. This first stage will enable us to show that anecdotes are discourse objects designed to be shared, and that the tourism mediation devices which use them want to make them objects of shared discourse. We shall then propose a framework for interpreting and understanding the difficulties associated with sharing inessential discourse objects in tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Anecdotes: Between Anonymity and Authorship</section>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Marie-Pascale Huglo and Claire de Ribaupierre, who both studied anecdotes in general, that is to say, without specifically examining their role in tourism mediation devices, highlighted the fact that they are discourse objects which are not only “iterable”, (Huglo, 1997), but which are also subject to intensive circulation. Anecdotes are therefore “constantly reused, transformed and adapted” (Ribaupierre, 2007, p. 7).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Despite their widespread use, anecdotes never fail to surprise. They are “repeated but never boring” (Ribaupierre, 2007, p. 7). They also carry implicit constraints: in order to exist as they are, they must be told so that they strike home. That is to say anecdotes are rooted in speech contexts and set a challenge in terms of rhetoric. Despite the fact that they are anonymous, they must still appear to be the work of a real author. Claire de Ribaupierre raises this aporia and summarises it thus: “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Paradoxically, anecdotes are both tied to their author and simultaneously anonymous, or in some way collective</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.” (2007, p. 12).<br/>The paradox mentioned by Claire de Ribaupierre is just a front. Indeed this oscillation between individual and collective utterances is the fate of objects destined to be repeated, and thus to vary, if we are to believe Marcel Detienne (1981) who posits that: they belong to everyone, but each speaker makes them their own. In other words, we can also say that it is precisely because they circulate that anecdotes are cultural objects which are imposed as the result of a process which is both anonymous and auctorial. It is therefore because they “change hands, just as they change mouths” (Ribaupierre, 2007, p. 11) that, while they are spoken, anecdotes can be inhabited by the speaker. By telling the anecdote, each “author” imprints it with their own style and, having made it their own, expresses they way they approach the world and indeed how they position themselves within it. “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Anecdotes enable us to convey meaning, to make the world our own, rather than being dispossessed of it: they are acts which make us unique</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Ribaupierre, 2007, p. 35).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In this way, they are therefore specific: they appear to be circulating cultural objects (Jeanneret, 2008) belonging to everyone and thus claimed by all. To tell an anecdote is to release into circulation an object which postulates its silence and its secret, its marginal nature and it uniqueness so that with each utterance it again establishes a way of existing in the world which then puts it back into circulation. The challenge in the final paragraphs will be to show that the same applies for specifically mediation or historical touristic anecdotes: their touristic and cultural destination being to circulate whilst providing the speaker with social authorship.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Anecdotes and the Spreading of Tourist Discourse</section>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">When questioned after a holiday, we often focus on the issue of stories. Rachid Amirou suggests that the third phase of a journey (that of return, preceded by departure and visit) is based on a specific socialisation which notably resides in the narration of the journey (1995). Jean-Didier Urbain also shares this vision of a journey in the form of a story continuing after tourists have left foreign soil to come back to the socio-cultural environment to which they belong (Urbain, 2008).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">More precisely, Jean-Didier Urbain defends the idea that stories are not simply part of a journey once the tourist returns home, but instead that they are part of the journey right from the beginning. According to him, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the belief that fiction, or stories more generally, are purely literary objects which are added to the reality of the journey, a narrative embellishment for poets, novelists or rhetoricians, is an illusion</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (2003 [1998], p. 288). Stories accompany journeys from the beginning to the end. Be they in the form of projects, programmes, or even memories, stories are ever present in travellers’ minds.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, tourism, and more precisely travel guides, can be considered as ways of attracting travellers’ interest about the world. They model, complicate and construct anecdotes so that tourists might transform their destinations into stories in which they themselves are the heroes. Guides which focus specifically on the emergence of a “story about the journey” (2003 [1998], p. 276), aim to impose themselves as mediation devices of space, and also as devices to facilitate the passing on of stories and indeed discourse in general. Mediation anecdotes can from here on in be considered as one of these discourse objects that tourists can bring back with them in order to be told to or to blend in to the story of their journey.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Anecdotes on the Linguistic Market</section>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We may ask ourselves why anecdotes participate in passing on discourse, especially if they are considered and indeed qualified as inessential. In other words, we may question what value sharing inessential discourse objects could possibly have. To begin reflection on this subject, let us come back to Pierre Bourdieu and particularly his approach to language (1977 ; 2002 [1977] ; 2002 [1978]).<br/>According to the sociologist, we can consider language acts as economic acts, in the sense that there is a “linguistic market” made up of exchanges and social values, which are particularly symbolic. Speaking means both taking a symbolic risk and attempting to make a profit. The communication situation participates in defining this market. Knowing how to evaluate the discursive opportunity of a social situation is thus a skill for the speaker to acquire, socially speaking. By producing discourse, we are not simply proposing a grammatical product, but indeed a discursive product insomuch as the language and the discourse situation are social.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The language of Pierre Bourdieu is, generally speaking, a social praxis. It is an action in the social world in the sense that it is “made to be spoken” and it is “made to be spoken about” (1977, p. 18). Manipulating language means exhibiting (both deliberately and unwittingly) a certain amount of intelligence both socially and in terms of the symbolic force of those connections from which is it constituted, as well as a certain positioning within this society. To summarise, this could be referred to as saying oneself socially, either explicitly or implicitly. And yet, according to Pierre Bourdieu, acting socially, either by action or speech, means entering in to a process of “distinction”. Speaking therefore means attempting to distinguish oneself. It implies demonstrating one’s social intelligence and acting according to this intelligence and to one’s own intentions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To come back to anecdotes ; if they are presented through the exercise of tourism mediation, it is surely because, on the linguistic market, these types of utterances earn profits. Similarly, if they are given to readers/travellers, it is to help them to make a certain profit in the coming discourse situations. In other words, if we follow Pierre Bourdieu’s thinking, we can consider that anecdotes are produced by the authors of travel guides and are then given to readers/travellers as distinctive discourse objects. And yet, the specificity of anecdotes in these guides is that they are not necessary for tourists’ adventures. This is revealed by their anecdotal approach. Therefore, in tourism in general and in particular in the guides, there are cultural objects which need to be seen or known (the must-see items favoured by short-stay guides) and others which are more of a luxury precisely because they are anecdotal.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Necessity and luxury must here be understood in the terms defined by Pierre Bourdieu. In defining them, he stresses that “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the real principle of the differences observed in the consumer field and elsewhere is the opposition between luxury tastes (or tastes for freedom) and tastes for the necessary</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (1979, p. 198). Tastes for the necessary are clearly those determined according to need, that is to say, those which guarantee human dignity in social terms, and luxury tastes are those which would under no circumstances be dictated by such a need, but rather by the simple pleasure of possession, experimentation or indeed contact. Here this refers to a representation of each of these two types of tastes as, in reality, the choice of one over the other is only rendered “necessary” by society.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mediation anecdotes, bearing in mind the manner in which they appear in travel guides, can be considered luxury products. By that we mean that their use and in particular the editorial differences by which they are differentiated, distances them from tourist necessity. By saying – or reading – anecdotes, we move away from the trips and lists of must-see items (the Louvre in Paris and the Mona Lisa at the Louvre, the Acropolis in Athens, or Karl-Marx-Allee and Museum Island in Berlin). Choosing an anecdotal utterance means distinguishing oneself by declaring one’s luxury tastes, but also means giving a (distinctive) discursive product to tourists. This means defining oneself as a “socialite” rather than “learned”, that is to say, to identify oneself as a social subject who, pushing towards the extreme, prefers to “enjoy without understanding” rather than “understand without feeling” (Bourdieu, 1979, p. 9)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Studying anecdotes in mediation devices highlights the fact that the tourist representations and tourism imaginaries in circulation are not limited to the world of monuments and must-see attractions ; they are also a product of the inessential elements of tourism and indeed of culture as a whole. These minute objects which make up the miniature tourism are undoubtedly more difficult to grasp than must-see attractions insofar as they are hidden within the features of the infra-ordinary. However, they nonetheless participate in creating tourism imaginaries through mediation devices.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">If they consitute culture in the world of tourism, it is partly because they are referred to as insignificant. This, in other words, is because they appear on the fringes of the cultural imperatives which are desired both by mediation specialists and tourists themselves. This fringe existence attributes them a certain socio-cultural flavour. Unlike institutionalised discourse, lowly objects belong to the cultural truths ; they have known how to open an informal path through history and in this sense reveal something authentic about the cultures to which they belong.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These miniature objects which take anecdotal form in the text are given over to the social aspect by the tourism mediation devices, via which they circulate. The driving force behind this circulation – and indeed the reason it occurs – is that utterances hold a profit for those who repeat them. This symbolic profit is anticipated by the devices as the result of social intelligence regarding communication situations, or indeed as a linguistic skill derived from its social aspects. Future tellers of historical anecdotes could, on the one hand, indicate that they knew how to attain the depth and authenticity of the cultures they visited as tourists and, on the other, make themselves known as socialites in the sense that, in distinguishing between the urgency of necessity and the apparent futility of the lowly, they were able to choose the second.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although they are lowly, these anecdotes tend to occupy an ever-growing place in tourism mediation devices. This is illustrated in the 2010 updated version of Petit Futé New York for example, which presents the Lincoln Centre in the same way, word-for-word as 2005, with just one small but by no means insignificant difference found in brackets: “Built in the 1960s between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenue (just as an anecdote, the film West Side Story was filmed here, just prior to the destruction of the old poor neighbourhoods which the centre replaced), the Lincoln Centre is home to the headquarters of major American and indeed international artistic and cultural institutions.” (Auzias &amp;amp; Labourdette, 2010, p. 304). The guide therefore favours a seemingly inessential and insignificant piece of information over more topographical and practical information (“extension of 9th and 10th Avenue from Central Park to 59th Street” [Auzias &amp;amp; Labourdette, 2005, p. 296]).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, generally speaking, these contributions surrounding the notion of the anecdote as inessential and insignificant enable us to suggest a number of ways they can be interpreted and to shed some light on the current influx of these “original” products. Indeed, anecdotes rely on the unknown (My little Paris [Collectif, 2010]), on secrets and hidden attractions (Paris secret et insolite [Trouilleux &amp;amp; Lebar, 2009], Paris Caché [Lepic, 2009]), on the original (Paris Décalé [Briand, 2009]) or even on the absurd (Paris Coquin [Béraud &amp;amp; Hermange, 2008]) ; so many objects’ draw from and found their value and their originality in the opposition that they construct vis-à-vis the imperative, “must-see” regime</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Amossy R., 1991, Les Idées reçues. Sémiologie du stéréotype, Paris, Nathan.</reference>
        <reference>Amirou R., 1995, Imaginaire touristique et sociabilités du voyage, Paris, Presses Universitaires de France.</reference>
        <reference>Auzias D. &amp; Labourdette J.-P. (dir.), 2007, Le Petit Futé Écosse 2007-2008, Paris, Nouvelles Éditions de l’Université.</reference>
        <reference>Barthes R., 1957, « Le Guide bleu », in Mythologies, Paris, Éditions du Seuil, 121-125.</reference>
        <reference>Bourdieu P., 2002, « Le marché linguistique », in Questions de sociologie, Paris, Éditions de Minuit, pp. 121-137, 2002 (1978).</reference>
        <reference>Bourdieu P., 2002, « Ce que parler veut dire », in Questions de sociologie, Paris, Éditions de Minuit, 95-112.</reference>
        <reference>Bourdieu P., 1977, « L’économie des échanges linguistiques », Langue française, vol. 34, n° 1, 17-34.</reference>
        <reference>Collectif, 2001, La Bibliothèque du voyageur. Le Grand guide du tour des Etats-Unis, Paris, Gallimard.</reference>
        <reference>Détienne M., 1981, « Par la bouche et par l’oreille », in L’Invention de la mythologie, Paris, Gallimard, 50-86.</reference>
        <reference>Gloaguen Ph., 2008, Le Guide du Routard Écosse, Paris, Hachette.</reference>
        <reference>Gloaguen Ph., 2006, Le Guide du Routard New York, Paris, Hachette.</reference>
        <reference>Gomez-Géraud M.-C. &amp; Antoine Ph., 2001, Roman et récit de voyage, Paris, Presses Universitaires Paris-Sorbonne.</reference>
        <reference>Gritti J., 1967, « Les contenus culturels du Guide bleu: monuments et sites “à voir” », Communications, vol. 10, n° 10, 51-64.</reference>
        <reference>Hadjadj D., 1990, « L’anecdote au péril des dictionnaires », in Montandon A. (dir.), L’Anecdote. Actes du colloque de Clermont-Ferrand, Clermont-Ferrand, Association des publications de la Faculté des lettres et sciences humaines de Clermont-Ferrand, 1-20.</reference>
        <reference>Huglo M.-P., 1997, Métamorphoses de l’insignifiant. Essai sur l’anecdote dans la modernité, Montréal, Balzac-Le Griot éditeur.</reference>
        <reference>Jullien D., 1993, « L’anecdote américaine chez Tocqueville: la méconnaissance du double », Romantisme, vol. 23, n° 82, 57-72.</reference>
        <reference>Leduc J., 2005, « Barreau de chaise 13 », 24 images, n° 123, p. 36.</reference>
        <reference>MacCannell D., 1999, The Tourist. A New Theory of the Leisure Class, Los Angeles, University of California Press.</reference>
        <reference>Montandon A. (dir.), 1990, L’Anecdote. Actes du colloque de Clermont-Ferrand, Clermont-Ferrand, Association des publications de la Faculté des lettres et sciences humaines de Clermont-Ferrand.</reference>
        <reference>Passeron J.-C, 1991, Le Raisonnement sociologique, Paris, Nathan.</reference>
        <reference>Procope et Isambert F.-A. (trad.), 1856, Anekdota, ou, Histoire secrète de Justinien, tr. de Procope, avec notice sur l’auteur et notes philosophiques et historiques, Paris, Didot frères.Rey A. (dir.), 1992, Dictionnaire historique de la langue française, A-L. Paris, Dictionnaire Le Robert.</reference>
        <reference>Ribaupierre (de) C., 2007, « Déchirer la vie: les stratégies de l’anecdote », in Ribaupierre (de) C., Anecdote, Zurich, JRP Ringier, 5-50.</reference>
        <reference>Souchier E., 1998, « L’image du texte. Pour une théorie de l’énonciation éditoriale », Les Cahiers de médiologie, n° 6, 137-145.</reference>
        <reference>Urbain J.-D., 2008, Le voyage était presque parfait. Essai sur les voyages ratés, Paris, Payot &amp; Rivage.</reference>
        <reference>Urbain J.-D., 2003, Secrets de voyage. Menteurs, imposteurs et autres voyageurs impossibles, Paris, Payot &amp; Rivages.</reference>
        <reference>Varillas A., 1689, Les Anecdotes de Florence, ou l’histoire secrète de la maison de Médecis, La Haye, Adrian Moerjens.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">There are seven guides (some of which are “cultural”: Guide Bleu, the Guide Vert, the guide from La Bibliothèque du voyageur and the guide Voir – ; and the others “practical” – Le Guide du Routard, the Lonely Planet and the Petit Futé) for two destinations, New York and Scotland.</note>
        <note id="2">See : http://misspotin.wordpress.com/</note>
        <note id="3">See : http://unjourunvoyage.viabloga.com/</note>
        <note id="4">It should be noted that the choice of terminology and the definitions given by Pierre Bourdieu are pejorative. The reason for this choice stems from the author’s wish to denounce universal pretention for each of these relationships with culture (their neutrality) rather than a judgment of these appropriation methods and cultural apprehension.</note>
        <note id="5">COLLECTIF, My little Paris, Paris, Chêne, 2010 ; TROUILLEUX Rodolphe et LEBAR Jacques, Paris secret et insolite, Paris, Parigramme, 2009 ; LEPIC Alice, Paris caché, Paris, Parigramme, 2009 ; BRIAND Cécile, Paris décalé, Paris, Lonely Planet, 2009 ; HERMANGE Aurélia et BERAUD Diana, Paris coquin, Paris, First, 2008.</note>
    </notes>
</article>