<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_JR_11-69_An_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4796" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.4796</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>16</numero>
        <annee>2019</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="4791">
            <traducteur nom="Graburn" prenom="Nelson" />
            Une plage habillée, sans bains : Fidjrossè à Cotonou (Bénin)
        </original>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Rieucau" prenom="Jean" email="jeanrieucau@orange.fr">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_JR_11-60_Un_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4791" lang="fr">Une plage habillée, sans bains : Fidjrossè à Cotonou (Bénin)</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Université Lyon 2 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>A dressed up beach, but with no bathing: Fidjrossè in Cotonou (Benin)</titre>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            African populations have unique relationships with the beach (water, sand, sun, body). In their sensory universe, a specific corporeality leads to an aversion to sand, an avoidance of the sun, the absence of naked bodies, and little interest in bathing in the sea for pleasure. Historical, ethnic, anthropological, religious reasons contribute to shaping a beach culture far removed from the 4 “S” (sea, sand, sex, sun) specific to Western civilizations. On the beaches of sub-Saharan Africa as well as in Madagascar, a specifically African beach culture has emerged, with very little borrowing and hybridization with the 4 "S".
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            Fidjrossè Beach in Cotonou, Benin, is an open public, open. All of Cotonou is there. This place is fashionable, especially for the youth of the economic capital of the country, for partying on weekends (music, dance, alcohol, hookah), mainly on Sunday afternoons. This relaxation area, without opening hours, would make up for the lack of public green and leisure spaces in the center of the city (gardens, public parks) (Coralli, 2007). This wide sandy strip serves as a vast playful, recreational, rest and leisure area.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            Europeans, even dressed in the Western style, who travel to this atypical territory, to photograph and investigate, are well accepted by the population. On the other hand, the <em>yovo</em> (western or anything that is not black) cannot take place on the beach in a swimsuit (Coralli, <em>op.cit.</em>). Fully clothed men and women are dressed in those elegant, dressed-up outfits that are worn in the rest of the city on a holiday. The ostentation of beautiful clothing is part of the awareness of living an important and unique moment. Traditional African clothes, compared to Westernized international outfits, are worn by two-thirds of those present. Unlike other beaches in black Africa, clothing does not constitute an identity marker or a religious affirmation (Kenya) (Rieucau, 2014). The virtual absence of bathing, the absence of sun-worship, excludes the wearing of bathing suits.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            Even though water is the mainstay of the economy of the city of Cotonou (shipping in the port, fishing activities), it is also feared. Among the Fon (38.4% of the country's population, the main African language of Benin), rivers have historically caused fear. In their perception of the beyond, the souls of the deceased would use them to reach the sea and reach the other world (Coralli, <em>op. Cit.</em>). The great danger of the beaches of the Gulf of Benin (frequency of drowning), the fact that an overwhelming majority of Beninese cannot swim, add to the cultural obstacles (absence of a seaside culture, ethno-religious beliefs) underlying this repulsion of sea bathing, except for splashing in the closest waves.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            The beach of Fidjrossè brings together an exclusively African populations. It is marked by an urban social mix. This "African" beach is devoid of international tourists and European expatriates. Visitorship of the place is mixed, half men, half women and is not uni-sexual like on other African coasts (Kenya). This coastal territory, with more a family style, welcomes many children and is broken down into groups of families, circles of male friends, and gatherings of women. The adults, two-thirds standing, motionless, a minority of them seated, but never lying on the sand, looking towards the sea horizon, are in a contemplative attitude facing the spectacle of the sea. Looking, showing, but without strolling, characterizes this beach. Spending a few hours at the beach is not intended for swimming, but to observe the panorama of the sea which explains why no one lies on the sand.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            Walking among the beach goers, a considerable number of street vendors, survey and crisscross the sand to offer peeled oranges, peanuts, drinks, toys, and so on. In this small nation classified as a Least Developed Country, this alternative economy makes up for the lack of permanent jobs. The omnipresence of these small sellers can also be explained by the absence of other commercial services nearby.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            All of Cotonou's beaches are threatened by marine erosion and are very dangerous. For decades, the city’s main beach was located to the east, next to the embassy district. The advancement of the Atlantic Ocean in this area caused its abandonment.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            The beach of Fidjrossè located to the south-west of the city, near the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, marks the beginning of the fishing route which links Cotonou to Ouidah. This road, parallel to the sea, is in fact a track that winds its way between coconut groves, palm groves and fishing villages. A small cliff separates the shore line from the top of the beach where tapered canoes are stored. Fidjrossè beach, with a coastal morphology close to that of the Route des Pêches, constitutes a multi-functional beach, alternating between fishing activity (weekdays) and leisure activities (weekends). On weekends, the street vendors, the children, the inhabitants of Cotonou replace the fishermen.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            African beaches frequently welcome animals; here a horse and its rider offer a walk on the beach, dromedary camels (Kenya), when the sandy shores are not invaded by poultry and herds of zebu cattle (Madagascar).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            The back beach of Fidjrossè, very large, sparsely occupied, carries nets for volleyball and small goal posts for football. Small all-male bands, elsewhere Nigerian hip-hop dancers, play romantic songs for the different circles of friends sitting on carpets. These groups seek a shaded shelter under the coconut palms and take advantage of the sea breeze. The Directorate General of Water, Forests and Hunting conducts forestation operations at the top of the beach. However, this large and very busy beach has no public toilets or aid stations to rescue the rare intrepid bather.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            The numerous small bistros, taverns and bar-restaurants, built behind the beach, are visited by all kinds of people. Access is by off-road car, Zemidjan (motorbike taxi) or automobile taxi. In the restaurant bars, traditional menus are served, based on rice and fish. At night the bar-restaurants are transformed into a dance halls, with a background of Beninese or Congolese music. Flat screens broadcast football matches from the European Championships and the places fill up with spectators for the African Cup of Nations football.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Coralli, M. (2007), "Bénin, la plage de Cotonou, un lieu pour se montrer " [Benin, Cotonou beach, a place to show off], Urbanisme, n ° 355, 5 p.</reference>
        <reference>Rieucau, J., Odiara, B. (2014), "Plage occidentale exclusive, plage africaine inclusive, sur le littoral swahili : Whitesands Beach et Jomo Kenyatta public beach", [Exclusive western beach, inclusive African beach, on the Swahili coast: Whitesands Beach and Jomo Kenyatta public beach.], in Rieucau, J. (Ed.), Le Kenya dans la 3eme révolution touristique. Au-delà du safari [Kenya in the 3rd tourism revolution. Beyond the safari.] Harmattan, Paris, pp. 109-138.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
</article>