<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_JFS_7-63_Iy_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3295" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.3295</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>14</numero>
        <annee>2018</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="3289">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            Entretien avec le réalisateur Patrice Leconte, réalisateur des Bronzés
        </original>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Staszak" prenom="Jean-François">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_JFS_5-36_Ls_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1645" lang="fr">L’imaginaire des guides touristiques</publication>
                <publication id="fr_BDJFSOT_9-36_Ts_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1057" lang="fr">Tourismes et dynamiques identitaires</publication>
                <publication id="fr_JFS_49-83_Ta_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/424" lang="fr">Tourisme et prostitution coloniales : la visite de Bousbir à Casablanca (1924-1955)</publication>
                <publication id="fr_JFS_5-26_Tr_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1632" lang="fr">Tahiti : l’envers du décor</publication>
                <publication id="fr_JFS_5-49_Le_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1516" lang="fr">La tour de Pise et le smartphone du post-touriste</publication>
                <publication id="fr_MGBJFSNG_62-69_Ls_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1829" lang="fr">L’érotisation des lieux touristiques. Espaces, acteurs et imaginaires</publication>
                <publication id="fr_JFS_12-23_Ir_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/2891" lang="fr">Introduction du dossier</publication>
                <publication id="fr_JFS_7-70_Es_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3289" lang="fr">Entretien avec le réalisateur Patrice Leconte, réalisateur des Bronzés</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Professeur de géographie, Université de Genève. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Interview with Patrice Leconte, director of the Bronzés trilogy</titre>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourists in films? For the French public, the most famous example has to be the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Bronzés</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> trilogy (“</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">French Fried Vacation</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” in English). Directed by Patrice Leconte with the troupe of the Le Splendid café-théâtre company, the three films (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Les Bronzés</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1978, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Les Bronzés font du ski</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1979, and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Les Bronzés 3 : amis pour la vie</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2006) were major box-office successes when they were released. Today, they still attract over 10 million viewers each time they are shown on television. The first two instalments have even been raised to the status of cult films, with their characters, certain lines and situations today a part of the French collective memory. The spirit of Jean-Claude Dusse, convinced he has “a chance” and hoping to “score”, even if only thanks to“a misunderstanding”, is still very present in Club Med villages and winter sports resorts. These films were big hits, marking their period because they managed to capture something of the spirit of the times. And their timeless nature is due to the fact that the situations and characters they portrayed have hardly changed over the years.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These films show tourists at work, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">in situ</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. They go swimming, they go on excursions, they play sports, they attend shows, they eat, they flirt (the latter being in reality their main activity, at least in the first two films). And all this in Côte d’Ivoire, in Val-d’Isère in France, and in Sardinia. In a holiday village very reminiscent of a Club Med resort and designed for middle-class tourists, in a sports resort with a diverse clientele, and in a luxury hotel. These places represent different microcosms in which the tourists are more or less isolated from the outside world. They serve as a backdrop to the comedy, the main aspects of which include the mediocrity of the characters, reduced to a few stereotypes, and their social interaction, friendships or romantic relationships, all stamped with the seal of pettiness. A potentially very dark vision of humanity if it were not counterbalanced by the real affection we feel for these individuals with whom we cannot help but identify.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Bronzés</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> films are neither a social satire nor a criticism of tourism in the sense that they target neither a particular group nor a way of life. Instead, they represent a human comedy, that of a group of characters placed in a configuration that reveals who they are and how they relate to </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">each other. Rather than the subject of the film, tourism is the recurring configuration in which this comedy is set.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">We wanted to interview Patrice Leconte, not so much because of the vision of tourism that he presented in these films (often portrayed as caricatured or critical, but which can in fact be considered quite realistic), but rather for the following two reasons. First, he chose three times to situate his comedies within a tourist configuration, and, from the point of view of tourism studies, it was relevant to ask him why. And second, the success of his films is such and their role in the making of the social consciousness about tourism so important that we cannot be interested in this subject without wanting to know more about the genesis of the films.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Cadé M. 2009, “Les Bronzés 1, 2, et 3 : une représentation des pratiques touristiques des classes moyennes aisées dans le cinéma populaire français”, in G. Ferréol and A.-M. Mamontoff (dir.), </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourisme et sociétés,</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Brussels, EME, pp.23-31.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lombard Ph., 2016, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Le Petit livre des Bronzés</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Paris, First Editions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Interview conducted at the director’s home in Paris on December 8, 2018. The interview, which lasted two hours, was recorded, transcribed and slightly rewritten to increase consistency and readability. Our sincere thanks to Patrice Leconte, who kindly accepted to answer our questions in a very open and honest manner.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
</article>