<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_LLFJETT_59-94_Cs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5321" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.5321</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Leuschen" prenom="Lara">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="de_LLTT_47-127_Le_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4644" lang="de">Landschaftsstereotype und Relevanz kreativwirtschaftlicher Narrative in der touristischen Vermarktung der Destination Bodensee </publication>
                <publication id="fr_LLTT_47-134_Se_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4687" lang="fr">Stéréotypes paysagers et pertinence des récits de l’économie créative dans le marketing touristique de la destination lac de Constance</publication>
                <publication id="en_LLTT_48-127_Ln_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4731" lang="en">Landscape stereotypes and potential of creative economic narratives in the tourism marketing of Lake Constance as a destination</publication>
                <publication id="de_LLFJETT_55-84_Ke_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5353" lang="de">Kreativwirtschafts- und Kulturtourismusstandort Bodensee – eine Mediendiskursanalyse</publication>
                <publication id="fr_LLFJETT_56-113_Ie_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5287" lang="fr">Industries créatives et tourisme culturel dans la région du lac de Constance — une analyse du discours médiatique</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                M. A., Cultural Managenent, ZHAW Zurich 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Eitzenberger" prenom="Florian J.">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="de_LLFJETT_55-84_Ke_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5353" lang="de">Kreativwirtschafts- und Kulturtourismusstandort Bodensee – eine Mediendiskursanalyse</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                M.A., Tourism Management, HTWG Constance 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Thimm" prenom="Tatjana">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="de_TT_41-131_Is_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1038" lang="de">Imaginäre Geographien klassischer und neuer Reisemedien – Wirklichkeitskonstruktion touristischer Intermediäre am Beispiel Sevillas</publication>
                <publication id="en_TT_41-136_It_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1044" lang="en">Imaginary Geographies of Classic and New Travel Media – Reality-Construction of Touristic Intermediaries with Sevilla as a Case in Point</publication>
                <publication id="es_TT_43-177_Go_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1050" lang="es">Geografías imaginarias en los medios de comunicación clásicos y nuevos sobre viajes. La construcción de la realidad de los intermediarios turísticos tomando Sevilla como ejemplo</publication>
                <publication id="de_TT_44-133_Gt_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/693" lang="de">Geschäftsmodell Tanztourismus in Sevilla und Buenos Aires – Bedeutungsdimensionen immaterieller Kulturgüter im Destinationsmanagement</publication>
                <publication id="en_TT_34-136_Dt_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/700" lang="en">Dance Tourism Business Models in Seville and Buenos Aires: dimensions of meaning of intangible cultural assets in destination management</publication>
                <publication id="es_TT_44-165_Ms_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/706" lang="es">Modelo de negocio del turismo del baile en Sevilla y Buenos Aires: aspectos de la importancia del patrimonio cultural inmaterial en la gestión de destinos turísticos</publication>
                <publication id="de_LLTT_47-127_Le_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4644" lang="de">Landschaftsstereotype und Relevanz kreativwirtschaftlicher Narrative in der touristischen Vermarktung der Destination Bodensee </publication>
                <publication id="fr_LLTT_47-134_Se_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4687" lang="fr">Stéréotypes paysagers et pertinence des récits de l’économie créative dans le marketing touristique de la destination lac de Constance</publication>
                <publication id="en_LLTT_48-127_Ln_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4731" lang="en">Landscape stereotypes and potential of creative economic narratives in the tourism marketing of Lake Constance as a destination</publication>
                <publication id="de_LLFJETT_55-84_Ke_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5353" lang="de">Kreativwirtschafts- und Kulturtourismusstandort Bodensee – eine Mediendiskursanalyse</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Prof. Dr., Tourism Management, HTWG Constance 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Creative industry and cultural tourism destination Lake Constance – a media discourse analysis</titre>
    <sousTitre>Peer-reviewed article</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        The following media discourse analysis examines the news media coverage of four regional online newspapers, about the topics “creative industries” and “cultural tourism” at Lake Constance region in the period from 2006 until 2016. The results show that, besides event-relater reporting, there is currently no vibrant media discourse on the topics “creative industries” and “cultural tourism”. Even though the image of the Lake Constance region is heavily influenced by tourism, “cultural tourism” also plays a secondary role when it comes to regional news reporting. Moreover, discourses do not overlap and thus no synergies within the local media discourse are formed. This result is relevant for the regional tourism development, because the cooperation between “creative industries” and “cultural tourism” creates opportunities such as the expansion of the tourism offer and an extension of the tourist season. To activate unused opportunities at the different destinations of the region, a supra-regional visibility of the sector “creative industries” should be developed and the cooperation of the sector with local stakeholders of cultural tourism should be promoted. 
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction </section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            The increasing pressure on destinations to differentiate themselves from each other, triggers an increasing number of initiatives and projects that try to specifically promote the potentials of cultural tourism and creative industries to ultimately also encourage local tourism (e.g. "CreaTour Portugal", "Creative Barcelona" or "Creative Tourism Austria"). There has always been a close economic interdependence between creative industries and cultural tourism. Sub-markets of creative industries related to design, art, music or the performing arts, are an important content provider not only for event- and attraction-based tourism, but also for interactive formats connecting creativity with local culture and customs (OECD 2014; Richards and Bartos 2014). Especially in Germany, many destinations have an extraordinary cultural tourism potential, yet this often plays only a minor role when it comes to destination marketing (Hepperle 2017, p. 422). This also applies to the region around Lake Constance, which is culturally very multifaceted due to its international location. Yet its image is primarily made up by its diverse natural landscape and its recreational value (Hassemer 2010; Leuschen and Thimm 2019a). Regional news media coverage can provide valuable information about how the Lake Constance region deals with its cultural and creative-economic potentials because mass media can spawn discourse and construct realities (Keppler 2005, p. 94ff.). The media discourse analysis offers the possibility to analyze regional reporting on different levels and with regard to different questions. Moreover, it makes interpretative conclusions about the “Creative–Industries-and-Cultural-Tourism-Destination-Lake-Constance” possible. The following study investigates the question of how the terms “creative industries” and “cultural tourism” are connoted within the regional media discourse and to what extent theses discourses are related to each other.  
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. Current State of Research </section>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Creative Industries </section>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            The economic sector called “cultural and creative industries” comprises those enterprises that are predominantly profit-oriented and deal with the creation, production, distribution and/or media dissemination of cultural/creative goods and services (BMWi 2014, p. 3). This includes eleven sub-sectors, namely: music, publishing, art, film, broadcasting, performing arts, architecture, design, press, advertising, as well as the software and game industry.  “Creative industries” is often used as an umbrella term for all of these sub-sectors, which also applies for the context of this study.  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            Since the beginning of 2000, creative industries have established themselves globally as a source of economic hope for regional development. This can be traced back in particular to the US economist Richard Florida, who exerted a lasting influence with his (sometimes controversially discussed) "Creative Capital Theory" (Florida, 2002) on the political debate around creative industries and local politics, also in European cities. Florida sees creativity as a source of economic growth and writes: "Many say that we now live in an 'information' economy or a 'knowledge' economy. But what's more fundamentally true is that we now have an economy powered by human creativity. Creativity [...] is now the decisive source of competitive advantage. In every industry, the winners in the long run are those who can create and keep creating. (Florida, 2002, p. 4f.). In his publication “Creative City. A toolkit for urban innovators” (2008) urban researcher Charles Landry also emphasizes the importance of a city's cultural life and its creative industry. According to Landry (2008), in order to develop the potential of a city, a creative space must be established in which innovations are created (Landry 2008). Here, soft elements like an urban lifestyle, image or the (cultural) identity of a destination play a significant role in attracting companies and qualified workers, especially coming from creative industries. These soft elements of a region are therefore principal factors, which play a role for location choice and are at the same time starting points for increasing the attractiveness of destinations (Böing 2016, p. 15). In the wake of Florida (2002) and Landry (2008), the concept of the creative industries was extensively discussed. In addition to ongoing debates on the state of creative industries (Boggs, 2009; Markusen <em>et al</em>., 2008; Pratt and Hutton 2013), excessive expectations of them have also been expressed. For instance, as a universal remedy against the decline of old industrialized cities, being highly relevant for social cohesion (McRobbie, 2011; Stern and Seifert 2008) or as a decisive factor in the competition of destinations (Evans, 2009). Ambivalent working conditions are often cited as characteristics of creative industries: precarious on the one hand (De Peuter, 2011; Goehler, 2006; Zimmermann <em>et al.</em>, 2009), innovative and highly interconnected with interesting and meaningful contents on the other (14). Amongst other things, some authors see new opportunities in the digitalization of creative industries (Friebe and Lobo 2009). In most literature, creative industries are primarily viewed as an urban phenomenon (Landry, 2008; Geppert and Mundelius, 2007; Lange <em>et al.</em>, 2011). Creative industries in smaller cities or in rural areas are underrepresented in reality and accordingly also in the scientific discourse about them (Waitt and Gibson, 2009; Schiller <em>et al.</em>, 2019). Nonetheless, creative industries as a growing and dynamic economic sector are of particular relevance for rural areas. The economic potential of creative industries is also recognized by regional and tourism marketing organizations, which, for some years now, have been relying specifically on creative narratives, such as Berlin's "City of Design" (Colomb, 2012) or destinations like Seville (flamenco) or Buenos Aires (tango), which are strongly oriented towards dance and music (Thimm, 2014). 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Cultural Tourism  </section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            Cultural tourism refers to a variety of forms of tourism. These forms all include, that by visiting cultural attractions, they satisfy the tourist’s need for information and experience on a topic, no matter if it is contemporary or historic (Richards, 2003). Richards and Raymond (2000) were the first to extensively address the role of creative elements within tourism, focusing mainly on those formats that enable visitors to develop their creative potential through active participation in courses and learning experiences (Richards and Raymond 2000, p. 18). The development of these tourism offers also makes strategic use of cooperation with stakeholders of local creative industries (Richards 2011; Richards <em>et al.</em>, 2018). The latter can thereby trigger innovations in both sectors (Leuschen and Thimm, 2019b; Santana Talavera, 2003). Cultural tourism, too, can expand its assortment of offers by adding creative elements (Richards <em>et al.</em>, 2018). This then allows tourists to move from a predominantly pure observational to a participatory, immersive and individual experience (Couret, 2012; Richards, 2012). If the tourist also hopes to participate, more in the local way of life through do it yourself or craft tourism, new opportunities for local support of artists and communities will open up (Creative Tourism Network, 2014). Cultural tourism has been predominantly perceived as an urban tourism and increasingly event-driven phenomenon (Liu 2012; Nadotti and Vannoni, 2019). However, cultural tourism is also seen as an economic and tradition-preserving source of hope for rural regions, which can work against the structural weakness of remote urban regions or is even seen as a tool to support the reduction of poverty in developing countries (MacDonald and Jollifee, 2003; Njovo and Makacha, 2018). Like most tourism market segments, cultural tourism is also growing worldwide, differentiating itself further in its products and services according to growing target groups, as well as benefiting from digitization and globalization trends (Richards, 2003; Tatarusanu and Iatu, 2018). 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Creative industries and cultural tourism in the region around Lake Constance </section>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            An in-depth examination of the location conditions of creative industries on Lake Constance was carried out through a study conducted by the University of St. Gallen in 2011. The potential analysis was carried out within the framework of the INTERREG programme, supported by the <em>Wirtschaftsförderung Bodenseekreis</em>. That is why, the study focused solely on the Lake Constance district (not the whole region), whose economic center is Friedrichshafen. One of the results of the study was that 8% of the local companies belong to creative industries, but that these are only responsible for just under 2% of all revenue (Scherer <em>et al.</em>, 2011, p. 19) and thus play a subordinate role. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            For the entire Lake Constance region, creative industries were examined in more detail in the first Creative Industries Report for the Lake Constance region (Schiller <em>et al.</em>, 2019). The report was able to identify a diverse mix of creative industry sectors in the Lake Constance region, which makes up around 9% of all businesses and can be found in both urban and rural areas (Schiller <em>et al.</em>, 2019, p. 64). In addition, the role of creative industries for the development of creative tourism services/products was discussed in the report. A quantitative survey of regional cultural providers and tour operators as well as expert interviews with tourism marketing organizations in the region showed that cooperation between actors from creative industries and cultural tourism is quite common in the creation of cultural tourism services, but that they can be expanded, especially for younger segments (Schiller <em>et al.</em>, 2019, p. 65). In particular, formats in which cultural and creative professionals give cultural tourists the opportunity to participate creatively themselves are only found sporadically in the Lake Constance region (Leuschen and Thimm, 2019b, p. 56f.). A discourse-analytical investigation of advertising material for the destination Lake Constance also showed that tour operators currently do not rely on “creative narratives” when marketing the Lake Constance region to tourists (Leuschen and Thimm, 2019a). This deficit of cultural tourism offers and the lack of marketing is in stark contrast to the growth of the cultural tourism segment and the increasing demand for creative tourism offers in general, as well as the cultural tourism potential of the Lake Constance region and the distinctive creative industries of the region in particular. The above-mentioned studies on creative industries and cultural tourism allow the drawing of conclusions about valuable synergies that can be created through the cooperation of the two sectors. Yet they provide little evidence as to why the Lake Constance region has not yet exploited this potential. By conducting a media discourse analysis of the regional reporting, a condition assessment of the media visibility of “Creative-Industries-and- Cultural-Tourism-Destination-Lake-Constance” is carried out, which can serve as a basis for the formulation of implications encouraging the activation of previously unused opportunities. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. Methodology </section>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            This article examines the regional media discourses on creative industries and cultural tourism in the Lake Constance region and attempts to identify interfaces. The study asks the following questions: 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            How and to what extent were creative industries and cultural tourism reported on in a selection of regional daily newspapers (online research)?  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            In the course of reporting on creative industries and cultural tourism, have there been any changes in the nature or scope of reporting?  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            How were the articles on creative industries and cultural tourism placed within the newspapers and what spatial focuses could be identified?  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            Which creative industry and cultural tourism topics or events were increasingly covered in regional reporting? 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            To what extent do the discourses on creative industries and cultural tourism intersect?   
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            The investigation of regional reporting is based on a media discourse analysis of online articles on the topics of creative industries and cultural tourism published in four regional media newspapers in the period from 2006 to 2016. By means of a systematic, intersubjective comprehensible description of contents and formal characteristics of the material’s corpus (Früh, 2015, p. 29), on the one hand conclusions are to be drawn about the manifest contents and the development of the regional media discourse, on the other the non-manifest context, i.e. the future development of the “Creative-Industries-and-Cultural-Tourism-Destination-Lake-Constance” (Merten, 1995, p. 15) must also be considered. The complexity of reporting is reduced by identifying central patterns (Rössler, 2017, p. 18). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            The individual units of analysis were not selected according to criteria of statistical representativeness, but were selected qualitatively. The decisive factor in the pre-coding process was whether the individual articles would expand knowledge about the subject of investigation, i.e. creative industries and cultural tourism. The relevance of an article was assessed based on the inductively developed selection scheme shown in Document 1. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
             
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            Only those articles in which the topics of creative industries and cultural tourism are dominant or important were included in the sample. In order to ensure intercoder-reliability, the codings were randomly checked. Cases of doubt were discussed within the selection team to ensure unified solutions (cf. Früh, 2015, p. 19). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            Due to their broad spectrum of contents and widespread distribution, the online daily newspapers listed below were selected for answering the research question (see Rössler, 2017, p. 65).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            The <em>Südkurier</em> is a regional daily newspaper, based in Constance, for the regions of <em>North-Western Lake Constance</em>, the High Rhine and Black Forest. The paper is published six times a week with a print run of approx. 118,000 copies and approx. 3,500 e-paper subscriptions. The analyzed text corpus comprises articles from the basic digital subscription, which were recorded using suitable search terms for the period from 01/2006 to 05/2017. The digital basic subscription only grants access to a reduced corpus of articles, which composition is at the discretion of the editors and does not follow a fixed scheme. Decisive decision factors for or against the publication of an article in the digital basic subscription are the news value and the presumed reach1.   
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            The <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> is a regional newspaper based in Ravensburg. Its distribution range stretches from Lindau on Lake Constance to Ellwangen in Upper Swabia, as well as from Trossingen in the district of Schwarzwald-Baar-Heuberg to Leutkirch in Western Allgaeu. It is published during working days and has a print run of about 170,000 copies2, of which 14,500 are the e-paper edition. It belongs to <em>Schwäbische Verlag GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG Drexler Gesser</em>, which, in addition to the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung,</em> also publishes other local newspapers. The examined text corpus comprises articles of the digital subscription <em>SchwäbischeBasic</em> from 01/2006 to 07/2017. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            The regional newspaper <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> is published by <em>Russmedia Verlag GmbH</em> and appears daily except Sunday. In the first half of 2017, 60,494 copies were sold3. The distribution range covers the Austrian province of Vorarlberg. On the website of <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> vn.at, the print newspaper and other articles are published as PDF. However, these two offers can only be read with the VN-Digital subscription. The examined text corpus includes articles from the website from 2012 onwards. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            The <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em>, based in St. Gallen, is the biggest regional newspaper in eastern Switzerland and publishes daily from Monday to Saturday. It belongs to the NZZ media group and has a print run of 119,453 copies. The distribution range extends from St. Gallen, Appenzell Innerrhoden, Appenzell Ausserrhoden, Thurgau to the Principality of Liechtenstein4.  The examined text corpus includes all articles of the website of <em>the St. Galler Tagblatt</em> tagblatt.ch from 01/2006 to 11/2017. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. Results </section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
             
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Intensity of Reporting  </section>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            The online daily newspapers of the <em>Südkurier</em>, <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em>, <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> and <em>St. Gallener Tagblatt</em> were examined for selected search terms for the period from 2006 to 2016. The search terms used and the respective number of hits are reporter in Table 1. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
             
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <strong>Creative Industries</strong> 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            The number of hits for the sector creative industries were compared with the number of hits for other economic sectors in the following. Noticeable is that the reporting on creative industries of the examined regional media shows a significantly lower frequency in comparison to the chemical industry, energy supply, mechanical engineering or the automotive industry and thus plays a rather subordinate role (see Table 2). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            Looking at the number of articles about creative industries during the individual years, one can observe strong fluctuations to some extent. General tendencies in the development over time are apparent, but only weakly distinctive. An indication for this is the strongly event-driven reporting in this field. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            For example, the largest source of inspiration for the <em>Südkurier</em>'s regional reporting was the <em>Creative Industries Fair</em> in Friedrichshafen (ten articles in the examined text corpus). The <em>Südkurier</em>, which had its own stand at the fair, had advertised the fair more strongly with several event notices. The <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> (12 articles in the examined sample) and the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em> (five articles in the examined sample) also reported on the organization of the fair from 2006 to 2008 and its cancellation in 2009. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            A further source of inspiration, since 2013, with regular articles about in the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> is the industrial park<em> Werk 8</em> in Trossingen (six articles out of all the examined cases). With the aim of developing a creative industry cluster with a focus on information technology, the municipal housing construction company <em>Wohnbau GmbH Trossingen</em> provides rental space in <em>Werk 8</em>. The <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> repeatedly reported on the ArtDesign Fair in Feldkirch (three articles out of all examined cases). The network <em>Zukunftsorte</em>, which connects innovative Austrian communities and encourages cooperation amongst themselves as well as the creative industries, was also presented (two articles out of all examined cases). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            The most profound discussion around the regional creative industries was triggered by the publication of a study, in 2011, on the creative industries in the Lake Constance region, conducted by the University of St. Gallen (four articles out of all examined cases). The readers were first made aware of the topic by calls for participation in the study and then informed about the study results.  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <strong>Cultural Tourism </strong> 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            Despite the economic importance of tourism for the Lake Constance region, cultural tourism plays a subordinate role in regional reporting. Other forms of tourism such as shopping tourism, bike tourism, health tourism and hiking tourism clearly predominate. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            Within the study period from 2006 to 2016, reporting with direct reference to "cultural tourism" or "cultural tourists" has remained relatively constant. An exception is the year 2009, in which considerably more hits could be identified in the <em>Südkurier</em>. The articles on topics related to cultural tourism mainly include announcements of events, which have cultural tourism potential, as well as the presentation of political strategy concepts and individual measures to support cultural tourism in the region. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            In general, it is hardly possible to identify dominant sources of inspiration in the reporting. In the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> less than 20% of the articles were classified as dominant or important. Six articles appeared in the <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> between 2012 and 2016 in which the subject of cultural tourism was explicitly mentioned. Although all of these articles were classified as relevant, due to the small amount, no central source of inspiration can be identified. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            Only in the articles of the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em>, there are sources of inspiration - the tourism marketing organizations <em>Thurgau Tourismus</em> and <em>St.-Galler-Bodensee-Tourismus</em>, which are repeatedly the subject of articles, as well as their plans to promote cultural tourism (three articles out of all examined cases). At the beginning of the research period, starting from 2008, the status of the Abbey District of St. Gallen as a UNESCO World Heritage Site is also repeatedly mentioned (three articles out of all examined cases). 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Positioning and spacial focus of the articles </section>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <strong>Creative Industries </strong> 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            In all of the media examined, the topic of “creative industries” is primarily placed in the local sections. Respectively, the larger cities in the distribution areas are dominantly represented. In the <em>Südkurier</em> these are Constance and Friedrichshafen; in the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> Friedrichshafen, Trossingen and Ravensburg as well as Ulm and Aalen; in the <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> Bregenz, Dornbirn and Feldkirch as well as in the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em> St. Gallen and Frauenfeld.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            In the supra-regional section of the <em>Südkurier</em>, the cities of Freiburg and Basel, which are close to the border, as well as Berlin and Leipzig, are repeatedly mentioned in the context of creative industries. The <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> reports supra-regionally on Lower Austria and Vienna. The St. <em>Galler Tagblatt's</em> supra-regional reporting focuses primarily on the international art market. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <strong>Cultural Tourism </strong> 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            In the <em>Südkurier</em>, the topic of cultural tourism, in particular the district of Constance and the Hochrhein, is also mainly dealt within the regional sections. On a supra-regional level, four articles critically discuss the development of cultural tourism and the sustainability of UNESCO World Heritage sites such as the pyramids of Giza or Carthage. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            The <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> deals with the topic of cultural tourism mainly in its local section. The spatial focus in the reporting on cultural tourism is on Upper Swabia. The communities of Weingarten and Sigmaringen stand out in terms of quantity with their efforts to expand cultural tourism. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            In the <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> cultural tourism is also mainly discussed in the local section. Due to the small number of articles, no spatial focus can be determined. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            The articles published in the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em>, explicitly using of the search term cultural tourism mainly refer to the distribution area of the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em>. The spatial focus is on the city of St. Gallen. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Topics of the articles </section>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <strong>Creative industries </strong> 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            Apart from reports on the above-mentioned study by the University of St. Gallen of 2011 on the creative industries in the Lake Constance district, there were hardly any supra-regional topics in the reporting examined. Instead, the local sections discussed relevant developments of the sector.  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            In the recent media discourse of the <em>Südkurier</em>, especially because of the publication of a study commissioned by the cities of Constance and Kreuzlingen in 2015, these included demands for the reconstruction of the Constance Cultural Office, which was dissolved in 2007 and replaced by the Cultural Bureau. With regard to the local development of creative industries, the study raises the question of where and how - also considering the lack of space in Constance - creative quarters can be developed, including gastronomy. The availability of commercial space and the consideration of creative industry enterprises in land use planning are also mentioned in the media, alongside a fast internet connection as a prerequisite for the regional development of this economic sector. Since 2016, the discourse has also been influenced by discussions about the cultural budget and the cultural services of the city of Constance. Regarding political panel discussions, politicians such as the Mayor of Culture, Andreas Osner, have rejected any cutbacks in the cultural budget of the City of Constance and have referred to the argument that culture is an important location factor for all economic sectors. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            In the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em>, the Creative Industries Fair in Friedrichshafen, which took place in the distribution area of the paper, was the most frequent topic in the media discourse around creative industries. A special role in the media discourse was also played by the two actors <em>Stadt</em> Trossingen and <em>IHK </em>Schwarzwald-Baar-Heuberg, which are both committed to promoting creative industries in Trossingen. Other venues in 2011 with use of creative industries was the <em>Kulturgut Ittenbeuren</em>, which is used for conferences, workplaces or as a theatre venue, and the Competence Park in Friedrichshafen. In addition, there were reports about new jobs for creative people in an office complex in Ravensburg, which is under construction until 2017, and, in 2016 and 2017, the use of <em>Ulm's Wilhelmsburg</em> (castle) as a "culture, peace or knowledge castle" in 2016 and 2017.  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            In the <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em>, the recent media discourse on creative industries is characterized by reports on co-working spaces and individual funding initiatives. These include in particular, <em>Campus V</em> in Dornbirn, the Art Design Fair in Feldkirch, as well as the creative industry consultancy firm <em>C hoch 3</em> and the network <em>Zukunftsorte</em>. In 2013 and 2014 there were also isolated reports on the general situation of the creative industries in Vorarlberg. On the occasion of an increase in the budget for the creative industries in 2014, Minister of Economic Affairs, Reinhold Mitterlehner, emphasized that the creative industries are an increasingly important success factor for Austria as a location, as they open up new market and growth opportunities. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            In the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em>, the economic potential of culture was the subject of a UNESCO report on creative industries, presented by the UNO cultural organization and the international umbrella organization of copyright collectives in 2015. Recent reports on the creative industries in the <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em> also focus on the establishment and expansion of local co-working spaces, creative clusters and temporary uses. One of these is the <em>Lattich</em> freight station in St. Gallen, which offers a temporary work spaces for the local creative industries in a temporary quarter built from mobile containers. The first coworking space "Coworking Frauenfeld" in Frauenfeld was also mentioned, which opened in 2016 and offers up to 20 flexible workstations. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            <strong>Cultural Tourism </strong> 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            The coverage of cultural tourism in the examined media focuses, at large, on the cultural tourism services at the tourism destinations in the Lake Constance region. Frequently, the cultural tourism potential of the respective destinations is made the subject of discussion. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            In various statements by politicians, tourism associations and the management of various cultural institutions, cultural tourism in the <em>Südkurier</em> is considered to be very important for regional development. Cultural tourism is discussed as an opportunity for regional cultural preservation and is perceived as a potential unique selling point. Critical voices have been raised in the Lake Constance region, especially in Constance, calling for an expansion of the cultural tourism services. The <em>Südkurier </em>also reported on concrete strategic concepts and projects for the support of regional cultural tourism. The Hochrhein region stands out with their tourism strategy concept 2020 of the Waldshut district, which focuses on topics such as health tourism, bike tourism as well as city and cultural tourism. A recurring theme is also the cultural tourism development of the Via Habsburg, a European cultural route, the geographical extent of which is based on the historic Habsburg estates. As a venue for events with cultural tourism potential, the region's castles, such as <em>Schloss Salem</em>, <em>Schloss Freudental</em> and <em>Schloss Bonndorf</em>, are particularly of mention. Their management intends to target cultural tourists. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            The media discourse on cultural tourism in the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> is characterized by reports on projects, especially those of Upper Swabian communities, to expand local cultural tourism. In the region of Upper Swabia, the marketing of the <em>Schwäbische Barockstraße</em> plays a role, which is intended to boost regional cultural tourism and is taken up several times in the paper. In 2014, the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> reported that the municipality of Bad Buchau, which is supported by the EU <em>Leader</em> program, will continue to focus on the preservation of the cultural and natural landscapes as the basis for soft tourism during the new funding period. In 2015, the <em>Schwäbische Zeitung</em> also wrote about an increase in the number of overnight stays in Bregenz and an increase in the number of visitors to the Salem monastery and castle complex. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            Both <em>Schloss Salem</em> and <em>Bregenz Tourismus &amp;amp; Stadtmarketing GmbH</em> plan to focus more on cultural tourists. Other projects and events that received media attention in the context of cultural tourism were the new concept for the Mesmer House in Meersburg in 2014, the reopening of the Ravensburg Art Museum in 2012, the opening of the season in <em>Schloss Achberg</em> in 2012 and Meersburg's membership of the South German “Half-Timbered Houses Route” in 2007. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            In the reports of the <em>Vorarlberger Nachrichten</em> on the subject of cultural tourism, it is apparent that the tourism strategy of Vorarlberg is positively evaluated by their professional audience. Industry voices are also optimistic on the 2013 Tourism Conference in Bregenz. To further exploit the growth potential, there is also the idea to significantly promote cultural tourism. Bregenz with the Bregenz Festival, the <em>Schubertiade</em> and architecture tourists is a very good example of how many tourists come for culture. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            The <em>St. Galler Tagblatt</em> reports on St. Gallen's participation in the "Unesco Plus" project, especially between 2008 and 2010. Together with the Abbey District, the aim was to raise awareness about special cultural services in the city of St. Gallen. In 2012, the marketing of textile culture in Eastern Switzerland for individual tourism was also a topic. To revive the region’s past, the association "Textilland Ostschweiz" had commissioned textile companies to furnish hotel rooms with their fabric creations. In 2016, due to a prestigious building extension to the art museum in Chur, the theme a supposedly emerging competition between art museums in Eastern Switzerland (Chur and St. Gallen). In 2017, the significance of cultural tourism for Switzerland was also addressed because of an exhibition by the <em>Fotostiftung Schweiz</em> in Winterthur. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. Discussion </section>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            The investigation of the media discourses on the topics of creative industries and cultural tourism has shown that both industries play a rather subordinate role in the reporting of the examined regional media. Creative industries show increased reporting only in the art market segment, which is due to their offering structure. Compared to other producing industries, comparatively few articles on creative industries are being published (see Table 2). No clear trends can be identified over time. The main sources of inspiration are local events, which are irregularly reported on.  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="53">
            The discourse on cultural tourism also shows clear deficits in comparison with other forms of tourism (see Table 3). In particular, reporting in areas close to the border (Singen, Constance, St. Gallen, Bregenz) focuses on Swiss shopping and health tourism at large.  When it comes to media impact, this kind of tourism is significantly more effective than cultural tourism, due to the infrastructural burden on residents. At least on the German side, there is also more articles on bike tourism. This suggests that cultural tourism as a topic has little media appeal and the potential of cultural attractions for tourism seems to be underestimated.  
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="54">
            The spatial focus of the articles tends to focus on the larger cities in the respective distribution areas of the examined regional newspapers. For the topic of creative industries these are Constance, Friedrichshafen, Trossingen, Bregenz, Dornbirn, Feldkirch, St. Gallen and Frauenfeld, and for cultural tourism mainly Constance, Bregenz and St. Gallen. In general, no cross-regional reporting on the discourses for the entire Lake Constance region can be identified. In the country-specific fragmentation of reporting lies an opportunity for more cross-border topics concerning cultural tourism and creative industries. Valuable impulses could be provided by charismatic events, such as the <em>Konziljubiläum </em>in Constance or supra-regional creative-economic cooperation between companies. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="55">
            The subordinate medial importance of cultural tourism and creative industries in the examined media of the Lake Constance region does not correspond with their economic potential. Considering the demographic change, which, with the growth of the 50+ target group in regional tourism, will also bring about a further shift towards cultural topics, from a long term perspective, a gradual expansion of cultural tourism services appears to be of economic relevance. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="56">
            In the reporting of all the examined media, the topics of creative industries and cultural tourism are usually not connected. Indirectly, however, the topics constantly cross through the connecting element of culture. The regional cultural offer is a decisive location factor for both creative industries and cultural tourism. For cultural tourism it is the basis for the development of cultural tourism products and services, and the cultural sector provides creative industries with commissions. Nevertheless, other sub-sectors of creative industries, such as the architectural, performing arts or design market, also offer opportunities for cultural tourism. Cooperation between the two sectors, by creating creative tourism offers, could support creative industries and promote cultural tourism. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="57">
            A limitation of the study is that the search for articles the compilation of the analyzed text corpus by using specific key words cannot cover the complete creative industries/cultural tourism discourse of the individual regional newspapers. This is especially true for the discourse on cultural tourism, but also to a lesser extent for the discourse on creative industries, as both topics are often dealt with indirectly in the regional press without using the specific key words. Due to the fact that articles of different online subscription formats are used as data sources, it should be noted that the selection criteria for the compilation of this sample is not completely transparent and may differ depending on the individual editorial offices. In addition, the sole focus on the print sector means that the overall discourse is only dealt with in excerpts, as social media, film or radio were not included. Since for some search terms and regional newspapers only a random sample was taken and no full survey was conducted, quantitative variables such as the intensity of reporting can only be interpreted to a limited extent. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion </section>
        <paragraphe num="58">
            The media discourse analysis on the reporting of four major local newspapers in the Lake Constance region has shown that there is currently no lively media discourse on the topics of creative industries and cultural tourism. There are relatively little reports on the keywords creative industries and cultural tourism. Apart from event-related reporting, the topic of creative industries is hardly present. Bregenz is the only city in the Lake Constance region that explicitly names creative industries as a competent economic sector. Cultural tourism also plays a subordinate role in regional reporting, although the image of the Lake Constance region is strongly influenced by tourism. This is in inverse proportion to its relevance, as cultural tourism holds the potential for extending the season or for year-round tourism, independent of weather conditions. Possible synergies between creative industries and cultural tourism are not discussed in the examined media. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="59">
            To activate unused opportunities at the tourism destinations of the Lake Constance region, a supra-regional visibility of creative industries would have to be established and the cooperation with local cultural tourism actors would have to be stimulated. In order to be able to make targeted implications for the region, in-depth research is required into the causes and reasons for the under-representation of both sectors in the media, as well as an analysis of different stakeholders in the Lake Constance region.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Boggs, J. (2009), «Cultural Industries and the Creative Economy», Geography Compass, Vol. 3, n°4, pp. 1483–1498.  </reference>
        <reference>Böing, J. (2016), Räumliche Identität und Kultur: Ausformungen und Nutzungspotentiale am Beispiel der Stadt Hagen, Springer VS, Wiesbaden. </reference>
        <reference>Bundesministerium für Wirtschaft und Technologie (BMWi) (2014), Monitoring zu ausgewählten wirtschaftlichen Eckdaten der Kultur- und Kreativwirtschaft 2012, Berlin. </reference>
        <reference>Colomb, C. (2012), «Pushing the Urban Frontier: Temporary Uses of Space, City Marketing, and the Creative City Discourse in 2000S Berlin», Journal of Urban Affairs, Vol. 34, n°2, pp. 131–152.  </reference>
        <reference>Couret, C. (2012), «Barcelona Creative Tourism», Journal of Tourism Consumption and Practice, Vol. 4, n°2, pp. 132-134. </reference>
        <reference>Creative Tourism Network (2014), «What do we mean by creative tourism», URL: creativetourismnetwork.org/about/ [last accessed 15.02.2020]. </reference>
        <reference>de Peuter, G. (2011), «Creative Economy and Labor Precarity: A Contested Convergence», Journal of Communication Inquiry, Vol. 35, n°4, pp. 417–425. </reference>
        <reference>Evans, G. (2009), «Creative Cities, Creative Spaces and Urban Policy», Urban Studies, Vol. 46, n°5&amp;6, pp. 1003–1040. </reference>
        <reference>Florida, R. (2002), The Rise of the Creative Class: And How It’s Transforming Work, Leisure, Community and Everyday Life, Basic Books, New York.  </reference>
        <reference>Friebe, H. und Lobo, S. (2008), Wir nennen es Arbeit. Die digitale Bohèhme oder Intelligentes Leben jenseits der Festanstellung, Heyne, München. </reference>
        <reference>Friebe, H. und Ramge, T. (2008), Marke Eigenbau. Der Aufstand der Massen gegen die Massenproduktion, Frankfurt/New York. </reference>
        <reference>Früh, W. (2015), Inhaltsanalyse: Theorie und Praxis, utb, Konstanz. </reference>
        <reference>Geppert, K. und Mundelius, M. (2007), «Berlin als Standort der Kreativwirtschaft immer bedeutender», DIW Wochenbericht Vol. 74, n°31, pp. 485-491. </reference>
        <reference>Goehler, A. (2006), Verflüssigungen. Wege und Umwege vom Sozialstaat zur Kulturgesellschaft, Frankfurt/New York, Campus. </reference>
        <reference>Hassemer, K. (2010), Identität und Image des Wirtschaftsstandorts Bodensee, Hochschule für Technik, Wirtschaft und Gestaltung Konstanz. </reference>
        <reference>Hepperle, S. (2017), «Schlüssel zum Erfolg. Kulturtourismus als Besuchermagnet für ländliche Räume», Der Landkreis, Vol. 87, n°8-9, pp. 422–423. </reference>
        <reference>Keppler, A. (2005), «Medien und soziale Wirklichkeit», in Jäckel M. (Hrsg.), Mediensoziologie. Grundfragen und Forschungsfelder, Springer VS, Wiesbaden, pp. 91–106. </reference>
        <reference>Landry, C. (2008), The creative city: a toolkit for urban innovators, Routledge, London.  </reference>
        <reference>Lange, B., von Streit, A. und Hesse, M. (2011), Kultur- und Kreativwirtschaft in Stadt und Region. Voraussetzungen, Handlungsstrategien und Governance, Selbstverlag, Bonn. </reference>
        <reference>Leuschen, L. und Thimm, T. (2019a), Die touristische Vermarktung der Destination Bodensee: Landschaftsstereotype und Potentiale kreativwirtschaftlicher Narrative. Working paper, Hochschule für Technik, Wirtschaft und Gestaltung, Konstanz. </reference>
        <reference>Leuschen, L. und Thimm, T. (2019b), «Kulturtourismus und Kreativwirtschaft: Synergien und Potenziale», Schiller J., Weckerle C. und Grand S. (Hrsg.), 2019, Kreativwirtschaft Bodenseeregion. Wertschöpfung zwischen Kultur, Wirtschaft und Technologie, Zürich, Zürcher Hochschule der Künste, pp. 52–60. </reference>
        <reference>Liu, Y.-D. (2012), «Cultural Events and Cultural Tourism Development: Lessons from the European Capitals of Culture», European Planning Studies, Vol.22, n°3, pp. 498–514. </reference>
        <reference>MacDonald, R. and Jolliffe, L. (2003), «Cultural Rural Tourism. Evidence from Canada»., Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 30, n°2, pp. 307–322. </reference>
        <reference>Markusen, A., Wassall, G. H., DeNatale, D. und Cohen, R. (2008), «Defining the Creative Economy: Industry and Occupational Approaches», Economic Development Quarterly, Vol. 22, n°1, pp. 24-45. </reference>
        <reference>McRobbie, A. (2011), «Re-Thinking Creative Economy as Radical Social Enterprise», Variant, n°41, pp. 32-33. </reference>
        <reference>Merten, K. (1995), Inhaltsanalyse: Einführung in Theorie, Methode und Praxis, Springer VS, Wiesbaden. </reference>
        <reference>Nadotti, L. and Vannoni, V. (2019), «Cultural and event tourism: an interpretative key for impact assessment», Eastern Journal of European Studies, Vol. 10, n°1, pp. 115-131. </reference>
        <reference>Njovo, M. and Makacha, C. (2018), «Cultural capital, digital capital and stakeholder partnerships: a holy trinity for a sustainable cultural tourism trajectory», African Journal of Hospitality, Tourism and Leisure, vol. 7, n°5, pp. 1-13.</reference>
        <reference>OECD, 2014, Tourism and the Creative Economy.  </reference>
        <reference>Pratt, A.C. and Hutton, T.A. (2013), «Reconceptualising the relationship between the creative economy and the city: Learning from the financial crisis», Cities, n°33, pp. 86-95. </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. and Bartos, P. (2014), «Creative Economy and Tourism: Developing effective cooperation», Report on a workshop organised in the context of the OECD Conference on Tourism and the Creative Economy, Linz, September 2014. </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. and Raymond, C. (2000), «Creative Tourism», ATLAS News, n°23, pp. 16–20. </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. (2003), «What is Cultural Tourism?», in van Maaren A. (Hrsg.), Erfgoed voor Toerisme, Weesp, Nationaal Contact Monumenten, pp. 1-15. </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. (2011), «Creativity and tourism», Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 38, n°4, pp. 1225–1253.  </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. (2012), «Tourism, Creativity and Creative Industries», Paper presented at the conference Creativity and Creative Industries in Challenging Times, NHTV Breda, November 2012. </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. (2018), «Panorama of Creative Tourism Around the World (Panorama do turismo criativo no mundo)», Paper presented at the Seminário Internacional de Turismo Criativo, Cais do Sertão, Recife, Brazil, Dezember 2018.  </reference>
        <reference>Richards, G., Wisansing, J. J. und Paschinger, E. (2018), Creating Creative Tourism Toolkit, Bookplus Publishing, Bangkog. </reference>
        <reference>Rössler, P. (2017), Inhaltsanalyse, utb basics, Konstanz. </reference>
        <reference>Santana Talavera, A. (2003), «Turismo Cultural, Culturas Turísticas», Horizontes Antropológicos, n°20, pp. 37–50. </reference>
        <reference>Scherer, R., Schwanke, K. &amp; Gutjahr, M. (2011), Die Kreativwirtschaft im Bodenseekreis : Eine Potenzialanalyse, St. Gallen.</reference>
        <reference>Schiller, J., Weckerle, C. und Grand, S., (Hrsg.) (2019), Kreativwirtschaft Bodenseeregion. Wertschöpfung zwischen Kultur, Wirtschaft und Technologie, Zürich, Zürcher Hochschule der Künste. </reference>
        <reference>Stern, M. J. and Seifert, S.C. (2008), «From Creative Economy to Creative Society», Culture and Community Revitalization: A Collaboration, n°6, URL: http://repository.upenn.edu/ siap_revitalization/6, [last accessed 15.02.2020]. </reference>
        <reference>Tatarusanu, M. und Iatu, C. (2018), «The interpretation of the cultural heritage for tourism in the era of globalisation», Pratical Application of Science, Vol. 4, n°16, pp. 21-25. </reference>
        <reference>Thimm, T. (2014), «The Flamenco Factor in Destination Marketing: Interdependencies of Creative Industries and Tourism — the Case of Seville», Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism Marketing, Vol. 31, n°5, pp. 576–588.  </reference>
        <reference>Waitt, G. and Gibson, C. (2009), «Creative Small Cities: Rethinking the Creative Economy in Place», Urban Studies, Vol. 46, n°5&amp;6, pp. 1223–1246. </reference>
        <reference>Zimmermann, O., Schulz, G. und Ernst, S. (2009), Zukunft Kulturwirtschaft, Essen, Klartext Verlag. </reference>
    </bibliographie>
</article>