<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_LB_3-98_Iy_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4767" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.4767</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>16</numero>
        <annee>2019</annee>
    </meta>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Boukhris" prenom="Linda">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_LB_33-94_Le_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1212" lang="fr">L’imaginaire touristique à l’épreuve du Costa Rica : entre « voir » et « faire » le territoire</publication>
                <publication id="fr_LBEP_21-58_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4097" lang="fr">Le tourisme à l’épreuve des paradigmes post et décoloniaux</publication>
            </oeuvres>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Interview with Nelson Graburn, Professor of Anthropology at the University of California, Berkeley</titre>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Nelson Graburn is Professor Emeritus of Anthropology at the University of California, Berkeley. He is also Curator at the Hearst Museum of Anthropology (UC, Berkley) and Co-Chair of the Tourism Studies Working Group (www.tourismstudies.org). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From his initial research on Inuit tourism in the Eastern Canadian Arctic, to his investigation of Japanese tourist practices, and more recently his research on minority tourism scholars especially in China, the purpose of this discussion was to explore some of his lifetime of questioning on indigeneity, alterities and hegemonies in tourism research. In particular, I wanted to ask Nelson Graburn to reflect upon the vast changes in the field of anthropology of tourism (the epistemologies, the methods, the geographies) he has witnessed (and driven) over the course of his career, interacting with scholars from different backgrounds and different parts of the world. I invited him to discuss some of the topics of this </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Via</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> special issue on postcolonial and decolonial paradigms.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">I first met Nelson Graburn in 2011 during a conference on “Tourism Imaginaries” that he organized at UC Berkeley, and we have been following each other’s research projects for the past years. </span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Bunten, A., Graburn, N. (eds.), 2018, Cultural Tourism Movements: New Articulations of Indigenous Identity, University of Toronto Press, 268 p.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., 1969, “Art and Acculturative Processes” in the International Social Science Journal for UNESCO, XXI, 3, pp. 457-468.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N. (ed.), 1976, Ethnic and Tourist Arts: Cultural Expressions from the Fourth World, University of California Press, 444 p.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., 1983, To Pray, Pay and Play: the Cultural Structure of Japanese Domestic Tourism, Centre des Hautes Etudes Touristiques, 89 p. </reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., 1999, “Ethnic and Tourist Arts Revisited” in Phillips R. B., Steiner C. B. (eds.), Unpacking Culture: Art and Commodity in Colonial and Postcolonial Worlds, University of California Press, pp. 335-353.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., 2008, “Multiculturalism, museums, and tourism in Japan” in Graburn N., Ertl J., Tierney K. R. (eds.), Multiculturalism in the New Japan. Crossing the Boundaries Within, Berghahn Books, New York-Oxford, pp. 218-239.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., 2018, “Anthropology, Alterity and Indigenous Peoples in Tourism”, Quai Branly Conference “Anthropology and Tourism”.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., 2019, “Inside and outside the Anglophone snake; tourism research, alterities &amp; hegemonies” in Salazar N., Graburn N., Zhu Y. (eds.), Conceptual histories of “tourism”: A transcultural dialogue, Conference Proceedings 18Th IUAES World Congress, pp. 41–51.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn, N., Shioji, Y., 2020, “Shuzo Ishimori: a pioneer of tourism studies in Japan”, Anatolia, An International Journal of Tourism and Hospitality Research, vol. 31, N° 1, pp. 159-166.</reference>
        <reference>Igloliorte, H. (ed.), 2017, SakKijâjuk: Art and Craft from Nunatsiavut. Fredericton, NB: Goose Lane Editions, and St. John’s: The Rooms.</reference>
        <reference>Lips, J., 1937, The Savage Hits Back or the White Man Through Native Eyes. Lovat Dickson Limited, 254 p.</reference>
        <reference>Nash, D., 1977, “Tourism as a form of imperialism” in Smith V. L. (ed.), Hosts and guests: the anthropology of tourism. University of Pennsylvania Press, p. 33-47</reference>
        <reference>Phillips, R. B., Steiner, C. B. (eds.), 1999, Unpacking Culture: Art and Commodity in Colonial and Postcolonial Worlds, University of California Press, 435 p.</reference>
        <reference>Salazar, N., Graburn, N., Zhun, Y. (eds.), 2019, Conceptual histories of “tourism”: A transcultural dialogue, Conference Proceedings 18Th IUAES World Congress, https://lirias.kuleuven.be</reference>
        <reference>Sarr, F., Savoy, B., 2018, The Restitution of African Cultural Heritage. Toward a New Relational Ethics, http://restitutionreport2018.com/ </reference>
        <reference>Shioji, Y., 2014, “Who Maintains “Old England”? - Tourism and Migration in the English Countryside”, Via, 6.</reference>
        <reference>Stoler, A., 2016, Duress. Imperial Durabilities in Our Times, Duke University Press, 448 p.</reference>
        <reference>Zhu, Y., Jin, L., Graburn, N., 2017, “Domesticating Chinese Anthropology of Tourism”, in special issue “Global Anthropologies of Tourism”, Dominguez V., Salazar N., (eds.), American Anthropologist, vol. 119, N° 4, pp. 730-735.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
</article>