<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_MPLL_106-79_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/459" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.459</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>8</numero>
        <annee>2015</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <traduction lang="ca" source="457">Estratègies de promoció gastronòmica associades al turisme en arees geograficament marginades</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="del Pilar Leal Londoño" prenom="Maria">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="es_MPLL_92-94_Es_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/445" lang="es">Estrategias de promoción gastronómica asociadas al turismo en áreas geográficamente marginadas</publication>
                <publication id="fr_MPLL_94-105_Ss_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/451" lang="fr">Stratégies de promotion gastronomique associées au tourisme dans des zones géographiquement marginalisées</publication>
                <publication id="ca_MPLL_93-93_Es_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/457" lang="ca">Estratègies de promoció gastronòmica associades al turisme en arees geograficament marginades</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                PhD. in Geography, spatial planning, and environmental management, University of Barcelona Ostelea School of Tourism &amp; Hospitality. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Related Strategies to Promote Gastronomy in Geographically Disadvantaged Areas </titre>
    <sousTitre>A comparative analysis of Catalonia and Scotland</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        The present article analyzes State and local level tourism-related strategies to promote traditional cuisine in two geographically disadvantaged areas : two districts in the Catalonian Pyrenees, and two Scottish islands. The article is developed on the basis of a literature review and seven interviews given to a variety of stakeholders involved in the strategies. The results are analyzed following the “four orders” of culinary tourism established by Hjalager (2002). The findings reveal that two, to all appearances, very different territories have some points in common in their strategies to promote their products and, ultimately, attract tourists and visitors through their food resources.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            The major consequences of consuming food at tourist destinations have recently been recognized and discussed (Mak et al, 2012). Food consumption, especially when eating out, is a pleasant sensory experience that, at a destination, is a “pull factor” and a marketing and merchandising tool that should not be underestimated (Kivala, 2006). Cuisine is an essential part of tourist trips (Bessière, 1998) if it is borne in mind that food represents approximately one third of all expenditure made by tourists (Hall and Sharples, 2003 ; Telfer and Wall, 1996) ; as such, culinary tourism can be stated to be a growing sector in today’s global tourism market (Antonioli Corigliano, 2002).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            For many tourists, trying the food and drink is one of their main reasons for visiting new destinations (Cohen and Avieli, 2004 ; Hall and Mitchell, 2001 ; Hall and Sharples, 2003 ; Hjalager and Richards, 2002). As Bessière (1998) states, a country’s cuisine is an expression of its culture, local food markets are recognized as an important part of a region’s cultural and tourism experience, and local identity can be reinforced by the products that are sold there. The relationship between local food production and tourism has therefore gained increasing recognition in the tourism sector (Hjalager and Richards, 2002) and impacts the supply of local food significantly (Mak et al, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            In addition, several authors (Bessière, 1998 ; Hall and Sharples, 2003 ; Hjalager and Richards, 2002) have discussed culinary links as an element of local tourism development, because food and cuisine act as the meeting point of production, processing, storage, transport, cooking and preparation (Antonioli Corigliano, 2002), and this creates complex relationships in a territory that range from food production to the sale of products.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            It is important to highlight the relationship between culinary tourism and local and regional development, especially in geographically disadvantaged areas where there is little scope for product diversification ; nonetheless, local development should not be seen only in economic terms. It has to be looked at from the cultural, social and even ecological perspectives (Rodríguez, 1998). These aspects can be applied to cuisine if cuisine is understood to also be the study of the relationship between culture and diet (see Boniface, 2003 ; Espeteix, 2007 ; Petrini, 2007 ; Scarpato, 2002) and not only represent one of a destination’s various economic activities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            Food can also play a major role in substantially differentiating between tourist destinations ; Okumus et al. (2007 :253) refer to how “cooking” is commercialized by nationality (Chinese, French, Italian, Turkish, Mexican, etc). The opportunity exists to create a positive association between a style of cuisine and a tourism destination. Despite the fact that there is extensive literature on the promotion of tourist destinations, there are few studies on the relationship between the promotion of tourism and food.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            Understanding culinary tourism and, within culinary tourism, the role played by the various stakeholders involved and the strategies devised to promote it, should contribute not only to strategies to promote food being applied more effectively, but also to local development strategies in territories that see in their food products a means of improving their socioeconomic status ; as Byrd et al. (2009), citing Oliveira (2003), point out, for tourism to be developed -and to be developed successfully- actions should be planned and managed in a responsible manner.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            The main objective of the present article is an examination of State and local level tourism-related strategies to promote traditional cuisine in areas with major geographical peculiarities. These differences can be strengths or weaknesses for attracting visitors and tourists. To achieve this objective, a literature review is carried out and seven people involved in different food-related activities are interviewed in the two study areas ; these include food producers, restaurateurs, and the (public and private) stakeholders involved who promote culinary tourism in the areas.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            The case study is conducted in two areas in Catalonia and Scotland. Two areas of the Pyrenees Mountains were chosen for the Catalonian case, and two island regions for the Scottish case. The study incorporates the theoretical and empirical elements developed by Hjalager (2002) in the second chapter of the book “Tourism and Gastronomy”, edited by Hjalager and Richards 10 years ago, in which the author analyzed the opportunities for developing culinary tourism in a variety of areas according to “four orders”. This book was one of the first European publications devoted to addressing and analyzing culinary tourism as a new mode of tourism. The choice of a comparative analysis contributes to enriching the territorial analyses undertaken in the field to date (Hjalager and Corigliano ; 2002 ; Mitchel and Sharples ; 2003 ; Okumus et al, 2007) with a knowledge and experimental base.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            The comparative analysis is justified in so far as it is an attempt to explain how two, so apparently different bio-geographic, social and economic contexts have points in common, not only with respect to the quality of the agrifood products that manage to differentiate them and position them to compete with others, but also in the strategies developed to promote their agrifood products through tourist activity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            Catalonia and Scotland are both undergoing what could be called a “culinary revolution”, which is expressed in the way that their cuisine and agrifood products have been recognized internationally through restaurants awarded Michelin stars and the presence in the media of chefs, such as Ferràn Adrià in Catalonia and Tom Kitchin in Scotland.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            Both these regions, with their sea and mountains, reflect a diversity and uniqueness of their products that is also found in their culinary traditions, imbued with a feeling of identity and of their local roots. Bearing all this in mind, and returning to Briden and Munro (2000), a comparative analysis of the two territories will enable less tangible factors to be focused on that can be tested in inter-regional and international scale comparisons.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Methodology</section>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            The analysis of the case studies enables a longitudinal analysis to be conducted of both the ”process and the context” surrounding the various actions and meanings that arise and are constructed within the specific social or organizational contexts (Hartley, 1994 : 212). Case study methods have designed a number of useful procedures in a variety of contexts (Xiao and Smith, 2006).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            The methodological focus for case studies applies triangulation as a valid procedure for qualitative research, as it represents a search for convergence between multiple information sources ; triangulation is a systematic classification process that uses data to find common themes through the elimination of overlying areas. In addition, Alain (1999) maintains that with its combination of data sources, methods and theories, triangulation opens up the way to richer and potentially more valid interpretations.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            Apart from the above-mentioned culinary tourism-related literature review and the different conceptions that exist around this recent tourism phenomenon, information is added that has been obtained from seven semi-structured interviews given to private and public stakeholders (four in the Pyrenees area, and three in Scotland). Said interviewees are responsible for managing the territory and promoting this new type of tourism in these areas ; the main objective of the interviews is to ascertain how the strategies are implemented and how other institutions on different levels are involved and linked to these strategies. Semi-structured interviews enable issues to be analyzed in greater depth (Robson, 1993).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            As part of the triangulation process, on the basis of the two-dimensional framework to locate the validity types the focuses entailed the use of a variety of data sources (information on the Internet, the culinary press, marketing brochures, food events in the areas under study, the literature review, and direct observation). The information was compiled and subsequently analyzed according to the “four orders” established by Hjalager (2002) that contribute to adding value to culinary tourism, and therefore, according to the author, generate tourism products in many cases.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            The first order focuses on places that enable the visitor to enjoy the food, such as festivals and campaigns, among other things.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            The second order is devoted to fostering a better understanding of food among visitors, such as the creation and promotion of Quality Seals and the standardization of a product in a region.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            The third order refers to experimentation via food packages and cookery schools.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            The fourth involves knowledge-sharing about food and diet in research centers.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            The author’s focus is being taken up once more on the tenth anniversary of the publication of one of her most cited<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a> books with the greatest impact on culinary tourism ; linking these concepts will therefore enable an assessment to be made of whether these territories can really commit to this new mode of tourism and how they are tackling it at the current time. Finally, the information is systematized throughout the article in the form of tables that seek to respond to the characteristics and the opportunities proposed for European food products in geographically disadvantaged areas, both in Scotland and in Catalonia.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">The territorial context of the areas under study</section>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            Tourism is a major sector of the economy in both Catalonia and in Scotland. According to the Scottish government’s statistics department (2012), tourism is one of the largest business sectors in Scotland, permeating both large cities and rural areas that, in many cases, depend on the activity for the creation of jobs and infrastructure. Its economic importance is also evident in the case of Catalonia, as the tourist sector accounts for 12 % of the region’s GDP and employs around 400,000 people (IDESCAT, 2012). What is more, in 2011 Catalonia became the main tourist destination in all Spain. Table 1 presents some data to compare the tourism dynamics in Catalonia and Scotland.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            As can be seen in Table 1, there is a greater amount of tourist activity in Catalonia than in Scotland, which can be attributed to the historical presence of “sun and sand” tourism. However, in 2011 both territories experienced a rise in their tourism figures according to the data provided by the two regions’ statistics agencies. García Pascual (2009) states that tourism is unevenly distributed in Catalonia, with greater concentrations along the coastal strip. As such, culinary tourism could have a greater significance for dynamizing tourism in the mountain areas of Catalonia and, broadly-speaking, in geographically disadvantaged areas in Scotland, too.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            In other respects, Scottish and Catalonian culinary products are recognized all the world over. Restaurants that have been awarded Michelin stars<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a> attest to this both in Scotland and in Catalonia. At the current time (2012), Catalonia has two restaurants that have been awarded the maximum three Michelin stars, while Scotland has three.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            Although the number of stars might not be an absolute benchmark for categorizing international prestige, according to Surlemont and Johnson (2005) it does contribute to influencing consumer choice and the imaginary of prestige cooking. This therefore enables these two territories to be recognized and positioned on the international culinary stage.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            Bearing in mind the above, the primary reason for choosing the two areas of study is the similarity between the two at the current time in the way that they promote their dishes and agrifood products. The study by Boyne et al., (2002) for Scotland was a first approach to knowledge of tourism-linked culinary activity there. For Catalonia, meanwhile, references to Catalonian cuisine and its tourism-related traditions were of interest to Ravenscroft and Van Westering (2002).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            This interest of the academic literature in the two regions suggests proof of what could be called “regional culinary activity”, and this is reflected in the fact that a variety of strategies have been put in motion in both Scotland and Catalonia in which cuisine is used as a resource and a tourism product for promoting destinations.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            In addition, the dishes and products in these two regions are firmly rooted in the traditions and ways of savoir faire. Both areas are witnessing a reappraisal of their dishes and products, including Haggis (Scotland) and Calçots (Catalonia), as popular traditional products in which the identity of the local people can be perceived. Identity is, therefore, another aspect which links Scotland and Catalonia, and to this can be added the geographic conditions. Both regions possess areas of mountain and an area of coast. These geographic features are expressed in their products and dishes, which mirror the uniqueness and influence of the sea and the mountains.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            The subsections below explain both the geographic aspects and other aspects related to the two regions’ tourism dynamics. An explanation is also given as to why two mountain areas were chosen for the case of Catalonia and two for the case of Scotland. However, it is also worth mentioning that the mountain areas were chosen with the aim of determining whether areas that usually do not benefit from tourist activities, which are usually concentrated in other geographical environments, might reap benefits from culinary tourism-related activities as a an option for promoting the areas.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            Catalonia
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            Catalonia is in the very northeastern part of the Iberian Peninsula and has a surface area of 31,932 Km2. It stretches from the Pyrenees to the Mediterranean Sea, varying from sea level to the 3,000+ m peaks of the Pyrenees, which explains the climate and pronounced biogeographic differences in the region (López Palomeque et al., 2002).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            Tourist activity is very important for the economy of the area ; in 2011 Catalonia was the leading destination by volume of incoming international flights, 13.2 million tourists, and the area that generated the highest volume of foreign expenditure in all Spain, equating to a quarter of the amount for the State as a whole. Expenditure by foreign tourists in restaurants in Catalonia for 2010 equated to 14.8 % of their budgets (IETE, 2010<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a>. On the political and administrative level, Catalonia is divided into “comarcas” (districts), which correspond to the pre-municipal scale.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            The “comarcas” under study 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            The following two “comarcas” were selected with the intention of focusing on two areas of Catalonia that could be classified as “disadvantaged” in geographic terms due to their poor accessibility and because they do not usually benefit from the Catalonia’s greater tourist activity, which is concentrated along the coastal strip : Alt Urgell and Ripollès. Both are Pyrenean mountain districts with Alt Urgell being the larger with a surface area of 1,446 Km2, while the surface area of Ripollès is 957Km2. Traditional economic activity in Alt Urgell has revolved around livestock farming, agriculture and forestry ; however, these activities have faded into the background with the appearance of other industries, such as dairy products, the metal industry, building materials and, above all, tourism<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            In other respects, and by way of a contextual framework, industry has always given a strong second line of support to agriculture, livestock farming and forestry in the district of Ripollès ; the textile industry on the banks of the rivers Ter and Freser, and the metal industry have also stood out. However, tourism is also one of the activities with one of the brightest outlooks<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            Scotland
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            According to “Scotland in Brief” (2003), Scotland is located in the north of the island of Great Britain and has a surface area of 78,722 Km2 ; Scotland has 790 islands, and its mainland can be split into three geographic regions : the Highlands, or high mountain areas, the Central Lowlands and the Southern Uplands. The Highlands and the islands comprise over half of Scotland’s total surface area.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            According to “Eat Scotland”, the agrifood products that characterize the nation are essentially based on beef, lamb, dairy products and salmon, which are some of the “star” products at the forefront of Scottish cuisine.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            In other regards, the importance of tourism for the region is quite apparent. According to the Scottish government’s report on tourism, in 2010 there were 16 million overnight stays in Scotland, which was an increase on previous years. And according to Tourism Intelligence Scotland (2010), visitors to Scotland spend around 21 % of their budgets on food and drink, which amounts to around £ 2 million per day in food and drink tourism. In addition, according to the same report, the trend is towards a growing importance of food. Between May 2007 and 2009, sales of products and distributors of Scottish brands in the United Kingdom increased by 21 %, whilst outside the United Kingdom sales increased by 16 % in two years<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            The islands selected
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            Two island territories were selected for the Scottish case that are considered to be geographically disadvantaged due to their difficult access. Both the Isle of Arran on the one hand, and the insular part of Skye and Lochalsh on the other, are islands with mountainous terrain. By way of context, the primary sector (agriculture and forestry) and services dominate the local economies of both, and there is a special dependence on tourism (Bryden and Munro, 2000). For example, based on the official page of the “Taste of Arran” it is estimated that around 90 % of business is in one way or another tourist-related on the Isle of Arran.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            The twoinsular regions are both considered to be “remote rural areas” that have developed effective strategies to contend with the disadvantages of their locations (Bryden and Munro, 2000). The Isle of Skye and Lochalsh have a total surface area of 2,732 Km2, 27 % of which is over 300 meters above sea level<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a>. The Isle of Arran, meanwhile, has a surface area of 432 km2 and the 874 meter-high “Goat Fell” is the dominant feature of its mountains<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            The whisky distillery and ale houses on the Isle of Arran are widely acknowledged and support the local economy. According to Bryden and Munro (2000), there is a wide diversification of activities in the case of Skye and Lochalsh, which is in part due to the historical half-time working day, seasonal economic activities and the nature of the harvests.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Literature Review</section>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            The current scenario for tourist activity is made all the more complex but, at the same time, all the richer and more diverse, by the increase in trends and the quest for experiences, as it allows these activities to be sited in places that had never before been tourist areas. Now, however, they offer natural and cultural conditions or facilities valued by users of new motivations, giving rise to the spatial formation of demand flows and the reshaping of tourist maps on all scales, local, regional and national (Antón Clavè, S., 2005).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            Today, changes in demand firmly targeted at the search for new experiences, together with major changes in mobility and the frequent use of information and communication technologies (ICT), have led to the emergence of “new modes of tourism”. It should therefore come as no surprise that tourist phenomena like culinary tourism should arise, which offers tourists this experience by way of their palates ; this is confirmed by Armesto and Gómez (2006), who state that food, or culinary, tourism is part of this new “experiential tourism” that has come to be embedded in types of postmodern tourism. In post industrial societies food represents more than basic sustenance, and pleasure is ranked above need (Everett, S., 2008).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            Therefore, the promotion of culinary tourism is important for catching tourists’ eyes and said promotion presents a strong relationship between product and territory that is important for marketing the combination of the two ; post modernism has brought with it, especially for the tourist, the interest of post industrial societies in “harking back to the past of their ancestors” in order to experiment with traditional elements that are new for post modern societies (Urry, 1990).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            For the specific case of mountain products, one of the findings of 9 project research on quality mountain-sourced agro-food products is the conclusion that these products certainly do possess specific attributes compared to other products, attributes that come from the method used to produce them and/or the raw material used.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            However, despite the potential of mountain agro-food products and their major organoleptic features, the spatial use of disadvantaged areas for tourist purposes varies and depends on accessibility. Clawson and Knetsch, cited by Shaw and Williams (1994), consider three types of rural recreation area to exist ; there are accessible areas that conform to this use, relatively scarce areas based on the resource but still with inaccessible physical attributes, and intermediate areas between these two types.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            Access does not depend on distance alone, and expressed demand is not the same as latent demand ; in reality, accessibility is socially conditioned. However, these aspects mean that tourist development might be more pronounced in remote areas that are difficult to access, such as the areas of mountain or island territories in this case study (Bessière, 1998).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            Food as a resource and a tourism product
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            Tourist destinations are the sum of all the products offered by a specific, delimited geographic region (Gandara, 2003), and these in turn are formed of resources that are transformed for the creation of tourism products. As such, the conceptual basis for cuisine requires an analysis that links the structural elements of any mode of tourism in such a way that it manages to establish how cuisine presents these elements, because it must be clearly seen to be a form of tourism, meaning that there is a process of experimentation, feeling and becoming acquainted through practice ; apart from this, it must also be recognized as an element of (individual and regional) identity capable of providing a time-honored experience of a place that is, perhaps, more powerful than many other commodities (Everett, 2008).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            However, as Hall and Sharples (2003) argue, it is important to avoid confusion between food tourism and food consumption as part of the travel experience. What for the authors can be identified as food tourism corresponds to what the prime motive for undertaking a journey is. For the present study, the distinction should depend on how food can be a resource associated with other modes of tourism or a tourism product in itself.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            Food as a tourist resource
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="53">
            These days culinary tourism is emerging as one of the most promising segments of the tourist sector (Antonioli Corigliano, 2002). Everything that has been stated above has led to it becoming more and more usual for food-based tourism products to be created as a resource that results in culinary tourism.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="54">
            Authors such as (Cooper, 2008 :117) define the resource as one that is formed by the environment (physical and social). Tourism resources can be classified as scarce (land, capital) and free, such as the climate and culture. Even so, the concept of resource is entirely subjective, relative and functional. What really constitutes a resource for Cooper (2008) depends on the motivations, desires and interests of the consumer and the social, cultural and economic context within which these motivations occur.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="55">
            The link between food and tourism has become a tourism resource for the creation of new products and for reinventing old ones that have come to the end of their lifecycles or that are in the last stage of the “tourist area cycle” developed by Butler (1980), cited by McKercher (2005). In other words, bearing in mind that for McKercher, (2005) destinations are amalgams of products that are grouped together geographically and include tourism products and services, both products and destinations need to be continually refreshed and revitalized. Tourism-linked cuisine can thus be a medium for revitalizing or reinventing tourism products and destinations.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="56">
            Cooking as a tourism product
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="57">
            Cooper and Hall (2008) mention the complexity and multifaceted nature of tourism products and their conception based on the context of exchange. In tourism, this exchange takes place in a destination within the bounds of certain social and political, environmental, technological and economic characteristics.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="58">
            It is also appropriate to say that the relationship between cooking as a tourism product and a tourist destination is synergetic, because the destination provides the foodstuffs, recipes, chefs and cultural aspects that make food an ideal product for consumption by tourists (Fields, 2002 ; Richards, 2002 ; Scarpato, 2002). Food tourism products are delivered to tourists through several distribution channels, such as markets, festivals and restaurants (Smith and Xiao, 2008).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="59">
            New tourism products are important for diversifying destinations, as they drive up sales and boost the use made of the competitive advantage. Cooper and Hall, (2008) put forward the idea of the product as an experience in which suppliers and destinations face the challenge of creating experience-based products ; these experiences are, therefore, personal and memorable, and arouse an emotional response in which tourists enter into a multifaceted relationship with both the actors and the destination that provide them with the experience.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="60">
            Culinary resources and tourism products in mountain areas
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="61">
            Knowledge of a territory’s food resources and tourism products enables or strengthens strategies to promote its cuisine. However, their geographic differences do not lead to different tourism food products despite their having different resources. In the cases of the geographically disadvantaged areas in Catalonia and Scotland the resources and tourism products can be summarized as follows : (see Figure 1)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="62">
            Broadly-speaking, the territories are characterized by their “typical and traditional” cooking, which is distinguished by the resources that they possess. In the Catalonian case, dishes reveal “mountain cooking” based above all on meat products ; however, in the Scottish case, the cooking is based on sea products with special features that come from the territories’ biogeographic conditions.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="63">
            Food resources are used and transformed to develop cuisine-linked tourism products ; these, in turn, shape the culinary tourism strategies designed and implemented by public, private and public-private organizations to promote products, dishes and, in short, tourist destinations.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="64">
            The strategies identified in the two areas under study are set out in detail below.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Culinary strategies</section>
        <paragraphe num="65">
            Using interviews and the information that is compiled, the culinary strategies in the chosen areas are developed hierarchically, starting on the larger scale led by public institutions, to which local and regional level strategies driven by private or mixed public-private organizations in each of the territories are assigned or linked. Primarily, two overarching or State strategies (on the largest scale) can be observed in both cases : in Catalonia the “Club Gastronómico” (2003) and the “Gastroteca” (2006) can be identified ; in Scotland, “Eat Scotland”, which is part of the main institution responsible for promoting tourism in Scotland, namely “Visit Scotland”, and a second strategy called “Taste of Scotland”.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="66">
            Both “Club Gastronómico” and “Eat Scotland” are strategies where businesses pay an annual membership fee ; one of the main benefits that they provide is involvement in the promotion and marketing done through a larger scale institution. The second strategy on the overarching scale to promote culinary products focuses on assembling a directory or website with information that includes both companies that produce the product and places where the product can be purchased, and information on where the product can be sampled. This can be seen to be the “Gastroteca”, in the Catalonian case, and “Taste of Scotland”. As Horng and Tsai, (2010), state, this is an acknowledgement of the Internet’s efficiency as a means to promote tourism that is able to contribute to the development of local brands.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="67">
            For Horng and Tsai (2010), websites to promote tourism, especially those developed by governmental institutions, are more frequently used by consumers as a research tool. As such, an appropriate tourism-related website design is now the key to marketing culinary or food tourism. Table 2 presents a summary of the strategies.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="68">
            Finally, another part of the abovementioned overarching strategy that came out of the interviews was the use of the image of renowned chefs as a promotional tool in both of the areas. As media figures they contribute to driving up the popularity of products and cooking in both Catalonia and Scotland. The use of the image of well-known chefs, such as Ferran Adrià (Catalonia) and Tom Kitchin (Scotland) has played a major role in not only national, but also international promotion. According to the interviews, this strategy, mainly driven by public institutions, contributes to validating a specific territory’s “prestige cooking”.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="69">
            Local strategies
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="70">
            Among the local strategies that have emerged in the chosen districts, initiatives such as the “Colectivos de Cocina” (Cookery Collectives) can be cited in the case of Catalonia. This is a pioneering phenomenon in Spain that seeks to promote the region’s cooking and food in general. Restaurants pay a fee to belong to “Colectivos de Cocina” and in doing so accept some joint principles relating to the promotion and preservation of traditional cooking in the region. “Colectivos de Cocina” are also members of the “Club Gastronómico”, and so any restaurants that are members of the “colectivos” can take part in the wide range of promotional and marketing activities that are organized around cuisine, both inside and outside the territory in which they are located.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="71">
            As in the case of Catalonia, Scotland has its very own phenomenon that is strong on the national level, called the “Farmers Markets” ; these markets contribute to driving the product, but have also become an attraction for visitors, inhabitants and tourists in general. These markets, such as the Edinburgh Farmers Market, are popular all over the United Kingdom, but in Scotland they are genuine tourist attractions.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="72">
            On the “Council Area” level in Scotland<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a>, “Visit Scotland” has supported the development of initiatives related to the cuisine of the local area with organizations such as the “Scottish Borders Food Network”. Created in 2006 this organization involves all the local producers, hoteliers, restaurateurs and food stores in the territory. These businesses have joined together to develop and make the region’s food known by organizing festivals, farmers markets and, naturally, through the organization’s website as a portal to promote those who are part of the strategy. Other examples are the “Isle of Arran Taste Trail” and the “Ayrshire &amp;amp; Arran Food Network”. The latter is private. It was founded in 2002 and comprises some 58 businesses, including producers, restaurateurs and stores that currently promote food production and culinary tourism in the area.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Comparative analysis of the two strategies</section>
        <paragraphe num="73">
            The comparison of both the overarching strategies to promote food and those in the selected case studies also includes the literature review, and the responses to the interviews that were conducted. The strategies are analyzed simultaneously according to the four orders laid down by Hjalager (2002), who considers these to be both the driving forces and, simultaneously, the barriers to creating culinary tourism in any given area. As was stated in previous sections, the four orders laid down by said author refer to the real possibility of a territory creating, promoting and cementing culinary tourism as a new mode of tourism.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="74">
            1) First order : autochthonous development
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="75">
            In the first order, culinary tourism within the existing economic structures collaborates with work networks and the knowledge base, and therefore comprises the following aspects (see Table 3) :
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="76">
            *Certification SALSA (Safe and Local Supplier Approval) 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="77">
            It can be observed for the two case studies that in this first order each of the aspects proposed by Hjalager (2002) is met. In addition, the public-private form is conspicuous in promoting tourism products, such as in campaigns focused on typical, regional agro-food products that can be considered to be attractive for tourists. Since, as Boniface (2003) states, the real role of festivals, shows, conferences, tours, tastings and samplings, demonstrations, visits to farms and production centers, cooking schools and vacations, etc., is to give tourists added value.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="78">
            Moreover, in this first order, regional quality standards and certifications can also impact on tourists’ choices when they purchase a “gastronomic souvenir”, as it is referred to by Richards (2002). According to Armesto and Gómez (2004 :85), these standards have led in part to actions to recover, preserve and valorize food heritage. The authors also state that the identification of quality cuisine frequently goes hand in hand with the existence of food with protection devices (Designations of Origin, Protected Geographical Indication, Specific Designations, Quality Designations, and so on).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="79">
            2) Second order : horizontal development
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="80">
            The second order is connected with adding value to the production process and the possibility of integrating suppliers both up and down the chain, but only in what is related to the material part of the production process. Among the aspects mentioned by Hjalager (2002) are : a) the possibility of incorporating precise criteria that any supplier who wants to obtain or raise his positioning would find easy to follow ; b) the presence of consultancy organizations capable of motivating and guiding suppliers as they take steps to improve quality ; c) creating competitive advantages for the accreditation of suppliers and ensuring added value between producers and across the whole value chain (see Table 4).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="81">
            This second order is also complied with in the two case studies and represents an important element for the food-related tourist sector, because it helps to strengthen the links between the interested parties and the inter-institution and inter-sector work required for the marketing activities to be implemented properly and, as such, for the quality standards of a tourist destination to be improved.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="82">
            3) Third order : vertical development
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="83">
            In this order the author refers to the development and addition of elements of services analogous to the supply of food material, which can create new types of links and collaborations related to the integration of food in other economic activities, including, for example : a) setting up trails ; b) setting up visitor centers and museums ; c) creating food and tourism based events, and d) cookery classes and cooking vacations (see Table 5).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="84">
            Both in the case of Spain and Catalonia, direct observation and the interviews lead to the conclusion that a tourism product like food trails is one of the main strategies to which the people in charge of designing these strategies turn. For, as Fandos Herrera et al. (2012) state, one of the most developed products in culinary tourism is the trail.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="85">
            In the two case studies Antonioli Corgiliano’s (2002) proposal is confirmed, that trails are said to usually link regional raw materials to other environmental and cultural tourism resources to ensure tourism use of the region. In the opinion of the author of the present study, the trail is a complex tourism product that entails interaction between different tangible and intangible components : services, the local environment and communities, and one of the most crucial issues for creating a trail is the management of the relational dynamics among the actors.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="86">
            Be that as it may, a food trail cannot be a simple list of restaurants where the traditional cooking of the area is practiced, or of stores where products can be purchased ; the trail has to be a route that traces the footsteps of both the cooking and the products and an adventure in which to enjoy them (Tresserras et al., 2007 : 229).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="87">
            4) Fourth order : diagonal development
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="88">
            The fourth order is connected with improving the knowledge base of the food experience in such a way as to contribute to creating “intelligent” food clusters in the economy. Additional knowledge of the resources and the ability to innovate has to be developed and addressed to interact with all food and tourism sectors as a whole.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="89">
            It is the opinion of the author of the present study that the diagonal approach needs to ensure the creation and transfer of knowledge by means of the food, cuisine and tourism sectors, and compensate for the typical structural defects in these sectors by taking into account the reluctance of small companies to form work networks, as they need to build trust with their potential partners.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="90">
            In this order of culinary tourism, the visitor target group is not only aimed exclusively at people who are on vacation, but also food and tourism industry professionals. Knowledge building abilities are applied in institutional agreements. Knowledge is the most important ingredient and these activities are crucial for the innovation process and the dissemination of knowledge (see Table 6).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="91">
            The fourth order proposed by Hjalager (2002) is especially relevant for the institutionalization and consolidation of culinary tourism, because the production of experts, the creation of a body of knowledge, the increase in professional experts and, in short, the creation and transfer of knowledge, all contribute to the professionalization and consolidation of a determined institutional field (Dimaggio, 1991), which in this case is culinary tourism.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="92">
            According to Hjalager (2002), the foregoing hierarchy does not mean that one level cannot be compatible with another, or that it is not possible to change from one to another. There is no uniformity in the way that patterns are developed. However, it is important to clarify that the aspects that are marketed and sold are not only food and entertainment, or food-related experiences ; but also knowledge, visions and concepts that can be modified and implemented in other regions. As a consequence, as Hjalager (2002) emphasizes, the relationship between local and overarching forces is dynamic and interactive.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusions</section>
        <paragraphe num="93">
            Hwever, according to Fandos Herrera et al. (2012) still only a minority number of tourists engage in culinary tourism. In fact, according to the author, it attracts a very select type of tourist with a high volume of expenditure on high quality products. In any case, culinary tourism is an opportunity for territories that see in their agro-food products a chance for sales through the link to tourist activity. This has been identified in the analysis of the two case studies, which also demonstrates how different actors from different sectors are involved in developing the strategies that enable this mode of tourism to be promoted.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="94">
            Geographically disadvantaged areas find elements of competitiveness and uniqueness that enable a response to be made to what, according to Gaztelumendi (2012), food tourists seek. These include, for example, the authenticity of places through food, by recognizing the value of food as a means to socialize and a space to share the lives of others and exchange experiences.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="95">
            In addition, the fact that a comparison of the figures for tourists in Catalonia and Scotland shows that the former presents higher values in terms of overnight stays and foreign travelers, for example, contrasts with the similarities found in the structure, design and implementation of food-linked strategies in each of the territories analyzed.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="96">
            The foregoing suggests that these territories are similar on both the State and regional / local scales in terms of culinary tourism planning and development, as set out in their strategies, and this justifies the application of the case study and comparative analysis as valid tools for finding points that they have in common in the territorial analyses.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="97">
            For the two case studies, the design and promotion of tourism food products is mainly based on the food resources that the territories possess. However, whatever the geographic area, the creation of tourism food products focuses on the creation of festivals, conferences, trails and food fairs or, in other words, on events. This supports Getz’s (2008) argument when he refers to how the “event in tourism” is generally recognized as an element that should be included in an integrated approach to tourism development and promotion.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="98">
            These promotion strategies based on the creation of food events are principally led by the public institutions on the regional or State scale in the two case studies. It can be said that the institutions in charge of designing and implementing the strategies assume the role of what Getz (2008) defined as Tourist Destination Marketing Organizations, where events are highly valued as attractions, places of interest and catalysts. These aspects were observed through the strategies assembled in the areas of study on both the State and regional / local scales.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="99">
            In addition, the promotional activities on the local level are a replica on a smaller scale of the activities developed on a higher administrative scale ; thus the responsibility for strategy planning and design by the competent institutions on the regional and State levels are more relevant.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="100">
            The analysis based on the four orders developed by Hjalager (2002) enabled the information related to food products for the two case studies to be compiled and analyzed from an integrated perspective. In other words, apart from depicting the tourism resources and products produced for the two areas in each of the selected territories, the four orders contribute to exploring the role or the actions also undertaken by other actors and institutions, which are normally not analyzed as part of tourist activity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="101">
            These “other” actors and institutions clearly have an impact on the planning and development of this economic activity in any territory (see fourth order, table 6).. As such, it can be said that analyzing other institutions according to the Hjalager (2002) classification can be a methodological analysis tool for future research in the present area of study.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="102">
            Apart from characterizing the strategies and reading like a list, the results also aspire to arousing curiosity and interest for the comparison of other cases, which could be reflected in the events and the activities developed in the areas of study. In other respects, it is also expected that they may contribute to stimulating ideas in other territories that see in their culinary products an opportunity for their commercialization through culinary tourism.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="103">
            A territory’s biogeographical conditions can also be stated to clearly determine its culinary resources and products and in turn limit accessibility to these. However, one of the strengths of geographically disadvantaged areas is the uniqueness of their products, which allows them to be widely valued and appreciated in the culinary tourism market of postmodern societies in which experiences and uniqueness play a major part. As Quang and Wang (2004) state, in the postmodern age, consumers’ experiences are a major part of economic and social life. We are said to be witnessing the rise of the experience economy, of which food has now become part.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="104">
            Although the profile of the culinary tourist is still not clear, as to date no government has followed up this market niche (Loverseed, 2009), it can be said that the strategies that have been implemented, such as the Gastroteca and the Club Gastronómico in Catalonia, increasingly raise the number of actors linked to this type of strategies. In addition, according to the Tourism Intelligence Scotland (2012) report, in Scotland strategies like “Taste of Arran” have enabled the island’s products to be sold to other parts of the United Kingdom, thus forging links with more restaurateurs, producers and specialized stores.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="105">
            All of the above not only enables an increase in demand to be deduced, but it can also be observed that unique agro-food-linked tourism strategies with differentiated features, such as the features presented by geographically disadvantaged areas, are both an opportunity for commercial expansion -and, as such, for these territories to diversify their economies- and also a way for them to make their identities and cultures known through the tourism resources and products that are designed and implemented.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="106">
            Finally, the comparative analysis that has been performed enabled two realities to be perceived that might be thought to be different, but which share points in common in the way that they promote food and are structured. It is hoped that the present study will have contributed to knowledge with the strategies that both public and private organizations currently design and implement to promote culinary products in response to a phenomenon that is on the rise, culinary tourism. However, this study is an exploration of, and a first approach to, the state of the art of the territorial promotion and marketing of food, which is the reason why it is suggested that more detailed approaches be made on a range of scales that can be made through comparative analyses in the international or interregional spheres.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Alain, D. (1999). Triangulation in qualitative tourism research. Tourism Management, 20 (1), pp. 157-161.</reference>
        <reference>Anton Clavé, S., Gonzàlez Reverté, F., Andreu Sunyer, N., (2005). Planificación territorial del turismo. Barcelona : Universitat Oberta de Catalunya.</reference>
        <reference>Antonioli Corigliano, R. (2002). The route to quality : Italian gastronomy networks in operation. In A. Hjalager, &amp; G. Richards (Eds.), Tourism and gastronomy , pp. 166-185. London etc. : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Armesto, X., Gómez, B. (2004). Productos agroalimentarios de calidad, turismo and desarrollo local : el caso del Priorat .Cuadernos Geográficos, 34 (1), pp. 83-94.</reference>
        <reference>Armesto, X. , Gómez, B. (2006). Tourism and quality agro-food products : An opportunity for the Spanish countryside. 97(2), pp. 166-177</reference>
        <reference>Bessière, J. (1998). Local development and heritage : Traditional food and cuisine as tourist attractions in rural areas. Sociologia Ruralis, 38(1), pp. 21-34.</reference>
        <reference>Boniface, P. (2003). Tasting tourism : Travelling for food and drink. Burlington, Ashgate.</reference>
        <reference>Boyne, S., Williams, F., Hall, D. (2002). “On the trail of regional success : tourism, food production and the Isle of Arran Taste Trail”.In Hjalager, A. &amp; Richards, G. (Eds.) (2002), Tourism and gastronomy. London : Routledge. Pp. 91-114.</reference>
        <reference>Bryden J., Munro, G. (2000) : New approaches to economic development in peripheral rural regions, Scottish Geographical Journal, 116 (2), pp. 111-124.</reference>
        <reference>Callizo Soneiro, J. (1991). Aproximación a la geografía del turismo. Madrid : Síntesis.</reference>
        <reference>Cohen, E., Avieli, N. (2004). Food in tourism : Attraction and impediment. Annals of Tourism Research, 31(4), pp. 755-778.</reference>
        <reference>Cooper, C., &amp; Hall, C. M. (2008). Contemporary tourism : An international approach. Oxford : Butterworth-Heinemann.</reference>
        <reference>Departamento de Empresa and Ocupación (2010). Dossiers Comarcales (Alt Urgell). Generalitat de Catalonia.Barcelona.</reference>
        <reference>Dimaggio, P. (1991). “Constructing an Organizational Field as a Professional Project : U.S. Art Museums, 1920–1940”. In Powell, W. &amp; DiMaggio, P. (Eds).The New Institutionalism in Organizational Analysis. Chicago : University of Chicago Press. Pp. 267–92.</reference>
        <reference>Espeteix, E. (2007). Los espacios turísticos del patrimonio alimentario. In Tresserras, J and Medina, F. (Eds.) Patrimonio gastronómico and turismo cultural en el Mediterráneo, pp. 153-174. Barcelona : Ibertur Publications.</reference>
        <reference>Everett, S., Aitchison, C. (2008). The role of food tourism in sustaining regional identity : A case study of Cornwall, south west England. Journal of Sustainable Tourism, 16(2), pp. 150-167.</reference>
        <reference>Fandos Herrera, C., Blanco, H, J., Puyuelo, A. J. (2012). “Gastronomy’s importance in the development of tourism destinations in the world”, In Jordan, P. (Eds), Global Report on Food Tourism, Madrid : World Tourism Organization.</reference>
        <reference>Fields, K. (2002). Demand for the culinary tourism product. Motivational factors. In Tourism and Gastronomy. Hjalager, A. M ; Richards, G. (editors). Routledge, London, pp. 36-50.</reference>
        <reference>Gandara, J. (2003). Hoteles sostenibles para destinos sostenibles, la calidad hotelera como instrumento para la sostenibilidad, Simposio internacional de turismo and ocio ESADE.</reference>
        <reference>In Departament d’innovació Universitats I Empresa (Eds.) (2009). Atles de Turisme de Catalunya. Barcelona : Generalitat de Catalunya. pp. 462-469.</reference>
        <reference>Gaztelumendi, I. (2012). Global trends of Food Tourism. In Jordan, P. (Eds), Global Report on Food Tourism, Madrid : World Tourism Organization.</reference>
        <reference>Getz, D. (2008). Event tourism : Definition, evolution, and research. Tourism Management, 29, pp- 403–428</reference>
        <reference>Hall, C. M., Mitchell, R. (2001). Wine and food tourism. In N. Douglas &amp; R. Derrett (Eds.), Special interest tourism : Context and cases, pp. 307–329. Brisbane : John Wiley.</reference>
        <reference>Hall, C. M., Sharples, L. (2003). Food tourism around the world : Development, management and markets. Oxford : Butterworth Heinemann.</reference>
        <reference>Hjalager, A., Richards, G. (2002). Tourism and gastronomy. London etc. : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Hjalager, A. (2002). A typology of Culinary tourism. In Hjalager &amp; Richards (Eds) Tourism and gastronomy, pp. 21-35. London : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Hjalager, A., Corigliano, M. A. (2000). Food for tourists ? determinants of an image. International Journal of Tourism Research, 2 (4) pp. 281–293.</reference>
        <reference>Hartley, Jean (1994). Case studies in organizational research. In Catherine Cassell &amp; Gillian Symon (Eds.),Qualitative methods in organizational research, a practical guide, pp. 208-229. London : Sage.</reference>
        <reference>Horng, J., Tsai, C.T. (2010), Government websites for promoting East Asian culinary tourism : A cross-national analysis. Tourism Management 31, pp. 74–85.</reference>
        <reference>IETE-Instituto de Estudios Turísticos de España (2010). Encuesta de Gasto Turístico (Egatur).Ministerio de Industria, Energía y Turismo de España.</reference>
        <reference>Kivela, J. (2006). Tourism and gastronomy : Gastronomy’s influence on how tourists experience a destination. Journal of Hospitality &amp; Tourism Research, 30 (3), pp. 354-377.</reference>
        <reference>López Palomeque, F., Font i Garolera, J., Sanchez Aguilera, D., and Majoral i Moline, R. (2002). Catalunya : Un análisis territorial. Barcelona : Ariel.</reference>
        <reference>Lorenzini, E., Calzati, V., Giudici, P. (2011) Territorial for Tourism development, a statistical analysis on the Marche region. Annals of Tourism Research, 38 (2), pp. 540–560.</reference>
        <reference>Loverseed, H. (2009) “Culinary tourism-International”. Travel &amp; Tourism Analyst. 4. pp. 1-42.</reference>
        <reference>Mak, Athena H.N., Lumbers, M., Eves, A. (2012). Globalisation and food consumption in tourism. Annals of Tourism Research, 39 (1), pp. 171–196.</reference>
        <reference>McKercher, B. (2005). Destinations as products ? A reflection on Butler’s life cycle. Tourism Recreation Research, 30(4), pp. 97-102.</reference>
        <reference>Okumus, B., Okumus, F. McKercher, B. (2007). Incorporating local and international cuisines in the marketing of tourism destinations : The cases of Hong Kong and Turkey. Tourism Management 28. pp. 253–261.</reference>
        <reference>Petrini, C. (2007). In Polifemo (Ed.), Bueno, limpio and justo : Principios de una nueva gastronomía (Polifemo ed.). Madrid.</reference>
        <reference>Ravenscroft, N., Van Westering, J. (2002). “Gastronomy and intellectual property”. In : Tourism and Gastronomy. In Hjalager, A. &amp; Richards, G. (Eds.) (2002), Tourism and gastronomy. London : Routledge,pp. 153-163.</reference>
        <reference>Richards, G. (Ed.) (2002). “Gastronomy : An essential ingredient in tourism production and consumption”.In Hjalager, A. &amp; Richards, G. (Eds.) (2002), Tourism and gastronomy. London : Routledge. pp. 3-20.</reference>
        <reference>Robson, C. (1993). Real world research. Blackwell, Oxford.</reference>
        <reference>Rodriguez, R. (1998). La Escala local del Desarrollo. Definición and aspectos teóricos. Revista de Desenvolvimento Economico, 1 (1). pp-6-16.</reference>
        <reference>Scarpato, R. (2002). Gastronomy as a tourism product : The perspective of gastronomy studies. In Hjalager &amp; Richards (Eds) Tourism and gastronomy, pp. 51-70. London etc. : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Shaw, G., Williams, A. M. (1994). Critical issues in tourism :A geographical perspective. Basil Blackwell.</reference>
        <reference>Smith, S. L. J., Xiao, H. (2008). Culinary tourism supply chains : A preliminary examination. Journal of Travel Research, 46(3), pp. 289-299.</reference>
        <reference>Surlemont, B., Johnson, C. (2005). The role of guides in artistic industries : The special case of the “star system” in the haute-cuisine sector. Managing Service Quality, 15(6), pp. 577 – 590.</reference>
        <reference>Telfer, D., Wall, G. (1996). Linkages between tourism and food production. Annals of Tourism Research, 23(3), pp. 635–653.</reference>
        <reference>Urry, J. (1990). The tourist gaze : leisure and travel in contemporary societies. London : Sage.</reference>
        <reference>Xiao, H., Smith, S. L. J., (2006). Case studies in tourism research : A state-of-the-art analysis. Tourism Management. 27 pp. 738–749</reference>
        <reference>Taste of Arran (http://www.taste-of-arran.co.uk/ )</reference>
        <reference>Taste of Skye and Lochalsh (http://www.tastelocal.co.uk/skye/awards/index.html)</reference>
        <reference>Ripollés district tourism web portal (http://www.elripolles.com/)</reference>
        <reference>Border Food Network (http://www.bordersfoodnetwork.co.uk/about_us.html)</reference>
        <reference>Ayrshire Food Network (http://www.ayrshirefoodnetwork.co.uk/default.php)</reference>
        <reference>Skye and Lochalsh tourism web portal (http://www.destination-skye-lochalsh.com/)</reference>
        <reference>Ayrshire and Arran tourism web portal (http://www.ayrshire-arran.com/)</reference>
        <reference>East Ayrshire Council web portal (http://www.eastayrshire.gov.uk/TourismAndVisitorAttractions/TourismStrategy.aspx)</reference>
        <reference>Scottish Islands events and festivals web portal (http://www.scotlandsislands.com/festivals-events/)</reference>
        <reference>Claire MacDonald website (http://www.claire-macdonald.com/Default.aspx)</reference>
        <reference>Highland Council review (2009) Tourism expenditure (http://www.slcvo.org.uk/copy-area-profile.html)</reference>
        <reference>Visit Arran (http://www.visitarran.net/eating/) official web portal</reference>
        <reference>Eat Scotland web portal (http://eatscotland.visitscotland.com/eating-out/bramblesseafoodgrill/)</reference>
        <reference>Skye and Lochalsh (http://www.lochalsh.co.uk/index.html) travel guide</reference>
        <reference>“Welcome Scotland” website (http://www.welcometoscotland.com/regions/ayrshire-arran-clyde/arran)</reference>
        <reference>“Desarrollo Ripollès” Consortium website (http://www.ripollesdesenvolupament.com/)</reference>
        <reference>Girona Tourism Board( http://es.costabrava.org/)</reference>
        <reference>Tourism Intelligence Scotland (http://www.tourism-intelligence.co.uk/) website</reference>
        <reference>Catalonian Statistics Institute (IDESCAT) website (http://idescat.cat/)</reference>
        <reference>SALSA (Safe and Local Supplier Approval (http://www.salsafood.co.uk/)</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">According to Google Academic statistics (2011), they are cited in over 127 articles.</note>
        <note id="2">Michelin is regarded as a highly respectable institution in the culinary world. Leader in restaurant classification with its star system, it influences consumer choice (Surlemont and Johnson, 2005).</note>
        <note id="3">Taken from the Survey on Tourist Spending (Egatur) prepared by IETE (Spanish Institute of Tourism Studies, 2010)</note>
        <note id="4">Department of Business and Labor (2010). District Dossiers (Alt Urgell). Generalitat de Catalunya (Catalonian regional government)</note>
        <note id="5">Taken from the Girona Tourist Board webpage (http://es.costabrava.org/)</note>
        <note id="6">Scottish Government (2009). Recipe for Success – Scotland’s National Food and Drink Policy</note>
        <note id="7">Taken from the official Highland Council (2012) website</note>
        <note id="8">Taken from the official “Visit Arran” (2012) website</note>
        <note id="9">The Euromarc project (2007-2010) has been developed as an integral part of a global project called “EuroMontana”. The main objective of the Euromarc project is to assess “the perceptions for and interest of European consumers and retailers of mountain food products in order to find ways of adding value to these products”.</note>
    </notes>
</article>