<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_MOV_40-133_Ts_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1083" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.1083</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>2</numero>
        <annee>2012</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="1074">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            La mobilisation des identités amazighes dans des projets de développement touristique. Dynamiques du branchement et de l’ancrage dans les montagnes marocaine
        </original>
        <traduction lang="es" source="1092">La movilización de las identidades “amazighs” en los proyectos de desarrollo turístico. Dinámicas de conexión y de vinculación al territorio en las montañas marroquíes</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Oiry-Varacca" prenom="Mari">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_MOV_37-157_Le_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1074" lang="fr">La mobilisation des identités amazighes dans des projets de développement touristique. Dynamiques du branchement et de l’ancrage dans les montagnes marocaine</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                University of Geneva and University of Marrakech 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>The use of Amazigh identities in tourism development projects. Interconnectedness and embeddedness dynamics in the Moroccan mountains</titre>
    <resume>
        This article examines the dynamics, challenges and impacts brought about by the emergence of a new tourism offer in the Moroccan mountains based on mobilizing Amazigh identities. It explores the embeddedness and interconnectedness dynamic which feeds these identity strategies implemented by the project managers, who search for territorial embeddedness by promoting heritage practices and objects they class to be representative of the latter. At the same time, they “interconnect” with global flow of identity imaginaries and referents, and with actor networks liable to back their discourse on any aspect of Amazigh identity. The different strategies, according to the objects, networks and referents used will be differentiated, and focus will be placed on the way in which these strategies work on collective identities and reinvent their territorial links. This paper is the result of fieldwork carried out in the Western High Atlas and Anti-Atlas regions.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">“Discover Amazigh hospitality, a culture, an art of authentic living”. These few words, which accompany the presentation of trips organized by the Association des Amis du Zat, symbolize the emergence of a new tourism offer in the Moroccan mountains. In recent years, the aim of tourism stakeholders has been to make tourism “cultural” and to promote “identity”. International and Moroccan tour operators have started to break away from their hiking trail activities in a shift towards discovery trips, while at the local level, associations, guides and foreigners are creating new tourism projects – building on the distinctive characteristics of the local communities and environments that they have shaped. These offers reflect a search for territorial embeddedness in which heritage practices and objects are given a symbolic status by the project managers. But at the same time, these offers illustrate how tourism stakeholders are able to “interconnect” with the worldwide flow of imaginaries and identity referents – by referring to Berbers, mountain peoples, indigenous persons – and the global stakeholder networks liable to back their discourse on any aspect of the Amazigh identity and to support their projects. The dual embeddedness-interconnection dynamic that fuels identity-related tourism projects deserves to be duly considered since project managers appear to make use of it, not only to generate new revenue and jobs, in regions with high marginalization, but also to strengthen collective identities and to reinvent their territorial links.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourism in Morocco has received very little attention in terms of identity dynamics and effects of scale, with the exception of a few authors who show how global referents such as “indigenous” can be used by tourism stakeholders in cultural and political recognition strategies (Cauvin-Verner, 2008). Although the use of heritage in new tourism offers has been the focus of growing attention in the social sciences</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, fringe tourism in fringe areas has been addressed more from a perspective of economic development than from one of identity dynamics. In general, authors who focus on identity issues (Boujrouf, 2004) regard tourism as a risk that considerably disrupts so-called traditional cultures, in line with the works of Cazes (1986). Other approaches offer the potential to refocus the field of tourism studies on identity dynamics in the fringe areas of Morocco. Some authors draw attention to the fact that tourism can be a lever of identity reconstruction (Picard, 1992) and underline the capacity of local stakeholders to make tourism a tool for specific strategies (Erb, 2001). For these authors, tourism is not only an economic resource, but a symbolic one too. On the one hand, it implies that tourism stakeholders of a given place should promote its specific characteristics so that it stands out from other places and appeals to tourists. A strategy of distinction consists of highlighting the distinctive cultural characteristics of a place. On the other hand, tourism is a vector for imaginaries, that is, representations and images constructed in the long term, consolidated over the course of history, with a global flow between points of reception and points of departure, all of which contributes to defining the social identity of those who live in the point of reception. For instance, this could be the identity attributed to the latter group by external individuals, in this case, the tourists and tourism stakeholders.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These imaginaries may influence the identity construction of the group, and can be exploited by individuals seeking to renew and assert their willingness and sense of belonging to this group, as shown by Derbarbieux (2012). These different development strategies – adopted by tourism stakeholders who have a local identity on the one hand, and those who mobilize and reinvest global tourism imaginaries, on the other – show that tourism lends itself well to embeddedness and interconnectedness identity strategies. Effects of scale in these strategies have not been widely studied. In the field of anthropology and geography, some researchers have conducted studies on how new forms of “alternative” tourism refer to the requirements of global stakeholders and fall within the scope of transnational networks (Doquet &amp;amp; Le Menestrel, 2006). Other studies have analyzed the strategies implemented by local actors to territorialize the flows of images and goods created by tourist mobility (Debarbieux et al., 2008).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This aim of this paper is to analyze tourism projects that promote the Amazigh identity: it will adopt the same line of thought as studies that consider tourism to be a potential identity strategy. It will also endeavor to extend this line of research by focussing on the embeddedness/interconnectedness paradigm.The common themes of the present study are how these projects shape collective identities and what their territorial links are. First, the theoretical and methodological approaches used will be set out, then the way in which interconnectedness dynamics foster embeddedness ones will be analyzed by examining local actors’ use of stakeholder networks, heritage objects, and identity referents at various levels. Next, types of identity strategies will be explained ; differentiated according to the networks, objects and referents used and the target objectives. Finally, the paper will seek to gain an understanding of the role that geographical referents play in the process of reconstructing collective identities through tourism projects, and to identify these referents.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This study was a multi-site one conducted in the Western High Atlas (Oukaïmeden, Ourika and Zat Valleys) and the Anti-Atlas (Taliouine region), using discourse analysis and referring to the literature of tourism stakeholders. Sources included both written and spoken material. The former comprised tourist brochures, websites of the studied projects, and official texts from international organizations and NGOs, and the latter consisted of semi-structured interviews with project leaders, managers on different administrative scales, i.e., at the commune (town or village), province and national level, and the network members with whom the project managers work (in Morocco and in France). I also took part in the organization of a stakeholder meeting in which actors from the Zat and Ourika Valleys were given the opportunity to express their viewpoints. This paper uses the initial results of the study.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Building collective identities: “embeddedness” and “interconnectedness” dynamics</section>
        <section niveau="h2">Embeddedness-interconnectedness, territorialization-deterritorialization: using analytical couplings</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Building collective identities in a context of globalization has provoked heated debates in the domain of social sciences. Contrary to the argument that sees globalization as a factor of homogenization, J-L Amselle (2000) states that identity consists of many borrowed forms, that it is the product of connections with incorporated signifiers and their transformation into sectional signifiers, and considers the process of contemporary globalization to be a symbolic resource: speeding up the spread of identity referents at the global level increases connection possibilities. His approach belongs to the field of political sciences and political sociology studies dealing with networks in a globalized world: a type of research which has become increasingly common since the 1990s (Appadurai, 2001 ; Giddens, 1994). These studies go beyond mere “interconnectedness” to consider “network” and “flow”: they explore the constitution of social- and political-actor networks and analyze how they mobilize flows of goods and capital, along with intangible entities such as information. In terms of “interconnectedness”, Amselle’s approach is interesting as he shows collective identities to be the product of strategies that use other immaterial, symbolic flows: identity and discourse referents. On the other hand, it is an approach that does not explain how a particular network actor uses a particular referent and heritage object. Links between these heterogeneous entities may be considered via the Actor-network theory (Latour 2006), in which the social is the product of ongoing interactions between networks of human and non-human agents. Amselle’s theory is also insufficient to grasp the multiscalarity of these networks – a characteristic which can also be analyzed in the light of research carried out by geographers on the reappraisal of institutional scales through the advent of networks (Featherstone 2007). Adopting the new research perspective of “cosmopolitanism”, put forward by sociologists, instead of mere “nationalism” (Beck, 2006), enables the transnationalism of networks to be taken into account and to consider identity discourses on the various levels to which they refer. Personally, I believe that the concept of “interconnectedness” implies a wider and more geographical sense than Amselle’s definition, as a type of research designed to capture the mobilization process by local actors in actor networks connected to spaces of transnational reference by the global identity referents and by heritage objects.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The concept of “interconnectedness” cannot be understood independently from that of “embeddedness” insofar as tourism project managers use the former for the benefit of a territorial embeddedness strategy. Indeed, they consider their chosen objects to be symbolic of a collective identity and of the space with which a group identifies. To understand the dialectic of interconnectedness and embeddedness, the conceptual discussions in the domain of geography on the territorial dimension of identity constructions, in the network age, should be mobilized. In particular, I base this belief on research showing that the construction of collective identities is carried out through the increasingly diverse ways in which they relate to the region (Debarbieux, 2006; Massey, 1991): while considering that transnationalization dynamics create identities that are not automatically linked to the region, these authors see in heritage dynamics the proof that the construction of anchored identities is more prevalent than ever. It appears that, far from being contradictory, connection and settlement constructs actually coexist. In addition, Stock (2006) illustrates that it is possible for individuals to identify with types of spaces other than territories, such as networks, as well as simultaneously identifying with these types of different spaces. My hypothesis is that interconnectedness fuels the production of spatialized identities, constructed in terms of identification with the various types of spaces. To understand how project managers make use of collective identities, how they value space, and territory in particular, I will use the analytical coupling of territorialization and deterritorialization – terms used to describe the process by which individuals or groups do or do not identify with a territory.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Using these analytical couplings to consider the identification process</section>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To successfully complete this analysis, a constructivist concept of identity will be adopted. I will discuss the identification process through which several individuals have shown their willingness to act collectively, to recognize themselves within the same “collective identity”, and to differentiate themselves from other groups and from the “social identity” imposed on them from the outside (Debarbieux, 2006). This will be a collective study contrasting “legitimizing identity” with “resistance identity” and “project identity” (Castells, 1996). This type of research, which deals with social movement (taking particular inspiration from Hannah Arendt’s philosophy), focuses on individuals’ intentionality and considers collective identity to be a series choices and commitments that individuals make, in action and interaction. The case of collective identities will be debated, insofar as they appear to be refined mainly by a group of actors – the project managers.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To understand how these identities are constructed, two approaches will be used. First, in keeping with narrative identity approaches (Ricoeur, 1985), I will consider collective identity as a kind of storytelling that gives meaning to the collective project. These theories, which focus on the actor and the discourse, enabled me to understand how the term “identity” is used by the stakeholders. It was found that the actors involved scarcely use it and when they do, it is in a contradictory fashion: sometimes identity is objectified, and sometimes it is a multiscalar and multireferential construction. That being said, all actors use this term strategically. To gain an understanding of these strategies, it seemed appropriate to use a pragmatic approach to identity, as the concept of performance provides a basis for understanding identities from the viewpoint of what the actors consider it to be. Performative studies have shown that individuals construct identities not only through language, but also through everyday practices, such as the relationship that they have with objects, i.e., in materiality – the spatial relationship (Nash, 2000). I will study stakeholders’ management of their identity through tourism projects and how this reflects their spatial relationships.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To address how identity is constructed through discourse and practices, two survey methods were chosen: interviews with tourism stakeholders (which enabled me to listen to their identity stories), and observation of their practices (which helped me to study their relationships with the other actors, their valued objects, and the spaces they occupy). Analysis of these interviews and observations required several approaches: (i) a semantic one to analyze an actor’s discourse and to understand how identity is used in this respect, (ii) a semiotic one to analyze stakeholder interaction with objects, other stakeholders and the interviewer, and (iii) an actorial one, inspired by the Actor-network theory, to understand how the diverse array of actors, objects, discourse and identity practices is composed in each identity strategy. To put these theoretical and methodical considerations to the test, the case of the Moroccan mountains seemed to be a particularly appropriate choice.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Mobilizing global identity resources in local tourism projects</section>
        <section niveau="h2">Developing cultural specificities for tourism purposes: a recent embeddedness study</section>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Since the very beginning of tourism in the western High Atlas mountains (which took place in the colonial era) culture has been one of the main attractions for foreign tourists. They appear to class these areas (Berber-speaking and with a reputation for rebel activity), that only experienced peace in the late 1930s, as more exotic than the better-known world of towns (Ramou, 2009).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From the 1970s onwards, and particularly from the 1990s (with the Central High Atlas Mountains Pilot Project launched in the Aït Bouguemez Valley by the Ministry of Home Affaires and with French cooperation) tourism offers have put the spotlight on the environment rather than on culture – this can be seen by the activities marketed to foreign clients which include hiking routes concentrated around the Toubkal and M’goun summits (Popp 1999). Alongside this development, national tourism has undergone similar growth in the valleys near Marrakech – aimed at making the most of the region’s climate which is fresh in the summer and mild in the winter – and offers include day trips, visits to thermal springs (as is the case in the Zat Valley), or holidays in secondary residences in the Ourika Valley. In the past, the cultural specificities of these places were not major factors in attracting tourists, but this is changing.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In recent years, cultural heritage has received growing attention from tourist operators. For example, tour operators specialized in trekking, such as Terre d’aventure, now offer “discovery trips” in addition to their sports holidays. They organize routes in lesser known regions – such as the Siroua Massif from Taliouine (Anti-Atlas), or the Yagour plateau (between Zat and Ourika) – which are presented as being well-suited for experiencing “traditional life”. More emphasis is placed on identity, with the discourse in their brochures evoking “Berber” identity and the region’s specific artisan skills (document nr.1).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">New, more recent projects strive to promote so-called heritage practices and objects, whose diversity includes buildings, artisanal objects, skills of the rural population, or agricultural products. These projects have been carried out by (mainly male) stakeholders with various profiles (private or associative status, whether originally from the mountains or foreign) who wanted to use their skills acquired in tourism (tourist guide, or owner of a Bed and Breakfast-type establishment, etc.) or other professions (university lecturer, biologist, collector, mayor, etc.) for projects which they claimed to be “alternative” because they respected the environment and the local culture, as opposed to the type of tourism that developed in the more well-known and developed tourist destinations such as Ourika. These stakeholders also advance the local embeddedness of their projects in order to differentiate themselves from the tour operators who, they believe, pursue purely economic objectives (creating new tourism products) whereas they, on the other hand, strive to strengthen community links by increasing the value of the groups’ very own objects and practices. They claim to promote a more “authentic” identity as it is more local and firmly grounded in territory than the “Berber” identity of the tour operators.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A context of global stakeholders in favor of embeddedness research </section>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To build on this groundwork, project managers use the discourse of international stakeholders, in an interconnectedness dynamic. They act within an environment they know to be favorable to the development of local characteristics for tourism purposes. In fact, several texts from the World Tourism Organization</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (UNWTO) recommend the development of types of tourism that respect the particular cultural and environmental characteristics of tourist destinations. Moroccan tourism authorities draw their inspiration from these recommendations. Therefore, one of the priorities for the Vision 2030</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> programme and the Pays d’Accueil Touristiques (PAT) federation is to promote “rural tourism” and “niche tourism markets” based on the natural and cultural resources of each “tourist region”. These texts are discursive and material resources for tourism stakeholders who strive to promote local heritage: to describe their projects, they use the standard expressions already circulating globally in official texts (“ecotourism”, “cultural tourism”, “heritage tourism”, “ethno-tourism”, etc.). In doing so, they attract the attention of tourists and funding partners alike. Other international texts that ensure the recognition of minorities</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> contribute towards creating a favorable climate for the implementation of identity-related projects, though the issue of Berber or Amazigh</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> identity continues to spark debate in Morocco, despite the adoption of a new Constitution in July 2011, recognizing Amazighity as an integral part of Moroccan identity. These texts are used by project managers who campaign to give tourists an alternative vision of the Moroccan identity by promoting its Amazigh component.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Project managers are increasingly using transnational and national actor networks liable to enhance particular local characteristics. Two types of networks can be distinguished. The first one brings together associations such as Association pour le Tourisme Equitable et solidaire (ATES) [Assocation for Sustainable and “Fair” Tourism] or Agir pour un Tourisme Responsable (ATR) [Action for Responsible Tourism], whose central concern is the development of an alternative form of tourism. Based in France, they unite NGOs and tour operators who propose “solidarity” trips, particularly in the Moroccan mountains, and work in partnership with the project managers who have adopted these networks’ charter and obtained their label. Some local stakeholders prefer to “interconnect” with national tourism actor-networks instead of transnational ones, such as the Réseau marocain d’Ecotourisme solidaire</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> [the Moroccan network of solidarity ecotourism]. For these stakeholders, the international level is too distant to consider the promotion of local identities, whereas the national level is more favorable to exchanges of experience and gives them heightened visibility. The second type brings together militant networks such as the Congrès Mondial Amazigh (CMA) [World Amazigh Congress]. This was the first transnational network; created in 1995 by members of the Amazigh diaspora in France. Other militant networks – such as Tamaynut, which is represented at the CMA – act at the national level and are structured in regional and local sections, enabling local tourism project managers to become members. These associated transnational and national networks are, for them, a resource of significant action. They voice and represent the demands of the Amazigh movement (effective recognition of the Amazigh identity as an integral part of Moroccan identity, enforcement of commitments on Amazigh language teaching, a specific aid policy for mountain regions, etc.), and they give media coverage to a new tourism concept, considered to be a tool in the defense of the rights of Berber-speaking populations and the promotion of endogenous development, decided upon and managed by the populations concerned. They can even go as far as to providing political support. In fact, through their lobbying efforts in the United Nations, the CMA is likely to exert pressure on the Moroccan public authorities to implement policies that are more respectful of Berber-speaking populations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Using globalized identity referents </section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Project managers also mobilize globalized identity referents that reflect “ethnic” kinds of knowledge, or categories, such as Berberity, or geographical ones such as the “mountain”. Words used to describe the mountain in tourist offers, especially in hiking trail brochures, include massifs, summits and valleys. These categories circulate spatially: some offers play on the Tuareg figure – presented as the archetypal Berber nomad – which in reality, does not exist in the Moroccan mountains (document nr.2).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">They also circulate temporally: figures of mountain peoples and Berbers relate to tourism imaginaries constructed in the colonial period, during which time, an equivalence was established between mountain spaces that were both difficult to access and marginalized, and the specific so-called nomadic way of life ; between the traits attributed to the Berber – pride, bravery and temerity – and the harshness of the mountain environment (Ramou 2009). Most tourism brochures on the Moroccan mountains continue to use these two referents together. For the very few tourism operators who use the terms “Amazigh” or “indigenous” – which refer to the “Imazighen” people and their continued presence in North Africa since the Arab Muslim conquest in the 7th century – they refer to a transnational militant imaginary, to the campaign led by the Mouvement associatif amazigh (the Amazigh associative movement) since the 1970s to change the caricaturized representations of Berber-speaking populations: tourism imaginaries passed down since colonial times have, according to them, helped to construct these representations. Stakeholders use these various referents as a basis on which to build and mobilize different identity stories.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Complex embeddedness and interconnectedness identity strategies</section>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Three constructs have been identified. The qualifiers given to them are those used by the project managers during the presentation of their approach in the interviews, and as such, they reflect the stakeholder’s viewpoints. They have been retained in the analysis as they enable the array of different actors, objects and identity accounts to be identified and presented. Amazighity is understood differently in each strategy, referring to scales of reference, and singular embeddedness and interconnectedness strategies. It is invoked in the strategies pursuing different objectives, according to specific methods: the networks used, the promoted heritage objects and their given meaning are all different and therefore, the way in which this identity is told differs also.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Heritage strategies</section>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This strategy can be symbolized by two types of projects, that offer different types of trips and involve different categories of actors who manage them. The first is associations that organize cultural hikes, a typical example being the circuits offered by the Association des amis du Zat (AAZ) since 2005 in the Zat Valley (walking tours designed for small groups of foreign tourists, whose routes take them between the association’s three bed and breakfast establishments). The second is private actors who offer visits to an ecomuseum. In the present study, the case of the Berber Ecomuseum in Ourika is used. These project managers are based in Marrakech: the AAZ founder, who is originally from Zat and is the mayor, is a retired university lecturer, and the founders of the ecomuseum, who are not from Ourika originally, are two French and Moroccan collectors who have created a museum dedicated to photography in Marrakech. They all show their willingness for local embeddedness and work in close collaboration with the local guides towards achieving this aim. Attempts are made to territorialize the tourism flows so that they are more beneficial to the local population. In this spirit, they try to place culture at the service of the valley’s social and economic development. In order to attract tourists and to ensure that they stay as long as possible in the valley, the project managers promote heritage objects, and agricultural/artisanal know-how which they believe to be steeped in heritage and representative of the local community’s identity. As such, the Berber Ecomuseum in Ourika sets out to promote the tangible culture of the Moroccan Atlas ranges with an exhibition of ancient and everyday objects – pottery, weavings, agricultural tools (document nr.3).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In its organized tours, the AAZ presents the region’s tangible historical heritage, such as the rock engravings in the Yagour Plateau. Tourists are also invited to discover inhabitants’ daily life through their tangible culture – such as the agricultural landscapes created by terrace farming, and cob-work architecture – and their agricultural knowledge – management of irrigation systems or sheep shearing (document nr.4). Through these skills and knowledge and the heritage objects themselves, project managers strive to promote an identity that in essence is both local and popular. The visit to the Berber Ecomuseum is run by a local community leader from the Tafza village who recounts its stories. When he talks about the motifs woven into a carpet, he explains what the women from Tafza have told him. He creates a living vision of the local culture by visiting his father’s pottery workshop, whilst giving this a temporal dimension by recounting how a local saint was responsible for giving the village its pottery skills. As for the AAZ president, his aim is to unveil the Zat Valley’s local identity.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This embedded research carried out through the promotion of objects and skills that are symbolic of a form of identity defined at the village or valley level, is supported by a singular interconnectedness strategy. On the one hand, the projects refer to identities defined at a wider scale. The ecomuseum highlights a “Berber” identity. The exhibition takes the form of panels, and its aim is to show that the villagers’ identity was fuelled by a Berber identity defined at the Moroccan level. This is why the presented objects do not just come from Ourika, but from all regions in Morocco that have a strong Berber culture. On the other hand, the project managers participate in the associative networks that support the development of alternative tourism. In its beginnings, AAZ worked with the ATR-certified French tour operator La Balaguère, in the hope of receiving financial and technical support, a client network, and an experience of cultural and solidarity tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Militant strategies </section>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Other initiatives (few in number and relatively recent), including some that are still at the planning stage, strive to advance the Amazigh cause through tourism projects. These only operate in the most marginalized regions with strong militant commitments, in Anti-Atlas and the Zat Valley. The projects run by the Association Yagour de développement (Yagour Development Association) are representative of this strategy. This association was created in 2000 by a militant who came from the valley, and whose life path typifies that of militants from the rural world: after his university studies in Marrakech, during which time he carried out militant actions with the Tamaynut network, he returned to the valley to work (in microfinancing) at the network’s national office as head of the local section, and he created an association with a valley-level action scale. Like other project managers, he is willing to participate in the development and promotion of local identities. Nevertheless, the strategy of embeddedness, and interconnectedness in particular, is different.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Militant project managers believe that marginalization is an essentially political process, and that promoting culture at the local level should serve as a national political struggle. Tourism is regarded as the means to give the mountain’s identity-related struggles an international profile, and they use the tourist to further their cause. Therefore, tourism is seen as an awareness-raising tool that, for both tourists and inhabitants, can increase the visibility of the Amazigh culture and the political marginalization to which it has fallen victim. This tool should be put to work in a system which, in their belief, only recognizes the Arab component of Moroccan identity and presents a caricatural vision of the Amazigh identity through its backing of tourism projects that convey a folkloric image.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The founding Vice President of the Association Yagour de développement explains that “tourism should be sustainable and cultural, and should make the most of local resources. It can be used to show the outside world that we [the Amazighs] are not Arabs, not all Moroccans are Arabs, and so it it can break down the blanket judgments and the false images. With cultural tourism, we are able to send this message to the authorities, tour operators, guides, tourists, and especially inhabitants, so that their identity will not be treated as folklore”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Militants refer to an Amazigh identity in order to differentiate it from the Arab identity. They also use the term “indigenous” to show that Amazighity is the bedrock of Moroccan identity and to prove that, in this respect, it forms an integral part of the national identity. They endeavor to explain the political stakes of the Amazigh issue in Morocco to tourists, and by doing so, the resolute identity account they give them is extremely different from that of the heritage stakeholders. The objects they highlight are also different, and they place more emphasis on oral heritage – such as songs and dances or stories – as they believe this to be a better representation of the living local identity. Through offering long stays in family homes, they try to offer tourists a more in-depth cultural integration of the inhabitants’ lives. As such, by using the figure of indigenous peoples, they promote a more localized identity, at a more refined scale, whilst still referring to a Moroccan Amazigh identity that must be strongly defended, and more generally to globalized identities. All of this is reflected by these stakeholders’ membership of networks such as the previously mentioned Tamaynut one. By organizing tourist guide training in which the young people of the Zat Valley have participated, these networks contribute to the construction of a militant tourism offer at the local level.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Business strategies</section>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A third strategy recognizes the business opportunity that lies in promoting Berber and local identities. Upholders of this strategy do not see the preservation of identity as an objective in itself, even a secondary one (e.g. the shopkeepers, who are sometimes from another Valley and usually live close to their point of sale which is roadside, in tourist centres such as Setti Fama (Ourika), or close to the tourist sites including the thermal springs). These projects promote an identity put forward as being linked to the valley (document nr.5).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This embeddedness strategy is supported by use of fashionable international vocabulary (“rural”, “authentic”, “traditional”), products (argan oil), organizational structures (women’s associations), and a mountain-Berber identity (document nr.6) that harks back to images from colonial times. As such, all of the tourist attractions are Berber: the “Berber house”, the “Berber mill”, etc. The artisanal objects on offer are much of a muchness and refer to generic imaginaries, sometimes in the Tuareg style: the blue “chech” is sold on all of the stalls in Setti Fatma.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Strategies that are sources of local conflict</section>
        <section niveau="h2">Heritage and militant project managers are critical of commercial strategies</section>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These three strategies, that have extremely different objectives, conceptions of Amazigh identity, and forms of action, are a local source of controversy. Heritage and militant tourism stakeholders dislike how traders from the Ourika and Zat Valleys use the Berber identity for commercial ends. For the former, preserving what they consider to be “authentic” identity is an aim in itself ; the business strategies act as counterexamples because they portray a caricatured and a false image of Amazigh identity, and one which needs to be changed. As such, there is a sign in the Berber Ecomuseum explaining that “Despite successful tourism development, not much is known about the Berbers”. The manager of the ecomuseum criticizes the women who sell argan oil in Tafza and try to convince tourists that it is entirely produced in the Valley, whereas in reality, the kernels used to make it originate from the Essaouira region. He also criticizes artisan traders for not selling products that have been made in Marrakech. He fears that excessive commercialization of the Berber identity results in its folklorization.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The case of the Zat Valley can particularly help us to understand the conflicts that divide supporters of heritage and militant strategies from supporters of business strategies: the different viewpoints were expressed during the stakeholder meeting organized by a research team in Tighdouine (the valley’s main town). The Sidi Ahmed El Wafi spring area experienced a tourist boom in 1989, when the water’s taste and healing properties were discovered. This is a place whose infrastructure is ill-equipped to cope with anything over 1 000 cars per day at the weekend, and since 2000, increasing numbers of unauthorized souvenir stalls. All this has led to open conflict between owners of souvenir shops and restauranteurs (who have formed an association), and the mayor of Tighdouine, who is also president of the Association des amis du Zat. The president criticizes the former for only looking to make a profit without participating in local development, and according to him, three fifths of them are not even originally from the Valley itself. He contrasts the logic of the AAZ with the businesses of the Source as follows: “The most important thing for the AAZ is quality tourism. We want tourism to be controlled. I know that it’s not easy, but we do it because other people refuse to do so. But you, at the Source, you cannot say no. It’s not that we’re not listening to what you say, but these are two philosophies, two different ways of thinking. You look at things from a commercial point of view, whereas ours is a non-commercial one”.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Even though the form of tourism proposed by the AAZ, with small groups of foreigners, would respect and promote the Source’s local identity, the lack of control over tourist flows by the owners’ association would cause ecological and cultural damage. He believes that national mass tourism has made this tourist site into a place where visitors come to let their hair down and prostitution is rife, and where the local identity is not respected. Furthermore, he considers that images of the local identity are far too restrictive, and are upheld through sales of some of the valley’s aromatic plants and water bottles that bear inscriptions in Arabic and the Amazigh dialect. Here, there is a clash of two different conceptions of the Amazigh identity: for the sellers, it is an objective factor whose basis is not always apparent, but in which the commercial argument is included. For the AAZ, it is a question of preserving an “authentic” identity, one that is defined according to criteria, and their manifestations, which are clearly identified. Furthermore, this is a vision that crystallizes the situation, even though the Amazigh identity is not considered to be self-evident, but the object of explicit reflection.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Conflicting links between heritage and militant strategies </section>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">During the stakeholder meeting in Tighdouine, the AAZ and militants of the Yagour Development Association expressed their viewpoints, in particular regarding the issue of Amazigh identity. For the AAZ president, “[the term] Amazigh identity should be avoided because it has political connotations. It underlines the clash between Moroccan, Arab, and Berber identities, although they are indissociable. In any case, nobody can be sure that there is pure Amazigh blood”. For him, identity must be a development tool, and not a political one, which in any case he finds unfounded because it is a threat to national unity. By defining identity through inheritance, he tries to show that Amazigh demands are based on a racist, racial conception of the Moroccan society, whereas for centuries, it has been characterized by the mixing of races. The president of the Yagour Development Association prefers to counter this vision with a non-essentialist conception of Amazigh identity to show that it does not jeopardize the unity of the Nation. He uses the historic argument in another sense, to remind people that the Amazigh identity is at the root of the Moroccan identity, itself included in an indigenous pan-Amazigh identity at the North African level, prior to pan-Arab identity. In an interview that was conducted after the meeting, he revolts against the Mayor’s “pan-Arab” ideology, defined as such because it belongs to a political party that relays, for militant Amazighs, the voice of Makhzen – the voice of the State. Once again, he opposes two identity conceptions: a univocal, objectivist conception that presents Amazighity as an origin transmitted through birth, and a multi-referential and multi-scalar one. Nevertheless, these attitudes are to be taken as strategies, as each stakeholder uses an identity conception enabling political opinions to be defended.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Both associations also disagree on practical ways to create identity. The intention of the president of the Yagour Development Association is “not to reduce culture to mere objects” and he advocates the promotion of oral culture, particularly Ahouach – community singing and dancing sessions. He makes every effort to invite tourists to these sessions, which are planned by the local community itself rather than organized specifically for tourists, and tries to explain to them the meaning behind the words and gestures, whereas, the AAZ president prefers to focus on tangible culture, and extols the risk of folkorization of such endeavours. This begs the question of which Amazigh identities are being reinvented through these controversies ?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Constructing Amazigh identities: territorialized or deterritorialized ?</section>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">By mobilizing Amazigh identities on different scales, and in different constructs and ways, stakeholders of cultural tourism projects work on these identities and contribute to reinventing the role of spatiality in these constructions. Therefore, the issue lies in knowing what types of spaces (reticular, territorial) the project managers refer to. These projects attempt to add value to an embeddedness strategy through interconnectedness dynamics with the actor networks and national/international identity referents, making the territorial referent appear central to the identification process. With Amazigh identities that have been reformulated by tourism, it is important to understand which territories are being referred to, and to take into account the strength of deterritorialization, which is partly linked to the dynamics of interconnectedness.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Dynamics of identity reterritorialization </section>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Through heritage and militant tourism projects, Amazigh identities are constructed with reference to territories. Firstly, to reterritorialize the identities constructed from a variety of scales, project managers strive to implement projects on the popular identification scale, appropriated by the inhabitants, and referring to a lived-in space. Recently, there have been coordination efforts between stakeholders following collective thought on this subject. During the aforementioned stakeholder meeting, participants expressed their willingness to work at the valley level, starting from the tribe, because this community is still a reference for the inhabitants (even though it is not an administrative unit). Therefore, the aim would be to coordinate new projects in the Zat and Ourika valleys by promoting a common deeply rooted basis – cultural membership of the federation of Massmouda tribes. There have been discussions about the joint organization of a festival promoting the specific characteristics common to both valleys. The underlying theme would be Pastoralism in the Yagour Plateau, which is a grazing space shared by the tribes of both valleys. Tourism projects carried out in the Taliouine region (Anti-Atlas) at the “pays du safran” (Saffron country) level present a more comprehensive approach to mobilizing a popular identification scale. The NGO Migrations et développement (Migration and Development) – founded in the late 1980s by French emigrants who wanted to participate in the development of their region of origin – was the first such project. It supported the forming of a network of hostels in pays du safran, in the style of traditional Saffron culture. The region’s tourism stakeholders have followed this project and tried to coordinate their efforts on this scale: the association of tourism stakeholders recently founded in Taliouine have authority to gather together pays du safran stakeholders. Public authorities have accompanied actor mobilization to this level through the creation of a “maison du safran” [House of Saffron], which currently serves as the point of sale for saffron, although it was actually designed to centralize the region’s tourism offers by acting as a showcase for a local identity that is orientated towards saffron.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Furthermore, the actors involved are striving to promote heritage objects representative of this lived-in territory, which will serve to bolster its identification links. In Taliouine, saffron is evoked as an emblem of the “country” in tourism brochures and on Internet sites (document nr.7). In Zat and Ourika, pastoral activity and the collective Yagour pastures could be the future heritage object that symbolizes local identity, and which is promoted in popular and tourist events. Through the promotion of these objects, the tourism offer strengthens the tourism-related image and attractiveness of the territory that the object represents.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">How project managers construct identities by reference to territories and networks</section>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This process of identity territorialization encounters several obstacles. First, it does not affect most inhabitants, as it is difficult to speak of a “collective identity”. It is implemented by and for the elite heritage and militant project managers, who have the ways and means to construct a plural identity with multiple referents, through both network and territorial embeddedness approaches. These project managers correspond to the image of the “deeply-rooted cosmopolitan transnational militant” evoked by Beck (2006). They all have links with both the town itself and, as foreign nationals abroad (like one of the founders of the Berber Ecomuseum) or emigrants who travel between Morocco and Europe (like the hostel owners on the Saffron route), can mobilize networks and support. They all have a secondary or higher level of education and this enables them to launch complex local projects to exploit different identity referents and discourse and to translate the referents into a local context. However, appropriation of these identities, which are simultaneously embedded, reticulated and territorialized by the roadside sellers and inhabitants, is a relative process. Interviews conducted with this latter group indicate that they are less aware of belonging to a group defined by its Amazighity or by a specific territorial link, than the heritage and militant project leaders.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">The impact of commercial projects and the public authorities on deterritorialization of identities </section>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A further obstacle to the territorialization of Amazigh identities is the fact that the dominant projects are those that use these identities for commercial objectives and which present a generic image of them. This domination can be explained by the many tour operators whose sole concern is to optimize tourism income in the short term and who thus remain indifferent to identity issues. Furthermore, stakeholders who offer an alternative vision scarcely coordinate their initiatives. Associations that bring together a region’s stakeholders, such as the one in Taliouine, are recent and rare initiatives. Proposals from other stakeholders are still poorly integrated. It remains to be seen whether the stakeholder meeting organized by the researchers in Tighdouine will, in fact, be followed up by common action. The project managers often prefer to play the national and international network card than the local coordination one. Therefore, the possible negative effect of the interconnectedness dynamic can be seen. Finally, projects promoting territorialized identities receive little support from public authorities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To date, the intentions declared by the provincial authorities to encourage coordination between tourism stakeholders and to form associations that bring them together, in the framework of the Pays d’Accueil Touristiques, have not been implemented. Mayors state that they do not have the means to coordinate the projects, and public authorities appear to be lacking a genuine will to encourage the implementation of tourism projects that promote identities in the marginalized regions. One could even go so far as to say that there is a genuine reluctance to support Amazigh identity-related projects to any extent, as they are perceived as a potential source of political tension within a “Moroccan springtime” context, and could be conducive to the affirmation of identity demands in Morocco. Furthermore, public authorities’ tourism action scales (in the PATs framework, this is the Province) do not correspond to the identification scales that the identity-project managers are striving to promote. This leads to a juxtaposition of scales for tourism management and identity referents. In this way, public authorities are holding back the process of identity reterritorialization.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Identity-based tourism projects in the Moroccan mountains show that identities could simultaneously foster forms of interconnectedness and embeddedness, and not necessarily just one or the other. In these projects, interconnectedness coexists with an embeddedness dynamic: project managers mobilize transnational, national and local stakeholder networks and reinvest equally in globalized tourism and political imaginaries, and localized identities. In this regard, tourism appears to be a real driver for circulating identity referents, which are seized by the stakeholders to redefine identities and their territorial links. Interconnectedness benefits embeddedness-based strategies.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Nevertheless, the strategies implemented are both multiple and complex. This diversity illustrates the central issue of reinterpreting/translating referents in circulation on a global scale with its own language and reference system. The territorial embeddedness of identities constructed by the actors involved varies according to the strategies used. Through projects promoting heritage practices and objects, heritage and militant tourism stakeholders contribute to building identities rooted in the regions they describe as lived-in territories, appropriated by the inhabitants. Yet, identities constructed through these projects, for lack of being truly collective, are still achieved by a heterogeneous group of tourism stakeholders who disagree on the political connotations of Amazigh identity. As such, several Amazigh identities can be differentiated: popular, heritage, militant and commercial. People who view Berberity as a commercial opportunity and as more than just an aim in itself, run against the dynamic of identity territorialization: by using tourism imaginaries inherited from the colonial period, they contribute to widening the gap between tourists’ imaginaries and the identities of heritage and militant tourism stakeholders. The latter’s efforts to be “vectors of identity” are further hampered by the lack of support from public authorities, who back projects that are outside of the scope of this “identity”. Amazigh identities are, therefore, being reinvented through a kind of “makeshift identity” process (Bayart 1996) within the networks – in the Latourian sense of the term – involving stakeholders, objects, discourse and identity practices, whose relationships undergo constant reconstruction when tensions arise between the different forms of territorial adhesion and between groups of tourism stakeholders who do not give identity the same place and meaning in their projects.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Amselle J.-L., 2000, Branchements: anthropologie de l’universalité des cultures, Paris, Flammarion.</reference>
        <reference>Appadurai A., 2001, Après le colonialisme. Les conséquences culturelles de la globalisation, Paris, Payot.</reference>
        <reference>Bayart J.-F., 1996, L’illusion identitaire, Paris, Fayard.</reference>
        <reference>Beck U., 2006, Qu’est ce que le cosmopolitisme, Paris, Flammarion.</reference>
        <reference>Boujrouf S., 2004, “Patrimonialisation de la montagne au Marc, le rôle du tourisme en question”, SaighBousta R. (dir), Le tourisme durable, réalités et perspectives marocaines et internationales, Marrakech, Faculté des Lettres de l’Université CadiAyyad, Marrakech, pp. 57-70</reference>
        <reference>Castells M., 1996, The power of identity, London, Blackwell.</reference>
        <reference>Cauvin-Verner C., 2008, “Les Hommes bleus du Sahara, ou l’autochtonie globalisée”, Civilisations, n° 57, pp. 57-73.</reference>
        <reference>Cazes G., 1989, Le tourisme international: mirage ou stratégie d’avenir ?, Paris, Hatier.</reference>
        <reference>Debarbieux B., 2012, “Tourisme, imaginaires et identités: inverser le point de vue”, Via@, Les imaginaires touristiques, n° 1, 2012, mis en ligne le 16 mars 2012.</reference>
        <reference>Debarbieux B., 2006, “Prendre position: réflexions sur les ressources et les limites de la notion d’identité engéographie”, L’Espace Géographique, n° 4, pp. 340-354.</reference>
        <reference>Debarbieux B., Del Biaggio C. et Petite M., 2008, “Spatialités et territorialités du tourisme. Dialectique du flux et de l’ancrage dans les Alpes”, Civilisations, n° 57, pp. 74-89.</reference>
        <reference>Doquet A. &amp; Le Menestrel S., 2006, “Tourisme culturel, réseaux et recompositions sociales”, Autrepart, n° 40, pp. 2-11.</reference>
        <reference>Erb M., 2001, “Le tourisme et la quête de la culture Manggarai”, Anthropologie et sociétés, n° 2, pp. 93-108.</reference>
        <reference>Featherstone D., Phillips R., Waters J., 2007, “Spatialities of transnational networks”, Global Networks, n° 4, pp. 383-391.</reference>
        <reference>Giddens A., 1994, Les conséquences de la modernité, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Latour B., 2006, Changer de société: refaire de la sociologie, Paris, La Découverte.</reference>
        <reference>Massey D., 1991, “A Global Sense of Place”, Marxism Today, n° 38, pp. 24-29.</reference>
        <reference>Nash C., 2000, “Performativity in practice: some recent work in cultural geography”, Progress in Human Geography, n° 4, pp. 653-664.</reference>
        <reference>Picard M., 1992, Bali: tourisme culturel et culture touristique, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Popp H., 1999, “Le tourisme de montagne dans le Haut Atlas central: état des lieux” in Berriane M. et Popp H., Le tourisme au Maghreb: diversification du produit et développement régional et local, Rabat, Publications de la FLSH, pp. 183-194.</reference>
        <reference>Ramou H., 2009, « L’émergence et le développement du tourisme de montagne dans le Maroc colonial et postcolonia l » in Zytnicki C. et Kazdaghli H., Le tourisme dans l’Empire français. Politiques, pratiques et imaginaires 19e – 20e siècles, Paris, Publications de la Société française d’histoire d’outre-mer, pp. 347-367.</reference>
        <reference>Ricœur P., 1985, Temps et récit. Tome III: Le temps raconté, Paris, Le Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Stock M., 2006, “Construire l’identité par la pratique des lieux” in De Biase A. et Rossi C., Chez nous. Territoires et identités dans les mondes contemporains, Paris, La Villette.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">The increasing number of symposiums on heritage and tourism in the fringe areas of Morocco is indicative of this trend. One example is the symposium in Ouarzazate, November 2011, entitled “Heritage Resources and Alternatives for Tourism – Between Oases and Mountains”.</note>
        <note id="2">Charter for Sustainable Tourism, UNWTO, 1995 ; Global code of Ethics for Tourism, UNWTO 2001; The Quebec Declaration on Ecotourism, UNEP and UNWTO, 2002.</note>
        <note id="3">Haut-commissariat au Plan, Prospective Maroc 2030. Tourisme 2030, quelles ambitions pour le Maroc ?, 2011 [Office of the High Commissioner for Planning, Forecast for Morocco 2030, Tourism 2030 – what are Morocco’s ambitions?, 2011].</note>
        <note id="4">United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, 2007.</note>
        <note id="5">Militants use the term “Amazigh” which means “free man”. They maintain that this avoids any reference to the colonial period, which systemized the use of the term “Berber” and gave it negative connotations.</note>
        <note id="6">This network, created in 2011, is a project inspired by those who oversee the Maroc Inédit association, which currently manages the “pays du safran” route and the hostels network created by the NGO Migrations &amp; Développement in the Siroua region (Anti-Atlas).</note>
        <note id="7">Interview with the Vice President of Association Yagour de développement, Tighdouine, 9 March 2011.</note>
    </notes>
</article>