<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_MATSABR_41-76_Ta_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/625" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.625</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>7</numero>
        <annee>2015</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="da Silveira" prenom="Marcos A.T.">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="pt_MATSABR_41-75_Ua_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/630" lang="pt">Urbanização turística no Brasil : um foco em Florianópolis – Santa Catarina</publication>
                <publication id="fr_MATSABR_42-80_Ua_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/617" lang="fr">Urbanisation touristique au Brésil : l’exemple de Florianópolis – Santa Catarina</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Associate Professor, Department of Geography, Universidade Federal do Paraná 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Rodrigues" prenom="Adyr B.">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="pt_MATSABR_41-75_Ua_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/630" lang="pt">Urbanização turística no Brasil : um foco em Florianópolis – Santa Catarina</publication>
                <publication id="fr_MATSABR_42-80_Ua_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/617" lang="fr">Urbanisation touristique au Brésil : l’exemple de Florianópolis – Santa Catarina</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Associate Professor, Department of Geography, Universidade do São Paulo 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Touristic Urbanization in Brazil : A Focus on Florianópolis – Santa Catarina</titre>
    <resume>
        This article is an approach the tourism development in Brazil focusing on the case of Florianópolis, city located in coastal zone of the State of Santa Catarina in southern Brazil. The objective is to discuss the socio-spatial transformations induced by the development of tourism in Florianópolis. In Brazil, tourism development is a process observed in the last three decades and mainly due to the growth of sunshine tourism practices and beach in several places located in the coastal area of the country, generating rearrangements in their organization socio-spatial. In most cases, impacts environmental, social and economic, negatives accompany this growth. In this context, it consider needed to put into practice, both in Florianópolis in the various places located in the coastal zone of Brazil, actions of tourism planning to minimize the negatives impacts of tourism and, at the same time, maximize its positive effects.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            In this article we address touristic urbanization on Brazil coastal zone focusing on the case of Florianópolis city, also known as Santa Catarina Island. The city of Florianópolis is the capital of Santa Catarina State and is located in Brazil’s south coast. The choice of Florianópolis as subject of analysis is due to the fact that it is one of the most touristified locations of the country’s south coast. In this context, this present work aims to present succinctly social-spatial changes promoted by tourism in Florianópolis, particularly those arising from touristic urbanization. In methodological terms, this work is based on bibliographic survey about the theme on screen and documents, reports and statistic data analysis on tourism in Florianópolis, as well as observation of city’s reality through field visitations.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Touristic Urbanization in Brazil Coastal Zone : a summary</section>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            In Brazil, touristic urbanization is a process observed especially over the last three decades, and is result of the growth of sun and beach tourism practices in several cities located across the country’s coastal zone, engendering rearrangements in its social-spatial organization. This touristic urbanization is characterized by the appearance and/or expansion of tourist resort-type complexes and urban centres – city-type tourist stations, whose touristic function is predominant (EQUIPE MIT, 2002 ; SILVEIRA, 2014), and that has generated economic, social and environmental changes in Brazilian coastline, according to several authors (RODRIGUES, 1999 ; LOPES JUNIOR, 2000 ; CRUZ, 2000 ; ABREU, 2005 ; TOMASI, 2011).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            In fact, especially after the 70’s, tourism is appointed as one of the vectors of significant territorial changes in Brazil’s coastal zone. Initially, with massification of practices linked to sun and beach tourism an intense process of urban expansion and real estate speculation has occurred in the country’s southeast. Next was the south coast, and more recently, northeast coast, where what has been called “real estate-tourist expansion” is marked by a new stage of sun and beach tourism development in Brazil, particularly from the early 90’s. This development is stimulated both by governmental agents actions and private promoters – businessmen and investors – established in Brazil’s most economically dynamic regions such as São Paulo and in other countries such as Spain, Italy and Portugal (SILVA, 2007 ; ANJOS, 2008 ; FONSECA, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            In this context, we can highlight two dimensions of tourism recent development in Brazil. The first is the spatial structuring, promoted with participation of federal, state and municipal governments, establishing conditions for private investments attraction through implantation of urban-regional infrastructures (airports, roads, basic sanitation, electrification, urban reforms etc.). This dimension is of key importance for the understanding of touristification process in several places of Brazil’s coastal zone, once public policies, by establishing the logic of spatial structuring, have contributed to direct touristic flows in national scale to regions previously little touristified.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            The second dimension as important as the first refers to private actors actions – investors and real estate promoters – who promoted investments on the implantation of tourism and leisure equipment (hotels, resorts, theme parks, second residence condominiums, etc.) in regional scale, making tourism in Brazil a more attractive business. Recent researches point Brazil as the fifth most sought-after country in the world for multinational investments linked to tourism (MELLO &amp;amp; GOLDENSTEIN, 2010). It is in this context that over the last two decades several international hotel chains have established themselves in places under touristification process, altering tourism economy basis in these places, in most cases in detriment of local population (COMERLATTO, 2015).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            Indeed, the arrival of large hotel chains, international-standard resorts and other tourism businesses, have had economic, social and environmental impacts of all kinds. In most cases, tourism development has been followed by several negative impacts. The first of them is the environmental impact reflected on uncontrolled extraction of natural resources. The second one is the social impact resulting in non-inclusion of local population in the process of tourism development, especially through disfigurement of traditional communities’ culture and way of life (RODRIGUES, 1999, LOPES JUNIOR, 2000 ; CAVALCANTI &amp;amp; LEAL, 2010).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            The third is the economic impact that can be seen in exploitation of local labour force and unfair competition with local basis tourism. This is because most hotel projects in Brazil are still small-sized, which has killed off small district businesses in many Brazilian cities. So one of the questions is how will local basis tourism be able to survive competing with large national and international hotel chains ?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            It is in this context that the touristification process of places in Brazil’s coastal zone has been configured according to the globalized model of “resortization”, in which, besides the phenomenon of second residence (allotments and condominiums), there is also the implantation of hotel complexes (resorts and private holiday clubs such as Clube Med). One of the characteristics of this process is the adaptation of coastal territories to the massified touristic use focused on the practice of sun and beach 3S-type tourism – Sea, Sand and Sun – and even 4S-type – Sea, Sand, Sun and Sex (SILVEIRA, 2014).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            In fact, a quick reading of the Brazilian coastal space touristic urbanization map reveals that tourism has attracted the attention especially of real estate promoters who since a long time have been appropriating the land along the beaches to promote real estate speculation. This speculation, which has strongly impacted the Brazilian northeast coastline over the last decades, has generated new territorial arrangements and urban configurations denominated by some scholars “Real Estate Tourism” (SILVA, 2007 ; CAVALCANTI &amp;amp; LEAL, 2010 ; FERREIRA, 2009 ; FONSECA, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            Specifically these new configurations take on new forms of occupation in the places where tourism has been expanding, with edifications that diverge from the standard historically built, as in the case of traditional second residences, giving rise to private condominiums, resorts, flats, apart hotels, among other types. Such urban forms dispute with local population environmental quality spaces in each location, confirming the process of social-spatial segregation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            In this sense, it is worth noting that this model of occupation and use of land destined to expansion of “Real State Tourism”, has produced many changes in the Brazilian coastal space organization, generating social-spatial segregation and environmental degradation in many places. Associated to the expansion of “Real Estate Tourism” there is the lack of public investments on urban infrastructure – garbage collection and disposal, water supply, sewage collection and treatment, etc. These are among the main factors that cause social-environmental impacts of several dimensions in many touristic places situated along the Brazilian coastal area, as well as give rise to several conflicts between communities and local public power (BARBOSA, 2003 ; ANJOS, 2008 ; HÜFFNER, 2010).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Tourism and Urbanization : the case of Florianópolis</section>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            The city of Florianópolis is located in Brazil south region, in the coast line of Santa Catarina State, between the parallels of latitude 27º50′ S and between the meridians of longitude 48º25′ W (see Fig. 1). Its territory is formed by a large oceanic island, the Island of Santa Catarina that has an area of 424.4km² and by a small continental peninsula with 12.1 km², totalizing 436.5km². Florianópolis has approximately 421,000 inhabitants, according to IBGE latest survey (2010), and during high touristic season, its population exceeds 1,000,000 people among residents and visitors.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            Especially from the 90’s, public and private actors sought to increase tourism participation in Florianópolis economic activities, investing on touristic market at national and international levels. This strategy was succeeded, and in 2013 Florianópolis was ranked among the five main Brazilian tourist destinations (MINISTÉRIO DO TURISMO, 2013).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            Nowadays tourism has been consolidated as one of the most important economic activities for Florianópolis, presenting an increasing flow of tourists, particularly during summer season. This flow is formed both by domestic and foreign tourists, mainly from Argentina, Uruguay, Paraguay and Chile (MINISTÉRIO DO TURISMO, 2013).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            Florianópolis touristification process started in the 80’s, when touristic activity became economically relevant and promoted cultural and landscape changes in the city’s territory. During the 90’s, Florianópolis presence in the media, advertised as the “Island of Magic” and “the country’s capital with the best quality life”, generated an increase in migration and tourist flows, and produced situations such as city centre urban expansion fragmentation to resorts, expanding demand for infrastructure, causing landscape disfigurement, beaches deterioration, real estate speculation, displacement of tradition population from their territories, and functional intervention in urban legislation through new forms of occupation and urban land use (CECCA, 1997 ; SUGAI, 2002 ; SANTIAGO et al., 2009).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            Because of physical-spatial configuration, Florianópolis does not follow the same pattern of urban agglomeration of other cities situated along the Brazilian coastal zone. Their urban centres are spread all over the territory formed by Santa Catarina Island, where communities of fishermen who have lived there for a long time have been transformed into resorts for leisure and sun and beach tourism practices, such as the case of Praia do Jurerê (Jurerê Beach) showed on figure 2.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            As in other places of Brazil’s coastline, most tourists who visit Florianópolis look for practices linked to seaside leisure, particularly those associated to sun and beach tourism. Therefore, these practices are characterized by a strong seasonality, once they depend mainly on summer vacations, a time considered as high season. During low season, Florianópolis has become also popularized among visitors whose primary motivation is business and participation in events and conventions. In five years, the number of tourists who visited Florianópolis practically doubled, going from 780,583 visitors in 2010 to 1.55 million in 2012. This flow of tourists includes visitors from abroad – foreign tourists -, Brazilian visitors of other states and visitors from Santa Catarina (SANTUR, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            As for touristic urbanization in Florianópolis, among the elements that confirm its insertion in this process we can mention high and stable population growth, which has determined the current configuration of its territory. Figure 3 shows the evolution of the city’s urban occupation, representing the years of 1938, 1978, 1990, and 1998, and the zones under urbanization process between 1998 and 2004 (ESPÍNDOLA &amp;amp; SANTIAGO, 2004).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            In the previous figure, the urban nucleus that originated the zone currently qualified as city centre is that close to the continent. Accesses between central nucleus and nucleuses spread through the island’s territory have been occupied as infrastructure and equipment installed expansion were produced in order to meet the increasing tourism demand. This expansion gave rise to new second residence allotments and hotel equipment to attend sun and beach tourism. This originated Florianópolis touristic urbanization process.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            On the other hand, the implantation of touristic equipment in some places unleashed not only the process of social-spatial urban segregation as well as generated the formation of a fragmented urban fabric, giving rise to what Bernal (2005) defines as “islands of urban occupation”, that is, urban agglomerations occupied by touristic activity, fruit of occasional interventions from private or State initiative (in form of public-private partnerships), usually with distinct characteristics of their surroundings, configuring true touristic-territorial enclaves.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            It is worth noticing the fact that in the territory configured by Florianópolis island, the reproduction of the known stages of touristic development that marked touristic places in other countries can be verified in small-scale. The first stage corresponds to limited touristic flows, in which tourism acts as environment’s revelator. In the following stage, mass tourism develops with focus on time and space, becoming a degradation agent of recipient space. After this second stage, usually requalification attempts of appropriating space by tourism arise through territorial planning actions. And the last stage is that of attempting tourism reconciliation with environment, where the environmental dimension is considered in touristic development plans (RUSCHMANN, 1997).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            In the case of Florianópolis, although it is not the historical responsible for the growth of environmental problems found in the place, we can state that in the 80’s touristic expansion started to have a key role in the expansion of natural landscape “creative destruction” (OURIQUES, 1999). This expansion is given with regional road system and the resulting change of the city because of improvement in circulation and transportation routes that increased inter and intra-urban integration nets, a process initiated during the 20’s that persists to this day.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            Since the beginning, still in the 70’s, tourism development in Florianópolis was conducted by the logic of the market, in which real estate speculation has operated as main vector of new forms of urban space use and occupation. Since then, this speculation has been spelling and orienting the island urban growth. Thus, protected environmental heritage sites were expropriated and places with rural characteristics were blended, urbanized and sold for construction of second resident condominiums, resorts, hotels, inns, and tourism equipment. Over the last two decades, touristic urbanization in Florianópolis’ island has intensified and in many places new edifications have been built to meet the growing demand of visitors, replacing and changing rapidly places where local population, formed mainly by fishermen communities lived before.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            In the present, two forms of land instalments coexist in Florianópolis : large allotments with private condominiums and large rural areas enterprises, fruit of great developers, and small properties previously located in traditional population centres that little by little have been subdivided into smaller segments. The first instalment mode is commonly explored either by external capital or local elite. The second, where small properties predominate, the thickening process is irregular and concentrated, with construction of several edifications in the same lot, usually used by tourists with rental purposes, characterizing some type of local population involvement with touristic activity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            With tourism growth, over the last years public investments have been directed to several places in the island, in which infrastructure has been improved, touristic equipment have been built, and then real estate-touristic expansion and occupation have generally occurred, particularly with proliferation of new allotments and edifications. This expansion and occupation took place without adequate planning, that is, in a wayward manner, which has been causing degradation of protected natural areas such as mangroves, sandbanks, dunes and beach zones. Only in 2012, according to the new city Master Plan, stricter guidelines of land use and occupation in the island are expected (PREFEITURA MUNICIPAL DE FLORIANÓPOLIS, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            In figure 4 demarcated Areas of Environmental Preservation in Florianópolis territory are represented, as well as urban occupation zones in Santa Catarina’s island are observed.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            Tourism development in Florianópolis has been stimulated both by public bodies and private promoters that consider natural resources as the main tourist attraction in the island, even if it has only rhetorical effect and market strategy. This strategy has also enforced the market logic as far as job generation for local population is concerned, thus contributing to the strengthening of local economic mono-activity, increasingly dependent on tourism (OURIQUES, 1999 ; MACHADO, 2000).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            In this context, equipment installation and tourist services offer, despite including local population in tourism development, have taken place in a precarious and marginal manner, in most cases causing remoteness of this population from traditional activities, as in the case of fishing. Gradually, local residents were inserted in tourism activities as seasonal and low-paid labour force. This problem deepened with the attraction of labour force from other localities, nurtured by the expectation of been absorbed by the touristic sector, competing, on one hand, with local population and on the other, contributing even more to workers wage reduction in the sector (OURIQUES, 1999).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            Nowadays, Florianópolis coexists with an antagonistic process of territorial occupation. At the same time it seeks to value natural beauties and consolidate its touristic vocation, disorganized occupation of its territory in some places causes waters pollution, permanent preservation areas’ destruction, soil compaction in sharp declivity areas, and transport system collapse that interconnects the places in the island, among other problems that interfere directly in its image of touristic destination (ESPÍNDOLA E SANTIAGO, 2004).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            In this context, Florianópolis natural landscape has been through changes derived from urban growth, stimulated by the “tourism industry” that moves ahead non-stop, towards the island resorts, as seen in figure 05. Deficiencies in urban infrastructure, as well as lack of public power actions in relation to control of environmental preservation areas have caused shortage of natural resources, which still are the main attractions in the island. Although conflicts become more evident during high season, some problems last all year around.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            Over the last holiday seasons, demand has increased in relation to attractions and equipment offer in some spaces such as in the northern part of the island. Localities of Canavieiras, Ingleses, Jurerê and Ponta das Canas present the characteristics of mass tourism with large concentration of people because of easy access. Stretches of sand in the beaches are disputed by bathers, vendors, inadequate constructions and several types of equipment.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            On the other hand, the eastern part of the island, where Lagoa da Conceição, Barra da Lagoa, Praia da Joaquina and Praia Mole are located, is characterized by concentration of hikers presenting infrastructure problems, signs of saturation and water pollution. Traffic congestions are also constant in this same region and get even worse during high season or weekends and long holidays (ESPÍNDOLA &amp;amp; SANTIAGO, 2004). In short, infrastructure and urban equipment distribution are becoming more and more precarious in those places where touristic demand has been growing.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            It has to be recognized that, on one side, tourism growth has produced many urban improvements in Florianópolis, with the implantation of a modern road and transport system, and the increase of services and urban equipment offer. On the other hand, this urban growth has been causing many negative impacts on the environment. With the improvement of access and road expansion, natural areas still preserved in the city are under risk of becoming saturated and degraded places due to intense tourists visitation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            As an example, we can mention the case of beaches situated in the north and southeast of the island that had a strong growth from mid 90’s. Resorts and hotel chains keep on establishing themselves in these regions and the new spaces touristic urbanization process continues without taking due care of environmental impacts and disregarding master plans and environmental legislation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            Over the last decades, urban occupation in the Island has intensified in several places that now concentrate a large amount of touristic equipment, especially hotel enterprises such as private condominiums, apart hotels and resorts (SANTOS, 2009).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            This concentration of touristic equipment aims to attend exclusively growing touristic demand, while local population has hardly benefited from the equipment installed in it. Central and east areas of the island are those that have better urban equipment offer. Then the north region of the island can also be highlighted. On the other hand, in the south region, more recently occupied, urban equipment are still insufficient. And the areas of slopes in the island, densely occupied by local population do not have the minimum of equipment and/or infrastructure, revealing a growing social-spatial segregation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            This picture shows a peculiar model of occupation and land use. We notice the search for touristic expansion profitability to the detriment of social and environmental concerns, which accentuates something recurrent in most touristic places : the exchange value is what dictates and frames the appropriation of land by tourism. Indeed, in Florianópolis’ island, several urban centres reflect the laws of real estate market. They are valued according to location, surroundings, neighbourhood, accessibility, equipment and urban services offer (electric power, water, sewage, street paving, etc.). The real estate market determines cost and origin of who will occupy each and every place. As the land represents wealth and poverty rates, real estate speculation and appreciation orient public services. Thus, the business class that has more access to the State allies itself with public power and has influenced for a long time urban-touristic growth in the Island (OURIQUES, 1999).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Final considerations</section>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            Inequality in benefits distribution that come from economic and touristic growth largely explains the increase of social-spatial segregation in Florianópolis, as well as in any other large city in the globalized world. Those inhabitants of the place who cannot afford privileged location sites with accessibility, transport, energy, water, sewage and a good neighbourhood are pushed to the outskirts, living in areas and/or districts that do not have basic urban infrastructure and, usually occupy sites illegally.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            In Florianópolis, the conception of tourism adopted by private promoters and public power indicates that social contrasts between rich and poor are the perverse face of tourism development. The lost of quality of life dimension in the process of tourism expansion may, in the near future, associate this activity to social iniquities and to the increase of negative impacts of the famous “Island of Magic” on the environment.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            Several studies have warned to the fact that in developed countries many touristic regions have put at risk their natural resources and cultural heritage without realizing what they have lost, for they sold their land and their right of use of nature. In this context, in Florianópolis it is imperative to put into practice actions of territorial and touristic regulation at the risk of destroying itself, as Jost Krippendorf, one of the great tourism thinkers, warned many years ago with his work “Les dévoreurs des paysages : le tourisme, doit-il detruire les sites qui le font vivre ?” (KRIPPENDORF, 1977).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            In the present context, tourism as social practice and cultural experience emerges strengthened by the process of globalization, influencing urbanization of many places around the world, giving them new spatial configurations (KNAFOU, 2007). As economic activity, tourism develops itself based on space production, characterized by territories “consumption”. This development may generate both benefits and losses to societies, the economy and to the environment of destination places.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>ABREU, C. V. de. Urbanização, apropriação do espaço, conflitos e turismo : Um estudo de caso de Angra dos Reis. Niterói, 2005. Dissertação de Mestrado, Faculdade de Arquitetura e Urbanismo, Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niterói, 2005.</reference>
        <reference>ANJOS, K. L. Turismo em Cidades Litorâneas e Transformações Sócio-espaciais em Porto de Galinhas, PE. In : Simpósio Espaço Metropolitano, Turismo e Mercado Imobiliário, Fortaleza, CE, 2008.</reference>
        <reference>BARBOSA, K. Turismo em Armação dos Búzios (RJ) : percepções locais dos problemas da cidade e diretrizes prioritárias de apoio à gestão ambiental. Dissertação de Mestrado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Ciência Ambiental da Universidade Federal Fluminense. Niterói, 2003.</reference>
        <reference>BERNAL, M. C. C. A nova configuração territorial do Nordeste : desigualdade e fragmentação. Cadernos do LOGEPA, Dep.de Geociências da Universidade Federal da Paraíba, vol. 4, n. 1, 2005.</reference>
        <reference>BRASIL. MINISTÉRIO DO TURISMO. Documento Referencial Turismo no Brasil 2010-2014. Available at : &lt; http://www.dadosefatos.turismo.gov.br/dadosefatos/outros_estudos/Documento_referencial/&gt; Access on Nov 19th 2013.</reference>
        <reference>CAVALCANTI, M. S. &amp; LEAL, S.M.R. De praias desertas a paraísos turísticos : A ação do capital imobiliário no Litoral Sul da Região Metropolitana do Recife. I Seminário Nacional de Governança Urbana e Desenvolvimento Metropolitano. Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte, Natal, 2010.</reference>
        <reference>CECCA – Centro de Estudos Cultura e Cidadania. Unidades de Conservação e Áreas Protegidas da Ilha de Santa Catarina : caracterização e legislação. Florianópolis, 1997.</reference>
        <reference>COMERLATTO, L. M. A cadeia de valor do turismo. Estudo sobre os resorts internacionais no Nordeste do Brasil. Tese de Doutorado. Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geografia, Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, 2015.</reference>
        <reference>CRUZ, R. C. Política de turismo e território. São Paulo : Contexto, 2000.</reference>
        <reference>DEBETIR, E. Gestão de Unidades de Conservação sob influência de áreas urbanas. Diagnóstico e estratégias de gestão na Ilha de Santa Catarina – BR. Tese de Doutorado, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Engenharia Civil – Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, 2006.</reference>
        <reference>ESPINDOLA, L. R. ; SANTIAGO, A. G. Os efeitos perversos do turismo na Ilha de Santa Catarina. Relatório final pesquisa cientifica PIBIC/CNPQ UFSC, 2004.</reference>
        <reference>EQUIPE MIT. Tourismes 1. Lieux comuns, Belin, Coll. Mappemonde, Paris, 2002.</reference>
        <reference>FERREIRA, Â. L ; SILVA, A. F. C. Para além do muro alto : “Turismo Imobiliário” e novas configurações sócio-espaciais na Região Metropolitana de Natal – RN/Brasil. In : VALENÇA, M. M ;</reference>
        <reference>FERREIRA, L. S. Planejamento e Ordenamento territorial do Turismo na Região Metropolitana de Natal-RN. Programa de Pós-Graduação em Geografia da Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte, Natal, 2009.</reference>
        <reference>GONÇALVES, T. C. A urbanização turística de Florianópolis : o papel das redes hoteleiras nacionais e internacionais. Anais do XIV Encontro Nacional da ANPUR, maio de 2011, Rio de Janeiro, Brasil.</reference>
        <reference>HÜFFNER, J. G. P. Estudo sobre os impactos do Turismo em Áreas Naturais em processo de urbanização : O Caso da Ilha de Cotijuba, Belém – PA. Dissertação de Mestrado, Programa de Mestrado em Desenvolvimento e Meio Ambiente Urbano da Universidade da Amazônia, 2011.</reference>
        <reference>KNAFOU, R. « L’urbain et le tourisme. Une construction laborieuse », dans DUHAMEL, P. et KNAFOU, R. (dir.), Les mondes urbains du tourisme, Paris, Belin, 2007, p. 9-21.</reference>
        <reference>KRIPPENDORF, J. Les dévoreurs des paysages : le tourisme, doit-il détruire les sites qui le font vivre ? Lausanne : Edition 24 Heures, 1977.</reference>
        <reference>LOPES JUNIOR, E. População e meio ambiente nas paisagens da urbanização do Nordeste : o caso de Natal. In : MELLO, G. &amp; GOLDENSTEIN, M. Perspectivas da hotelaria no Brasil. BNDS. 2010.</reference>
        <reference>MACHADO, E. V. Florianópolis : um lugar em tempo de globalização. Tese de Doutorado – Faculdade de Filosofia, Letras e Ciências Humanas Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo (SP), 2000.</reference>
        <reference>PREFEITURA MUNICIPAL DE FLORIANÓPOLIS. Anteprojeto do Plano Diretor de Florianópolis. 2012.</reference>
        <reference>RODRIGUES, A. B. Turismo e espaço : rumo a um conhecimento transdisciplinar. São Paulo : Editora Hucitec, 1999, 2ª. Ed.</reference>
        <reference>RUSCHMANN, D. Turismo e Planejamento Sustentável : A Proteção do Meio Ambiente. São Paulo, Editora Papirus, 1997.</reference>
        <reference>OURIQUES, H. R. A apologia do turismo em Florianópolis-SC : mitos e contradições. Revista de Ciências Humanas, Florianópolis, n.25, p. 63-81, abril de 1999.</reference>
        <reference>TOMASI, V. T. Urbanização turística litorânea e grandes projetos urbanos promovidos por investimentos públicos em Belém (PA) e Fortaleza (CE) entre 1990 e 2010. Dissertação de Mestrado. Departamento de Geografia, FFLCH, Universidade de São Paulo, 2011.</reference>
        <reference>SANTOS, F. M. dos. O desenvolvimento do setor hoteleiro em Florianópolis – Santa Catarina – Brasil. Trabalho apresentado no XII Encontro de Geógrafos de América Latina, EGAL 2009. Montevideo.</reference>
        <reference>SANTA CATARINA TURISMO S/A. Pesquisa de demanda turística 2012. Florianópolis : SANTUR, 2012. Available at : &lt; http://www.santur.sc.gov.br/estatistica-do-turismo-catarinense-santur.html&gt; Access on Nov. 19th 2013.</reference>
        <reference>SILVEIRA, M. A. T. da. Geografia aplicada ao turismo. Fundamentos teórico-práticos. Editora InterSaberes, Curitiba, 2014.</reference>
        <reference>SUGAI, M. I. Segregação Silenciosa : investimento e distribuição sócio-espacial na área conurbada de Florianópolis. Tese de Doutorado. São Paulo : FAU-USP, 2002.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
</article>