<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_MHCCH_50-65_Fa_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3083" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.3083</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>14</numero>
        <annee>2018</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="3038">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            “ Bons baisers de… » : tourisme et touristes dans la saga James Bond
        </original>
        <traduction lang="it" source="3126">“Dalla Russia con… ”: turismo e turisti nella saga di James Bond</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Chevrier" prenom="Marie-Hélène" email="marie-helene.chevrier@ens-lyon.org">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_MHCCH_50-68_Bd_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3038" lang="fr">“ Bons baisers de… » : tourisme et touristes dans la saga James Bond</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Doctor of Geography, Laboratoire Image, Ville, Environnement (UMR 7362), Université de Strasbourg. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Huvet" prenom="Chloé" email="chloehuvet@gmail.com">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_MHCCH_50-68_Bd_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3038" lang="fr">“ Bons baisers de… » : tourisme et touristes dans la saga James Bond</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Doctor of Musicology, Conservatoire à Rayonnement Régional de Perpignan/Université de Perpignan Via Domitia (CRESEM). 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>From James Bond with love: tourism and tourists in the Bond saga </titre>
    <resume>
        ‘We could meet at the Saint Sophia mosque. – Like we were tourists,’ suggests James Bond to Russian agent Tatiana Romanova in From Russia with Love. Since 1962 and the release of Dr. No, tourism and tourists have played an important role in the James Bond saga in terms of affording viewers some escapism. Each film turns into a picture postcard as it takes the hero off to new destinations. The Bond films play on archetypes of destination (which they reinforce) and of tourism practices. These archetypal representations, from mass tourism to luxury tourism and from collective practices to individual practices, are all linked in the films to the image and sound (music and sound design) environments. In this article, we highlight how the Bond saga reflects the evolution of the core tourism practices and representations in Western societies from the 1960s to the present day.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The James Bond film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Dr. No</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> opens in Jamaica. Its premiere on 5 October 1962 was held almost two months to the day after the island’s proclamation of independence on 6 August 1962. Although the film’s opening scene focuses on the strategic secrets behind Britain’s presence in Jamaica, the island is presented throughout, in both the images and the soundtrack, as a paradise island that was very popular with tourists at the time. As the scene shifts to London,the hero appears for the first time, playing Baccarat at the Les Ambassadeurs Club’s Le Cercle, launching an almost uninterrupted film saga spanning 56 years. From the very first moments of the very first James Bond film, then, tourism-associated places and practices are present.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This substantial collection of films (24 feature films released since 1962, generating $7.1 billion in international box office revenue to date</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) has generated an extensive body of literature in a number of different fields, including film studies. Each new release has given rise to scientific and journalistic articles on the different economic, aesthetic and sociological aspects of the ‘James Bond phenomenon’ (Lindler, 2009; Simpson, 2006). With the nationalities of Bond’s enemies evolving in parallel with Western politics, the films have also been subject to analysis from a geopolitical perspective (Dodds, 2003; Black, 2005; Duprat, 2015). Furthermore, the media often highlight the impact of the films on a location’s notoriety and economy. However, with the notable exception of Bourgeat and Bras in 2014, few have looked in depth at the impact that the films have had on places. Bourgeat and Bras (2014) noted the significant role played by franchising in the global creation, or reinforcement, and diffusion of landscape and cultural archetypes. These archetypes, which include the paradise island, the mountain resort, the seaside resort and leisure venue (casinos, amusement parks), are often the same as those found in tourism activity. The creation of such archetypes has been elucidated by the French research group Equipe MIT (2005). Those that appear in the James Bond saga are not, however, limited to tourist destinations. They also often apply to the characters, especially the tourist characters. Indeed, Michael Denning (2009) has pointed out that Bond could be considered the ‘ideal tourist’. Little attention has been paid, however, to the other tourists in the films, despite the fact that they populate these paradisiacal places visited by the hero, either as his opponents or his adjuvants. Most are presented as ‘travel idiots’ (Urbain, 1991). Very often, they are foils, introducing a comic element into the situation. They are such an intrinsic part of the Bond franchise that they also feature in all the parodic films inspired by the secret agent (Johnny English, OSS 117, Austin Powers) and in the competing franchises (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the Jason Bourne films, the Kingsman films). Both mass and luxury tourism are represented in the Bond films, allowing a very diverse audience to recognise both themselves and the other. These representations are nevertheless not fixed, and the main focus of this study relates to the longevity of the James Bond franchise. We will highlight here the way in which the saga has developed over its 56 years in terms of narrative, visual elements and soundtrack, since these reflect the evolution of the core tourism practices and representations in Western societies.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The corpus used in this study comprised the 24 official films produced by EON Productions, MGM and United Artists (excluding the 1983 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Never Say Never Again </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and the 1967 parodic </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). We refer to this collection as a ‘saga’ in the Umberto Eco sense of the word: ‘the saga repeats, in spite of its historicized form, celebration in appearance the passage of time, the same story’ (Eco, 1985: 169). The uniqueness of this series of films lies in its longevity and in the multiplicity of actors who have interpreted the title role (six to date). Each of these actors, while retaining the protagonist’s main characteristics, has brought unique personality traits to the character. The plots are all based around the same principles, but the threat facing the hero has evolved over time in line with the international geopolitical context (Dodds, 2003), as have the representations of the places and practices mobilised.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Set within the field of tourism geography and drawing on a cinematographic and musical analysis of some key extracts, this study first highlights the recurring background presence of tourists and tourism that runs through the Bond saga and then looks at how the saga reflects the major developments that have taken place in tourism practices and the tourism ecumene.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. The Bond saga: touristic blockbusters?</section>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In his study of Ian Fleming’s novels, Denning noted that ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">travel and tourism make up much of the interest and action of a bond thriller</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’. Indeed, tourism influenced Fleming to such an extent that his prose sometimes read more like a tourist guide (Denning, 2009: 64).Tourism is omnipresent in the films, and each new opus has presented an opportunity to visit new destinations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Tourists are forever: a contrasting representationof tourists</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The way in which Bond is portrayed as a tourist and the representation of the tourists themselves in the films take various forms and offer a contrasting picture that fulfils different functions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            The man with the golden visa: 007, the ideal tourist
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">First, the ‘guided tour’ aspect can be a very useful tool for providing the viewer with the geographical context. For example, in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Man with the Golden Gun</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1974), Bond takes a tourist ferry from Macao to Hong Kong, giving the viewer a whistle-stop tour of the different islands in the bay.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Bond’s cover story during his missions is generally that he is on a business trip as an employee of Universal Exports. When he is accompanied by a female, however, his cover involves playing the tourist. On these occasions, honeymoons and romantic trips form part of his recurring alibis, such as when he is on the Orient Express with Russian agent Tatiana Romanova (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From Russia with Love</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1963), crossing the United States by train with Solitaire (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Live and Let Die</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1973), infiltrating the poker game with Vesper Lynd in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2006) or entering Bolivia incognito with agent Fields (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Quantum of Solace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2008). Even his own luggage participates in his cover story. His very ordinary and apparently harmless tourist suitcases conceal various weapons, including explosives and machine gun cameras, in short, ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Everything for a man on holiday</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">,’ according to Q (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Licence to Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1989).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Whether on honeymoon or on a business trip, Bond would therefore be classed as a tourist in the eyes of the World Tourism Organization. As mentioned, Denning has even categorised him as the ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ideal tourist, always alone and always superior</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (Denning, 2009: 66). The secret agent possesses a very strong touristic capital, in the Bourdieu sense of the word (1979). Wherever he is in the world and whatever he is doing, he has substantial monetary capital to hand, always in the appropriate currency, which seamlessly provides for all his needs and satisfies his taste for luxury tourism. We know, for example, that he is in the habit of visiting the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Yacht Club</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> when he goes to Hong Kong (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Die Another Day</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2002), the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">New Otani</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> ($303 per night) when in Tokyo (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">You Only LiveTwice</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1967) and the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Cipriani</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> ($1,547 per night) when in Venice (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2006). Furthermore, he always changes hotels when the standard does not seem to meet his high expectations (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Quantum of Solace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2008). In addition to his monetary capital, 007 has cognitive capital. Despite the fact he never has a map, GPS or a dictionary, he never encounters orientation problems or linguistic difficulties. His crowning capital, however, could be described as political. The secret agent never encounters any problems when crossing borders, even though he travels with false papers and a number of dangerous items. He even seems immune to all the inconveniences that jet lag and changes in diet can bring. This idealisation of travelling, which forms an intrinsic part of the Bond character, resurfaces regularly in other films. The OSS 117 character probably best illustrates this, albeit from a zany, assumed unrealistic perspective. For example, he arrives in Cairo without knowing a single word of Arabic but manages to have an in-depth conversation and sing in the language the very next day. He has a much poorer sense of direction than Bond, however, because he gets lost in the medina (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">OSS 117: Cairo, Nest of Spies</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2006). All of these Bond qualities have been subject to derision, and all of them underline the gap between the professional traveller (Bond) and the simple tourist.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            Squeezing the living daylights out of travel: the touristic mass
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The exceptional touristic capital that 007 is endowed with sets him in stark contrast to the touristic mass depicted in the films, which seems to be systematically presented to valorise the hero, including physically (Bourgeat and Bras, 2014). This reflects the low opinion that the hero himself has of tourists. Fleming revealed in his novel </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From a View to a Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1960) that Bond does not like Paris: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It was the heart that was gone – pawned to the tourists […], pawned to the scum of the world who had gradually taken the town over</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (Fleming, 1960). This disenchantment is rendered well in the attendant film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A View to a Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, where the hordes of tourists congesting the streets and pavements complicate the hero’s task during a high-speed chase that begins at the Trocadero and ends on a bateau-mouche (17:00-20:35)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. In addition to the impersonal mass of tourists (represented as mere spectators who generally just get in Bond’s way) are the unfriendly locals in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A View to a Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The Parisian taxi driver, in particular, is painted in a very unflattering light, combining boorishness with a caricatured French accent when he speaks English. He only serves as a hindrance to the hero, and the action is interspersed with his swearwords and exaggeratedly hopeless facial expressions as he sees the secret agent drive away in his taxi (18:43-19:10). The montage in this film thus accentuates the schism between the seriousness and urgency of Bond’s mission and the inadequate attitude of the other characters present in the scene.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The profile of the tourist in the Bond films is not very flattering. Always white, Western and recognisable by their casual dress (shorts, shirt, sun hat) and shoulder-strap camera, they are very close to the ‘ridiculous stereotype’ of the travel idiot: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">a big red nose, burnt by the sun, balancing opaque pince-nez and topped off with a small white bucket hat</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (Urbain, 1991: 11)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.The ridiculousness of this archetype is reinforced by the </span>miseen scène <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and music in the Bangkok canals (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">klongs</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) scene in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Man with the Golden Gun</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1974; 55:45-01:00:46). In this film, the tourists sport the regulatory sun hats, and their cameras never leave their faces. The flowery dresses, garish tunics and shirts emblazoned with pseudo-ethnic motifs that the costume designer Elsa Fennell dressed some of the protagonists in also reflect a chintzy exoticism. Totally out of keeping with the context, some of the female characters wear showy jewellery, most notably the female companion of Sheriff J.W. Pepper, who is bedecked with a heavy pearl necklace to match her nail polish. Confined to the retrograde and reductive role of the ‘little housewife’ in her fuchsia pink outfit, all the female stereotypes of American classical cinema and, more broadly, of the patriarchal studio system are concentrated in this character. She is superficial, extravagant, naive, talkative and dependent on her husband (Mulvey, 1989: 14-26, 29-38). As for the sheriff, he could not fit the description of the travel idiot better.The tightly framed shots accentuate his unflattering appearance, while his outrageous acting makes him an unlikeable character with an annoying voice. His coarseness and contempt for the local environment (delighted ridicule tinged with racism of the Thai men who fall in the water when 007 slices their boat in half as it sits across his path [59:51-59:56]; invective against the baby elephant searching his pockets [59:57]) is finally turned against him in a gag that is music-led. Almost entirely absent from the entire boat chase scene, the orchestral accompaniment makes a noteworthy reappearance when the baby elephant takes revenge for the sheriff’s insults and slaps to his trunk by pushing him into the water with an incensed trumpet. The character’s farcical nosedive head first into the canal accompanied by a big scream (01:00:28) is replicated in a long, descending glissando on a harp that is typical of Mickey-Mousing</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">,thus taking the form of ‘stylised sound effects of visual events’ (Mari, 2007: 52). A dual correspondence is created here between, on the one hand, the musical design and the visual trajectory and, on the other, the water and the harp, which is culturally and symbolically associated with aquatic environments. Comically loaded through its descriptiveness and conspicuousness, this Mickey-Mousing thus reinforces the ‘now the boot is on the other foot’ gag and contributes to the laughable portrait of the tourist. Emblematic of the lighter tone of the Bond films featuring Roger Moore, the use of this musical process is repeated several times during the film, sometimes more joyfully than others, as the composer himself admitted: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Director Hamilton liked an occasional nod to the humor: delicately amusing clarinet for Nick Nack, and wah-wah trumpet sounds for Bond attacking sumo wrestlers’ private parts […], a slide whistle to the daring car stunt when Bond and passenger J. W. Pepper do a complete flip in mid-air. “Earlier on, I’d have played it for all it was worth as a really dangerous moment,” Barry said, “I just took the liberty of poking fun at it. It made a mockery of Bond, looking back on it”’</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Burlingame, 2012: 121).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sometimes 007 is mistaken for one of these tourists. For example, in the preceding scene, a young hawker climbs into his boat in the middle of the high-speed chase and tries to sell him an elephant statuette. Bond, who does not really appreciate the boy’s error, brusquely sees him off, pushing him into the water. The boy shouts after the hero: ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Bloody tourist!</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (58:07).The capital that the touristic mass possesses is much lower than Bond’s, both financially and cognitively. Wanting to explore the country but not wanting to learn the language, they prefer organised trips and guided tours. What we see presented here is mass tourism with a clear recreational goal.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This tourism, which is characterised by a ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">controlled relaxation of emotional self-restraint</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (Equipe MIT, 2005, p. 341) made possible by the break with everydayness, leads to a certain recklessness among the tourists in the films who, blissfully unaware of how close the threat is, appear all the more out of step with the hero. As such, they very often become his involuntary opponents. Alongside the Parisian scene in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A View to a Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1985) examined above, one of the best examples of this is the chase through the centre of the Swiss ski resort Grindelwald in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On Her Majesty’s Secret Service </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(1969). An old-fashioned Christmas song entitled ‘Do You Know How Christmas Trees Are Grown?’ (performed by Nina van Pallandt and a children’s choir) foregrounds the soundtrack. The innocent lyrics, the tourists’ laughter and shrieks of joy and the shimmering colours of the sets and the characters’ clothes all counterpoint the danger faced by Bond, who tries to hide among the crowd. The increasing rapidity of the intercutting generates a feeling of suffocation, as if the agent were surrounded on all sides by faceless opponents. The tourists’ carefree fun paradoxically seems to precipitate the loss of the hero, who is saved in extremis by Tracy (01:40:12-01:43:10). The tourists also play the role of adjuvants, although rather more rarely. With the exception of Sheriff Pepper who comes directly to the aid of 007, however, these are generally unwitting adjuvants who have had their vehicles or accessories requisitioned by Bond.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. A touristic view to a kill: a very Western representation of tourism</section>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">James Bond is one of a small number of figures who embody Britain in the global collective imagination. As such, he conveys a certain vision of the West, and this is reflected in the representation of tourism that lies at the heart of the films in the saga.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            Representation of tourism’s ‘time wasted’ 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Almost all the franchise’s films feature ‘logistical’ touristic moments, such as time spent on transport (planes, taxis), checking in at hotels and going through passport control. Such events, which are generally considered to be time wasted by tourists (Equipe MIT, 2002) or even the source of various difficulties, do not pose a problem for 007, who has the benefit of his significant touristic capital. There are many examples of this in the films. For example, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From Russia with Love</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1963) – in a scene clearly parodied in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">OSS 117</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2006) – shows Bond being checked into his hotel followed by his careful inspection of the room for bugs. In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Quantum of Solace</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2008), there is the sequence that begins with Bond in a private jet followed by his taxi ride to a nearby, pre-booked hotel. The welcome and setting are not to the hero’s liking, however, so he travels onwards to a luxury hotel, where the sequence ends with him procuring a room, despite having no reservation, thanks to his substantial financial resources.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Far from being time wasted, then, these logistical moments, which would be of very limited interest in other types of films, are key elements of the plot in the Bond films. Airports are places of transition and, as such, likely starting points from which to be tailed. They are generic places. They function in a very simple and standardised way, and everything is organised to channel and direct the arrivals and departures. The limited number of access doors and walkways makes it very difficult to avoid the established routes and checkpoints but conversely very easy to spot someone. In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From Russia with Love</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1963), Bond is tailed by Bulgarian agents working for the Russians, who are in turn followed by Donald ‘Red’ Grant, an agent from the criminal organisation SPECTRE. Bond is also regularly ambushed by his enemies when he is travelling on trains (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From Russia with Love</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1963; </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Live and Let Die</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1973; </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Spy who Loved Me</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1977; </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Spectre</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2015), taxis (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Live and Let Die</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) and planes (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Goldfinger</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1964; </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Man with the Golden Gun</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1974). Even an uneventful flight can be an opportunity for Bond to get to the heart of the plot. In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Die Another Day</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2002), for example, the newspaper offered by the airline contains – coincidentally – a lengthy article on the man who Bond suspects. In this case, tourism’s time wasted is actually time saved on plot development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            Representation of stereotypical tourist destinations
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Bourgeat and Bras (2014) showed how the James Bond franchise participated in the creation of spatial and cultural archetypes, such as the tropical island with its white sand and palm trees and Switzerland with its mountains and financial institutions. These archetypes facilitate recognition and understanding for the viewer. Like spatial metonymies, the pyramids, the Eiffel Tower and the Golden Gate immediately suggest Egypt, Paris and San Francisco. However, it should be noted that while these emblems have appeared on screen, it is possible the scenes were actually filmed in a studio or in a similar landscape far away from the one depicted. The viewer does not notice the difference (Bourgeat and Bras, 2014). The range of tourist sites appearing in the Bond saga is extensive, including cultural destinations (Rome, Venice, Paris, Istanbul, etc.), paradise islands (Jamaica, Bahamas, Phang Nga Bay), major natural landscapes (Alps, Ha Long Bay, Icelandic Fjords, Atacama desert) and emblematic routes (Orient Express, Atlantic cruise).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The tourist resort (seaside, spa or winter sports) has been omnipresent among these spatial archetypes since the first opuses appeared in the 1960s, a decade that saw the emergence and growth of integrated resorts. The resorts frequented by Bond and his enemies, however, are exclusively those reserved for a wealthy clientele. For example, the Fontainebleau Miami Beach, a prominent Miami seafront hotel (7:59-14:20), was represented in the third opus (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Goldfinger</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1964) in a scene that showcases the building’s distinctive, functionalist-inspired architecture and organisational structure. It shows an elongated semi-circular block, composed of spacious rooms with balconies overlooking a swimming pool. We see a two-storey terrace complete with sunbeds and parasols, where the guests can enjoy swimming, sunbathing, reading or, as in the case of Auric Goldfinger, gambling. Similarly, a long way from the integrated resorts that resulted from France’s Plan Neige programme</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Grindelwald in Switzerland (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On Her Majesty’s Secret Service</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1969) and La Cortina d’Ampezzo in Italy (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For Your Eyes Only</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1981) are village resorts that have welcomed British tourists since the 18th and 19th centuries. The architecture in these resorts retains traditional features, and the longlow-rise blocks and tall towers of the integrated resorts are nowhere to be seen.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Some of the resorts that appear in the Bond saga are totally fictional. The viewer may not realise this, however, because they are modelled on real resorts. One example is Isthmus City, capital of the fictitious banana republic of Isthmus in Central America, where the drug baron Franz Sanchez reigns supreme in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Licence to Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1989). The ocean view is heavily exploited in this film. The seafront comprises hotels and a coastal road lined with palm trees. In addition, following the 19th-century seaside and spa resorts model, the waterfront is structured around a central point, the casino. This conformity to the seaside resort model is facilitated here by the filming locations, Acapulco and Cancun, two of Mexico’s main seaside resorts.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These stereotypical tourist sites, which are presented globally through these films, not only reinforce spatial and landscape archetypes but also represent an excellent medium for the action within the framework of an internal logic and conventions specific to the genre. The viewer masters the codes and organisation of the spatial framework and can then concentrate on the plot and even anticipate the characters’ actions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            Representation of tourism practices
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The tourism practices represented in the Bond films are also stereotyped. A very clear distinction is made between the practices of, on the one hand, 007 and his enemies, who are associated with luxury tourism, and, on the other, the anonymous extras, who are associated with mass tourism. Bond only submits to the latter when his mission requires him to. His character is associated with certain distinctive tourism practices. For example, he regularly avails himself of the services offered by luxury establishments, such as valet parking (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2006), room service, swimming pool (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Golden Eye</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1995; </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Skyfall</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012), jacuzzi (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A View to a Kill</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1985) and massage service (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Die Another Day</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2002). The British agent also regularly frequents casinos, although he is only interested the gaming tables. Even when he goes to Las Vegas (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Diamonds are Forever</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 1971), he only passes through the slot machine rooms; he does not stop there. Bond ignores these more popular games, preferring to gamble with higher stakes and a more restricted audience.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The more commonly shared tourism practices, such as sea swimming, sunbathing, water sports and winter sports, are also well represented throughout the films, as are some practices that are more specific to mass tourism, such as organised trips, guided tours and excessive photographing. The latter are, however, represented only to serve as an alibi for the hero (for example, his visit to the Blue Mosque in Istanbul allows him to recover the map of the Russian embassy left by Tatiana Romanova) or as a backdrop to the action. One notable example of this is the sound and light show at the Luxor site in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Spy who Loved Me</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1977, 26: 19-31:34). Using the anonymity of the crowd of tourists, Russian agents exchange information, 007 follows these Russian agents and the enemy commits a murder. These multiple narrative threads are highlighted by a dual musical perspective. The sequence is particularly interesting in that it blurs the very nature and function of musical accompaniment. At the beginning of the sequence, the context of the sound and light show immediately indicates the diegetic status of the music, which is reminiscent of the soundtracks composed for the film epics ofthe 1950s and 1960s. Marvin Hamlisch’s pompous, grandiose, imposing music matches the visual monumentality of the Sphinx and the Pyramids of Giza in long shot and the theatrical, sententious diction of the voice-over. Hamlisch ostensibly draws on a number of musical codes typical of those used in the film epics– hieratic brass fanfares, woodwind instruments to represent the double-reed instruments of Antiquity, parallel and empty fifths – and punctuates these with synthesiser sounds that strongly anchor the music in the diegetic and filmic era (the late 1970s).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, at certain dramatic moments, the music becomes detached from the scene, from its status as a simple diegetic background sound, and takes the form of an extra-diegetic, empathic</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> accompaniment, emphasising certain salient actions as if closely following the narrative. Hence, the short descending, sinuous</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">motif from the oboe (Eflat-D-A-E flat) is synchronised with the close-up shot of Anya in discussion with Fekkesh as Bond spots them among the large audience attending the show (26:50). On the one hand, the oboe comes from the film epic tradition, where it is often used to symbolise the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">aulos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. On the other, the melodic phrase highlights the female character, whose beauty is emphasised by sophisticated make-up and a subtle halo of light, while the instrumental timbre references a codified musical representation of femininity (Kalinak, 1982). Further on in the film, several musical topoi of suspense are introduced every time Jaws appears (27:19). For example, there are tritone tremolos (a culturally dissonant interval associated with an evil dimension) and crescendos followed by total silence as Jaws breaks the padlock with his steel teeth (29:08). Fekkesh’s anguished expression as the enemy swoops on him (27:56) is accentuated by a descending tremolo motif on treble strings coupled with a harp, and we hear dramatic punctuations</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">from kettledrums as Bond moves towards the recess where the Russian agent’s body lies (30:07). Finally, the wordless women’s choir accompanies the final climax of the scene with its angelic tones as Bond discovers, using a cigarette lighter for light, a hand-written clue in the murdered man’s wallet (30:33). The timbral luminosity thus reflects the warm light of the flame, which symbolises the ‘illumination’ of the discovery that is about to relaunch 007’s mission. Anya is again highlighted musically, as Bond spots her in a beam of light. This moment is accompanied by a short ascending glissando, a great orchestral crescendo, the women’s choir and the harmonic color provided by the bright flat major perfect chord, which follows unexpectedly on from an E minor chord (30:43). Hence, the musical accompaniment unfolds continuously throughout the scene, but its status changes according to the shots. With its pompous and dated character, the music not only generates another level of irony in respect of the life and death stakes for the agents – making the tourist setting itself a (involuntarily) comic springboard through its incongruity–but also participates fully and very directly in the dramatic action that takes place behind the scenes. Although Giza only acts a backdrop, the composer has nevertheless seized on the setting and the editing choices to offer a singular, rich orchestral accompaniment that goes beyond a simple geographical illustration.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">While the mass tourism practices in the Bond filmsare used to frame theplot and the action, those associated with luxury tourism play a full role in them (for example, the casino gaming tables are the setting for a direct confrontation with the enemy).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II- From ‘travel idiots’ to the notably absent: a significant evolution in the representation of tourism</section>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The clear dichotomy defined above between mass and luxury tourism practices has been coupled throughout the saga with an evolution in the representation of tourism and tourists.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Licence to change: representations reflecting the times</section>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ian Fleming’s first James Bond novel, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, was published in 1953. His subsequent Bond novels appeared at a rate of one a year. They are all strongly and positively influenced by the massification of tourism that was underway at the time and alternate, as far as tourism places and practices are concerned, between a ‘paradisiacal’ vision, which is a form of ‘staged authenticity’ (MacCannell, 1973) corresponding to mass tourism, and a ‘realistic’ vision, which Bond has privileged access to through his spy activities (Denning, 2009).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            The grandeur and decadence of mass tourism
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Both these visions – idyllic and realistic – can be found in the Bond films of the 1960s starring Sean Connery. In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Dr. No</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1962), for example, 007 takes advantage of Jamaica, a tropical tourist island with palm trees, cocktails and young women in bikinis, but he also forges an alliance with Quarrel, a resident of the island, who gives him access to behind the scenes. The same is true in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From Russia with Love</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1963), where Bond has contact with the gypsy community through Kerim Bey. Mass tourism is not pejoratively connoted in these early films of the 1960s.The tourists represented are more recognisable by their practices (guided tours, sunbathing) than by their attire or equipment, and 007 does not seem to be differentiated from them. This is illustrated by the group of visitors in Istanbul in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From Russia with Love </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(1963), who are dressed in elegant smart casual wear, holding an explanatory brochure and visibly focused on the guide’s explanations. There is not a camera in sight except Bond’s, which goes completely unnoticed as he stands at the back of the group.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The representation of tourists in the films changes significantly in the 1970s, during the Roger Moore period, reflecting both a certain ‘anti-tourism contempt’ (Urbain, 1991) and a growing challenge to the environmental, economic and cultural degradation being attributed to tourism at the time. Mass tourism and its practitioners became a comic springboard that was central to the saga during this decade. These tourists were venturing further and further away from their homes and usual resorts, popping up not only in ‘historical’ tourist sites (Venice, Cairo, etc.) but also in destinations that had opened up as a result of air transport (Bangkok, Rio, etc.). The distinction between these tourists and 007 is now clear, as shown by the group presented in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Man with the Golden Gun</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1974), who are immediately identifiable by the cameras stuck to their faces and their inelegant casual clothes (motif-covered shirts, bucket hats and caps). The tourists’ attention is captured here not by any historical and cultural explanations or intellectual enrichment but by the photographs to be taken and the souvenirs they have to bring back – the ‘postcard’ dimension. In all the films of the Moore era, these tourist archetypes appear when the film goes beyond the realm of espionage and lapses into (sometimes schoolboy) comedy. The Venetian sequence in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Moonraker</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1979) provides a good example of this (36:33-39:35). In the first part of the sequence, although the suspenseful aspect of the chase on the canals is suggested by John Barry’s use of the main Bond theme music here (albeit at a relatively slow tempo), which highlights the hero, the image has many humorous shifts. A gondolier, after much effort, narrowly manages to avoid a collision with the boat operated by 007 only to have his gondola then sliced in half by Bond’s pursuers (38:26). A close-up shot of some traffic lights changing from green to red (which traditionally represents danger) introduces the dramatic undercurrents of the next twelve shots (38:15), which follow on from one another at a pace that is enhanced by their brevity. However, this visual and narrative dramatic register is immediately abandoned during the collision and replaced by a light, comical tone. Completely wrapped up in one another, the two embracing tourists do not even notice they are sailing aboard half a gondola. The gag thus fully exploits the stereotypical image of Venice as the‘city of lovers’.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            In the second part of the sequence (38:44-39:35), when Bond transforms his gondola into a hovercraft and crosses St Mark’s Square as stunned tourists and Venetians look on, a total change of musical atmosphere along with the reaction shots of the amazed spectators reinforces the eccentric absurdity of the action. Johann Strauss II’s <em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tritsch-Tratsch-Polka</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which is both playful and grandiloquent, fills the entire sound space. This disconnects the action from reality by playing the pure spectacle card to the full while highlighting the clumsy, anxious and confused reactions of all the characters in the scene. These characters are filmed in either close-up or close shot to highlight their stunned expressions and inappropriate gestures.The shots of the hero, by contrast, are taken from further away to capture the astonishing unfolding spectacle of his escape, which is emphasised by the vortex removed from the polka. Here, the disruption of ordinary everydayness, the ‘small blip’ that brings the traditional picture postcard scene to a grinding halt, is highlighted by this musical joke. There are other such musical jokes in the film (Burlingame, 2012: 141).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although tourists are ridiculed in the Bond films, it is always done with affection. The clichés that appear on screen are only those that tourists themselves actually apply to </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">other</span></em> tourists. Hence, the aim is not to alienate mass tourism practitioners, because they, after all, make up a significant proportion of the James Bond audience.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <strong><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The great disappearance</span></strong>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In 1987, Timothy Dalton introduced a more ‘serious’ version of the character in his attempt to align it more closely with Fleming’s literary hero, who had received a mixed reception. Apart from the opening scene of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Living Daylights</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1987), during which Bond parachutes into the yacht of a young woman (who is not caricatured) on holiday in Gibraltar, tourists have been obliterated from the Dalton era. Only luxury tourism is presented here. This is also the case during the Pierce Brosnan era in the 1990s. There are few major scenes featuring tourists. The only significant scene, which appears in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Die Another Day</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2002), focuses on market developments. The tourists make the most of a luxury hotel nestled on the Cuban shoreline with a private white sandy beach, escort girls and many other services pending their admission to the exclusive private clinic on the island of Los Organos. This high-end medical tourism can also be found in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Spectre</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2015), where the scene is based on the Alpine winter sports resort model. The tourists, however, are almost invisible in the scene, having been relegated to the background of the restaurant.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This was the major change in the late 2000s. The tourists have disappeared, even from places where their presence seems essential. The casinos and paradise islands are still full, but no importance is given to the extras in the image. Moreover, the tourist destinations visited by Bond are sometimes completely empty. In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Spectre </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(2015), for example, the pavements in Rome and the banks of the Tiber are notably deserted, including around the Vatican and St Peter’s Square, which is a major tourist destination. The hero only encounters a dozen cars during the chase that takes place there (44:26-50:49). This change goes hand in hand with the decision to move towards more ‘realistic’ films (in the verisimilitude sense</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) with the aim of strengthening the viewer’s commitment to the storyline. For example, this pursuit takes place at the beginning of November at around one o’clock in the morning – certainly not the most touristic season or time of day in Rome. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The scene is characteristic of the audiovisual aesthetics of chase sequences in digital-age films (Huvet, 2017: 439-449), which, visually, involve among other things ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">speedy editing, aninterplay between two polarities – either between general (long shot) and singular (close-up) or between fast movement and statis –and techniques to foster empathy (such as the subjective camera)</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (Bolduc-Cloutier, 2018: 52). Sound is expressed in this scene through the foregrounding of the sound design (where the sound conveys the musicality through the intense timbre of the engines and the frequent screeching of the tyres) and a shift away from the musical narrativity to mainly rhythmic writing. The extra-diegetic music, which has a very strong kinetic function, maintains an intense dynamism to reinforce the sensation of visual speed. The physical absence of tourists is thus compensated in a way by the excitement of the chase and the sensory onslaught of images and sounds. Suddenly producing an incongruous contrast with the perilous situation, a touch of local colour is introduced as we hear the diegetic music being listened to by the driver of the Fiat 500 (46:07-46:49). Like all good Romans (!), he is enjoying an opera aria ‘Libiamo Ne'lieti Calici’ from Verdi’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Traviata</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (46:15). Beyond the cliché, however, the use of this music in the image is interesting in several respects. Far from simply being a geographically connoted background sound, the aria becomes the sound materialisation of an energy discharge, a forward thrust and a visual trajectory. Several inserts on the speedometer (46:32, 46:38) showing the Fiat’s sudden acceleration under the impetus of the Aston Martin, correspond with a growing musical intensity (a pronounced vibrato from Luciano Pavarotti and Joan Sutherland, a faster, continuous rhythm, gradation in the treble and vocal crescendo) until the final, climactic cadential resolution synchronises with the straight-line trajectory of the Fiat, which ends up slotting perfectly intoa parking space. The exalted final chord of the music thus humourously corresponds with a close-up of the front of the car coming to a halt just before the pavement and hitting a safety post (46:49). Tourists are thus almost entirely erased in favour of an immersive and spectacular sound accompaniment, which manages to give an audiovisual nod to the locality and its culture.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">During the Daniel Craig era, tourists and tourism are replaced by locals and leisure practices (for example, the Body Worlds exhibition in Miami in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> [2006]). In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Skyfall</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2012), the London chase scene takes place not in the city’s tourist districts but in the Underground, a context that is paradoxically more alien to Bond than any of the international sites he has ever visited. As Q points out, 007 seems to be discovering the Underground at rush hour for the first time. Like the Rome scene in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Spectre</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2015), the locals (and the London workers) are a perfect replacement for tourists here.They have exactly the same role as passive opponents of the hero and very occasionally serve as a comic springboard in a much darker, edgier and more violent film.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This reorientation towards everyday practices, leisure and locals coincides both with a move in recreational practices towards individualisation and generalisation and with a desire to practise a type of tourism that is more mindful of the locals and the places visited (sustainable tourism, solidarity tourism, etc.). These evolutions affect not just tourists but also tourist destinations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. The world is not enough: Bond, travel agent</section>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The impact of the Bond films on the development of tourist destinations is indisputable. During each pre-production phase, cities and countries deploy a range of arguments aimed at attracting the British spy.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            Goldmaker: the extension of the tourism ecumene?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In addition to the direct economic benefits generated by the presence of film crews, the Bond films increase, or generate, awareness of the locations that play the role of tourism incubators (Beeton, 2005). Following the 2006 film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which led 007 to Montenegro for the first time, a British newspaper headlined: ‘How James Bond put Montenegro on the map’ (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sunday Express</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2012).This was particularly significant because Montenegro had gained its independence on 2 June 2006, just a few months before the film was released and one month before shooting had ended. The name‘Montenegro’ appears on the screen (57:50) with no further clarification during 007’s train trip to the eponymous casino, which is therefore assumed to be located in a small Montenegrin town whose name is never disclosed. There is good reason for this. The key scenes were not shot in Montenegro and neither the train that 007 was travelling on nor the hotel, Splendid, where he stayed existed at the time of the film’s release. The director Martin Campbell admitted he had never set foot in Montenegro. However, the film incorporates all the key elements of the archetypal representations of tourist destinations and luxury tourism, such as the high-speed train with its exclusive first-class facility and a fortified village complete with castle nestled in the oxbow of a river in rolling countryside. This latter scene was filmed using aerial shots, thus reinforcing the picture postcard aspect (01:05:23). The representation of Montenegro was created from scratch using locations in the Czech Republic, but very few viewers realise this. Nevertheless, the real Montenegro experienced a very strong real estate boom between 2006 and 2009, which was linked to the purchase of second homes by Russian and British investors (Werner, 2013). At the same time, it saw a significant increase both in visitor numbers and in investments in its tourism sector. Hence, through a simple written mention at the beginning of a scene, the film has conferred a concrete existence on a country that had only just recreated itself. The Bond ecumene is quite similar to the tourism ecumene. Both are reminiscent of the maps whose blanks had to be filled in at the time of the great explorations. When 007 goes to a new destination, it appears on the tourist routes and contributes to the expansion of the tourism ecumene. This applies at all levels, from the London Underground</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> to the State of Montenegro. The saga has even led to the emergence of a form of tourism that specifically follows in Bond’s footsteps. Its adherents plan their holiday destinations and programmes according to the locations presented in the films and the filming sites (Reijnders, 2010).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            The Spy who never showed up: an atrophied film and tourism ecumene
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">While it is interesting to study the tourist destinations created or reinforced by Bond, an analysis of a map showing his movements across all 24 films also suggests that some regions have been ‘condemned’ by 007</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2006) is the only film that offers a brief visit to Africa, for example, but the scenes depicted are a long way from any tourist destinations or landscapes. The viewer sees a warlord’s camp located in the middle of the Ugandan jungle in the rain, an arena for animal fighting, a building site and the Nambutu embassy on the island of Madagascar. M, who is 007’s superior, discusses an ‘African mission’ in the introductory scene to </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Moonraker </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(1979), but we only see Africa during his return trip.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Other areas such as the Arabian Peninsula, Iran and Oceania have also never attracted Bond despite their obvious geopolitical potential. These ostracisms suit Bond’s competitor in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Ethan Hunt, however. Apart from a few common locations (London, Moscow, Rome), </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> does its best to fill in the blanks left by Bond. The cinematographic rivalry between the two is also played out geographically. For example, Prague played a prominent role in the 1996 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, but the city was not visited by the British agent until ten years later, and then only briefly (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2006). The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">sequels feature Spain, Australia (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible 2</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2000) and the United Arab Emirates (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Mission: Impossible - Ghost Protocol</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2011), all of which have been totally ignored by Bond. Only sub-Saharan Africa is still excluded from this ecumene created by the major spy/action/adventure franchises. Even the Jason Bourne films, which have sought out more realistic places and situations, have not ventured onto African territory.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Over James Bond’s 56 years in the cinema, the representation of tourism and tourists has evolved considerably in relation to global tourism activity. Bond came to the screen at the height of the development of mass tourism and, by the end of the 20th century, had to negotiate what Violier (2016) theorised was the ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">third tourism revolution</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’. The most recent films in the franchise, including the four films from the Daniel Craig era, allow us to examine this theoretical proposal. According to Violier (2016), the third tourism revolution is characterised by three main elements: an extension of the tourism ecumene, ‘new relations’ between tourism actors and a ‘hybridisation of practices’. The more recent Bond opuses effectively take the viewer to new destinations that have hitherto been ignored by tourism (for example, Montenegro) and transform certain everyday realities (for example, the London Underground) into tourism objects, evidencing an extension of the tourism ecumene. They break with the archetypal representation of tourists in favour of a renewed interest in the locals of the places visited by the hero.They also show the new relationships between the tourism actors and the hybridisation of practices that are at the root of the boom in contemporary forms of tourism that involve discovering and even sharing the daily lives of the locals. Paradoxically, while luxury is ever more present in these films (due to product placement), everydayness and ‘the ordinary’are also heroised and re-enchanted. A new representation is created. Like Alice’s mirror, these everyday places conceal the way to an extraordinary fantasy. This breakaway is at the very root of tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These different representations in the films of tourism destinations, tourism actors and their evolution are highly dependent on production. The images, music and sound design contribute strongly to the construction of tourism archetypes in the minds of the viewer, including in the most ordinary of places. The soundtrack produces local colour and audiovisual gags while highlighting the heartstopping suspense of the frequent chase sequences that take place in these tourist locations. This is especially true of the Bond films shot in the digital era and in the franchise’s narrative and aesthetic shift, from </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Casino Royale</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2006) onwards, to graphic violence and a darker and more tortured approach, fully subscribing to the paradigms of the spectacular and intensified cinematic immersion (Smith, 2013). James Bond has probably not finished sending us postcards yet, and no doubt they will come from increasingly unexpected destinations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Beeton S., 2005, Film-Induced Tourism. Bristol, Buffalo, Toronto, Channel View Publication, Aspects of Tourism.</reference>
        <reference>Black J., 2005 [2000], The Politics of James Bond: From Fleming’s Novel to the Big Screen, Lincoln, University of Nebraska Press.</reference>
        <reference>Bolduc-Cloutier H., 2018, ‘Musique et immersion spectatorielle dans les scènes de poursuite des films d’action du cinéma hollywoodien contemporain’, in Huvet C. (ed.), Revue musicale OIRM, ‘Création musicale et sonore dans les blockbusters de Remote Control’, vol. 5, no 2, 48-77, forthcoming.</reference>
        <reference>Bourdieu P., 1979, La Distinction. Critique sociale du jugement, Les Editions de Minuit.</reference>
        <reference>Bourgeat S., Bras C., 2014, ‘Le monde de James Bond : logiques, pratiques et archétypes’, Annales de Géographie, 2014/1, no 695-696, 671-686.</reference>
        <reference>Burlingame J., 2012, The Music of James Bond, Oxford, Oxford University Press.</reference>
        <reference>Chion M., 2003, Un art sonore, le cinéma : histoire, esthétique, poétique, Paris, Cahiers du cinéma.</reference>
        <reference>Darbellay F., Clivaz C., Nahrath S., Stock M., 2011, ‘Approche interdisciplinaire du développement des stations touristiques. Le capital touristique comme concept opératoire’, Mondes du tourisme, no 4, 36-48.</reference>
        <reference>Denning M., 2009, ‘Licensed to look: James Bond and the heroism of consumption’, in Lindler C. (ed.), The James Bond Phenomenon: A Critical Reader (2nd edition), Manchester, Manchester University Press, 56-88.</reference>
        <reference>Dodds K., 2003, ‘Licensed to Stereotype: Popular Geopolitics, James Bond and the Spectre of Balkanism’, Geopolitics, vol.8, no 2, 125-156.</reference>
        <reference>Duprat J.-A., 2015, James Bond dans le spectre géopolitique, Le Bouscat, L’Esprit du Temps.</reference>
        <reference>Eco U., 1985, ‘Innovation and Repetition: Between Modern and Post-Modern Aesthetics’, Daedalus, vol. 114, no 4 ‘The Moving Image’, 161-184.</reference>
        <reference>Equipe MIT, 2002, Tourismes 1. Lieux communs, Paris, Belin.</reference>
        <reference>Equipe MIT, 2005, Tourismes 2. Moments de lieux, Paris, Belin.</reference>
        <reference>Evin G., 2002, Goldmaker. Comment James Bond est devenu le plus gros succès de l’histoire du cinéma, Paris, Fayard.</reference>
        <reference>Fleming I., 1960, For Your Eyes Only, London, Jonathan Cape.</reference>
        <reference>Genette G., 1968, ‘Vraisemblance et motivation’, Communications, no 11, 5-21.</reference>
        <reference>Huvet C., 2017, D’Un nouvel espoir (1977) à La Revanche des Sith (2005) : écriture musicale et traitement de la partition au sein du complexe audio-visuel dans la saga Star Wars, PhD thesis, Université Rennes 2/Université de Montréal.</reference>
        <reference>Kalinak K., 1982, ‘The Fallen Woman and the Virtuous Wife: Musical Stereotypes in The Informer, Gone with the Wind and Laura’, Film Reader, no 5, 76-82.</reference>
        <reference>Mari J.-C., 2007, Quand le film se fait musique : une nouvelle ère sonore au cinéma, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>McCannell D., 1973, ‘Staged Authenticity: Arrangements of Social Space in Tourist Settings’, American Journal of Sociology, vol. 79, no 3, 589-603.</reference>
        <reference>Mulvey L., 1989, Visual and Other Pleasures, London, Macmillan.</reference>
        <reference>Raento P., 2017, ‘All in – and More! Gambling in the James Bond Films’, UNLV Gaming Research &amp; Review Journal, vol. 21/1, 49-68.</reference>
        <reference>Reijnders S., 2010, ‘On the Trail of 007: Media Pilgrimages into the World of James Bond’, Area, 42, 369-377.</reference>
        <reference>Simpson P., 2006 [2002], The Rough Guide to James Bond, London, Rough Guides.</reference>
        <reference>Smith J., 2013, ‘The Sound of Intensified Continuity’, in Richardson J., Gorbman C., Vernallis C. (ed.), The Oxford Handbook of New Audiovisual Aesthetics, New York, New York University Press, 331-356.</reference>
        <reference>Urbain J.-D., 1991, L’idiot du voyage. Histoires de touristes, Paris, Plon.</reference>
        <reference>Violier P., 2016, ‘La troisième révolution touristique’, Mondes du tourisme [online], Special issue.</reference>
        <reference>Werner J., 2013, ‘Revenue Mobility in a Transitional Economy: “Casino Royale” in Montenegro and the Negative Effects Towards the Local Units’, in Biethahn N., Werner J., Sucky E., Kolke R. (ed.), Mobility in a Globalised World 2012, Bamberg, University of Bamberg Press, 46-56.</reference>
        <reference>Filmography</reference>
        <reference>Bird B., 2011, Mission: Impossible – Ghost Protocol. Music by Michael Giacchino.</reference>
        <reference>Campbell M., 1995, GoldenEye. Music by Éric Serra.</reference>
        <reference>Campbell M., 2006, Casino Royale. Music by David Arnold.</reference>
        <reference>Foster M., 2008, Quantum of Solace. Music by David Arnold.</reference>
        <reference>Gilbert L., 1979, Moonraker. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Gilbert L., 1977, The Spy who Loved Me. Music by Marvin Hamlisch.</reference>
        <reference>Glen J., 1981, For Your Eyes Only. Music by Bill Conti.</reference>
        <reference>Glen J., 1989, Licence to Kill. Music by Michael Kamen.</reference>
        <reference>Glen J., 1985, A View to a Kill. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Hamilton G., 1971, Diamonds are Forever. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Hamilton G., 1974, The Man with the Golden Gun. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Hamilton G., 1964, Goldfinger. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Hazanavicius M., 2006, OSS 117: Cairo, Nest of Spies. Music by Ludovic Bource and Kamel Ech-Cheikh.</reference>
        <reference>Hunt P., 1969, On Her Majesty’s Secret Service. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Mendes S., 2015, Spectre. Music by Thomas Newman.</reference>
        <reference>Mendes S., 2012, Skyfall. Music by Thomas Newman.</reference>
        <reference>Tamahori L., 2002, Die Another Day. Music by David Arnold.</reference>
        <reference>Woo J., 2000, Mission: Impossible 2. Music by Hans Zimmer.</reference>
        <reference>Young T., 1963, From Russia with Love. Music by John Barry.</reference>
        <reference>Young T., 1962, Dr. No. Music by John Barry and Monty Norman.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">Source: Nash Information Services, www.the-numbers.com.</note>
        <note id="2">The main shots and scenes analysed throughout the article are indicated in timings shown in brackets.</note>
        <note id="3">Unless otherwise indicated, this and all subsequent citations from French sources have been translated from the French.</note>
        <note id="4">Popularised by Walt Disney’s cartoons and later by American classic cinema films of the golden age, this process consists in literally imitating certain gestures or movements in the image through music.</note>
        <note id="5">A programme launched in 1964 by the French Government to develop highly functional winter sports resorts.</note>
        <note id="6">Chion defined empathic music as music ‘that participates directly in the emotion of a scene, of a situation, that vibrates in sympathy with it, envelops it, prolongs it, and amplifies it’ (Chion, 2003: 382).</note>
        <note id="7">Verisimilitude helps to suspend the viewer’s disbelief by making the events or objects represented plausible with regard to the codifications of the genre and the work’s internal logic. Depending on the degree to which the film conforms with the conventions of its genre, verisimilitude results from a construction and, implicitly, a ‘tacit contract between the work and its audience’ (Genette, 1968, p. 8).</note>
        <note id="8">The Tube is an essential part of London’s identity and very well touristified by Transport for London. It appears in films and on television programmes, such asin the ‘The Empty Hearse’episode from the BBC series Sherlock (2014) and in Darkest Hour (2017), when Churchill ventures into the Underground. This contributes to a certain re-enchantment of everydayness by offering the viewer an extraordinary representation of an ordinary place.</note>
        <note id="9">We refer here to the interactive map produced by ESRI UKto mark the release of Spectre (2015): https://resource.esriuk.com/james-bond-travel-map/.</note>
    </notes>
</article>