<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_MD_59-99_Mn_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5428" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.5428</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="5391">
            <traducteur nom="Graburn" prenom="Nelson" />
            Paysage millénaire et développement touristique en Chine. Le cas des rizières en terrasses des Hani du Yunnan
        </original>
        <traduction lang="es" source="5467">Desarrollo turístico y paisaje milenario en China. El caso de las terrazas de los Hani en Yunnan</traduction>
        <traduction lang="ca" source="5488">Desenvolupament turístic i paisatge mil·lenari a la Xina. El cas de les terrasses dels Hani a Yunnan</traduction>
        <traduction lang="zh" source="5648">中国的千年景观和旅游业发展 以云南哈尼族水稻梯田为例</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Dao" prenom="Myriam">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_MD_55-109_Pn_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5391" lang="fr">Paysage millénaire et développement touristique en Chine. Le cas des rizières en terrasses des Hani du Yunnan</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Myriam Dao is an artist, architect and independent researcher. Holder of a master's degree "Gardens, Landscapes, Territories" from EHESS and the National School of Architecture of Paris La Villette, she has conducted ethnographic research on vernacular cultures on the borders of Southwest China since 1987. In 2018, she won the Villa Saigon artistic residency program in Vietnam, and presented her work on Tử Vi, the Vietnamese divination, at ICAS11, International Conference of Asian Scholars, in Leiden in 2019. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Millennial landscape and tourist development in China. The case of the Hani rice terraces in Yunnan</titre>
    <sousTitre>Peer-reviewed article</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        Between 1995 and 2015, I conducted fieldwork in a rice-growing village in southwest China as an artist-researcher. In this text, I examine the profound changes taking place in rural border areas inhabited by non-Han minorities, and particularly those of the Hani in the Yunnan Red River Valley. What future is there for the Hani ancestral model of irrigated rice terraces, and what are the stakes? My work combines a sensitive approach through diverse artistic representations of landscapes – from classical Chinese art to the works of contemporary artists, including mine – and examines landscape planning and patrimonial policies. The conservation stakes are not only environmental – biodiversity, sustainable development – but also identity-based through vernacular and minority cultures. I will point out the limits of this landscape planning and outline its future.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Preamble</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            The concept of "cultural landscape" applied to cultivated land raises questions - objectification, heritage, commodification of territories - of the same order as those that stir the art world in relation to otherness and to some of its corollaries: exoticism and cultural appropriation.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a> In the Chinese context, landscapes are made or "maintained", designed bodies (Yu, 2018), fictions are constructed, and constitute new imaginations (Augé, 1997). Contemporary art in particular, since the artistic event Documenta 11 whose curation was provided in 2002 by Okwui Enwezor, is challenged by questions inherent in global / local friction, and questions the representations that are made of it, from a postcolonial perspective.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a> The artist not only puts the world into images, he questions, shakes up the imaginary, and his work is a source of reflection. This is why it seemed necessary to me, after having described the cultural environment in question - a Hani village, to look at consumption - in the sense of a visual anthropophagy - of landscape and ethnicity, in China, and on the interpretation that contemporary art makes of these phenomena.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            All artistic creation carries its subjectivity, which in a way becomes the artist's manifesto.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a> Mine would be my triptych <em>Riken no ken</em>, portrait of three women - I am one of them, dressed in Hani costume.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a> It synthesizes the questions that underlie my work as an artist, architect and researcher, my point of view also reflecting my experience as a woman in a "visible minority" position.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a> I therefore share a peripheral status in France, with that of the Hani in China, all things considered. Like Georges Condominas who questioned his desire to integrate into the culture of the mountain dwellers of Central Vietnam in the light of his own origins (French and Portuguese-Sino-Vietnamese), I can empathize with him.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            How can we understand the cultivated spaces of the Hani, with what analytical tools? If, in 2020, decentralization is de rigueur, in 1995 when my research started it was not topical. Since then, Philippe Descola has reflected on <em>Beyond Nature and Culture</em> (Descola, 2005). Augustin Berque returned to his notion of a proto-landscape society which induced a hierarchy between "advanced" civilizations which produce representations of the landscape, and others which do not (Berque <em>Country Landscape</em>, 1998 2nd edition of 1994). However, when I went to China for a six-month Villa Medicis Hors les Murs artist residency in 1995, the main French theorists decreed the appearance of the landscape during the Renaissance, on the basis that "there is no landscape without representation, pictorial or literary,” - by studying essentially two societies: western society and that of ancient China (Berque, 1994). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            These literary frameworks were not effective among the Hani of the Red River, a society without writing that transmits an oral culture from generation to generation. This led me to move away from the academic framework and scientific authority to adopt the subjectivity of the artistic vision, abandoning my thesis on "The culture of the landscape, rice fields of the Hani", to conduct this research by following other routes. There are no interviews in the ethnographic sense of the term; I am housed as a distant relative would be with the Hani family with whom I have forged emotional ties. Imitation and the application of a method are the antithesis of the artistic process. However, if the artist or the architect invent an answer for each given context, produce archives and visual materials in situ (drawing, photography, survey, video), it might be inferred to bring the artist's vision closer to that of the handyman (<em>bricoleur</em>).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            Because if I do well by assembling, collage and analogy, I can just as easily list or sketch a typology of the Hani house, make an inventory of derivative works in the rice fields, or even retrace the catalog of embroideries of female clothing.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a> By embroidering these patterns, the Hani women caught my attention during my last stays in 2005 and 2015, and this encounter with their bodies, their hands, their mode of visual expression, lead me to give another orientation to my research, according to what Jacques Rancière names <em>play</em> and <em>encounter</em> (2004). Hal Foster called this new function of art "the ethnographic turn" in an article published in 1996. At the end of my first stay in 1995-1996, I presented the series of black and white photographs “Elevation”, which reverse the plunging point of view on the rice terraces which remain literally "on the surface" of these flooded areas. I was changing focus, offering other perspectives. (Document No. 1)
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. The Hani Model, Ecosystem and Symbolic Landscape</section>
        <section niveau="h2">A. The Red River Hani ecosystem</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            The Chinese province of Yunnan is crossed by three major rivers which then flow through the Asian continent, the Mekong (Lancang), the Blue River (Yangzi Jiang), and the Red river (Hong He) (Document No. 2). Hani rice farmers in the Red River valley practice rice cultivation on irrigated terraces, built on the mountainside, between 800 m and 1,800 m altitude in the Hani and Yi Autonomous Prefecture of Honghe, covering nearly 13,000 hectares. The Hani build their villages in the immediate vicinity of springs located upstream, in the forest. From these sources, sacred places, leave canals originate, and branch out, irrigate all the rice terraces built downstream of the village. (Document No. 3)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            The irrigation network first runs through the village, fills up with human and animal excrement, and deposits this organic fertilizer in the canals before they channel the water into the cultivated plots. Bypass systems made up of stones placed in the secondary irrigation canal, distribute the water in all the ramifications of the network. In addition to this water supply system, there are drain holes to regulate the volume of water in each plot, as well as to temporarily dry it out (See Document No. 4).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            The environment of the Hani is not only based on rice cultivation. The cultivation of rice shares space with other agricultural productions which provide a supplement for food and also contribute to an agrarian balance (Bouchery, 1999). The plots cultivated at the low end of the village function as nurseries, collect organic waste (plants, animals and humans) transformed into compost - nitrogen fixative - which fertilize the plants before they are transplanted downstream. That is the principal of permaculture. The irrigated plots are home to ducks who feed there while clearing the soil of insects and other pests. In the downstream plots, the Hani farm fish (See Document No. 5.). This form of permaculture thus brings together various species and develops in relation to any living organism. Man, nature, animals co-exist in the same world (Jiao Y., 2011 and 2014).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Symbolic landscape of the Hani world</section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <strong>In Hani mythology</strong>, water is the source of all things, and according to Li Zi Xian, it mentions: “<em>a vast expanse of water spread on earth</em>.” Hence the origin of the world. "<em>The aquatic animals that populated this ocean created all human species</em>." It was probably between the 7th and the 10th century, under the Tang dynasty, that this myth began to take shape in the Hani imagination (Bouchery, 1995). “<em>A gigantic female goldfish created the heavens, the earth, everything, gods, men, seeds</em>.” (Document No. 6)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            Water is a shared good. Through collective water management, which is everyone's responsibility, it is a social and, so to speak, virtuous organization, which expresses itself here. Each upstream irrigated terrace has an overflow that leads to the rice field below, and so on. Each plot is an individual property belonging to a family, but the water that circulates in it is shared by all. The plots are not only adjoining, they share the same water in a top-to-bottom relationship, from upstream to downstream, therefore hierarchical in space. The expression of a strong community relationship is therefore inscribed in each plot according to a complex nesting (Bouchery, 2012). One can affirm that among the Hani, the cultivated mountain is the place of a sociability - feasts take place there - and even of a sociality.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <strong>Do the Hani, an ideal society, have a cosmogony of "mountains and waters"?</strong>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            The concept of "beautiful landscape" or ideal landscape is described in this way by the Hani: "<em>Xaota-xaotae xu-sa, uphu tsaodzae xu-sa</em>", literally "a mountain environment where water flows quickly" (Bouchery, 1995).<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a> The mountains and the stream are the ideal landscapes for the Hani. The importance of these two elements, the mountain and the water - present in the thought of Taoist China - should not minimize that of another factor: the rapid flow of water, in other words, movement. If they have a culture specific to their particular territory, the Hani of the Red River belong, however, geographically, to the Chinese world.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a> The Red River Valley is a part of the Yunnan Province. Therefore, it seems relevant to me to draw a parallel between the Hani world and the Taoist landscape.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Taoist Landscape</section>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            Mountains and waters are the two main motifs of the Chinese landscape, to the point that what designates them in Chinese <em>shan shui</em>, has become synonymous with the Chinese pictorial genre "landscape". The object of Chinese painting is to create a microcosm, “<em>truer than Nature itself”</em> <a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            If the man is not figuratively represented, he is not however absent; his presence in the world in the guise of nature, which, lived or dreamed by him, is none other than the projection of his own deep nature all inhabited by an inner vision. Thus, to paint the Mountain and the Water, it is to make the portrait of the man, and more precisely, of the dynamics even of the human body (Cheng, 1979). Thus Taoist painters establish a correspondence between microcosm and macrocosm through the Taoist conception of the world and the vital processes which animate it - the meridians.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            Man is in symbiosis with the landscape, and it is precisely this harmony that must be shown by the painter (See Document No. 7). Taoist China does not know the separation between the physical world and the phenomenal world, contrary to what emerged with modernity in the West. However, the phrase <em>shan shui</em> rather designates representation, not reality. It is about a landscape apprehended visually therefore, even a mental landscape, in which the poets travel when they "visit in spirit". The work of art takes us on a visual journey. What about today? Far, far from the Taoist conception of the landscape, regional planning in China responds more to a theatrical movement of the landscape - in the spirit of the “entertainment society”, than to a concern to place man in harmony with the cosmos. Mircea Eliade already noted in 1965: "... <em>The Cosmos has become opaque, inert, dumb: it does not transmit any message, does not carry any number</em>".<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn13" id="bodyftn13">13</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. A Family of Hani Rice Farmers / 1995-2015</section>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            In 1995, it was Mr. Ma<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a> born around 1930, today great-grandfather, who welcomed me in the Hani village, where I stayed twice for three months. Although I do not present any testimony from villagers on the subject of tourist development, I chose not to mention the name of the village. Mr. Ma lived in the baked brick house, rebuilt with the help of neighbors, to replace that of his parents built of raw earth. Built on stilts, the space on the ground level is devoted to the buffalo, only the first floor is inhabited with a tiny attic on the second level. Without running water, it is partially covered with thatch, the other terrace part is dedicated to drying crops.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            In 1995, Mr. Ma’s son, born around 1950, the 2nd generation - now "the grandfather", works in town at a factory. Among his four children - the 3rd generation born in the 1980s, today "the parents", the two eldest go to school in the capital of Hong He (Red River) prefecture, and the last two, enrolled in the village school, live with their grandparents whom they help with minor agricultural work. During this first stay, my work focuses on the rice terraces, their irrigation system, the close link between the built village and its environment.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            When I returned in 2005 for two weeks to focus on the patterns of women's clothing, Mr. Ma's son had taken over the family home with his wife and in turn exploited the rice fields. Mr. Ma, retired, settled in the capital of the prefecture, surrounded by his two little girls (the 3rd generation whom I had known as schoolgirls), in turn mothers each of a boy, belonging to the 4th generation (the great grandchildren). It was during this second stay that I could establish a link between the embroideries of women's clothing and the outline of the rice fields. Curls, curves and reverse curves embroidered on ancestral clothing, which are still worn today by young Hani girls and women, but in a manufactured version. Note that the tour operators have made this into commercial argument, which proposes vacation plans in the Red River valley, illustrated in the brochures half showing portraits of women in colored ethnic costume, and for the other half the terraced rice fields (see below, Indigenization of the landscape). They describe the minority nationalities (少数民族, shǎoshù mínzú) as a "human mosaic", and the rice fields as a "shimmering patchwork". The landscape and textile metaphor is at its peak in the Red River valley!
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            In 2015 I returned to the village for three weeks. The two sisters of the 3rd generation work in town in commerce. In China rural-urban migration has become generalized in recent decades, due to economic disparities between town and country, and the sociological effects have been studied (Kleinwechter, 2012). This is the case of their two brothers who had to migrate to a more distant region, in Kunming, the capital of the province of Yunnan, a day's drive away, to work in industry, leaving their children in the care of their grandparents. The latter still cultivate the rice fields, although Mr. and Mrs. Ma told me they have reached the legal retirement age (60 years for a man, 50 years for the wife of a farmer). Thanks to the money earned in town by their children, the grandparents were able to completely rebuild their house.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            The new concrete post-beam structure with brick walls, greatly increases the built area on the plot, and doubles the total height. Running water, heated by a solar panel on the roof, is installed like in most new Hani houses. The change in lifestyle is obvious. What struck me during this stay in 2015 was the transformation of the village. All recently enlarged houses have encroached on public space, reduced to its simplest form. Progress has arrived, but the Hani system is unchanged. As a result, the wastewater from dishes and washing machines, which always circulates from upstream to downstream, supplies polluted water along with detergent to the rice fields downstream. The doctor came on a home visit to the village to give the grandmother an intravenous antibiotic injection to treat a cold. Twenty years earlier, this same lady had taken healed me, rubbing herbs and the back of a spoon on my neck to cure my fever.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            I wonder if the great grandchildren will take up rice farming. I fear that on my next trip, in 2025, the rice cultivation of the Hani village will be nothing more than a beautiful carpet of colors changing with the seasons, maintained by the poorest inhabitants for the pleasure of tourists. Those who have taken the turn, and the great grandchildren of Mr. Ma will undoubtedly be of these, will have opened guest rooms in their enlarged house, and the rooftop which was used for drying harvests, will welcome backpackers seated in front of their sodas.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. Changes</section>
        <section niveau="h2">A. New flows across the territory</section>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            Until the late 1990s, the territories of the Red River valley remained difficult to access, peripheral to and not inhabited by the majority Han ethnic group. Previously located near the borders, these regions today belong to a geopolitical space of primary importance, in contact with four countries - Burma, Laos, Vietnam, and Thailand, the first three directly since the opening of common borders. China has gradually normalized relations with ASEAN and since 2010 has established itself as the world's largest free trade area. This phenomenon will develop in the coming years with the construction of the new "Silk Roads of the 21st century". The province of Yunnan will be at the convergence of the China-Burma-Bangladesh corridor and the China-Indochinese Peninsula-Malaysia-Indonesia corridor.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            The improvement of transport networks in the valley as part of central policy<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a> - since 2005 the Hani village has been accessible from a motorway, precipitated a symbolic break by cutting the village off from its complementary "mountain-forest-source" entity. This highway facilitates commerce - peasants will sell their foodstuffs and buy industrialized goods, but the "virtuous circle" of the Hani ecosystem is broken as the inhabitants modify their consumption habits, lifestyles and standards. Immediately noticeable in architectural, clothing and dietary changes, the impact is just as important in terms of ecology (see Document No. 9) (Xin, 2000). This openness to a globalized world has repercussions on the landscape, and also on the structures of intangible culture which underlie it: due to a strong “sinicization” the minority languages are being lost; even the Hani names are no longer passed down in the Ma family or in other families of the village. The Hani epic was, however, based on a genealogical account.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. The Geographic Theater</section>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            As a direct result of the new traffic highways, the rice terraces are integrated massively into the tourist circuits. Photographers come first from all over China, then from all over the world. They endeavor to give a very "pictorial" or "picturesque" image of the Hani landscape of the Red River, a vision immediately conveyed by tourist operators. Chinese photographers have “aestheticized” the rice terraces - to borrow this expression from Alain Roger (1997) - that is to say, they have made these fields cultivated on terraces an object worthy of artistic representation - because it is necessary note the absence of this motif in classical Chinese painting.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn17" id="bodyftn17">17</a> Borrowing the codes of this pictorial genre, the photographers emphasized an aesthetic shrouded in clouds.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a> Posted for hours at the top of the valleys, they wait for the moment when the mist envelops the flooded plots. A new pictorial motif is produced: one that depicts flooded rice fields, sparkling in the light, with colored variations depending on the position of the sun and the seasons, but with one constant: a representation of the plunging view. The rice fields are becoming iconic. Only flooded plots are favored by photographers. But it is not the concept of food or cosmic flow that attracts them. The presence of water only applies to their images because it allows a play of mirrors with the sky.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            However, Chinese painting of mountains and waters, according to Philippe Descola<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn19" id="bodyftn19">19</a> "i<em>s in no way an art setting or an artificialisation of a natural environment, but the image of a correspondence between man and the cosmos which makes visible what, in the world, comes into consonance with human dispositions. (…), it is always a “world in miniature”, to use the expression of Rolf Stein</em>, (…) <em>which reproduces the wide world in which man can both weave affinities and find shelter</em>". This quote echoes the Hani cosmogonic miniaturization, existing through the <em>Bararama</em>,<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn20" id="bodyftn20">20</a> the ceremonial jewel which synthesizes the correspondences established by the Hani (cf. supra Document No. 6). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            Photographers ignore the environment, the ecumene, just as the modern eye has distanced itself from the world. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            Mass tourism requires panoramic views of the landscape, and so observation decks are developed. Like François Jullien I ask the question: “<em>Is it only by sight that one can access the landscape?</em>” For him, in fact, the landscape is “<em>not only a matter of sight, but also of living</em>” (Jullien, 2014). In response to the need for contemplation, the Hani landscape is staged. Landscapes worthy of a "theater scene" or setting. John Brinckerhoff Jackson, in his article "Landscape as Theater", noted the rapprochement between theater and landscape scene, which has operated since the 16th century (Brinckerhoff, 1979). English makes the comparison better with the word scenery. So, in Yunnan, we visit the terraced fields scenery and not only the rice fields, but the inhabitants themselves!
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">C. Indigenization of the landscape</section>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            The regions located at the southern and western margins of China are the ones with the largest proportion of the population who do not belong to the majority Han nationality. Thus, the province of Yunnan, alone embraces 25 ethnic groups - out of the 56 national minorities or ethnic minorities officially listed by the People's Republic of China, including populations of Hani, Tai, Miao and Yi who live nested with each other.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn21" id="bodyftn21">21</a> These ethnic groups who also live beyond the Chinese borders, in Burma, Laos, Vietnam, and Thailand, define their membership with a certain vagueness, as much in relation to a physical territory, as to a national identity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            A source of inspiration in all spheres of Chinese society, the return to tradition is caught up by marketing, which makes it a weighty argument, even a caricature (Liu, 2019). Chinese cultural and heritage tourism therefore plays on several factors: the staging of the landscape, and that of ethnic cultures (Milan, 2012), and therefore offers a journey through the villages of the Red River valley, “packaging” together - combining minority ethnic groups with colorful outfits and rice terraces.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn22" id="bodyftn22">22</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            In addition to the historical propaganda on ethnic minorities inherited from Chinese Marxist social science schools (Wu, 2015 and Guo, 2019), there is the tourist industry's appetite for storytelling. This is how the legend surrounding Hani "mushroom houses" was idealized: <em>“Mount Re Luo is red and green, mushrooms grow everywhere. The little mushroom is not afraid of wind or rain, with a beautiful unforgettable appearance”</em> (Rongxing, 2018) (Document No. 10). The myth of a Hani bioclimatic house "<em>warm in winter and cool in summer, ventilated and dry</em>" (Gao, 2013), thus justifies the choice of property developers who do not hesitate to make the "mushroom house" style an argument sales of stilt houses in their holiday villages (Document No.11).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            Through this marketing strategy for the tourism industry, we are brushing against what the Chinese artist Qiu Zhijie, who was invited to speak at the Louis Vuitton foundation in 2016, denounced as “the superficial exploitation of stereotypes of tradition”.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn23" id="bodyftn23">23</a> He explains: a usage that exploits the appearance of tradition without seeking, either to understand or deepen it, or to deconstruct or make it evolve.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">D. The Heritagization of the "cultural landscape"</section>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            The year 2013 marks even more the turning point in heritage for the Red River valley: the Hani landscape becomes an "object" registered on the UNESCO World Heritage lists,<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn24" id="bodyftn24">24</a> as a cultural landscape, to say that the whole of the ecumene is recognized as having to be preserved, with all the social, religious and ecological organization from which it derives. According to UNESCO: "<em>Works mixing nature and the imprint left by human beings, cultural landscapes express the long and intimate relationship of people with their environment</em>". The Chinese government is required to implement protection and enhancement measures. At first glance, these measures should benefit villages and their populations, unless the vernacular is instrumentalized, it being understood that in China, there can be no question of identity issues. While indigeneity may be recognized as cultural, in no way is political indigeneity recognized; there are no “indigenous peoples” in China.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. Towards New Paradigms</section>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <strong>The "ecological civilization" of the Chinese government</strong>: the challenges of the program: "<em>Ecology, the fight against pollution and climate change, the preservation of biodiversity, are today central concerns for the Chinese authorities</em>", according to the Methodological Guide of the French agency of development, AFD of Beijing.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn25" id="bodyftn25">25</a> Creating the conditions for an "ecological civilization" is a watchword of President Xi Jinping. In 2016, China thus became the world's largest producer of renewable energy (according to the International Energy Agency). In addition, his government wants to close the City / Country inequalities by advocating the economic development of the rural world. This is where tourism, especially eco-tourism, plays a leading role.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            These three factors - ecological transition, economic development, heritage designation of the cultural landscape, in the context of the rice fields of the Red River valley, naturally converge towards the creation of protected areas. In order to avoid the arbitrariness of a top-down policy, several stages will have to be looked at carefully: the concordance of local characteristics with the criteria listed by the experts and ensuing labelling.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Natural Parks: wild landscape vs cultivated landscape</section>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            Sacred vs profane? My photographic works "Degrees I and II" by juxtaposition of the images, pointed out this dualism (Document No. 12). Today, China is faced with this duality in the reflection carried out by its institutions on the creation of "natural parks"<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn26" id="bodyftn26">26</a> studying with interest two models: that of the American National Parks, which concern, "wild" spaces, and the French model, applied to rural and populated areas.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <strong>- US National Parks</strong> could inspire the development of "uninhabited wilderness" in western China. The American model carries with it the threat of relocation of the few populations scattered through the territory to be developed, in order to reinforce the myth of the wilderness. The creation of the American National Parks had heavy consequences for the indigenous populations, in particular that of Yellowstone, on areas supposedly qualified as "uninhabited wilderness", sacred lands belonging to the Cheyenne, among other tribes (Burnham, 2000). But in this, China has no need of a model, having already shown that population displacements are not an obstacle to its spatial planning policy (cf. Three Gorges dam<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn27" id="bodyftn27">27</a>).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <strong>-</strong> <strong>The French model of Regional Natural Park PNRs </strong>is already implemented, with the help of the French Development Agency<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn28" id="bodyftn28">28</a>, in the very dense Zhejiang province, where Xianju National Park (PNX) is nearing completion, on the model of the Ballons des Vosges Regional Natural Park with which it has a partnership. Created in the late sixties, French parks are intended to preserve ecosystems as well as local, artisanal or rural economies (Wang, 2019). The PNX project promises lasting effects "<em>through the establishment of consultative and participatory processes at regional level and capacity-building actions on the governance aspects of the park</em>", with the ambition of replicating this model on a larger scale.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            Same strategy for the WHITRAP agency based in Shanghai and made up of international and Chinese experts (heritage, architecture, anthropology, law, town planning, ecotourism, agronomy, sociology, etc.), which positions itself on small localities, and claims to 'build on local knowledge. In their texts, everything seems well mastered, and extremely virtuous.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            "<em>No territorial strategy should be developed without understanding the complex territorial systems at play and without identifying the cultural and natural, tangible and intangible values of which these landscapes are carriers</em>" (Pola, 2019).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            However, the implementation of these principles attests to another reality.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">V. Perverse Companies of Local Development29</section>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Ecotourism Consumes More Electricity</section>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            This is one of the paradoxes of sustainable development. Because if mass tourism offers development potential in China, it is accompanied by a setback: an exponential demand for energy. Investments by the French Development Agency for Xianju National Park, for example, will only pay off if tourism is full there. However, this is the model that could be applied in Yunnan, in the Red River valley. The sites will only be preserved in exchange for an increase in tourist capacity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            As we mentioned in the introduction, this province is located almost at the source of three rivers with significant flows. As a result, many dams produce hydroelectricity in abundance, so much so that Kunming, the provincial capital of five million inhabitants, runs on all-electric (cars and two-wheelers). Since the construction of hydroelectric dams upstream of the Red River, there have been disturbances in its downstream part, such as those that Vietnam already deplores. But there is reason to fear that the entire river will run out of water to irrigate the terraces, as well as an increasing risk of erosion.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn30" id="bodyftn30">30</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <strong>Two-speed ecology</strong>. Experts from the National Cultural Heritage Administration rehabilitate the villages that are part of the World Heritage List. Question: what will happen to the villages which do not meet all the heritage criteria and which, falling outside the analytical measures of experts, are not eligible for a development policy? The Hani village described above is a typical case of this: located less than 10 km from a village identified, him, as "of high heritage value", and preserved as such, (explanatory panels in English-Mandarin in front reconstructions of wash house, rice mill, buffalo sacrifice altar, controlled waste management) it eludes the cultural and environmental preservation strategy. Preservation does not concern the village or the rice fields that feed it. Unchanged at first glance, rice fields are today polluted by the water that feeds them, laden with products resulting from changes in consumption by residents. In the village streets, the gutters carry the wrappings of candy paper and other packaged products<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn31" id="bodyftn31">31</a> now replacing the tofu skewers of local merchants (Document No. 13). The village is distorted by a wild development of new construction, disastrous waste and wastewater management, and all these points would become problematic if the village welcomed tourists. Not to mention the problematic destruction of the forests and the alteration of its ecosystem.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. Cultivating the landscape for rural tourism</section>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            The heritage of the rice terraces in the Red River valley calls for a question (Chan <em>et al.</em>, 2016). Will the “UNESCO World Heritage” label condemn the Hani rice farmers to <em>cultivate the landscape</em> forever, and soon be subsidized to maintain this tourist place?<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn32" id="bodyftn32">32</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            The inscription on the UNESCO World Heritage List was immediately followed by action. Thus, in 2013, as part of the policy of reviving rural "Chinese Traditional Villages", the Chinese government launched extensive propaganda, relying on television. Rural heritage is presented here as an important lever for economic development for local governments and the tourism industries. The television documentary series <em>Nostalgia</em>, produced by the "Central Propaganda Department of the State Administration for the Press" for CCTV, the national channel, depicts the village of Huanglingcun, in the province of Jiangxi, surrounded by forests and terraced fields. The reconstructions of traditional dwellings are a counterpart to the landscape setting, and the cultivated fields in terraces are planted with different seeds varying according to the seasons and the aesthetic expectation of visitors who can admire them from an overhanging walkway.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">VI. Alternatives</section>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            The description of the village of Huanglingcun did not come from a dystopia, but from one of the perverse effects of the very vertical system of rural development. Critical voices are heard from different spheres, both in the social sciences - anthropologists are attentive to the changes at work in the Chinese minority ethnic groups,<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn33" id="bodyftn33">33</a> as in that of contemporary arts and cinema, all inspired by a back to basics. They stress the importance of the local and peripheral point of view (McLaren, 2011).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. “Native” Ecology</section>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            At the end of the 1990s, a concept emerged in the literature, then in the academic world, that of yuanshengtai (原 生态), which could be translated as “native ecology” or primitive (Yu L., 2018). This notion is found at the intersection of concerns about the harmony between nature and man, the coexistence and preservation of heritage, knowledge and indigenous arts. The notion of "native ecology" has been widely misused by marketing and the media, after having been the prerogative of cultural elites, the risking becoming a fixed vision of the "primitive" and the "authentic", particularly in landscape planning policies.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. The return to the land of contemporary Chinese artists</section>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            In 2016, the Louis Vuitton foundation presents the exhibition "Bentu, Chinese artists in the turbulence of change".<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn34" id="bodyftn34">34</a> Bentu, (本土 běn tǔ), literally, these are the roots, in the sense of going back to the origins, a term which could have been perceived as deeply derogatory twenty years ago, with even a chauvinistic connotation, but which knows a particular revival in China, especially in the field of contemporary Chinese art. This concept which can echo that of <em>yuanshengtai</em>, is today at the center of the reflections of artists, critics and researchers. Artists claim cultural heterogeneity, unlike a culture imposed from a center, and tend to abolish the distance between center and periphery.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn35" id="bodyftn35">35</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            Artist Liu Xiaodong, from a village in Liaoning Province, returns to the scene thirty years later. His oil portraits on canvas are related to the vernacular photography, in form, as in approach, for example when he documents the daily life of his worker and peasant friends in a space where he noted the deep transformations, social, urban, ecological (Document No. 14).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            Inspired by classical painting, Qiu Zhijie offers <em>From Huaxia to </em>China, a panorama composed of mountain and river landscapes that reflects the mutations that have transformed China in recent years, culturally, economically, politically and spiritually (see above, Qiu Zhijie's critical discourse on the exploitation of tradition, during a conference at the Louis Vuitton Foundation) (Document No. 15).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            The works of these artists of different generations reflect new trends in economics and ecology and among them, notably, the transformation of the urban/rural relationship. Artist Hu Xiangqian goes even further in a critique of centralized governance in 2013 with his video work "Speech at the Edge of the World". We see the artist performing a speech before an assembly of students lined up in a row. Coming from a city that he locates as <em>a corner of land lost at the end of the world</em>, in the far south of Guangdong province, he addresses students as a coach would do to motivate them, according to methods in the management of the business world, urging them to “<em>And then we will find solutions to these problems</em>”,<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn36" id="bodyftn36">36</a> this <em>we</em> being understood to be that of the people directly concerned, a local <em>we</em>, and not the <em>we</em> of a central or a global world.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            To satisfy both local interests - poverty reduction, maintenance of ancestral culture, and challenges on the scale of a globalized world - tourism economy, the experiences of other rural landscapes developed for tourism in China can be rich in education. In the autonomous region of Guangxi, the village of Ping An presents a similar problem, with a community of rice farmers in irrigated terraces of Zhuang nationality.<a class="endnotecall" href="#ftn37" id="bodyftn37">37</a> In 1993, during an ethnographic mission with the Nanning Academy of Social Sciences, I was able to note the existing tensions between rice farmers and players in an emerging tourism economy. While the latter took off at the expense of agriculture, the major question was already that of maintaining the terraces cultivated as tourist objects, with the concern for finding labor. Since then, local governance has created grants for families who make their only livelihood from the land. We can already take stock of the first studies conducted (Kimel, 2015). Here I give some directions in order to preserve the future and minority landscapes and cultures.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="53">
            The first track primarily concerns the inhabitants, the first concerned.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="54">
            They would aim to ensure self-sufficiency or at least food security, to make them benefit equitably and consequently from the spinoffs of the tourist economy and related sectors such as that of leisure real estate, by avoiding speculation on cultivable land, to ensure the representativeness of the Hani in the local authorities (provincial, municipal and village), this to counterbalance the ideological influence of the central government, to encourage the actors of tourism to consume local and equitable, this by limiting the "branding" of the territory and by strongly involving local actors.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="55">
            The second part concerns the environment in its entirety, mountain, forest, spring, village, rice fields and river. It would anticipate ecosystem risks by reforesting, treating soil erosion and landslides, controlling water and soil pollution. Then, it could be necessary to limit consumption (water, electricity), by educating and encouraging less harmful practices by limiting motorized traffic, and encouraging crop diversification, by helping to maintain local food crops. But the fundamental question is that of water resources, which can only be dealt with at the same time as that of energy (dams, reservoirs), which is a national question. Tourism can help protect cultivated landscapes, as is the case in Japan, the Philippines and Indonesia. Clifford Geertz studied the ancestral irrigation system in Bali, and said, "<em>An established society is the end product of such a long history of adaptation to its environment that it has made this environment, in a way, a dimension of itself</em>”.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="56">
            What I want to recall with this quote is that, however important the changes that the Hani have been going through since the early 2000s, the foundation of their culture will remain partly because it is already listed as World Heritage and artists and researchers continue to document it. Although in 2015 Hani rice farmers were primarily concerned with leaving precarious living conditions, it may be that in a few years young Hani people will find an interest in the existence of a visual archive fund which, modestly, I will have participated. Each of my visits to the Ma family has led me to see parts of their culture disappear. This observation motivated my work as an artist mainly consisting of inventorying, securing traces, imprints of what existed, creating the visual archive. My primary objective was to give them these collections of drawings and photographs.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="57">
            The objects I work on are not neutral, politically speaking. By deepening them, I clearly saw their connections with the global world, the sharing of resources, the challenges of spatial planning, as well as the relationship between a minority culture and a dominant culture. As part of a French tradition of intellectuals and committed artists, I chose, as an artist working on coloniality, to position myself on the side of the dominated and threatened culture, that of the Hani culture (Quiroz, 2019).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="58">
            So I also wanted to point out the risk of seeing a minority culture disappear, replaced by the standards of life of the dominant Han culture, whether in language, education, architecture, environment and landscape. There remains, in my opinion, another development model to invent in the decades to come.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="59">
            The artist is a whistleblower, a role that the Chinese artists I have cited have seized upon to point out the traps of branding or folklorization of tradition, both for material and intangible culture. This paper is therefore intended to be an illustration of the questions that contemporary artists - in the movement of the “artist as an ethnographer” identified by Hal Foster, can raise and make visible, and, from there, this paper attempts to move the lines between the academic and artistic spheres, giving a different status to the image, that of a manifesto.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Augé, M. (1997), La Guerre des rêves. Exercices d'ethno-fiction, Le Seuil, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Bái, Y. (2013), 哈尼族服饰文化中的历史记忆:以云南省绿春县"窝拖布玛"为例, 云南人民出版社.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (1994), Dirigé par, Cinq propositions pour une théorie du paysage. Pays Paysage, Champ Vallon, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (1995, réed. 1998), Les Raisons du paysage. De la Chine antique aux environnements de synthèse, Hazan, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Bouchery, P. (1995), Les Hani, introduction à l’étude d’une population tibéto-birmane du Yunnan en relation avec la Chine. Thèse de doctorat, Université Paris X, Nanterre.</reference>
        <reference>Bouchery, P. (1999), « La rizière, "écosystème spécialisé" ? Un cas dans le sud-ouest chinois », in Études rurales N°151-152, Autres temps, autres lieux, pp. 133-165.</reference>
        <reference>Bouchery, P. (2010), “Terrace Cultivation and Mental Landscapes in Southern Yunnan”, in Lecomte-Tilouine (Ed) Nature, Culture and Religion at the Crossroads of Asia, Routledge, New Delhi.</reference>
        <reference>Bouchery, P. (2012), « La cosmogonie des Hani au regard des matériaux de la Chine ancienne », in Archives de sciences sociales des religions, 2012/2, N° 158, Éditions de l'EHESS, p. 11-31, https://doi.org/10.4000/assr.23821, (accessed May 2020).</reference>
        <reference>Brinckerhoff Jackson, J. (1979), “Landscape as Theater”, in The Necessity of Ruins and other Topics. Univ. of Massachusetts Press.</reference>
        <reference>Burnham, P. (2000), Indian Country, God's Country: Native Americans and the National Parks, Island Press, Washington, D.C.</reference>
        <reference>Chan J., C., Ying, Z., McDonald, T. and Qi, X. (2016), “Entrepreneurship in an indigenous community: sustainable tourism and economic development in a newly inscribed UNESCO World Heritage Site”, in Iankova K., Hassan A. and L'Abbe R. (Eds), Indigenous People and Economic Development: An International Perspective, Routledge, New York, pp189-204.</reference>
        <reference>Cheng, F. (1979), Vide et plein – Le langage pictural chinois, Seuil, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Condominas, G. (1965 réed 2006) L’Exotique est quotidien. Sar Luk, Vietnam central, « Terre humaine », Plon, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Cuthbert, D. (1998) “Beg, borrow or steal: The politics of cultural appropriation”, Postcolonial Studies Vol. 1, N°2, pp. 257-262.</reference>
        <reference>Descola, P. (2005), Par-delà nature et culture, Bibliothèque des sciences humaines, Gallimard, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Eliade, M. (1965), Le sacré et le profane. Paris, Gallimard.</reference>
        <reference>Enwezor, O. (2002), “The Black Box,” in Okwui Enwezor et al., eds., Documenta11_Platform 5: Exhibition catalogue, Hatje Cantz, Ostfildern-Ruit, pp. 42–55.</reference>
        <reference>Enwezor, O. (2012), Intense proximité : une anthologie du proche et du lointain, CNAP, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Ex-Souza, F. (2020), "Du nous au je. Recherche artistique décoloniale", Tumultes n°54.</reference>
        <reference>Foster, H. (1996), "The Artist as Ethnographer," in The Return of the Real, Cambridge, The MIT Press.</reference>
        <reference>Gao, K. (2013), “Form and god of the cultural landscape on Hani terrace in Honghe”, Journal of Kunming University of Science and Technology, Social Science Edition, Vol. 6 n°13, pp. 91-97.</reference>
        <reference>Geertz, C. (1972), "Religious change and social order in Soeharto’s Indonesia", Asia (New-York/ N.Y./USA: Asia Society), Vol. 27 N°1, pp. 62-84.</reference>
        <reference>Guo, W. (2019), Narrating Southern Chinese Minority Nationalities: Politics, Disciplines, and Public History. New Directions in East Asian History, Palgrave Macmillan, Singapore.</reference>
        <reference>Jiao, Y., Liang, L., Okuro, T. and Takeuchi, K. (2011), “Indigenous ecological knowledge and natural resource management in the cultural landscape of China’s Hani Terraces”, Ecological Research, Vol. 27, pp. 247–263.</reference>
        <reference>Jiao, Y., Liang, L., Okuro, T. and Takeuchi, K. (2014), “Ecosystem Services and Biodiversity of Traditional Agricultural Landscapes: A Case Study of the Hani Terraces in Southwest China”, in Hong SK., Bogaert J. and Min Q. (Eds) Biocultural Landscape, Springer, Dordrecht.</reference>
        <reference>Jullien, F. (2014), Vivre de paysage ou L'impensé de la Raison, Gallimard, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Kimmel, C.E., Perlstein, A., Mortimer, M.J., Zhou, D. and Robertson, D.P. (2015), Sustainability of tourism as development strategy for cultural-Landscapes in China: case study of Ping'An village, Journal of Rural and Community Development, Vol. 10, pp. 121-135.</reference>
        <reference>Kleinwechter, U. (2012), "Rural-urban migration in China: An analytical framework of migrants’ contributions to rural development", in Journal of Alternative Perspectives in the Social Sciences Vol. 4, No 4, pp. 757-789.</reference>
        <reference>Lévi-Strauss, C. (2011), L’anthropologie face aux problèmes du monde moderne, Seuil, coll. La librairie du XXIe siècle, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Liu, Y. (2019), “Authenticity, Tourism and Residents: the Dilemma of Heritage Conservation in China”, in Modu Magazine: A Tale of Urban China, https://www.modumag.com/articles/authenticity-tourism-and-residents-the-dilemma-of-heritage-conservation-in-china/ (accessed March 2020)</reference>
        <reference>McLaren, A. (2011), “Environment and Cultural Heritage in China: Introduction” in Asian Studies Review Vol. 4 n°35, pp. 429-437.</reference>
        <reference>Milan, P. (2012), « Contournement et instrumentalisation de l’identité culturelle Mosuo dans la rencontre touristique », in Via Tourism Review n°2 (accessed March 2020)</reference>
        <reference>Mullaney, T. (2001), Coming to Terms with the Nation, Ethnic Classification in Modern China, University of California Press, Berkeley.</reference>
        <reference>Pola, A. (2019), When Heritage Is Rural: Environmental Conservation, Cultural Interpretation and Rural Renaissance in Chinese Listed Villages, https://www.academia.edu/39691605/When_Heritage_Is_Rural_Environmental_Conservation_Cultural_Interpretation_and_Rural_Renaissance_in_Chinese_Listed_Villages (accessed March 2020).</reference>
        <reference>Quiroz, L. (2019), "Le leurre de l’objectivité scientifique. Lieu d’énonciation et colonialité du savoir", Nouveaux Imaginaires, La production du savoir : formes, légitimations, enjeux et rapport au monde, accessed June 2020 : https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02422696.</reference>
        <reference>Rancière, J. (2004), The Politics of Aesthetics. The Distribution for the Sensible, (trans Rockhill G.), York and New York, NY.</reference>
        <reference>Roger, A. (1997), Court traité du paysage, Gallimard, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Rongxing, X. (2018), “The Pattern Language Construction of Landscape Space of Hani Traditional Settlement in Yuanyang, Yunnan Province”, https://www.atlantis-press.com/proceedings/ieesasm-17/25889611 (accessed March 2020)</reference>
        <reference>Wang, Q. « Parcs naturels, valorisation des paysages, reconversion des territoires », conférence du 15 octobre 2019, en ligne sur le site de la Cité de l'architecture et du Patrimoine : https://www.citedelarchitecture.fr/fr/evenement/parcs-naturels-valorisation-des-paysages-reconversion-des-territoires (accessed June 2020)</reference>
        <reference>Wang, Q. and Zhou, J. (2019), The Balance Between Environmental Protection and Regional Development: France's “Regional Natural Park” System and Practice/Yang Chen. Planners, n°17 pp. 36-43.</reference>
        <reference>Wu, K. (2015), Reinventing Chinese Tradition: The Cultural Politics of Late Socialism, University of Illinois Press</reference>
        <reference>Xin, L. (2000), In One’s Own Shadow: An Ethnographic Account of the Condition of Post-reform Rural China, University of California Press, Berkeley.</reference>
        <reference>Yuen, S. (2014), "Une nouvelle réforme foncière chinoise ? Évaluation et perspectives", trad.in Perspectives Chinoises N°1, pp. 65-70.</reference>
        <reference>Yu, L. (2018), “Alternative Indigeneity in China? The Paradox of the Buyi in the Age of Ethnic Branding” in Verge: Studies in Global Asias n°2, Vol. 4 pp. 107-134.</reference>
        <reference>Zhu, Y. (2012), “Performing Heritage: Rethinking Authenticity in Global Tourism”, Annals of Tourism Research Vol. 3 n°39, pp. 1495-1513.</reference>
        <reference>Zhu, Y. (2015), “Cultural Effects of Authenticity: Contested Heritage Practices in China”, International Journal of Heritage Studies, Vol. 6 n°21, pp. 594-608.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">Cultural appropriation manifests itself when a dominant group borrows or consumes elements of a minority culture, such as the presence of Native American headdresses worn in fashion shows in recent news, for example; I would like to make it clear that this is not a bilateral cultural exchange. (Cuthbert, 1998).</note>
        <note id="2">Enwezor defines the Documenta 11 exhibition as “a constellation of disciplinary models that seek to explain and interrogate ongoing historical processes and radical change, spatial and temporal dynamics, as well as fields of actions and ideas, and systems of interpretation and production” (Enwezor, 2002, p49 Platforms: Five Constellations, Domains of Knowledge and Artistic Productions, Circuits of Research).</note>
        <note id="3">In the context of this article, these are minority ethnic groups in a province of the People's Republic of China which does not recognize indigenous peoples, but the pre-eminence of the doctrine of the center over that of the periphery is established there.</note>
        <note id="4">On the use of the I, see Fabiana Ex-Souza (2020)</note>
        <note id="5">The title Riken no ken, an expression of Japanese Noh theater, meaning "the detached gaze" (Zeami 1363-1443) inspired Claude Lévi Strauss who questions the position of the ethnologist (Lévi Strauss 2011). He evokes the technique of expatriation as a means of placing oneself within and which allows the ethnologist to identify with the group whose existence he shares, at the same time as he can stand at a distance allowing him to see himself - from the outside. Hani women wanted me to put on their costume, the Riken no ken portrait is the result of a collaboration.</note>
        <note id="0">he curator of the exhibition, Okwui Enwezor claimed this distance while defending the concept of "Intense Proximity" for the 2012 Triennale at the Palais de Tokyo. (Enwezor, 2012)</note>
        <note id="6">“Visible minority” means that, although I am French by birth, I am assigned a separate identity because I appear to be on an “ethnic” origin.</note>
        <note id="7">In ethnography, a conversation with Martine Bouchier, published in Afrikadaa, I cite Georges Condominas “How can we be Métis? heHe writes, planning to devote an ethnological study to the Métis, each of whom is in a way a small ethnic minority ”. Afrikadaa n°9 (2015), pp. 120-127, accessed June 2020 : </note>
        <note id="0">ttps://issuu.com/afrikadaamagazine/docs/_9-anthropologismes</note>
        <note id="8">I report in detail on this process and on the function of drawing, a medium that allows interaction, in a conversation with Martine Bouchier (ibid.)</note>
        <note id="9">Translation by Pascal Bouchery.</note>
        <note id="10">Bouchery, (2012) on Hani cosmogony: “its narrative structure has affinities with the story of a cosmogonic nature contained in the famous Almanac de Qu from the Warring States period."</note>
        <note id="11">For the connection between ancient Chinese cosmogeny and that of the Hani, see Bouchery 2010 and 2012.</note>
        <note id="12">Quote from the painter Zong Bing, 4th century, Hurvitz L. 1970, "Tsung Ping's Comments on Landscape Painting", Artibus Asiae, Vol. 32, No. 2-3, pp. 146–156</note>
        <note id="13">Quote from Mircea Eliade in The Sacred and the Profane, 1965.</note>
        <note id="14">The surname has been changed. My hosts are not my "informants" in the sense of ethnological research. Also, I do not want to exploit their image or the opinions delivered in a private context. It would have been very different if they had expressed the wish to participate and at that time, I would have liked them to be co-authors. The abandonment of my thesis in geography, my leaving university, and the choice of artist status were for me acts of deconstruction of the university status. I am fully aware of the fact that the artist is sometimes in a dominant position similar to that of the anthropologist. But in my opinion, this dominance is closely intertwined with the future of the "materials" collected, transformed or created: will they be exhibited, sold, in other words, is the culture of "the Other" subject to a kind of cultural appropriation? I continue to wonder about these complex issues.</note>
        <note id="15">This knowledge, in particular the very rich pharmacopoeia noted by Bouchery (1999), undergoes a form of epistemic oppression.</note>
        <note id="16">Beijing's policy which included the first two phases - the construction of an institutional and governance framework to revitalize rural areas by 2020, and the modernization of rural areas and agriculture by 2030. https://www.scmp.com/news/china/politics/article/2189358/china-plans-law-make-reviving-rural-areas-priority-modernisation</note>
        <note id="17">The only representations of rice fields are from the 1637 Tiangong Kaiwu Treaty (天工 開 物), "The Exploitation of Works of Nature", including illustrations from the point of view of agriculture and crafts.</note>
        <note id="18">https://www.chinahighlights.com/kunming/photography-tips-at-yuanyang-terraces.htm</note>
        <note id="19">Op. cit.</note>
        <note id="20">The Ma family separated from this ceremonial jewel, and I found a photograph of it in a work published in Yunnan (Bai, 2013, p. 91)</note>
        <note id="21">少数民族, shǎoshù mínzú, minority nationalities, the number 56 was contested in 1953 before being officially adopted in 1954; this was particularly true in the Province of Yunnan where 200 different ethnic groups claimed to exist (Mullaney, 2011).</note>
        <note id="22">Yu L., “Packaging Craftwork, Sharing Heritage: Collaborative Brand Promotion in Multiethnic Southwest China”, International Conference of Asian Scholars, ICAS 11, 2019, Leiden.</note>
        <note id="23">Invited to the Symposium held at the Louis Vuitton Foundation on March 12, 2016 on the sidelines of the Bentu exhibition, by Philip Tinari, co-curator and director of the UCCA art center in Beijing.</note>
        <note id="24">Cultural landscape of the rice terraces of the Hani of Honghe: https://whc.unesco.org/fr/list/1111/</note>
        <note id="25">Agence française de développement website: https://www.afd.fr/sites/afd/files/2018-10-11-24-38/guide-methodologique-dispositif-analyse-avis-d%C3%A9velopement -sustainable.pdf</note>
        <note id="26">Wang Q., “Natural parks, enhancement of landscapes, reconversion of territories”, conference of October 15, 2019, online on the site of the City of Architecture and Heritage: https://www.citedelarchitecture.fr/fr / event / natural-parks-enhancement-of-landscapes-reconversion-of-territories</note>
        <note id="27">The socio-political effects of forced migration in China, related to major hydraulic works: see the example of the Three Gorges Dam https://www.sciencespo.fr/ceri/sites/sciencespo.fr.ceri/files/etude103.pdf</note>
        <note id="28">Agence française de développement website: https://www.afd.fr/sites/afd/files/2018-10-11-24-38/guide-methodologique-dispositif-analyse-avis-d%C3%A9velopement -sustainable.pdf</note>
        <note id="29">I borrow this expression from Michael Cernea, quoted here: https://journals.openedition.org/geocarrefour/504#ftn2</note>
        <note id="30">2005 World Article, "Hydroelectric dams, modern scourge of minorities in Chinese Yunnan" https://www.lemonde.fr/asie-pacifique/article/2005/07/02/les-barrages-hydroelectriques-fleau-moderne- des-minorites-du-yunnan-chinois_668681_3216.html</note>
        <note id="31">Minhua L . L. Consumption of Packaged Convenience Food among Left-behind Children in Rural China, International Conference of Asian Scholars, ICAS 11, 2019, Leiden.</note>
        <note id="32">Agricultural work is particularly difficult due to the steep slope of the land, which results in narrow plots which are thereby unsuitable for mechanization.</note>
        <note id="33">As attested by the case of anthropologist Yu Xiaogang who became a fervent defender of the environment of minority ethnic groups within the NGO Green Watershed, https://chinadialogue.net/en/climate/8785-yu-xiaogang-wins-prize-for-community-conservation/</note>
        <note id="34">Exhibition catalog, edited by Pagé S., Bossé L. and Tinari P., 2016, Bentu: Chinese artists in the turbulence of mutations, The exhibitions, Paris, Louis Vuitton Foundation</note>
        <note id="35">Dao M., 2016 “Return to the Countryside. The : Chinese artists at the Louis Vuitton Foundation” http://vernaculaire-adventice.com/retour-a-la-campagne-artistes-chinois-a-la-fondation-louis-vuitton/</note>
        <note id="36">“We should seek for the source of the problem, and then try to find the solution”. Translation by Hu Xiangqian</note>
        <note id="37">However, it should be noted that the status of the "Autonomous Region" of Guangxi "offers more autonomy to the Zhuang of Guangxi than that of "the province" of Yunnan to the Hani</note>
    </notes>
</article>