<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_MLVR_58-82_Im_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3474" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.3474</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>15</numero>
        <annee>2019</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <traduction lang="pt" source="3499">Comunidades indígenas do trapézio amazônico colombiano: imaginários sociais e turismo</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Rivas" prenom="Marta Lucía Vélez" email="martha.velez@uexternado.edu.co">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="pt_MLVR_74-85_Co_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3499" lang="pt">Comunidades indígenas do trapézio amazônico colombiano: imaginários sociais e turismo</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Anthropologist, National University of Colombia. PhD candidate in Social Studies, Universidad Externado de Colombia. Teacher-Researcher Faculty of Tourism and Hotel Business Administration University Externado of Colombia. Bogota Colombia. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Indigenous communities of colombian amazon trapeze: social imaginaries and tourism</titre>
    <resume>
        The objective of the research is to understand the social imaginary concerning the indigenous communities that reside in the Amazonian Trapeze and its influence on the tourist experience. The historical relationship of mestizo society towards indigenous communities, is expressed in power relations constructed since the colonial past, which is materialized today in exclusion, social inequality, exoticization and ignorance of the other. Such a relationship also comes alive in the tourist imaginary: what is offered to the tourist reproduces the power plays and market relations that exist between businessmen, tourists and indigenous communities. The latter in turn, resignify identities and practices, as forms of resistance or adaptation, which influences the construction of new imaginaries and the tourist experiences.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            Social imaginaries build realities that influence the relationships that are woven between individuals or social groups. Although they are based on subjectivity and imagination, they have a significant impact on such relationships.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            These imaginaries are built up, in some cases, during a long-term historical process, created from different voices and discursive forms.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            For tourism purposes, they can determine, to a large extent, the tourist’s choices, their itineraries and their experience in the territory, as well as tourist advertisements and products and the roles of the participating actors.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            The analysis of the social imaginary and particularly of the tourist imaginary allows us to understand the tensions and dynamics of the relationships that are woven between tourists and local people.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the case of the Amazon, the social imaginary about the original peoples is forged from the narratives of chroniclers of the Indies, in the 16th century. Gaspar de Carvajal accompanied the first expedition of Francisco de Orellana along the Amazon River, in search of cinnamon, and gave a name to this territory, a name that refers to Greek mythology and that survives until today with the same mythic power.<br/>Subsequently, imaginary has been forged from the stories told in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, by travelers, adventurers and scientists who visited the Amazon, and including texts, photographs, drawings and manuscripts. They are part of European scientific expeditions composed of French such as Paul Marcoy, the expedition led Count Francis Castelneau between 1843 and 1847; or by Coudreau and Crevaux and by the Italian Boggiani</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">; as well as by the English as Captain Thomas Whiffen, author of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Northwest Amazon: Notes of some Months Spent among Cannibal Tribes </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(1915) and by Germans such as Theodor Koch-Grünberg, who wrote </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Cannibalism in the Indians of South America</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1899), </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Concerning Animism among South American Indians</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1900) and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Two years among Indians: Trips through the Brazilian northwest 1903-1905 </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(re-published in 1967), among other documents.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Many films that have depicted the Amazon, but some classics such as </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Aguirre or the Wrath of God</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1972) and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Fitzcarraldo</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1982) by Werner Herzog stand out; more recent ones include, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Apaporis, Secret of the Jungle</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2012) by Antonio Dorado, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Grip of the Snake</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and currently, on Netflix, the production </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Green Border</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.<br/>Literature has also constructed an imaginary of the jungle, as the "Green Hell", recreated in the novel </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Vorágine</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1924) by José Eustasio Rivera, "which was portrayed as the echo of wild nature, where men were infected - in a kind of mimesis - with the same wild condition” (Pineda, 2005, p.122), a novel that was compulsory reading for schoolchildren during the twentieth century.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Some other novels that have the Amazon as a backdrop are: </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lost in the Amazon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1978) by Germán Castro Caicedo; </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The River of desolation: a Journey through the Amazon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2006) by Javier Rerverté; the historical novel, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Conquest of the Amazon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2000) by Edward Rosset; and the trilogy about the conquest of the Amazon by William Ospina: </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ursúa</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2005), </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Country of Cinnamon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2008) and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Snake without Eyes</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2012).<br/><br/>The chronicles of the Indians, such as the literature by travelers, expeditionaries, explorers, novels, and cinema, have built both the social imaginary of this territory and of the indigenous communities that inhabit it, which is reflected in the imaginary created in tourist activities. Thus, in tourist practices, the representations and images that are developed for the promotion of the destinations of the Amazon are inspired by the social imaginary about the indigenous communities and, generally, the most “exotic” or “authentic” elements of their cultures.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            As a consequence, a seductive game is presented: on the one hand, there are images made by tourism agents that seek to attract travelers to a still pristine and untouched world, where authenticity is the main merchandise (Cohen 1979; 1989; Errington and Gewertz 1989; Simondson 1995 cited by Salazar, N., 2006, p. 104), which is constructed through the "tourist gaze" (Urry, 2002). On the other, the representations that the local communities make about themselves, are more similar to the external images projected on them, so that the imaginary of the tourist becomes a reality. The power relations alternate between them although, in general, the tour operators are the ones who have the last word because they “pay” to see what they have “sold” to tourists, thus constructing the staged authenticities, as described by MacCannell (2013). The insertion of these communities into global system is demonstrated by generating ruptures in the pretense of showing tourists a culture not permeated by external forces.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. Methodology</section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To understand the social and tourist imaginaries concerning indigenous communities, secondary sources were analyzed to develop the theoretical-conceptual framework (Gravari-Barbas and Graburn, 2012; Hiernaux, 2002; Lindón and Hiernaux, 2012; MacCannell, 2003; Debarbieux, Staszak, and Tebbaa, 2012; Silva, 2013). On the other hand, primary sources were also collected: narratives and stories in chronicles of the Indies (Gaspar de Carvajal), tourist guides (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">le Petit Futé</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">), websites of tourism advertizing in the Colombian Amazon and travel blogs. A survey of thirty-two students who visited the region was carried out. The survey was undertaken in order to learn the perceptions that tourists have about the Amazon and its indigenous communities, as well as to determine the most visited places, the means through which they obtained knowledge of the Amazon and its indigenous communities, and the ways they lived their experience with each other.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            A field visit was also made to the municipalities of Leticia and Puerto Nariño as well as to the Isla de los Micos and Macedonia. Such field data illustrates the touristic opportunities that include indigenous communities as well as the relationships that are woven between visitors and host populations.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">II. Social and tourist imaginary</section>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            The perspective of the social and tourist imaginaries - understood as both subjective and as a manifestation of the human condition associated with the imagination - allows us to understand the contemporary dynamics that occur both in the visiting territories and in the present relations between residents and tourists (Gravari-Barbas and Graburn, 2012; Hiernaux, 2002; MacCannell, 2003).<br/>These imaginaries are built in various stages: before, during and after the trip, and through stories associated with tourism or independent of it. They also incorporate family and social experiences as well as narratives and stories embodied in literature, film, plastic media and social networks, among other sources.<br/><br/>Tourism agents, meanwhile, circulate such imaginaries, mediating them for their purposes (Debarbieux, 2012) and promoting the resignification of territories, landscapes and cultural practices, transforming them into consumer products (Gravari-Barbas and Graburn, 2012), creating new local identities (Salazar cited in Gravari-Barbas and Graburn, 2012) and thus modifying the way in which local communities see and represent themselves (Debarbieux, Staszak, and Tebbaa, 2012).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            A relevant aspect of social imaginaries is their effect on social relations, since they are experienced as truths, although they cannot be empirically proven (Silva, 2013). Therefore, "the imaginary, (...), is real as a social effect" (2013, p.30), because it obeys "rules, representations, deep discursive and social formations, of deep cultural manifestation" (2013, p. 38) that make socially accepted truths emerge (Silva, 2013), hence the social power and the importance of its understanding and analysis. This conception differs from that proposed by Cornelius Castoriadis, who starts from the imaginary as "absolute invention" or from the displacement of meaning of symbols that are invested with meanings different from "normal" or "canonical" ones; however, it develops the concept of radical imaginary, as a matrix that forms the basis of thought, of acting and of perception and that gives meaning to the social.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            According to Hiernaux, the imaginary 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The tourist imaginary is then defined by Hiernaux as "that portion of the social imaginary relevant to the tourist event, that is, the numerous manifestations of the corporate travel process" (2002, p. 8).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, the tourist imaginary is created about the tourist place and the active participants in tourism, particularly the tourists and the host communities: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The stories, narratives and images that go to make up social and tourist imaginaries can influence the decisions of tourists. Therefore, the consultation of guides, photographs, blogs of travelers and social networks in which opinions are exchanged concerning the tourist experience, regain such importance and have such power over potential tourists that it may be able to make them give up or change course, in search of destinations more in line with their expectations. The power of these statements depends largely on the credibility of their enunciators. Opinion influencers fulfill the function of motivating readers towards what is fashionable, but also any traveler who leaves their opinion recorded in the networks can influence travel decisions. Such influencers can be famous characters in national life, in the international jet-set, they can be young bloggers or youtoubers, magazines or prestigious publications that infect their readers with the "new" trends.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">III. Historical relationship of Colombian society towards the Native Communities of the Amazon rainforest.</section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">One pillar in the construction of social imaginaries of the indigenous communities of the Amazon rainforest is found in the descriptions made by chroniclers of the Indies which led to colonial policies of submission and exclusion that justified ill-treatment and slavery, and which subsequently had repercussions on Colombian society<br/><br/>Then, the story of travelers strengthens the images refined in difference, an image reaffirmed in principle by science and then used for publicity about the destination.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The relationship of the white, patriarchal society to indigenous communities has been marked by exclusion and a lack of recognition of indigenous societies as having a social and political organization and ancestral knowledge. This relationship makes a pillar of “the difference” and such a view of the Other has repercussions in public policies, in government initiatives and in the approach of a society that, although mixed, feels more identified with the Spanish white heritage, and in that sense reproduces, in some way, exclusionary practices.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Since their arrival, the Spaniards persecuted and exterminated a large proportion of the original communities of the territory, claiming that they professed a system of "diabolical" beliefs and religious practices outside Christian morals. Also, and primarily, the Spaniards were driven by the desire to accumulate territory, wealth and power. With them the caste regime was established, based on ethnic discrimination, in which the Spanish were at the top of the pyramid and enjoyed rights and privileges that decreased as individuals moved away from this racial paradigm. At least sixteen racial types were distinguished according to mixtures and mergers, however, by the middle of the 18th century due to the intense miscegenation, such a system lost its validity and applicability. Currently, social exclusionary practices in the country reproduce in some way the colonial mentality and persist with greater vigor towards the same population groups as at that time: Afro-descendants and indigenous people, women and the poor population.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These positions on the submission of the Indians were permanent, with exceptions such as Bartolomé de las Casas (1474 or 1484-1556) who became one of the greatest defenders of the rights of the natives, while mostly the encomenderos, chroniclers and Spaniards who lived in America or even those who had not stepped on American soil considered the indigenous people as belonging to a lower culture that deserved to be subjugated.<br/><br/>During the colonial period the caste regime then constituted a form of social regulation through which the hegemony of the white social group is privileged, heirs of the Spaniards who held privileges and rights that were denied to the other social groups.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Such thinking was dominant even during the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, a time when Colombian humanists and thinkers resumed the perspective that gave continuity to an exclusionary interpretation of society.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">José María Samper (1828-1888), was one of those intellectuals; described as a humanist, journalist, writer, politician, in his "Essay on political revolutions" (1861) collects concepts that are focused on the races to which he describes as pure-impure, and therefore to societies with a prevalence of barbarian characteristics line up against others, who would be civilized. Associates elements such as "racial" purity, wealth, the opulent, beauty, the refined, the nobility, the enlightened, the esteemed, the splendid, the worthy of Europe, the "upper classes of the society” (Gómez Muller 1997, p.15).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the contrary, the state of barbarism is associated with the "racially" impure, ugliness, the poor, the unhealthy, the terrible, imbecility, and the despicable. In Colombia the barbarian human type is the indigenous, the black and the zambo [Afro-American Indian mixtures]; the civilized type, "racially" more pure, is concentrated in the highlands of the interior, that is, in the regions of temperate and cool climate where the "white of Spanish origin" lives mainly and where the most refined populations produce literary works ...” (Gómez Muller 1997, p.15).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Luis López de Mesa (1884-1967), Colombian, psychiatrist and psychologist at Harvard University (1918), estimated that: “The mixture of the indigenous people of the Eastern Cordillera with that African element and even with the mulattos derived from it, it would be a fatal mistake for the spirit and wealth of the country: the vices and defects of the two races would be compounded, instead of eliminated, and we would have a cunning and indolent bastard, ambitious and sensual, hypocritical and vain at the same time, ignorant and sickly. This mixture of impoverished blood and lower cultures determines maladaptive, disturbed, nervous, mentally weak products, vitiated by madness, epilepsy, crime, that fill asylums and prisons when they get in touch with civilization ” (López de Mesa 1927, p. 12).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Also from the political and normative point of view, in the Constitution of 1886, which governed us until 1991, the conservative, centralist, catholic, patriarchal, white and exclusive position prevails. Article 40 says that “the exercise of all cults that are not contrary to Christian morals or laws is permitted” and article 41 states that “Public education will be organized and conducted in accordance with the Catholic religion,” making a clear allusion in both cases to the recognition of a single creed. Such a position changes only a century later with the Political Constitution of 1991, in which the recognition of a multi-ethnic and multicultural country becomes explicit, thus making a social assessment of the different social groups that make up the nation.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For five centuries, stories, narratives and images prevailed that legitimized the perspective of inferiority of the indigenous and Afro-descendant communities perceived devoid of culture, language, knowledge and religion that were necessary to assimilate into an idea of homogenizing nation-state. They are described as idolatrous peoples with dialects and characterized by having superstitions; that is, they are described as barbarians, as homogeneous societies, possessing time-frozen traditions and essentialized identities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, these cultural differences begin to acquire value, promoted both by the intellectual elites and by the 1991 Constitution, through which the country is explicitly recognized as "multi-ethnic and multicultural", which materializes in identity movements and of resistance as well as in cultural spaces such as museums that claim the “authentic” identity of the original peoples (Sarrazin 2009). Also the growing recognition of indigenous "spirituality", more linked to the New Age movement, constitutes another form of valorization of these indigenous cultural practices and the knowledge associated with them (Sarrazín 2008), which includes shamanic practices in cities such as Bogotá, responding to a growing demand of individuals in search of new paths linked to personal growth. In this sense, the idealization of diversity and otherness has come about (Sarrazín 2006).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">IV. Construction of the Amazon rainforest as a mythical space of reverie and terror.</section>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Amazonian indigenous communities have a close historical, aesthetic and symbolic relationship with the jungle, while the rest of society has approached it from the construction of imaginary that oscillate between seduction and terror.<br/><br/>The construction of the myth and the legend about the jungle starts from Gaspar de Carvajal, chronicler of the Indies, in the 16th century, who accompanies Francisco de Orellana in the search for gold and spices, particularly cinnamon, along the Amazon River. Carvajal describes the encounter with a tribe of women warriors as the encounter with the Amazons, thus embodying the Greek myth in this territory; from that moment the imaginary began to be forged on this territory and its inhabitants.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Herzog in the film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Aguirre, the Wrath of God</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, filmed in 1972, recreates, in part, the chronicles of Gaspar de Carvajal in a film that dramatically narrates the relationship of Europeans with this territory and with indigenous people, a relationship marked by the fear of the unknown, with a masterful staging of Klaus Kinski who embodies the brutality of Aguirre, his immersion in the jungle and his relationship with the natives, which is mediated by fear, and submission of such populations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Páramo in his book </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lope de Aguirre or the Maelstrom of the West: jungle, myth and rationality</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2009), quotes Miguel Ángel Perera (1994) who estimates that, </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Páramo estimates that Aguirre is, together with Arturo Coba, the protagonist of one of the most emblematic novels of the Colombian twentieth century, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Vorágine</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1924), the archetype of liminal beings: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Vorágine</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, José Eustasio Rivera, refers to the indigenous communities settled in the jungle, as “those rudimentary and nomadic tribes: they have no gods, no heroes, no homeland, no present, no future” (Páramo 2009, p. 19), configuring them as tribes far from the values of Western civilization, giving continuity to a thought that had been forged since the 16th century.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Other stories of the twentieth century, such as the novels </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lost in the Amazon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1978) by Germán Castro Caicedo; the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">River of desolation: a journey through the Amazon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2006) by Javier Rerverté, a historical novel, describes the Amazon rainforest as an inhospitable place, conducive to the development of illicit activities: in the first half of the twentieth century, the rubber exploitation; In the second half, animal skin trafficking and recently the production and marketing of cocaine took place. It has also been a refuge for groups outside the law and rebel groups.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">V. The indigenous communities of the Amazon and their approach to tourism</section>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The images of the Amazonian indigenous populations embodied in engravings, paintings and later in photographs accompany the stories and narratives of explorers and travelers (Paul Marcoy, Coudreau et Crevaux and the Italian Boggiani; the English captain Thomas Whiffen, and the German ethnologist Theodor Koch-Grünberg, among others), who advance scientific explorations particularly since the 19th century, and represent the indigenous as belonging to a “pure”, untouched society, with a pristine, rich and “authentic” culture, whose cultural practices accentuate the sense of the difference".</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These images are reproduced both in the written media and in social networks as a mechanism of seduction for travelers and tourists, who, fascinated by the search for exotic, pre-modern societies, are launched to meet the indigenous communities of the Amazon in the search for "Good savage", of his knowledge and "spirituality", which remains in the imaginary of travelers and tourists who visit the Amazon and in the images of promotion of the destination.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, the relationship of these communities with the foreigners was more intense with the arrival of the different bonanzas: the exploitation of rubber by the Casa Arana, a Peruvian company that implemented practices of extreme violence towards the natives, who sought the subjugation of these groups, through fear, murder, persecution, the disintegration of families and clans. Subsequently, other bonanzas were presented: the skins and the coca, with an important profit for the traffickers and only a small gain for the natives who exposed their physical integrity to risk in each endeavour.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In relation to tourism, considered by some authors as a new bonanza in the region, (Ochoa 2008) the situation has not been no more fortunate: the Yagua indigenous communities originally from Peru were used since the 60s of the twentieth century as “attractive tourist". In Peru, as described by Baca in 1981, quoted by Chaumeuil, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">in the last two decades, some native groups face a new form of penetration by the dominant groups: tourism, with the desire to seek new forms of enrichment and show off the exotic, tourism companies are responsible for moving to their shelters, native groups with the purpose of showing, or exhibiting their way of existence, deformed and accommodated to obtain greater clientele, resulting in the loss of identity and native self-esteem, which leads to an accelerated deculturation process</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> ”(Chaumeil, p.24); The author estimates that tourism among the Yagua has been imposed since the 1960s, due to the exoticism of their dresses in palm and their hunting practices with blowguns, curare and the ease of access to their communities (p.29 ). Given the abuses of tourism companies, the Yagua requested respect for their cultural practices, the dates of their festivals and rituals as well as autonomy for the formation of their own tourism companies, with benefits in economic, social and cultural (Chaumeil 1984, p.74). To Colombia they are transferred by Mike Salinsky (or Mike Tsalikis, according to some reviews) from their place of origin. He made tours so that tourists, mostly Americans like him, had the experience of observing supposed native dances with semi-naked natives. Such a tourism project, one of the first in the Colombian Amazon, brought about the displacement and deterritorialization of such groups as well as its accelerated acculturation by separating them from all their cultural, symbolic and cosmogonic references, generating deep social and cultural ruptures (Vélez 2017). At the moment, the tourist presentation of the indigenous communities, oscillates between the visit to the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">malocas</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> [traditional longhouses], with presentation of “traditional” dances, the visit to caciques who make a story about their conception of the world and the sale of handicrafts, adapted for tourists according to the demand.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">A. Referents of travelers on the Amazon territory and the indigenous communities settled there.</section>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the first survey on the preliminary knowledge of travelers to this territory and their indigenous inhabitants, the traces of stories, narratives and known images have been come, in some cases, from childhood, from the first years of education to the reference to novels, recent movies and documentaries.<br/><br/>The reference to </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Vorágine</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1924) is more or less recurring, a novel that is frequently read by college students, in which a crude description of the jungle is made out to be a “green hell,” a place that was the setting of the cruelty to which the natives were subjected during the time of rubber extraction. The novel has also been broadcast by appearances in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Arcadia</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> magazine and recently, a television series has been made, demonstrating the validity of the subject.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">There are also references by students to magazines such as </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">National Geographic</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the book </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tales of the Jungle</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> by Horacio Quiroga and the movie </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Book of the Jungle</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the documentary </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild Magic</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2015) and the movie </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Hug of the Snake</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, directed by the Colombian Ciro Guerra, where the encounter between Europeans and indigenous people is narrated. Other of the mentioned references make reference to other works of Colombian literature. William Ospina is referred to by his trilogy: </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Country of Cinnamon</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Serpent without Eyes</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ursúa</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, whose scenario is the jungle from the Spanish colonization and that creates an imaginary in travelers. It was also mentioned as a reference of the Amazon region to Kapax, somehow remembered as Amazonian superhero who crossed the Amazon River and several others, to make visible the regional and environmental problems of these regions forgotten by the State (Gallo 2016).<br/>We believe that each of the novels, films and characters mentioned have helped in the construction of the social imaginary of travelers on this territory, which also translates into the means used by tourists to recognize the destination and its residents.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">B. The Amazon from the guides and the tourist publicity among indigenous communities.</section>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Guide books are a fundamental tool for the traveler, they also contribute to the recreation of social and tourist imaginaries and serve as instruments of decision, so they fulfill a performative function, that is, they create realities for tourists, because they determine their itineraries traveling, the attractions to visit, the places to avoid and even the expected behaviors of each other, in addition to the spaces of fear and danger in addition to those that can be enjoyed peacefully. The guides seek to elucidate with whom, how and where to share, in short, they seek to convey the ABC of the trip.<br/><br/>With respect to Colombia, until recently the guides advised against their visit and put red or orange alerts as a dangerous place. At present, when Colombia becomes more visible to the world, due to the recent peace treaty, the tourist offer plays a fundamental role in the construction of the imaginary.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> it states that "Colombia reappeared in the tourism radars and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lonely Planet</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> should devote a guide to this unknown destination!” Later, it says: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">As for the Amazon, in this same guide, in 2016, the immensity of the forest and the diversity of its ecosystem are highlighted: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, the absence of reference to indigenous communities and restless settlers, elevates tourist visits solely to a jungle rich in flora and fauna, but devoid of human life. The description of the fauna, centered only on certain animals, seems to invite the tourist to know the native Amazonian species, such as piranhas, perhaps recognized for their ferocity.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The guide </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Petit Futé</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, invites you to discover "Locombia". </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the 2018-19 version of the guide, an element further qualifying the country has been added, talking about the country of El Dorado that offers unknown treasures to the traveler.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Some of its attractions are described: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Close the presentation with the slogan of a state campaign created by Procolombia, in 2007, to promote the country and which also refers to the risks that the traveler runs on his trip: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the description of the country, the guide compares it to its flag: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It is striking that a number of imaginaries are recreated here: El Dorado, as the place of enchantment and excess, the place of hidden treasures, risk and adventure, all of them in one place. The new allusion to the country of El Dorado, activates the memory the social imaginary built from the Chroniclers of the Indies, since the Spaniards searched for El Dorado, the magic of the encounter with a rich and mysterious country, with a past of exuberant beauty and enormous riches that made characters like Orellana and his men cross the jungle and its dangers, contacting "wild" and hostile peoples, because of the reward, the value of its treasures.<br/><br/>They recreate an imaginary about risk, which is worth running to discover a hidden place, full of treasures, but that will lead to an authentic experience.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The joy of the Latino, another of the social imaginary, is also mentioned, not counting the plight of the country, particularly the political situation, drug trafficking and violence, despite the recent signing of the peace agreement between the guerrilla forces Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia (FARC) and the Colombian State.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the other hand, the tourist offer on visits to the indigenous communities of the Colombian Amazon are announced by some non-indigenous operators as experiences that oscillate between marriage with rituals typical of the Tikuna communities, the “recreation” of a supposed ancient cannibalism, promoted by the agency Amazonas Colombia</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the intake of ritual plants such as yagé</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and the practice of facial painting between dances and local music.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourist publicity is accompanied by images that allude to the indigenous in “traditional”, “authentic” costume with a tiger’s teeth necklace (actually American jaguar) and with a crown of feathers. The dances are done by groups dressed in costumes made with Yanchama, a jungle bush traditionally utilized by the communities. However, the costumes in Yanchama are only part of a staging just like the crowns and necklaces that are actually used only by some dignitaries and in very particular rituals. Recreating rites of passage, such as a performance of indigenous marriage ceremonies as a social event for citizens eager for authenticity and exoticism, can become a double game of representation and power.<br/><br/>There operators, travel agencies, or promoters of the destination, require indigenous spaces, their </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">malocas</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and someone who knows some of the traditional knowledge or at least willing to simulate them, to stage the rite of passage or the evil cries and supposed cannibalism. Until a couple of years ago in a civil society reserve that promotes clean environmental practices, as part of the re-creation of the “culture” a pot with bones was displayed, alluding to that ritual, feeding the social imaginary of the savage Amazonian.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="53">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Other tourist offers between indigenous communities revolve around “traditional” dances mainly in a place very close to Leticia, called Macedonia, the sale of “handicrafts” at that same point and on the Island of Micos, and the visit to grandparents and grandmothers in their </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">malocas</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and the knowledge-elders who carry on conversations with groups of visitors. Also the opportunity of healing with Yagé, is done more carefully because of the consequences that this experience could have if it were not carried out in the right conditions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="54">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourist publicity renders invisible the contemporary dynamics of the indigenous communities facing an accelerated process of globalization, where they are incorporated in different ways, still leaving their places of origin and moving to the municipal capitals, to the capitals, integrating themselves in a market logic far from their own productive dynamics. Rather, this presentation seeks to nurture the social imaginary about indigenous communities as social groups arrested in time, with rituals and cultural practices that are exoticized, commercialized and put at the service of consumption.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="55">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, indigenous communities also incorporate in their routine the role of being “Indians” for tourists, in quite asymmetrical relationships, inserting themselves into a labor market in which the operators get all the benefits, recreating an image of themselves and of their culture according to the tourist demands: making representations of their “dances”, or healing rituals, selling their medicinal products to tourists who seek first of all to respond in the encounter with “authentic” communities underlain by a relationship of otherness marked by tensions and power.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusions</section>
        <paragraphe num="56">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The construction of social and tourist imaginaries about the indigenous communities of the Colombian Amazon is nourished by the chronicles of the Indies, stories of travelers and explorers, literature such as novels and finally by film and television. One of the most important milestones is </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">La Vorágine</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, a novel that recreates an imaginary that still survives today in the memory of Colombians of all ages, a book that is often consulted and read in school.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="57">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From the perspective of the stories associated with tourism, guide books build an imaginary that oscillates between the ignorance of the existence of Amazonian communities and the exoticization of them as societies where authentic experiences can be lived. But the social imaginary of the Amazonian indigenous communities is most definitively created and shown more forcefully is in the widespread tourist publicity, where some ancestral and other newly created or resignified cultural practices are recreated to nourish the tourist experience. The narratives and stories that accompany both the guide books and the tourist publicity create realities about the territories and the inhabitants of the tourist destinations, and determine tourists’ travel decisions except for those who go in search of their own experience even contravening the indications or warnings in the guide books.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="58">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">These tourist narratives are part of the images and historical stories about the native inhabitants of the Amazon, and recreate the relationships of otherness and its evolution over time, from the arrival of Orellana to the present day. Probably, these changes are not significant enough to transform the relations of society and its original communities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Aponte Motta, J. (2017), «Leticia para turistas: imaginarios, narrativas y representaciones de una ciudad amazónica », Cuadernos de Geografía, Revista Colombiana de Geografía,  nº26, 2, pp. 93-111, Bogotá, Universidad Nacional de Colombia. Doi 10.15446/rcdg.v26n2.59210.</reference>
        <reference>Argod, P. (2014), L´art du carnet de voyage, Paris, Gallimard Alternatives.</reference>
        <reference>Austin, J. (2008), Cómo hacer cosas con palabras. Palabras y acciones, Buenos Aires, Paidós.</reference>
        <reference>Castoriadis, C. (1983), La institución imaginaria de la sociedad, Barcelona, Tusquets Editores.</reference>
        <reference>Chaumeil, J.P. (1984), Entre el zoo y la esclavitud: los Yagua del oriente peruano en su situación actual, Documento IWGIA 3, Copenhagen. URL : https://www.iwgia.org/images/publications/0375_3_Zoo_Yagua.pdf</reference>
        <reference>Courant S. (2012), Approche anthropologique des écritures de voyage. Du carnet à la correspondance, petit inventaire des productions scripturales de la fin du XXe au début du XXIe siècle », Paris, L´Harmattan, Collections: Tourismes et Sociétés.</reference>
        <reference>Debarbieux, B. (2012), «Turismo, Imaginarios e Identidades: invertir el punto de vista », Via [On line], 1 | 2012, mis en ligne le 16 mars 2012, consulté le 15 avril 2018. URL : http://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1204 , DOI : 10.4000/viatourism.1204</reference>
        <reference>Debarbieux, B., Staszak, J.F.  and Tebbaa, O. (2012),  «Turismos y dinámicas identitarias », Via [On line], 2 | 2012, mis en ligne le 13 décembre 2012, consulté le 19 avril 2018. URL : http://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1061</reference>
        <reference>Ducrot, O. (1986),  El decir y lo dicho. Polifonía de la enunciación, Barcelona, Ediciones Paidós.</reference>
        <reference>Ducrot, O. (1988), Polifonía y argumentación, Conferencias del Seminario Teoría de la Argumentación y Análisis del Discurso, Cali, Valle, Universidad del Valle.</reference>
        <reference>Gallo, I. (2016), El ocaso de Kapax, el Tarzán colombiano, Las2Orillas [On line] URL: https://www.las2orillas.co/el-ocaso-de-kapax-el-tarzan-colombiano/</reference>
        <reference>Gomez-Muller, A. (1997), Alteridad y ética desde el descubrimiento de América, Madrid, Ediciones Akal.</reference>
        <reference>Gravari-Barbas, M., Graburn, N. (2012), « Imaginarios turísticos », Via [On line], 1 | 2012, mis en ligne le 16 mars 2012, consulté le 15 avril 2018. URL : http://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1185</reference>
        <reference>Hiernaux, D. (2002), «Turismo e Imaginarios», in Imaginarios Sociales y Turismo Sostenible, 7-36, Costa Rica, Facultad Latinoamericana de Ciencias Sociales FLACSO.</reference>
        <reference>Le Petit Futé (2016), Colombie, URL : https://www.petité.com/p162-colombie</reference>
        <reference>Lefébure, A., (2005), L´Amazonie disparue: Indiens et explorateurs.1825-1930, Paris, Éditions La Découverte.</reference>
        <reference>Lindón, A., Hiernaux, D. (2012), Geografías de lo imaginario, Barcelona, Anthropos.</reference>
        <reference>Lonely Planet, Colombia, 2018, URL https://www.lonelyplanet.fr/destinations/amerique/colombie</reference>
        <reference>Lonely Planet, s.f., Colombia, https://www.lonelyplanet.com/colombia/activities/medellin-private-pablo-escobar-tour-with-la-catedral-option/a/pa-act/v-29265P3/363305</reference>
        <reference>López de Mesa, L. (1927), El factor étnico, Bogotá, Imprenta Nacional. </reference>
        <reference>MacCannell, D. (2003), El turista. Una nueva teoría de la clase ociosa, Barcelona, Melusina.</reference>
        <reference>Naef, P. (2018), «Touring the ‘comuna’: memory and transformation in Medellin, Colombia», Journal of Tourism and Cultural Change, 16, 2, pp. 173-190, DOI: 10.1080/14766825.2016.1246555</reference>
        <reference>Ochoa,G. et al. (2008), Turismo en el Amazonas. Entre las alternativas convencionales y las alternativas ambientales amigables, Bogotá, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Sede Amazonía, Instituto Amazónico de Investigaciones, Imani.</reference>
        <reference>Páramo, C. (2009), Lope de Aguirre o la vorágine de Occidente. Selva, mito y racionalidad, Bogotá, Universidad Externado de Colombia.</reference>
        <reference>Pineda, R. (2005), «La historia, los antropólogos y la Amazonía», Antípoda, 1, pp. 121-135, Bogotá, Universidad de Los Andes. ISSN 1900-5407 </reference>
        <reference>Rivera, J. E. (2018), La Vorágine, Bogotá, Editorial Lo que leo. ISBN9789589002711.</reference>
        <reference>Salazar, N.B. (2006), «Antropología del turismo en países en desarrollo: análisis crítico de las culturas, poderes e identidades generados por el turismo», Tabula Rasa, 5, pp. 99-128, julio-diciembre, 2006, Bogotá, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, ISSN 1794-2489. Disponible en: http://revistatabularasa.org/numero-5/salazar.pdf, Consultado: 15 de abril de 2018.</reference>
        <reference>Sarrazín, J.P. (2006), Idées globalisées et constructions locales: L’image valorisée de l’indianité dans la Colombie contemporaine. Autrepart, 38(2), pp.155-172. doi:10.3917/autr.038.0155.</reference>
        <reference>Sarrazín, J.P. (2008), « La “espiritualización” de los discursos neoindigenistas en Colombia », Trace [On line], 54 | 2008, mis en ligne le 24 juillet 2009, consulté le 10 septembre 2019. URL : http://journals.openedition.org/trace/470</reference>
        <reference>Sarrazín, J.P. (2009), «Le rôle des élites intellectuelles dans le processus de visibilisation des indigènes en Colombie», E-Migrinter [On line], N° 4, 100-106. ISSN : 1961-9685. URL: https://www.academia.edu/775759/Le_rôle_des_élites_intellectuelles_dans_le_processus_de_visibilisation_des_indigènes_en_Colombie</reference>
        <reference>Silva, A. (2013), Imaginarios, el asombro social, Bogotá, Universidad Externado de Colombia.</reference>
        <reference>Urry, J. (2002), The tourist gaze, London, Sage Publications, 2nd. edition.</reference>
        <reference>Vélez, M. L. (2017), «Trapecio amazónico: turismo e imaginarios sociales sobre un territorio exotizado», Cuadernos de Geografía: Revista Colombiana de Geografía, [S.l.], v. 26, n. 2, 113-131, jul. 2017, Bogotá, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, ISSN 2256-5442, Disponible en: &lt;https://revistas.unal.edu.co/index.php/rcg/article/view/59229&gt;, https://doi.org/10.15446/rcdg.v26n2.59229. </reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">These latest expeditions narrated recently in the book L 'Amazonie disparue. Indiens et explorateurs 1825-1930 [The Lost Amazon: Indians and Explorers 1825-1930], which also describes the era of rubber exploitation, a tragedy for Amazonian indigenous communities.</note>
        <note id="2">URL: http://amazonascolombia.travel/canibales-amazonas/</note>
        <note id="3">Yagé: sacred plant of Amazonian indigenous communities that has medicinal effects on the physical body and the spirit, originally used in a strict ritual context, the taking of yagé has been gradually popularized and commercialized, as an activity associated with tourist visits in certain population centers and even in the cities, including Bogotá.</note>
    </notes>
</article>