<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_POAO_55-94_Tc_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/903" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.903</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>4-5</numero>
        <annee>2014</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="897">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            Difficultés d’une gestion touristique durable : Dzanga-Sangha en République Centrafricaine
        </original>
        <traduction lang="de" source="907">Managementprobleme eines nachhaltigen Tourismus: Dzanga-Sangha in der Zentralafrikanischen Republik</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Ouoko" prenom="Peggy" email="peggyouoko[at]yahoo.fr">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_POAO_56-90_De_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/897" lang="fr">Difficultés d’une gestion touristique durable : Dzanga-Sangha en République Centrafricaine</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Peggy Ouoko is a geographer. She studied at the University of Bangui and is currently a PhD student at the UMR CNRS Espaces et Sociétés of the University of Rennes 2. She is also a member of the Laceg laboratory of the University of Bangui. She worked in the Balé-Loko regions for UNESCO during the second year of her Master’s degree and is specializing in tourism and heritage for her dissertation on representations and rural communities of Bayanga and of Mbéko. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Ouallet" prenom="Anne" email="anne.ouallet[at]uhb.fr">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_POAO_56-90_De_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/897" lang="fr">Difficultés d’une gestion touristique durable : Dzanga-Sangha en République Centrafricaine</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Anne Ouallet is a university professor and researcher in Geography at the University of Rennes 2 and works with UMR ESO. Her approach is a social geographical one, sensitive to the actors and their socio-spatial productions. She is interested in heritage issues, namely through the selection, the development and the management of sites classified among the World Heritage of Humanity. Her analyses are based on fieldwork in Africa. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>The difficulties of sustainable tourist management: Dzanga-Sangha in Central African Republic </titre>
    <resume>
        The aim of this article is to reflect on the model of tourist-oriented world heritage in the context of sustainable development. The Central African project of Dzanga-Sangha in the South-West of the Central African Republic is the framework of this analysis. The development, through ecotourism, of spaces classified as World Heritage sites for the wealth of their biodiversity and the intangible culture of the Pygmies associated with the forest shows a certain number of limits, linked namely to the type of governance of this project. For the processes of development and of the management of the cultural and natural heritage to be sustainable, they should, for example, take care to better ensure the participation of local communities as a whole.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Today, sustainable development is an essential reference in environment- and heritage-related discourses and actions, as regards selection, protection, management and development. It is a polysemous concept, but when applied to World Heritage management it poses above all the question of how to conciliate the protection of this heritage, how to preserve the exceptional universal value it carries and how to ensure a harmonious development which can also benefit local populations. For several years, international institutions, non-governmental organizations and national policies have been active in the context of heritage preservation, by attempting to make the latter profitable for their residents as well. Sustainable development, through the preservation of a heritage of Humanity, may thus become an ideal model allowing for the transmission of elements of an exceptional value (both tangible and intangible), and thus of diversity and of memory, as well as for an access to well-being, but also for a fairer distribution of wealth. The principles of this acceptation are based on economic efficiency, social equity and the quality of the environment. In this context, tourism appears as one of the key sectors for promoting local development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Central African example of the site of Dzanga-Sangha, which appears on the World Heritage list, will allow us to see how this tourism can appear as a model of development for places identified as heritage sites and what the main stakes and risks associated with them are. This area is situated in the subprefecture of Bayanga (document 1), in the South-West of the country, in the zone of a great forest reserve belonging to the tri-national reserve of Central Africa : the National Park of Dzanga Ndoki in Central African Republic, to which Dzanga-Sangha belongs, the National Park of Nouabalé-Ndoki in the Republic of Congo and the National Park of Lobéké in Cameroon.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, there often seems to be a discrepancy between the goals set and the identified modes of operation. This discrepancy raises questions about the concrete practices of governance of the development programs and of the management plans, namely concerning the satisfaction of the fundamental needs and the essential aspirations of human beings. Criticisms can be made on the management undertaken, from which a certain number of frustrations may result.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the end, we will have to consider whether the tourist development of protected areas always really contributes to protecting the heritage, and according to what measures, what modes and within what limits it can benefit or not the social development of the rural population concerned. Does taking into account ecotourism as a process of development and of the sustainable protection of the cultural and natural heritage represent a viable alternative ?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The answers provided in this article come from a precise analysis of the local situation which was made possible thanks to fieldwork conducted in 2012 during two successive phases</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and which favoured an accelerated method of participative research (MARP). As such, this research required a good integration within the populations. It was based on observations and the collection of information from local communities via a focus group and limited discussion groups, with the advantage of being able to interview several people at the same time. For example, this method allowed to draw up, with the villagers, an historical profile and a map of the land, and to pinpoint the social incidences of the development program. Institutions and the representatives of the main actors who were locally involved were also interviewed.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Sustainable development and heritage recognition</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">From the Copenhagen summit</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1972, which brought together key leaders to combat global warming, to the first “Planet Earth” summit in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, then to the last “Rio + 20” summit held in 2012, the environmental question has evolved and is now part of the sustainable development framework. The latter issue is henceforth presented as an essential point of public policies, public-private partnerships, private companies and, in general, the commitments of the different programs of territorial development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Conciliating the preservation of the environment, economic activities and the well-being of populations is now put forward as a guideline for actions (Benhamou, 2010). The policies for enhancing the heritage and for developing tourism are at the heart of these concerns and actions (Cosaert, Bart, 2001).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Responding to challenges</section>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The stakes of sustainable development are to be linked to a certain number of challenges that encourage, for example, reappraising the role of public goods within the context of the vast movement of heritage recognition which concerns both natural and cultural heritage, adapting supply to demand, but also responding, with a certain detachment, to fads, to solicitations which are sometimes out of step with the local situations of outside actors and of tourists and to take into account the needs of local populations as a whole. One of the challenges is also to match the discourse on sustainable development with concrete situations as they are experienced by the populations in development programs.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The realities at the local level are subjected to the combined pressures of different actors from various scales (notably governments, but also international bodies and funding agencies) and undeniably lead to a major restructuring of the forms of public action. However, the new sharing of responsibilities is not necessarily the one stated in the principles of sustainable development. Territorial reorganization should be observed in light of these new principles of universalized management and of the conflicts which accompany them. New forms of action guide policies and practices. As suggested by J. Theys, “the final goal is no longer to simply introduce more stringency in administrative action (first concept), to find new modes of coordination (second concept), or to extend the criteria of rationality (third concept) ; but also to redistribute power on a very wide basis around new forms of solidarity – solidarity among neighbours, among regions…– which necessarily gives governance a political meaning” (Theys, 2002, p. 12).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Observation of the selection modes of heritage and then of the tourism development of the Bayanga area through the Dzanga-Sangha project, serves in this case as a test to analyse the degree to which these principles are respected. The type of governance which has been implemented in this forest zone of the Central African Republic which is richly endowed with heritage resources, provides information on the degrees of sustainability of tourism activities and heritage preservation. It should also be compared to the degree of efficiency of the apportionment of engendered benefits and thus of the “quality” of the governance.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">What heritage recognition ?</section>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Since heritage no longer only includes buildings, Africa has been better represented in international rankings. Indeed, heritage now also includes the natural environment, landscapes, know-how, and various elements of culture such as certain ceremonies (Ouallet, 2007). Classification criteria are now established both on the tangible register and on the intangible one, on what is natural and on what is cultural (Gravari-Barbas, Anguis Guichard, 2003).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Conjointly, heritage policies have also multiplied, from the international to the local scale. For example, at the beginning of the 1970s, the UNESCO Heritage Convention introduced the label of international heritage : a community-owned asset, an estate, wealth transmitted by ancestors can be classified as world heritage of Humanity (UNESCO, 1972) and thus be included on the list of world properties. The goods and charges contained in this newly designated heritage thus represent what is called a “universality of estate”. Heritage elements presented to UNESCO by the Central African government have been classified following this principle.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Governments themselves establish inventories and draw up proposals for heritage development in order to find funding. Following the work and the alarming assessment on the degradation of biodiversity conducted in 1988 by an American researcher, Richard Caroll, the Central African government, through the intermediary of its Ministry of Water, Forests, Hunting and Fishing, and its Ministry of Development, Culture, Crafts and Tourism, thus issued a proposal for managing the biodiversity of forest areas and requested that the Aka Pygmy culture be classified. This resulted in the signature of a partnership agreement between the Central African government and the W.W.F-U.S.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> which gave rise to the Dzanga-Sangha project on 29 December 1990. Popular tradition itself is often a source of know-how which allows for the preservation of heritage. Previously, then concurrently with institutional policies, the cultural practices of populations have also included, through traditions, possibilities for the protection of the environment (UNESCO, 1998 ; Cormier Salem et al., 2005) and references for the cohesion of societies (Ouallet, 2012).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This is done informally, but it corresponds totally to heritage conservation practices. Traditionally, populations often want to preserve resources that depend directly on the spaces they occupy, on their exploitation and on their management (Mainet, 2004). These traditional management methods are developed in the name of tradition. Thus, for Aka Pygmies, a number of practices, used in an ancestral fashion, traditionally lead to the recognition of nature as a heritage. This traditional know-how is reconfigured depending on different evolutions. These are instances of living heritage which correspond to popular forms of heritage. This cultural heritage, which is often intangible, is transmitted from generation to generation. It is “permanently recreated by communities and groups depending on their background, on their interaction with nature and on their history” (Grenet, 2006, p. 1). These practices associated with a protection are often identified as belonging to the common basis of societies and as requiring transmission to the following generations. They were of interest to researchers and development practitioners even before they became an object of institutional referencing by UNESCO through the establishment of a category of intangible cultural heritage in 1993.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Institutional labelling allows one to consider heritage as a new territorial resource through tourist development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Tourism as a means of exploiting an endangered heritage</section>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The heritage potential of the Dzanga-Sangha forest reserve, which is situated in the Bayanga subprefecture, is based on the association between a remarkable biodiversity and an exceptional cultural wealth. These two elements which led to its classification on the World Heritage of Humanity list in 2008 make the region of Bayanga one of the major potential zones of tourist development in the Central African Republic. However, past and present types of exploitation of space turned out to be and still represent a serious threat for this heritage identified as a new local resource. The culture of the Aka Pygmies and their natural environment have already suffered from numerous attacks historically and continue to be greatly threatened by the devastating effect of present economic activities. The current project relies on tourism to boost local development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Wealth of the selected heritage</section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The classification as World Heritage retained the dual criteria of natural heritage around the biodiversity of Bayanga forest, and cultural heritage with the designation of the intangible culture of the Aka Pygmies. The oral tradition of the Aka Pygmies of the Bayanga region was declared an oral World Heritage of Humanity by UNESCO in 2008 following the proposal of the Central African government</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The dimension of an intangible heritage is thus an important element of a classification which recognizes the forest of Bayanga as an ecosystem of biodiversity totally linked to an environment of exceptional value : that of the Pygmies, a population which draws its essence and its raison d’être from the natural elements provided in this forest. The Pygmies of this region call themselves the Ba Aka, the Aka “friends”.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It was first the housing and the camps of the Aka Pygmies of Lobaye (a subprefecture located south of Bangui) which had been classified as heritage as early as 1980, already further to the proposal of the Central African government. Indeed, the techniques, symbolism and aesthetics associated with these constructions were noted as possessing an exceptional value due as much to the respect for the environment shown by these constructions as to the cultural and social representations they convey. Pygmy houses, which are entirely constructed from natural materials supplied by a reasoned selection of forest elements, are, for experts, both a mark of authenticity and a guarantee of environmental sustainability. The Aka are the only ones who construct this type of hut, who possess its construction techniques and know the associated ritual codes. The habitat represents the basis, the very foundation itself of the Aka culture. To construct, one first needs to demarcate the location and the layout of the land, and then invoke the spirits of the gods in order to protect the community from any misfortune. The construction of the hut is carried out by women, since the latter represent procreation and fertility, thus symbolizing the perpetuation of the transmission of social values through the act of building. The architecture and the materials used are taken from nature in a sustainable way.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The links that the Aka community have developed with its environment thus correspond in quite an exemplary fashion to the notion of sustainability as advocated at the Rio summit for sustainable development in 1992 : an economic link binding the population to the natural or cultural exploitation of a heritage, the quality of the social links, the transmissibility of nature and culture to future generations and the environmental link created by the population to preserve its natural and cultural resources. This symbiosis between the social and natural environment of the Pygmy culture is exemplary of a measured management of a forest area, but it has also been undermined for more than a century by other activities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Pressures on biodiversity and an endangered cultural heritage</section>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The territory of Bayanga possesses an important natural resource that is rich in fauna and flora. However, the historic use of this territory has already seriously affected what is currently designated as heritage capital. The successive development schemes by the Germans and French since colonial times to begin with, followed by the pursuit of a predatory exploitation of wealth following independence, have damaged the forest, its resources and the functioning of the ecosystem. The different concession companies and the timber, agricultural, forest and mining companies have introduced methods of exploitation which have disturbed balances in local nature and culture.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ivory exploitation companies had a negative impact on the elephant population as early as the beginning of the 20th century (1900-1909) and the exploitation of animal skins, namely antelope hides, have put unprecedented pressure on the wildlife.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Forest companies have conducted deforestation without undertaking any reforestation. Logging companies have remained very active up until very recently with an anarchic mode of exploiting the flora. As early as 1945, the proliferation of private estates for the exploitation of rubber and coffee destabilized the environment through an excess of agricultural production. The coffee exploitation company (1950-1959) and the cocoa exploitation company considerably enlarged the areas meant for plantations while destroying the primary forest. The exploitation of mining resources, notably diamonds, was carried out concurrently in an uncontrolled manner.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The upheavals introduced have also led local populations to adopt management methods which are poorly adapted to the preservation of the original biodiversity, by the increase of itinerant slash and burn agriculture, for example. This type of agriculture that relies on fallow land, leads first to deforestation then to the constitution of other plant forms. The first consequence of this is the decrease in the density of the forest, and in the long term, soil and possible climate modifications. Following these anthropogenic pressures, the primary forest has thus deteriorated. It is progressively becoming a secondary forest that may later result in the region becoming savannah.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Concurrently, the fauna has been damaged by the development of such activities. Non-selective hunting of great mammals such as the elephant, the bongo or the gorilla has aggravated the situation. Orders from the numerous traffickers who operate in the zone have increased illegal kills.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The alarming assessment made in 1988 by the American researcher Richard Caroll insists on this excessive pressure of anthropogenic activities which are badly controlled to the detriment of natural diversity. The outrageous appropriation of space has introduced important imbalances which threaten both biodiversity and the Aka culture. In this hazardous zone of upheavals, serious ecological degradation and endangered cultural heritage, heritage preservation inevitably entails a more reasonable management of local resources.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Management proposals</section>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Faced with the concern about the disappearance of these natural and cultural resources, international organisations, in agreement with the government, have initiated a procedure for the protection of the environment. In 1990, the management proposals resulted in the signature of a partnership agreement between the Central African government and the W.W.F-U.S. and in the concrete implementation of the Dzanga-Sangha project at the end of December 1992. The initial idea was to protect the forest of Bayanga through an integral management of the biodiversity, one in which human activities were forbidden. It was then thought preferable to integrate the populations while insisting on a management through the conservation of natural resources. The stated objectives are to reinforce efforts for safeguarding biodiversity through the creation and development of a multipurpose conservation zone (a special reserve) in the heart of the Dzanga-Sangha forest with the national park of Dzanga-Sangha in its centre. However, preserving the ecosystem must be done by reducing as much as possible human impact on the region. The usefulness of designing and implementing a participative program for rural development as well as strengthening local institutional capacities is established.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Finally, the project relies on a development and management plan for natural resources which includes different zones of restrictive activities (document 2). The community development zone and the village’s hunting zone are the spaces where populations from the entire reserve can conduct their agricultural and hunting activities in order to guarantee a food base for the local communities. The local populations’ levying activities on the forest ecosystem (cynegetic, harvesting and agricultural activities) are, however, forbidden in the safari</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> hunting zone which is exclusively reserved for tourists’ safari activities. It is the same for the parks in the Dzanga and Ndoki sectors which are reserved for tourist activities, notably the viewing of wild animals. The populations’ traditional activities must thus be restricted to a limited portion of space around Bayanga. Many villagers complain of such sectorization which prevents them from accessing the resources of the forest next to their home, and despite the bans and the controls, there is much trafficking throughout the area.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The discourse on an integrated development in which local communities would have their place has, in fact, given way to a vision dominated by the idea of consuming biodiversity and local culture through the implementation of a tourism project which is very restrictive for the local populations.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Tourist resources for sustainable development ?</section>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">If, in the countries of the South, tourism appears more and more as one of the levers for managing World Heritage sites, in practice, the relations between heritage preservation and local development remain complex. The combined pressure of international organisations, governments and local authorities comes up against realities on the ground where pressure linked to local priorities, to problems of endemic poverty and to particular cyclical events often make actions complicated.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The implementation of the Dzanga-Sangha project is set out within the context of sustainable development. It places tourism development at the heart of the program.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The tourist option retained is thus one of green tourism that is presented as the main guideline for economic development. Its promotion should make it possible to raise funds to enable both the financing of the national park and community development. The term used is also that of ecotourism. Here it is an ecotourism based on nature, and, in this regard, the main motivations of tourists are to observe and appreciate the variety of natural wealth as well as the traditional cultures which exist in this zone, more specifically the Pygmy culture in this case.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The wealth of fauna in Dzanga-Sangha is extolled : there are a great number of elephants, gorillas, buffaloes, sitatungas, and bongos. The integration of the Pygmies in the development process of the zone is also part of the development program of this ecotourism and it appears to be one of its main attractive elements, albeit presented as an intangible cultural heritage.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, the forest and the Ba Aka culture are understood to be further possible sources of income via the tourist boom, and the tourist project is supposed to guarantee a better living environment for local communities. In this space where heritage resources have been clearly identified through the biodiversity and the cultural wealth of the Pygmies, tourism is thus clearly seen as being one of the possible levers for sustainable development in the region. However, the relationship between heritage preservation, tourist development and the improvement of living conditions for the populations remains a sensitive subject, since the forms taken by tourist management present a discrepancy with the realities of local modes of operation.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Governance issues concerning the Dzanga-Sangha project</section>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Conditions for sustainable development depend as much on the quality of the economic ties which link the population to the natural and cultural exploitation of their heritage as on the environmental and social links maintained by the population in the context of the protection of natural and cultural resources. The transmissibility of the natural diversity and cultural wealth to future generations, the preservation of social links and the sharing of responsibilities among the populations are vital to maintain a balance. The analysis of the modes of governance applied to the Dzanga-Sangha project, notably through the development and the management of tourist resources, provides information on the sustainability of such an undertaking. Beyond the links that the populations maintain with their heritage and the relations which link them to tourist activities, it is by questioning the limits of acceptable changes that the sustainability of such a project can be assessed. How benefits from tourism activities are shared plays a significant part in the margin of acceptability.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Tourism management</section>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The development program of tourism activities within the project is led by a Ministry of Water and Forests technician who is responsible for the promotion of ecotourism, the training of guides and trails and campsite maintenance. For the conservation aspect, a surveillance system has been implemented in order to reduce poaching. Controls are difficult and seizures vary from year to year. Information campaigns are run concurrently in order to limit damages to the biodiversity and to try to maintain this exceptional ecosystem whose wealth attracts tourists.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ecotourism activities consist in tourists participating in excursions and in the observation of the traditional activities of the Pygmies. In small groups and accompanied by guides and other necessary escorts, tourists visit the ecomuseum, go to the Dzanga-Sangha</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> salt flat to see the large mammals and view the gorillas and other primates. Two gorillas have been especially habituated to ecotourism through an adapted program for accustoming gorillas. Visitors can also enjoy recreational activities during which they discover hunting and fishing with the Pygmies and they can attend the harvesting of raphia wine. The demonstration of songs and dances is held at the Doli-Lodge : the Ba Aka are dressed in their traditional clothing of animal skins and bark wrapped around their waists to perpetuate in front of tourists the local Pygmy culture which has been identified as an exceptional heritage.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The accommodation and catering infrastructures comprise a Visitor Centre, the Doli-Lodge hotel complex with 28 beds, a restaurant privately managed by the owner of a travel agency, Bushtracks, whose headquarters are located in the United States, and other less costly lodges. There are also three campsites on the main attraction sites of Dzanga (the salt flat), Mongambé and Baï-Houkou.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The aim of the Visitor Centre is to organize tourist visits inside the protected zones, namely by facilitating their transportation, the formalities, and their stay in general, and to inform them of the fees.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourists come from all over the world : the majority are from Europe (44 % of all tourist visits in 2004), then from America and Asia (26 %). As for African tourists, they represented less than 10 % of total visitor numbers in 2004. The high season for tourism is the dry season which runs from November to February. There are very few tourists for the rest of the year. Tourist income thus varies a lot depending on the season. This appears to be one of the factors limiting local tourism-based development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Economic benefits of the Dzanga-Sangha project and distribution of the tourist income</section>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The economic input from tourism is thus limited to four months. This is the first weakness in the longevity of a development mainly focused on tourism and which minimises, in any case in the project, the other activities. The other obvious pitfall is that the distribution of income from the project far from benefits all of the actors involved, despite the installation of some community facilities. A number of frustrations have been expressed on this subject.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, ecotourism represents a source of substantial income for the Dzanga-Sangha project. In 1998, the fees paid by tourists covered the running costs of the tourist services (Wilkie et al., 1998). Tourist revenue originates mainly from the park entrance fees, rental of equipment and tourist services, and the royalties (percentages on the prices the tourists are charged) paid by the Doli-Lodge hotel complex. Added to that is the financing from the funding agencies, which mainly include American (USAID</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">), and German (GTZ</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) organizations, NGOs (WWF-US, CARPE, SRAFM, CIFOR …) and foundations (Fayadol</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Sacharuna</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the administrative level, tourism revenues represent a substantial income. Fifty per cent of the revenues are allocated to the project itself and mainly go towards the management of the park : development of trails and pathways, maintenance of tourism infrastructures (Doli-Lodge, Visitor Centre, watchtowers), local supplies, guides’ salaries, and payment for officials’ allowances and recurrent expenses. Ten per cent goes towards the forest and tourism fund for the development of other parks and 40 % is reserved for the accounts of local NGOs and should thus directly benefit the population. A Bayanga development committee was created for this purpose. It was then dissolved, which the villagers complained about. Indeed, the park’s internal regulations provide that 40 % of the revenues generated by tourism be allocated to this development committee for the implementation of micro-projects. A number of projects were carried out in certain communities : the construction of four wells for drinking water, a mother and infant health program, vaccination campaigns, the establishment of health centres and a primary school, the organization of village activities, and a sewing workshop for women. However, since the dissolution of the development committee, some neighbourhood leaders have complained that they are unaware of how the usually allocated 40 % of tourist income is used. The commission now only works with the administrators (the mayor and several project staff). They have thus denounced a confiscation of the benefits of the project.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The origin of the revenues is equally enlightening. The greatest revenues are from the Doli-Lodge hotel complex, exceeding those of gorilla viewing which themselves are more substantial than revenues originating from the entrance fees for the protected areas. One of the lessons of this situation is that a majority of the revenues potentially leaves the region since the Doli-Lodge hotel complex is managed by the owner of a Cameroonian tourist agency. On the other hand, the tour operators who take the tourists to Bayanga are also from outside the area. The Doli-Lodge is able to organize tourist trips from Yaoundé or Douala and to conduct its own negotiations with other tour operators.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Furthermore, an important part of tourists’ consumption involves non-local products since, for example, the Doli-Lodge hotel structure imports its fresh produce (fish, meat, sausages, hams, fruit juices) either from Limbongo, or from Douala, and thus from Cameroon. As for tinned food, this is purchased from the town of Bayanga, but is sold by Mauritanian sellers who obtain their supplies from outside. The local fish farmers in particular regret that the Doli-Lodge does not buy their products directly, since they could supply the restaurant with fresh fish. This represents a real loss for them, as it does for a number of other local producers. In general, many traders also say they do not perceive the benefits from tourism because the project staff get their supplies either from Bangui, or from Limbongo in Cameroon. Outsourcing all of these activities reduces the interest of the project for the local populations who, moreover, now feel excluded. In addition to increasing the use of local products for tourists’ consumption, local populations insist on the necessary opening up of the region through the purchase of vehicles which would allow them to transport their products outside the region as well.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It would be advisable to create a local agency to reflect on the best ways to integrate the project locally, to coordinate the partnerships among the different stakeholders and funding agencies, and to implement better tourist strategies in order to develop the site.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Involvement required of all the local populations</section>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The argument of sustainable development used to support the stated directions can only be conceived by developing ongoing activities lasting all year round, with local results perceptible to the populations. Sustainability thus entails a model that proposes mechanisms for coping and adjusting to emerging imbalances. It refers to a reality in which the actors involved in implementing the development project must share responsibility and involvement. The question of participation appears to be a central issue in this context. It is, in fact, this participation which is requested by the populations. Furthermore, the mere designation of the Pygmy culture as an element of intangible World Heritage has introduced an actual competition between communities whereas it is the village community as a whole that certainly deserves to be taken into account. These two points have turned out to be important sources of tension within the Dzanga-Sangha project.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Bayanga development committee that is defined as a local representative institution, does not, for example, fulfil its role. Yet, this committee was supposed to serve for the conduct and the taking of decisions concerning the allocation of the income generated from tourism activities. Thus, the decision to finance public utility works was supposed to be made collectively through this representation of the community. Following the ensuing dissolution, representatives of the populations are now asking to participate once more in managing the 40 % of revenues allocated to Bayanga community.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Likewise, the village action plan, which had in fact been announced and which is supposed to enable these villagers to contribute to the sustainable management of the forest resources, does not really seem to work. The traditional socio-economic activities practiced by local populations and which are vital alternatives to tourism, receive very little support. These activities also contribute to sustainable development, yet they are relegated to very limited and badly protected territories. Slash and burn agriculture is practiced on a very small cultivated surface, on a 300 to 500 metre-long band along the roadside. The dominant cultures of plantains, manioc and coffee are regularly trampled by the elephants. Yet, agriculture is the main activity of the entire population. Gathering (of tubers, leaves and fruit) and harvesting (of insects, caterpillars, snails, termites, mushrooms, honey, raphia wine, stripped bark…) which are essentially carried out by the Ba Aka population are highly regulated. Hunting and crafts activities are undertaken by the different communities present within the population : Ba Aka and the Bilo (local non-Pygmy populations).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The presence of tourists offers new possibilities to develop a number of activities, particularly in the crafts sector. The fact that only the Pygmy culture was distinguished by UNESCO as an intangible heritage creates an inequality that is felt by the different populations. Indeed, beyond the conservation, preservation and development aspects, the heritage also carries values and legitimacy for those it targets or those who know how to profit from the label and the benefits arising from it. If the heritage is an instrument of preservation, it is concurrently an instrument for controlling societies and delineating territories, since the materialization of the territory through the process of territorialisation is one of the ways of constructing the identity of a society or a group (Di Méo, 1998 ; Bosredon, 2005). The Dzanga-Sangha project represents, for the Central African government, a form of integration strategy of the Aka minority within the rural community of Bayanga in particular and within Central African society in general. However, concretely, two types of frustration are apparent.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the one hand, Ba Aka, who are the identified population, do not have the capacity to really capitalize on the benefits of the label they enjoy, even if the project considers that their living standard is a little higher than in the past. In the Visitor Centre, out of eight specialized guides, only two are Ba Aka. Likewise, the Ba Aka do not really benefit from the income directly or indirectly linked to the dance and song performances which they give at the Doli-Lodge.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the other hand, a number of Bilo do not understand the lack of interest in their culture. Many of them are also able to produce beautiful local crafts and wish to promote their know-how, as well as their art and cultural objects. They say that the tourists are not interested in them, but are only interested in the Ba Aka. In general, the funding agencies tend to target the Ba Aka in their projects. Thus, the European Union and the WWF released a school financing fund which allowed for the project to give monthly support to teachers (15 000 F CFA</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> a month in 2010-2011) and to contribute to the school fees of the Ba Aka children. Support for an artist community was also supplied by the European Union for the sum of 1 500 000 F CFA, which enabled them to build a crafts centre. The Bilo feel neglected and have become aware of the importance for them to integrate their culture into the local tourist activities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="52">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Numerous needs remain on the local level for all. The populations point out, for example, in terms of health, the need for a doctor, the usefulness of developing a health structure and the necessity of having an ambulance to transport serious cases to the major urban centres. The issue of the lack of jobs also appears to be one of the main obstacles since the Wood Exploitation company stopped its activities. Developmental observers note that the population expects everything from the Dzanga-Sangha project, whereas it should organize itself as an NGO or in small associations to initiate micro-projects itself. Thus it can be said that on a more general level, the populations’ expectations also concern training programs which would allow them to participate more in local life and be able to integrate the development structures. The populations clearly express their need for training through support in order to know how to undertake official administrative procedures in implementing NGOs and associations, and in terms of professional training and the management of income and its reuse. They also express the wish to be able to engage negotiations with new tour operators in order to better control the development network through tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="53">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The state of degradation of the forest’s biodiversity and the deterioration of the heritage of the Ba Aka Pygmies of the Bayanga region has encouraged the implementation of an ambitious development program announced within the framework of the Agenda 21 project. This policy, which fits into the international discourse on sustainable development, relies on the preservation of natural and cultural resources.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="54">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Development through ecotourism has appeared to be a palliative solution to local development problems, but it is carried out in a very delicate context which makes its success rather uncertain, requires true cooperation between Northern and Southern countries and implies taking into account national and local characteristics. The national uncertainties are those linked to the advent of political pluralism and to the economic readjustments realized in a troubled situation in which great financial difficulties are corrupting the Central African Republic economy. At the local level, the biodiversity of the forest associated with the cultural wealth of the Ba Aka Pygmy community has attracted the attention of potential international stakeholders and of foreign funding agencies, but for the moment, tourist development is facing a certain number of difficulties. At the environmental level, the protective measures are largely effective, but trafficking and poaching continue to exist. At the economic level, tourism is undeniably a source of income, but the latter is unequally distributed. The employment rate for residents and the use of local products remain too low to trigger any real local development. Tensions linked to the different exploitations of the site and to the diverging interests of the different actors render local development on the sole basis of this ecotourism very uncertain. The mode of acquisition of environmental resources in the domestic economy of the Aka community constitutes a true wealth, but it is also falls within the more global mode of operation which integrates other populations beside the Pygmies. These populations, however, receive little consideration. Yet the links and the relationships upheld by the rural community as a whole with the natural and cultural heritage and with the tourist activities are one of the essential elements to be taken into account to meet the challenge of such a development. Insufficient social consensus, the lack of transparency and information provoke criticisms on the governance of the project. A broader governance including real participation would certainly contribute to better social cohesion.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="55">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Despite the building of certain facilities to enable tourism to effectively become a model of sustainable development, certain conditions are required : better relationships between local actors, collective experimentation, an adapted political intervention and the participation of the entire rural community in this development project.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Amadou B., 2004, “Aire protégée et construction de territoire en patrimoine : l’exemple de l’île de Karey Kopto (Niger)”, Les cahiers d’Outre-Mer : revue de géographie de Bordeaux et de l’Atlantique, vol. 57, pp. 155-174. </reference>
        <reference>Benhamou F., 2010, “L inscription au patrimoine mondial de l’humanité, La force d’un langage à l’appui d’une promesse de développement”, Revue Tiers Monde, n° 202, avril-juin.</reference>
        <reference>Bosredon P., 2005, Alep, Harar, Zanzibar : une étude comparative des processus de construction patrimoniale et de classement au patrimoine Mondial des centres historiques de trois villes du sud, Mémoire de master 2 sous la direction d’Anne Ouallet, Rennes, Université Rennes II.</reference>
        <reference>Cormier Salem M., Boutrais J. &amp; al., 2005, Patrimoines naturels au Sud, Territoires, identités et stratégies locales, Paris, IRD éd.</reference>
        <reference>Cosaert P., Bart F. (dir.), 2001, “Patrimoines et développement dans les pays tropicaux”, Espaces tropicaux, n° 18, Dymset, Pessac, Actes des 9èmes journées de géographie tropicale, La Rochelle.</reference>
        <reference>Di Méo G., 1998, Géographie sociale et territoires, Paris, Nathan.</reference>
        <reference>Gravari-Barbas M. &amp; Guichard-Anguis S. (dir.), 2003, Regards croisés sur le patrimoine à l’aube du 21ème siècle, Paris, Presses Universitaires.</reference>
        <reference>Grenet S., 2006, “La polyphonie corse traditionnelle peut-elle disparaître ?”, in Patrimoine culturel immatériel et transmission, pp. 1-7.</reference>
        <reference>Mainet G., 2004, “Patrimoines et développement dans les pays tropicaux”, Les cahiers d’Outre-Mer, n° 18, pp. 339-340.</reference>
        <reference>Mounkaila H., 2010, “Espace frontalier et appropriations territoriales : jeux et enjeux autour de l’île de Lété (Niger)”, Les cahiers d’Outre-Mer : revue de géographie de Bordeaux et de l’Atlantique, vol. 63, pp. 121-140.</reference>
        <reference>Ouallet A., 2013, “Les patrimoines : entre pluralité, ressource et lien social, exemples maliens”, in Khaznadar Ch. (dir.), Le patrimoine, oui, mais quel patrimoine ?, Arles, Babel/Actes-Sud, pp. 441-459.</reference>
        <reference>Ouallet A., 2007, “Patrimoine et temporalités dans les villes africaines du patrimoine mondial : exemples maliens et éthiopiens”, Espaces Populations et Sociétés, n° 2/3, pp. 317-331.</reference>
        <reference>UNESCO, 1998, Sites sacrés naturels : diversité culturelle, diversité biologique, Symposium international, Paris UNESCO/CNRS/MNHN.</reference>
        <reference>UNESCO, 1972, Convention Concerning the Protection of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage.</reference>
        <reference>Wilkie D. S. &amp; Carpenter J. F., 1998, Le tourisme peut-il aider à financer les aires protégées dans le bassin du Congo ?, Document de travail soumis à Oryx.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">All the fieldwork was carried out by Peggy Ouoko from 15 February 2012 to 25 February 2012 and from 15 June 2012 to 30 August 2012.</note>
        <note id="2">The Copenhagen Summit was preceded by the United Nations Conference on the Environment held in Stockholm in the same year, 1972.</note>
        <note id="3">This NGO for nature conservancy was founded in 1961 in the United States by a big private international organization including 28 affiliated or associated national organizations around the world. It is regularly supported by more than four million donors. Its international headquarters are located in Geneva and the regional headquarters of Central Africa is in Yaounde. The national headquarters for the Central African Republic are established in Bangui.</note>
        <note id="4">Submitted by the Central African Republic on 11 April 2006 and approved by UNESCO in 2008.</note>
        <note id="5">The term safari comes from the Swahili language and means “journey”.</note>
        <note id="6">The term Dzanga is an expression from the lindjiali language which means “sacred place”.</note>
        <note id="7">USAID : United States Agency International Development.</note>
        <note id="8">GTZ : Deutsche Gesellschaft für Technische Zusammenarbeit.</note>
        <note id="9">Fayadol finances ecotourism.</note>
        <note id="10">Sacharuna is an American foundation which finances the health activities of Ba Aka, ecotourism, the supervision and control of poaching, environmental monitoring and the follow-up of relationships with the different partners (forest companies, hunting safaris…).</note>
        <note id="11">This represents around 23 euros.</note>
    </notes>
</article>