<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_PA_20-114_Fr_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3207" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.3207</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>14</numero>
        <annee>2018</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="3177">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            Du road movie au « voyage sauvage » : la quête d’aventure sur la route et le mythe du voyageur héroïque
        </original>
        <traduction lang="pt" source="3251">Do road movie a "viagem selvagem": a busca de aventura na estrada e o mito do viajante heróico</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Argod" prenom="Pascale">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PA_19-97_Le_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/516" lang="fr">La médiatisation d'un tourisme « hors des sentiers battus » dans une édition touristique créative</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PA_22-103_De_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3177" lang="fr">Du road movie au « voyage sauvage » : la quête d’aventure sur la route et le mythe du voyageur héroïque</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Docteure en sciences de l’information - communication, enseignante-chercheuse au MICA de l’université Bordeaux - Montaigne (https://mica.u-bordeaux-montaigne.fr/argod-pascale/) 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>From the Road Movie to Wilderness Travel: The Quest for Adventure on the Road and the Myth of the Heroic Traveller</titre>
    <resume>
        The conceptions of ‘wild’, as addressed in fictional travel diary films, question our relationship with space and the form of travel that gives rise to self-transcendence through a confrontation with the environment. The lived experience of the journey of discovery (adventure, exploration, expedition) defines the travel diary genre, which has become an off-the-beaten-track tourism medium. The reference points for two American travel diary films Into the Wild (2007), written and directed by Sean Penn, and Wild (2014, directed by Jean-Marc Vallée, are Jack Kerouac’s On the Road and the American pioneer front. These films mark a generation of travel diarists in search of the dream and anti-travel. The return to the wild, as a cultural confrontation, formative journey and self-transcendence, is said to shape the travel diary genre, which takes the form of either a piece of self writing or an autobiographical film (sometimes called a biopic) on the experience of travelling. We thus extend the road movie genre to robinsonades and films on the experience of a natural environment. The aesthetics of the image, panoramic landscape and grandeur of nature are thought to be a legacy of the notions of ‘picturesqueness’ and the ‘pioneer front’, while the renewed myths of both the wandering hero (Benoliel, 2011) and the quest for a new world seem to have developed from the literary references of On the Road and the Beat Generation’s ‘Beat ethos’.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The dream of being a traveller rather than a tourist (Urbain, 1991) is nurtured by the myth of travelling to </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">‘terrae incognitae’</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. This is a paradoxical dream, however, in this age of satellite and digital technology and mass tourism. The film viewer’s tourist trips contrast with the filmmaker diarist’s out-of-the-ordinary or extreme travels. The voyage of discovery myth and the attraction of adventure and travel stories explain the popularity of the audiovisual travel diary genre. Defining this new genre (Argod, 2011) means adopting a new point of view with regard to the increase in audiovisual production since 2012, which seems to have gone beyond a quest for authenticity to mediatise extreme travel. In France, the myth of the contemporary hero and this taste for exceptional travel are in line with the French geographical tradition that emerged with the creation of the Société de Géographie</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">in 1821. This tradition has been revived with the popularity of self-transcendence and out-of-the-ordinary travel adventures, whether on foot, bicycle or snow sleigh. The </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Rendez-vous du carnet de voyage de Clermont-Ferrand</span></em><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">offers some good examples of this. However, what does the way in which it is presented in the cinema teach us about tourism and the traveller figure? How does cinema influence off-the-beaten-track tourism (Argod, 2016)? How do filmmaker diarists mediatise out-of-the-ordinary and extreme travel? The reference points for the two American travel diary films </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2007)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, written and directed by Sean Penn, and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2015), directed by Jean-Marc Vallée, are Jack Kerouac’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and the American pioneer front. These two films have proved very popular with the younger generation, who are open to mobility, film tourism (Tzanelli, 2007) and new tourism territories (Delaplace and Gravari-Barbas, 2017), such as Alaska. The success in America of Jon Krakauer’s book </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which was on the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">New York Times</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> bestseller list for two years, corroborated the two awards received by the film in 2008 (the Golden Globe Award and the Lumières Award) as well as the box office ticket sales in France of 1,245,920 and the US box office receipts of 56.82 million US dollars (slightly higher than the 52.5 million US dollars for the film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Art of Sketching: 400 Years of Travel Diaries</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Argod, 2014), we see how each diarist contributes to developing the genre, which varies according to their appropriation of reality, their experience of travel, their personal experience, their relationship to others and to the environment, their experience of the camera, their practice regarding reporting in images and their creativity in contact with the environment. In short, their vision of the world. In 2011, we envisaged six versions of the film genre</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            The mythical route to India: birth of the travel diary (Roberto Rossellini, Louis Malle, Pierre Brouwers)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            The trial (Robert Kramer, Bernard Henri Lévy, Michko Netchak, etc.)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            Inspirational film sketches (Pier Paolo Passolini, Wim Wenders, etc.)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            The literary form (Chris Marker, Frédéric Mitterrand, Bernard Giraudeau, Patrice Leconte, Frédéric Leclerc with Jean d’Ormesson, etc.)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            Ethnology and cinéma vérité (Robert Flaherty, Jean Rouch, Edgar Morin, etc.)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            Reportage (Dziga Vertov, Chris Marker, Jean-Claude Bringuier, Raymond Depardon, etc.)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            The scientific expedition (Haroun Tazieff, Jacques-Yves Cousteau, Jean-Louis Etienne, Patrice Franceschi, Christian Clot, various members of the Société des Explorateurs Français, etc.).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In this article, we would like to elucidate how the journey of discovery seems to determine a typology of travel diaries compiled in a defined corpus</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. In what way is the notion of ‘extreme travel’, in terms of both discovering a hostile physical environment and adapting to a different human environment, inherent in the audiovisual travel diary? Does its mediatisation feed the imagination of the traveller and the tourist in their anthropological or geographical quest? How can we follow the touristic trajectory of a place (Gravari-Barbas and Grabum, 2012) or a particular type of natural space, the wild, through an analysis of imaginations and their ideological, aesthetic, philosophical and political foundations? ‘Touristic imagination and the tourist’s imagination are one and the same thing, because the tourist is at once the producer of imagination and an imagined element themselves’</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. These questions emerged after the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Carnets de voyage</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> were broadcast in 2008 on the French television programme </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Envoyé Spécial</span></em><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">on France 2, which has devoted the audiovisual and television genre to off-the-beaten-track tourism since July 2012</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. So, what is the touristic mediation that disseminates the audiovisual travel diary?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. The notions of extreme travel, the wild and the journey of discovery as catalysts for mediation in the travel diary genre</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The travel diaries circulated in France on television channels, documentaries and personal accounts aim to provide access to out-of-the-ordinary travel that examines human experiences in hostile or wild environments and to promote a tourism mediation that advocates off-the-beaten-track travel in the ‘backstage’ sense, in other words discovering the reconstructed environments or secret places that lie behind the scenes of the established tourism locations (Maitland, 2013). These two conceptions of extreme or wild travel, which are addressed in both fictional travel diary films and television documentary travel diaries, question not only our relationship with reality and discovery but also the form of travel itself, including the environment or nature as defined by the senses, the means of locomotion and the traveller’s cultural and mythical references. While the travel diary itself valorises cultural confrontation (Argod, 2011), the intermediality of the genre seems to orient the travel diary film towards transcending wild or hostile environments. Extreme spaces are indeed the subject of films focusing on out-of-the-ordinary climatic conditions, unpopulated desert areas, predatory wildlife and the risk of death, providing a window onto the instinct to survive in these natural environments. This valorisation of extreme travel concerns the type of travel as well as its purpose. Would immersion in the wild, as a ‘natural’ rather than a cultural shock, share similarities with a cultural confrontation or an encounter with the Other? Does extreme travel involve the ‘extime’, a neologism coined by Tournier (2002) to refer to a private response to the grandeur of an external environment? What off-the-beaten-track adventure is the film diarist looking for, and in what way does it reference the myth of the heroic journey? How can the travel diary genre be redefined? And how can the characteristics and typology of the genre be refined with regard to the notions of extreme, the wild or wilderness, nature, adventure, truth, authenticity and off the beaten track? How do these notions feed the traveller’s imagination and hence that of the tourist, because it means engaging in a ‘tourism without geographical or physical limits in order to go beyond symbolic, imaginary or cultural limits’ (Lemasson and Violier, 2010) or, put simply, going ‘off the beaten tracks’ (MacCannell, 1976)?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The travel diary genre, which takes the form of either self writing or an autobiographical film on the experience of travel (sometimes called a ‘biopic’), seems to be shaped by a relationship with nature and the requirement for a ‘lived journey’. We thus extend the road movie genre, which ‘combines locomotion and mediamotion within a specific cultural mobility’ (Moser, 2008), to robinsonades and films on the experience of a natural environment, such as maritime films (for example, Joachim Ronning’s 2012 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Kon Tiki</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Christophe Offenstein’s 2013 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Turning Tide</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, J.C. Chandor’s 2013 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">All is Lost</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">), mountain films (for example, Kevin Macdonald’s 2003 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Touching the Void</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Abel Ferry’s 2009 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">High Lane</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Philipp Stolzl’s 2008 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">North Face</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) and walking films (Emilio Estevez’s 2010 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Way</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Danny Boyle’s 2010 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">127 Hours</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Priscilla Telmon’s 2012 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Voyage au Tibet Interdit</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">). It is worth noting that, in France in 2016, there were approximately fifteen film festivals focused on nature and the environment, eleven festivals specialising in mountain films</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, three well-known festivals on maritime films</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and more than a dozen on adventure films, that is around forty festivals in all. If we also take extreme travel into account, the filmography</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> would include some survival (or disaster) films and epics that tell the story of the life force of characters who help individuals fulfil their destiny by sometimes transforming society. The diversity of film genres</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> could actually be defined according to their relationship to nature, hence the road movie, the robinsonade, the maritime film, the mountain film, the walking film, the survival or disaster film, and so on. The two American travel diary films mentioned above, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, have moved the travel diary genre into the same literary heritage bracket as Kerouac’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the American pioneer front and the myth of the journey of discovery and adventure.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Participating in the ‘wilderness’ myth (Depraz and Héritier, 2012), the territory of wild animals</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and the ambivalence of unspoiled or wild nature (Larrere, 1997), these two road movies play on the aesthetics of the image, from the panoramic landscape to the picturesque grandeur of nature. This is a trademark of the travel diary. It must inspire awe in the viewer through the poetic emotions it arouses, which are specific to the picturesqueness, in reference both to Jack London (</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Call of the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, published in 1903) and to geopoetics (White, 1994). The myths of the travelling hero and the quest for a new world are renewed here, particularly in the road movies, because a spiritual and temporal experience is just as important as the lived spatial experience. It is an inner experience, a one-way journey during which the protagonist searches deep within themselves through contact with the ‘extime’. It is a quest that is more temporal than geographical. In the road movie, openness to the intercultural is ‘foundational to the very matrix of the genre. The fact that the protagonist is leaving everything behind, moving towards the unknown and facing radical contingencies can translate into a particularly open disposition for encountering the cultural Other and other cultures’ (Moser, 2008). In addition, there is the quest for the wild in the travel diary genre. Exploration expands the limits not only of geographical knowledge but also of self-transcendence and personal achievement. However, ‘the logic of the extreme’ is, according to Baudry (1996), all relative and a function of the notion of ‘the extreme body’ (Baudry, 1991): ‘This transcendence only ever means an improvement of this same world, limited to the same sameness’. We might therefore wonder how this medium can be relevant in expanding the horizon of ‘extreme’ knowledge and exploration.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. Two contemporary road movies about the wild that have inspired a generation of travel diarists in search of the dream and anti-travel</section>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Galvanised by the success of Sean Penn’s 2007 film Into the Wild, the director Jean-Marc Vallée released Wild in 2015. Wild is a biopic of an adventurous traveller, inspired by the Charlie Starkweather character in Terrence Malick’s 1973 Badlands. The quest for these extreme journeys has rejuvenated the road movie genre by creating a travel diary genre that is closer to reality and the autobiographical, to the lived experience of travel. Backpacking tourists love to visit the Magic Bus in Alaska made famous in Into the Wild (see </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Reportages Découverte</span>, <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">broadcast on Saturday, 2 July 2016 at 1:30 pm on the French TV channel TF1</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, plus various travellers’ blogs, including the Alaska forum on Routard.com</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">)</span>.<span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Film-induced tourism (Beeton, 2005, 2016) is therefore a consequence of Into the Wild’s reputation as one of the top ten adventure films, according to film critics. It is indeed a hymn to freedom, to roaming without a vehicle</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn17" id="bodyftn17">17</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and to discovering the American West (cf. the Klondike Gold Rush, which Jack London participated in in 1897). Above all, it is a critique of the materialism of existence. It also references adaptations (examples include D.W. Griffith’s 1908 film, William A. Wellman’s 1935 film and Ken Annakin’s 1972 film) of Jack London’s novel The Call of the Wild, which showcases Yukon’s wild landscape. The gold rush of the late 19th century is transposed into a quest for unspoiled landscape and a return to nature, for osmosis with the nurturing and identity-affirming Mother Earth. In Into the Wild, we find the same motivations as those of backpackers (Lachance, 2015), namely the search for a sense of freedom, the quest for authenticity, the ability to adapt and to put oneself to the test and a sometimes relative originality (Le Bigot, 2016). Literary references, including Tolstoy, London and Thoreau, are present from the very beginning of the film. Indeed, this biopic about Christopher J. McCandless (who died in 1992), the hero of the biographical novel Into the Wild written by Jon Krakauer in 1996, is peppered with quotations from Henry D. Thoreau, who retired to nature in 1844 to seek the truth that leads society astray. Thoreau’s two-year experience, which he recounted in Walden; or, Life in the Woods, was at the source of the transcendentalist movement, which believed in the superiority of intuition over reason and militated for the freedom to think, be and act</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Hence, the film Into the Wild references Lord Byron (1788-1824) in Childe Harold’s Pilgrimage (1812-1818, Canto IV, Verse 178): ‘</span>There is a pleasure in the pathless woods, There is a rapture on the lonely shore, There is society where none intrudes, By the deep Sea, and music in its roar: I love not Man the less, but Nature more’<span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Constructed in four chapters, Birth, Adolescence, Adulthood and Accessing Wisdom, the film’s narrative turns the journey into a quest for self-discovery and self-construction, as revealed by the protagonist’s pseudonym, Alexander Supertramp. In his own words,</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The main thing is, it’s not how far you go but how you get there... (Back translated from French) Give me truth [...] I read somewhere how important it is in life not necessarily to be strong but to feel strong [...]</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span>The very basic core of a man’s living spirit is his passion for adventure. The joy of life comes from our encounters with new experiences, and hence there is no greater joy than to have an endlessly changing horizon, for each day to have a new and different sun.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">He wants to leave his life behind to experience the wild and live in the moment, and he keeps track of his journey in his diary (Courant, 2013) and on his camera. He notes his impressions, his emotions and the key words from his quest: ‘the freedom and simple beauty is just too good to pass up’, ‘I will get up, I will orient myself on my compass, I will go for broke’</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Back translated from French), ‘to lose myself in the depths of nature’ (Back translated from French)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">in order to reach ‘death in full life’ (Back translated from French), the epitaph that concludes the film. During the time he spends in Alaska in the Magic Bus, the wild, the untamed landscape (Floquet, 2012), and the solitude that accompanies this environment reveal their devastating power. They turn him into a predator in order to survive. This contrasts with time spent in society, which can be full of love and spiritual revival. The last words in his journal read ‘Happiness only real when shared’. It is as if he is denouncing the myth of Mother Nature the benefactor as ‘a parable of disenchantment’ (Hubner, 2013). Pétillon elucidated the dialectic of the road, which refers to the idea of both escape and confinement, of being enclosed and being on the run (Pétillon, 1979). The film Wild tells the story of a woman who treks on foot from Mexico to Alaska on a quest to find herself and the meaning of life following a bereavement. This biopic was inspired by the true story of Cheryl Strayed. She regained control of her life by opening herself up to the world after experiencing self-transcendence during a 1700-kilometres solo journey through the deserts of the American West.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. The return to nature as a cultural confrontation, formative journey and self-transcendence</section>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The legacy of the literary myths of Ulysses’s epic journey is that travel has become a tool for formative learning, emancipation, liberation and discovering self-transcendence. The return to nature or confrontation with the natural elements prompts an awareness of what separates the civilised and the wild, society and the individual. This dual confrontation is said to be formative as a result of the personal journey of discovery that travel fosters when it involves a confrontation with the wild or another culture. Ulysses’s journey has been the subject of two famous adventure films, Mario Camerini’s 1954 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ulysses</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (in Italian, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ulisse</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) and Andrei Konchalovsky’s 1997 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Odyssey</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which went on to influence a number of maritime expeditions and films. However, it is the robinsonades, the various adaptations of Daniel Defoe’s novel </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Robinson Crusoe</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1719), that have taken us on extreme journeys in the cinema, including George Mélies’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Robinson Crusoe</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1903, Luis Bunuel’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Adventures of Robinson Crusoe</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1954 and Rod Hardy and George T. Miller’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Robinson Crusoe</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1997. Daniel Defoe was inspired by the real-life adventure of the Scottish sailor Alexander Selkirk, who lived alone from 1704 to 1709 on an island in the archipelago off the coast of Chile. Extreme living conditions on a desert island in a hostile environment triggers the survival instinct. The individual must battle not only against their new environment but also against themselves. The numerous adaptations of Johann David Wyss’s novel </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Swiss Family Robinson</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and William Golding’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lord of the Flies </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">evidence the fact that</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">film productions</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn19" id="bodyftn19">19</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> are inspired by the theme of the one-way journey. However, it is the road movies that ask the pertinent questions about the journey as a tribute to individualism and self-denial. This is clear in the closing lines of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Moreover, the relationship seems to be authentic,</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            T<span lang="en" xml:lang="en">he audiovisual travel diary, with its ‘cultural bifurcations’ (Gin, 2008), is marked by the notion of interculturality (Argod, 2011), notably through the various road movies (since 1992 and the release of Fernando E. Solanas’s film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">El Viaje</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> [</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Journey</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">], which inspired Walter Salles’s 2004 </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Motorcycle Diaries</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and a Franco-Moroccan road movie by Ismaël Ferroukhi entitled </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Le Grand Voyage</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 2004). However, the cultural confrontation that is a feature of the travel diary is replaced in the audiovisual travel diary by a confrontation with the wild. Our two American examples advocate anti-travel</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn21" id="bodyftn21">21</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> as a formative journey and source of wonder. Chanvallon elucidated the return to nature in her social anthropology and ethnology doctoral thesis:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The return to nature as a scientific geographical construct that fosters self-transcendence is fundamental for explorers such as Christian Clot, a member of the Société des Explorateurs Français, who explains the attraction of unexplored lands:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. The aesthetics of the image, of the panoramic landscape and of the grandeur of nature: the legacy of the notions of ‘picturesqueness’ and the ‘pioneer front’.</section>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Pushing the border towards the West in order to extend the pioneer front forged American culture and the American nation. The West was being settled and developed by humans facing the wilderness now represented by Alaska in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Wide open spaces and harsh landscape are at the heart of American mythology. In </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, they are the subject of the tracking shots and panoramic views that are reminiscent of the picturesque Alpine views painted by English watercolour artists. This notion of ‘picturesqueness’ in the art should be linked to the notion of authentic, true images in cinematographic art and more especially to ‘staged’ touristic authenticity (MacCannell, 1976), which has become a form of ‘communicative authenticity’ (Cohen, 1979). The director’s comments in </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild: The Experience</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (17 min) showcase the quality of the images, which were achieved through shooting in situ, on the one hand, with a skilful management both of the climatic calendar at each stage of the film from Mexico all the way up to Alaska and of the harsh shooting conditions and, on the other, with a lightweight camera carried on the shoulder to produce </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">cinéma vérité</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Graff, 2011), a technique inherited from Dziga Vertov and promoted by Edgar Morin.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The term ‘picturesque’ is an old one. It appeared in France in 1708 in its Italian sense </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">‘pittoresco’</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which describes ‘a composition that is striking to the eye’. The term was accepted by the Académie Française in 1732 and defined in 1726 by the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Encyclopédie</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> as ‘a piquant and singular choice of the effects of nature’, in short, a particular way of relating to nature</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn24" id="bodyftn24">24</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. From 1730 to 1790, British landscape art, which was free of any academicism, highlighted the irregularities and strangeness of nature as noted by the aristocrats and artists travelling in Italy who admired the paintings coming out of the School of Rome. We know the influence Claude Lorrain’s in situ paintings had on nineteenth-century landscape realism. Picturesqueness implies the staging of self as both an actor in and viewer of the world, which is perceived as sublime (Klingender, 1988). It brings together the picturesque, the poetic and the romantic to encourage contemplation, to speak to the mind and stimulate sensibilities and to offer a palette of emotions, including surprise. The picturesque site aspires to feelings of admiration and fascination, and these must be accentuated in the perspective adopted by the artist until it becomes a so-called picturesque view: ‘that which pleases by some quality is likely to provide an advantageous subject for painting’</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn25" id="bodyftn25">25</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Moreover, the American artist Edward Hopper inspired the road movie (Hurault-Paupe, 2007) as well as representations of the wild and the solitude of wide open spaces. In filmmaking, the notion of ‘picturesqueness’ is conveyed both through the editing, which produces synthetic, rhythmic and rhetorical effects, and through referencing </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">cinema vérité</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Graff, 2011) by staying as close as possible to the landscape. Director Sean Penn, who could have been drawing on Mario Ruspoli’s words (Gauthier, 2010), said on the subject: ‘Being invisible, making yourself part of the landscape, merging with the crowd is fundamental for the director who seeks to approach reality (Back-translated from French). In addition, the internal deigetic sounds, where the source of the sound is visible in the image, and the ambient sound of the scenes being played have been prioritised for the sake of authenticity and realism (Gauthier, 2010), in order to stay as close as possible to the lived experience.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The notion of time is essential in accessing the poetics of travel. The autobiographical narrative must convey a style and a framework to communicate a message and retrace a journey, since physical effort has a symbolic dimension. This ‘nomadic’ rite becomes a rite of passage. For Jean Didier Urbain (1991) and Marc Augé (1997), it is essential to experience wonder and learn to see again. A journey requires non-knowledge. It requires spending some time in a place, before you move on to the next, so that you can immerse yourself in that place and exchange with the population, the bewilderment and the boredom. A journey implies creating a distance from the world, which results in ‘a break with the ordinary, inducing an aesthetic consciousness (Back translated from French). This aesthetic of Otherness is what makes it possible for the writer-traveller to write. They are receptive to all these details that allow them to represent a different reality to the reader. According to Kenneth White (1994), openness to and interest in the world facilitate the poetics of travel, which in turn allows us to understand the world. For Franck Michel (2005), travel is an encounter with the Other that enables us to access the myth and fight against the banalisation of the world.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">V. The renewed myths of the wandering hero and the quest for a new world: the legacy of Jack Kerouac’s On the Road and the Beat Generation’s ‘Beat ethos’26</section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The two films </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> were inspired by the pioneers’ conquest, which fundamentally marks American literature through works such as Jack London’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Call of the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The ‘backpacker subculture’ (Richards and Wilson, 2004) is said to be at the origin of road movies. Jack Kerouac’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1922-1969) is the mythical work of all globetrotters</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn27" id="bodyftn27">27</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> ‘The open road is life. It replaces the ancient “trail” of the pioneers in their advance on the West’ (Back translated from French). It continues the long folk tradition of the American journey. Clearly identifiable as a work from the Beat Generation, it recounts the story of Jack Kerouac, Neal Cassady and Lu Anne Henderson’s 1949 Hudson car trip from New York to San Francisco (6,200 km) in three days and three nights. The ethnographic writer (Bibeau, 2004) Kerouac rediscovered his natural and spontaneous flow as he wrote </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1951. Neal Cassady was full of admiration for this famous first draft. Kerouac typed for three weeks without stopping on a 40-metres-long continuous scroll fed into his typewriter to maintain the internal jazz rhythm</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn28" id="bodyftn28">28</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The major works produced from 1957 onwards by the Beat Generation were Kerouac’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Dharma Bums</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Ginsberg’s</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Howl</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and Burrough’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Naked Lunch</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. They are symbols of freedom, of protest at bourgeois values and of revolt at world greed</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn29" id="bodyftn29">29</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sur le chemin</span></em><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn30" id="bodyftn30">30</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which Kerouac wrote in French in 1952 when he was in Mexico City, was to be a preliminary draft of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Kerouac reworked </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sur le chemin</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> in 1953 and proposed a French version under the title </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sur la route</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, which subsequently inspired a film adaptation, released in 2012 by Walter Salles.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The road movie style was inspired by the Beat Generation, which, under the impetus of Jonas Mekas, developed an underground cinema in 1955. This brought together twenty-three independent directors seeking to free themselves from the diktats of Hollywood and to make cinema a means of personal expression rather than the product of an industry. As such, the road movies were the fruits of a counter-culture and a political and social protest</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn31" id="bodyftn31">31</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. They were inspired by the Beat theme of the quest for self through wandering and the transcontinental drift on Route 66, and they introduced a new type of hero, the ‘magnificent loser’, borrowed from </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Migozzi, 2000). In 1969, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Easy Rider</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, starring Dennis Hopper (director), Peter Fonda (producer) and Jack Nicholson, became a cult film for the Beatnik generation. It marks the birth of the road movie, presenting the journey of three hippy motorcyclists who plan a trip in search of a lost America (Benoliel and Thoret, 2011). It is the romantic myth of the open road as the ultimate escape from the past. Mobility was synonymous with wandering and the desire for non-conformity. Individuals used the journey of discovery to go off and find themselves in order to then shape themselves in opposition to the social norm. Wandering, marginality and freedom allowed them to experience America. In preparation for shooting </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Paris, Texas</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, Wim Wenders became a filmmaker-traveller and travelled the American West for three months to photograph the filming locations. He also travelled across the world before directing the film </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Until the End of the World</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. His approach was that of a traveller, camera in hand, in search of his film. Before creating his work of art, he would make notes and sketches as part of his research. This approach is said to be reminiscent of Eugène Delacroix’s travel diary </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Album d’Afrique du Nord et d’Espagne</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, a historical model of the genre created in 1832 (Argod, 2012) in the tone of the travel diaries of the romantic and orientalist painters. He produced a ‘little book of inspiration’ in preparation for his work of art. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In short, extreme journeys are thought to be motivated by a desire to experience the wild, to move from the cultural back to the natural and to self-transcend in order to reach the ‘truth’. This exploration of the unknown beyond our physical and mental limitations is thought to convey both a contemporary heroism, that of the figure of the traveller as explorer-adventurer (Venayre, 2002, 2006) as opposed to the tourist, and a temporality that is specific to the experience of the hypermodern subject. According to Tesson, ‘we distil time to free ourselves from space’</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn32" id="bodyftn32">32</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. This journey of discovery (which is both a response to </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Call of the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and a desire to be </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">) to expand our horizons is said to be as much a change of world</span> f<span lang="en" xml:lang="en">or the explorer as a construction of self for the adventurer. It is about encouraging off-the-beaten-track, backpacker-type, out of the ordinary, unconventional travel, with no guide. The travel diary genre stems from this definition of extreme travel (mind map and filmography) and is positioned somewhere between creative documentary and fiction since it recounts a journey in images. The journey is, after all, only a receptive view of the world, an interrogation of reality inherited from Jean Rouch’s work. The travel diary, as a little book of inspiration, an artistic quest in preparation for a work of art or a philosophical or anthropological reflection on the world or the Elsewhere, deals with reality and the formation of the individual rather than fiction, despite the 1960s road movies trend. In fact, according to Walter Moser,</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion </section>
        <section niveau="h2">A touristic practice of discovery: transcending the extreme of the world through the experience of travel</section>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Based on the notion of ‘extreme travel’, we have profiled the audiovisual travel diary genre as fictional film, but it can also be compared with the documentary</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn34" id="bodyftn34">34</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. In addition, despite the plurality of genres (biopic, road movie, creative documentary, travel programme, reportage, ethnologist film, etc.), the travel diary is above all a narrative in images of the lived experience of travelling, and, as such, it is autobiographical. This production, most often a creative documentary, valorises freedom and the unconventional, the authentic and the picturesque, the original and the creative. The transformation of the traveller who confronts reality is often at the heart of the account. Through their lived experience, this audiovisual genre wishes to achieve the notion of touristic and communicative authenticity. Whether transcribed in the form of a road movie or a creative documentary, the wild has stamped its seal on both the quest for adventure on the road and the literary myth of the heroic traveller, inherited from Ulysses’s journey and the robinsonades. Two films, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Into the Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Wild</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, have established wild travel as a search for the dream and anti-travel, the quest of travel diarists. These works combine three characteristics: the return to nature, the aesthetics of the image and the renewed myth of the ‘wandering’ hero. These three features all have their literary and artistic origins and form a cultural melting pot containing the robinsonade, the picturesque and above all the Beat ethos of the Beat Generation, which formed in the wake of Kerouac’s </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the Road</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Self-transcendence, a panoramic landscape and the quest for a new world turn nature into a manifesto for extreme travel. An appetite for adventure and the journey of discovery is mediatised by the evocation of extreme spaces. This genre (Argod, 2009) is based on the definition of both the quest for travel and the interaction of three notions, namely the environment, the autobiography and the narrative depicted in (sometimes epic) images. Observing the terrain, discovering other cultures and viatic imagination are the attractions of the travel diary, which probably circulates values of travel that go beyond the notion of the wild and the fears to be overcome. As a revelation of self, a path for discovering real-life experiences, a passport to the Other and a construction of self and freedom, the travel diary becomes a tool for evaluating our being in the world (Argod, 2014).</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Argod P., 2016, “ La médiatisation d’un tourisme “ hors des sentiers battus » dans une édition touristique créative », Via, 9.URL : http://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/516; DOI : 10.4000/viatourism.516</reference>
        <reference>Argod P., 2014, L’art du carnet de voyage. Gallimard - Alternatives, (version en anglais “ The Art of Sketchking : 400 years of Travel Diaries » parue en février 2016 puis en chinois et en coréen).</reference>
        <reference>Argod P., 2014, "Le carnet de voyage. Outil d’évaluation de l’être au monde et de la valeur initiatique du voyage", in Quand l’Homme voyage, les passeurs d’empreintes, L’Harmattan - SEH, Société d’écologie Humaine, 2014, 401-412.</reference>
        <reference>Argod P., 2012, De l’Orientalisme. in Carnet de voyage-reportage, Hypotheses.org. URL : http://cdevoyage.hypotheses.org/223</reference>
        <reference>Argod, P., 2011, Carnet de voyage sans frontières, Reflets d’ailleurs, 2011 (Pars en thèse).</reference>
        <reference>Argod P., 2011, "Le carnet de voyage audio-visuel ou cinématographique : genre intermédial, quête et diffusion du voyage “ authentique » ", Revue Téoros, Revue de recherche en tourisme, université du Québec à Montréal, UQUAM, août 2011, numéro sur “ Le ciné - tourisme » dirigé par Alain Grenier, 117-125.</reference>
        <reference>Argod P.,2009, Le carnet de voyage : approches historique et sémiologique, Thèse de Doctorat, université de Bordeaux III.</reference>
        <reference>Augé M., 1997, L’impossible voyage : le tourisme et ses images, Paris, Rivages..</reference>
        <reference>Baudry P., 1996, “ La logique de l’extrême », in : Communications, 61,. Natures extrêmes, 11-20.</reference>
        <reference>Baudry P., 1991, Le Corps extrême, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Beeton S., 2005 (2016), Film-induced Tourism.Bristol, Buffalo, Toronto, Channel View Publications, Aspects of Tourism.</reference>
        <reference>Benoliel B &amp; Thoret J.-B., 2011, “ Charlot ou le mythe exemplaire », in Road movie, USA, Hoëbeke.</reference>
        <reference>Bibeau G., 2004, "Voyages et fictions chez Jack Kerouac : une ethnographie de la franco-américanité ?", Anthropologie et Sociétés, Volume 28, n° 3, 59-89.</reference>
        <reference>Chanvallon, S., 2009, Anthropologie des relations de l’Homme à la Nature : la Nature vécue entre peur destructrice et communion intime. Thèse de Doctorat Anthropologie sociale et ethnologie. Université Rennes 2 ; Université Européenne de Bretagne. </reference>
        <reference>Cohen E., 1979, “ A Phenomenology of Tourist Experience », Sociology, n° 13, 179-201.</reference>
        <reference>Courant S., 2013, "Backpackers et carnets de voyage, récit biographique d’une expérience itinérante", Téoros, 32-1</reference>
        <reference>Delaplace M., Gravari-Barbas M., 2017, Nouveaux territoires touristiques. Invention, reconfigurations, repositionnement, Coll. “ Tourisme », Presses de l’université du Québec.</reference>
        <reference>Depraz S., Heritier S., 2012, “ La nature et les parcs naturels en Amérique du Nord », L’Information géographique,. n° 76, no. 4, 6-28.</reference>
        <reference>Floquet P., 2012, Into the Wild : la Nature, ce n’est pas du cinéma !.. Mise au point : cahiers de l’association française des enseignants chercheur en cinéma et audiovisuel, n° 4.</reference>
        <reference>Fournier F.S, Chatagner C., Bernié-Boissard C., Crozat D., 2014, Les cultures du déplacement : séminaire du 14-16 juin 2012, Presses universitaires d’Aix-Marseille, PUAM.</reference>
        <reference>Gauthier G., 2000, Le Documentaire, un autre cinéma, Nathan.</reference>
        <reference>Gauthier G., 2010, Géographie sentimentale du documentaire : l’esprit des lieux, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Gilpin W., 1982, Trois Essais sur le beau pittoresque, sur les voyages pittoresques et sur l’art d’esquisser les paysages, suivi d’un poème sur la peinture de paysage, paru en 1792 et traduit de l’anglais par le Baron de Blumenstein en 1799, postface de M. Conan, Éd. du Moniteur, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Gin P., 2008, "Les bifurcations culturelles du road movie contemporain", Cinémas : revue d’études cinématographiques / Cinémas : Journal of Film Studies, vol.18, numéro 2-3, 31-45.</reference>
        <reference>Graff S., 2011, “ ” Cinéma-vérité » ou “ cinéma direct » : hasard terminologique ou paradigme théorique ? », Décadrages [En ligne], n° 18, 32-46.</reference>
        <reference>Gravari-Barbas M., Grabum N., 2012, “ Imaginaires touristiques », Via [En ligne], 1 | 2012, mis en ligne le 16 mars 2012, consulté le 27 août 2018. URL :http://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1178</reference>
        <reference>Hubner P., 2013, D’On the Road à Into the Wild : la parabole du désenchantement. Le prisme américain, Babel, littératures plurielles, n° 28, 109-122.</reference>
        <reference>Hurault-Paupe A., 2007, "Edward Hopper et le Road Movie", in Sipère D., Cohen A. J.-J. (dir.), Les autres arts dans l’art du cinéma, Presses universitaires de Rennes, 85-91.</reference>
        <reference>Kingender F.D., 1988, "Le sublime et le pittoresque", Actes de la recherches sociales, volume 75, n° 75, 2-13.</reference>
        <reference>Lachance J., 2013, “ Le rapport à la temporalité du backpacker », Téoros [Online], n° 32-1, URL : http://teoros.revues.org/2398</reference>
        <reference>Larrere C., 1997, Les philosophies de l’environnement, Paris : PUF, coll. “ Philosophies ».</reference>
        <reference>Le Bigot B., 2016, “ Le “ tour du monde » des backpakers, voyage normalisé ? », Via, n° 9. URL : http://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/316; DOI : 10.4000/viatourism.316</reference>
        <reference>Lemasson J.P.,Violier P., 2010, Destinations et territoires, Volume 2 Tourisme sans limite, Les Rendez-vous Champlain sur le tourisme, Presses universitaires du Québec, 2010.</reference>
        <reference>Mac Cannell D., 1976 (1989), The Tourist, A New Theory of the Leisure Class, Berkeley-Los Angeles- London, University of California Press, 1976.</reference>
        <reference>Maitland R., 2013, “ Backstage Behaviour in the Global City: Tourists and the Search for the ‘Real London’ », Procedia – Social and Behavioral Sciences, n° 105, 12-19 . URL :10.1016/j.sbspro.2013.11.002</reference>
        <reference>Michel F., 2005, Désirs d’ailleurs : essai d’anthropologie des voyages, Presses de l’université de Laval, Québec.</reference>
        <reference>Migozzi J., 2000, De l’écrit à l’écran, littératures populaires : mutations génériques, mutations médiatiques. actes du colloque organisé en 1998 par le Centre des littératures populaires de l’université de Limoges associé au Centre de recherche en littérature québécoise, Limoges, PULIM.</reference>
        <reference>Moser W., 2008, "Présentation. Le road movie : un genre issu d’une constellation moderne de locomotion et de médiamotion", Cinémas, n° 18(2-3), 7–30.</reference>
        <reference>Omhoyer C., 2014, "Quelques reconfigurations contemporaines du “ wilderness » dans la fiction et les arts visuels du Canada anglophone", in Fournier F.S., Chatagner, C. Bernié-Boissard C.,Crozat D. (dir.), Les cultures du déplacement : séminaire du 14-16 juin 2012, Presses universitaires d’Aix-Marseille.</reference>
        <reference>Petillon, P.-Y., 1979, La Grand-route. Espace et écriture en Amérique, Le Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Richards G., Wilson J., 2004, “ Travel writers and writers who travel: Nomadic Icons for the backpacker subculture? », Journal of Tourism and Cultural Change, vol. 2, no 1, 46-68.</reference>
        <reference>Tesson S., 2012, La géographie de l’instant, Ed. Des Equateurs.</reference>
        <reference>Tournier M., 2002, Journal extime, La Musardine.</reference>
        <reference>Tzanelli R., 2007, The cinematic tourist: explorations in globalization, culture, and resistance, London, Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Urbain J.-D., 1991, L’Idiot du voyage. Histoires de touristes, Paris, Plon.</reference>
        <reference>Vernex J.-C., 2004, "Du voyage de l’œil à l’appréciation du paysage : le pittoresque comme une des origines culturelles du paysage", in : Le Globe. Revue genevoise de géographie, tome 144 Voyage, tourisme, paysage.</reference>
        <reference>Venayre, S., 2006, Rêves d’aventures 1800-1940, De La Martinière.</reference>
        <reference>Venayre S., 2002, La gloire de l’aventure. Genèse d’une mystique moderne, Aubier.</reference>
        <reference>White K., 1994, Le plateau de l’albatros : introduction à la géopoétique, Grasset.</reference>
        <reference>Filmographie classée par ordre de citation dans l’article</reference>
        <reference>Sur le carnet de recherche "Carnet de voyage -reportage"(P. Argod) sur Hypotheses.org dans la rubrique "Corpus intermédia", juin 2016 : http://cdevoyage.hypotheses.org/category/corpus-intermedia</reference>
        <reference>Penn S., 2007, Into the Wild, 147 minutes. Paramount Vantage [US]</reference>
        <reference>Vallée J.-M., 2014, Wild, 126’. Fox Searchlight Pictures Pacific Standard [US]</reference>
        <reference>Ronning J., Sanderg E., 2012, Kon Tiki, NO, 120’. Recorded Picture Company, Roenbergfilm, Nordisk Film Production A/S, DCM Productions [GB, NO, DK].</reference>
        <reference>Offenstein C., 2013, En solitaire, BE, 96’. Gaumont, Les films du Cap, TF1 Film Production, Scope Pictures, A contracorriente Films. [FR, BE, ES]</reference>
        <reference>Chandor J.C., 2013, All is lost, 106’.Universal studio [US]</reference>
        <reference>Macdonald K., 2004, La mort suspendue, Touching The Void,FR, 106’. Darlow Smithson Productions [GB]</reference>
        <reference>Ferry A., 2009, Vertige, FR, Sombrero Productions, Canal + [FR]</reference>
        <reference>Stolzi P. , 2008, Duel au sommet, Nordwand, DE, 126’. Dor Film West, Medienkontor Movie gmbH, Dor Film [DE, CH]</reference>
        <reference>Boyle D., 2011, 127 heures, GB, 94’. Cloud Eight Films, Darlow Smithson Productions, Decibel Films [GB, US]</reference>
        <reference>Estevez E., 2010, The way la route ensemble, ES, 123’. Filmax, Castelao Producciones, Producions A Fonsagrada [ES]</reference>
        <reference>Telmon P. 2012, Au pays interdit, Bonne Pioche, 75’</reference>
        <reference>Camerini, M., 1954, Ulysse (Ulisse), 118’. Lux Films [IT]</reference>
        <reference>Konchalowvsky A., 1997, L’Odyssée, 172’. Hallmark Entertainement, American Zoetrope Production San Francisco [US]</reference>
        <reference>Melies G., 1902, Les Aventures de Robinson Crusoé,Georges Méliès, Star Film [FR]</reference>
        <reference>Bunuel L. , 1954, Les Aventures de Robinson Crusoé,90’. Oscar Dancigers [Mexique]</reference>
        <reference>Hardy R., Miller G. T., 1997, Robinson Crusoé, 92’. Touchstone Pictures [US]</reference>
        <reference>Solanas F. E., 1992, Le voyage - El Viaje, 140’ ; Cinesur, Buesnos Aires [Argentine]</reference>
        <reference>Ferroukhi I., 2004, Le Grand voyage, FR, 108’. Ognon Pictures [FR, MA]</reference>
        <reference>Salles W., 1998, Central Do Brazil, 113’. VideoFilmes [BR, FR]</reference>
        <reference>Salles W., 2004, Carnets de voyage : Che Guevara, Diarios de motocicleta, 120’. </reference>
        <reference>Nozik M., Tenkoff K., Redford R., South Fork Pictures / Edgard Tenembaum, Tu Vas Voir Productions / Film Four / Daniel Burman, Diego Dubcovsky, BD Ciné / Senator Film Produktion [Brésil/Argentine/Grande-Bretagne]</reference>
        <reference>Malick T-F., 1975, La balade sauvage, Badland, 94’ Badlands Company, Jill Jakes Production [US]</reference>
        <reference>Hopper D., Fonda P., 1969, Easy Rider, 94’. Columbia Pictures Corportion, Pando Company Inc., Rayber Productions. [US]</reference>
        <reference>Wenders W., 1984, Paris-Texas, 147’ 20 th Century Fox [US]</reference>
        <reference>Wenders W., 1991, Jusqu’au bout du monde, Bis ans Ende der Welt, [FR, AU, DE]</reference>
        <reference>Salles W., 2012, Sur la route, On the Road (adaptation du roman de Jack Kérouac), FR, 137’ MK2 Films, Film 4, American Zoetrope [FR,GB,US]. </reference>
        <reference>Griffith D. W., 1908, The Call of the Wild, 15’. American Mutoscope and Biograph Company</reference>
        <reference>Wellman W. A., 1935, The Call of the Wild, L’appel de la forêt, 95’. 20th Century Pictures</reference>
        <reference>Annakin K., 1972, The Call of the Wild, 100’. Central Cinéma Company Film, Massfilms Limited, Norsk Film A/S, Oceania Produzioni Internationali Cinématographe, Towers of London Productions, Universal Pictures France, Izaro Films SA [FR, GB, NO, IT]</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">The 17th Rendez-vous du Carnet de Voyage, held from 18 to 20 November 2016, was a Europe-wide event with international influence: http://www.rendezvous-carnetdevoyage.com/ Its president, Jean-Pierre Frachon, is a mountaineer, renowned for his ascent of the Seven Summits.</note>
        <note id="2">All references relating to the films and videos cited in this study are grouped together in the filmography at the end of the article.</note>
        <note id="3">http://www.allocine.fr/film/fichefilm-110101/box-office/</note>
        <note id="4">See the mind map and filmography in Argod’s 2011 article in the issue on ‘Le ciné-tourisme’, edited by Alain Grenier, p. 117-125 (9 pages).</note>
        <note id="5">Attached here as an appendix and available in Argod’s research logbook, Carnet de voyage-reportage, on Hypotheses.org: https://cdevoyage.hypotheses.org/1075</note>
        <note id="6">Idem. Unless specified otherwise, this and all subsequent quotations from French sources have been translated from the French.</note>
        <note id="7">See the 75 travel diaries online: http://envoye-special.france2.fr/carnet-de-voyage.html?id_mot=200</note>
        <note id="8">See the title Vacances chez les pygmies for France 2 programme’s ‘le carnet de voyage d'envoyé spécial’, Thursday 19 July 2012.</note>
        <note id="9">http://www.fodacim.fr/les-festivals-de-films-de-montagne-et-daventure/</note>
        <note id="33">d Festival du Film de Montagne in Autrans from 30 November to 4 December 2016: http://www.festival-autrans.com/ </note>
        <note id="0">egards d’altitudes, 21-23 April 2016 in Barcelonnette: http://www.festival-film-montagne.fr/</note>
        <note id="10">Festival international du film maritime, d’exploration et d’environnement, FIFME mid-December in Toulon:</note>
        <note id="0">ttp://www.fifme-toulon.com/</note>
        <note id="0">estival international des films de la mer FILMAR in Hendaye, 16-17 March 2017: http://filmar.hendaye.com/</note>
        <note id="0">he 8th Festival International de Films Pêcheurs du Monde was held in Lorient from 14 to 20 March 2016:</note>
        <note id="0">ttp://www.pecheursdumonde.org/</note>
        <note id="11">See the selection in Argod’s research logbook, ‘Carnet de voyage -reportage: intermédialité, interculturalité, médiation, patrimoine’, available on Hypotheses.org under the heading Corpus intermédia, June 2016: http://cdevoyage.hypotheses.org/category/corpus-intermedia</note>
        <note id="12">See Argod, Filmography on extreme travel and defining film genres according to their relationship to nature, June 2016: http://cdevoyage.hypotheses.org/category/corpus-intermedia</note>
        <note id="13">Claire Omhover. ‘Quelques reconfigurations contemporaines du “wilderness” dans la fiction et les arts visuels du Canada anglophone’. In Les cultures du déplacement: séminaire du 14-16 juin 2012. Edited by F.S. Fournier, C. Chatagner, C. Bernié-Boissard, D. Crozat. Presses Universitaires d’Aix-Marseille, PUAM, 2014, p. 79-91. </note>
        <note id="14">Translation from Old English.</note>
        <note id="15">http://www.programme-television.org/news-tv/Reportages-decouverte-TF1-Sur-les-traces-du-film-Into-the-Wild-4333975</note>
        <note id="0">ttp://unduvetpourdeux.com/plongez-au-coeur-dinto-the-wild/</note>
        <note id="0">ttps://littlegypsy.fr/faire-trek-magic-bus-into-the-wild-alaska/</note>
        <note id="0">ttps://www.blog-trotting.fr/voyage/etats-unis/1735-alaska-the-last-frontier</note>
        <note id="16">https://www.routard.com/photos/alaska/92420-bus_142_du_film_into_the_wild.htm</note>
        <note id="0">ttps://www.routard.com/forum_message/3102775/sur_les_traces_d_into_the_wild_magic_bus_alaska.htm</note>
        <note id="17">drifters (Cohen, 1972); nomads (Cohen, 1973); wanderers (Vogt, 1976).</note>
        <note id="18">The name of the Transcendentalism movement, which comes from a work by Emmanuel Kant (1724-1804), revolutionised American philosophy and literature.</note>
        <note id="19">See the seven films listed in the online filmography on Carnet de voyage-reportage, hypotheses.org.</note>
        <note id="20">Jocelyn Lachance, ‘Le rapport à la temporalité du backpacker’, Téoros [Online], 32-1 | 2013, Online since 15 December 2015 URL: http://teoros.revues.org/2398</note>
        <note id="21">See Muriel Cerf’s book, L’antivoyage, published in 1974, which recounts her travels in India in 1970, long before the French travel guide Guide du Routard made its appearance. It opened up the route to India for French hippies.</note>
        <note id="22">Stéphanie Chanvallon, Intermède: Retour vers la Nature - Des ‘remédiations’ à la peur. In Anthropologie des relations de l’Homme à la Nature: la Nature vécue entre peur destructrice et communion intime. PhD thesis. Anthropologie sociale et ethnologie. Université Rennes 2; Université Européenne de Bretagne, 2009. French. p. 224-228 &lt;tel-00458244v2&gt;</note>
        <note id="23">Extract of Christian Clot’s interview on the French television programme Ma Vie est une Aventure on France 3, presented by Cécile Gauthier. Posted on YouTube on 14 May 2010.</note>
        <note id="24">Jean-Claude Vernex, Du voyage de l’œil à l’appréciation du paysage: le pittoresque comme une des origines culturelles du paysage. In: Le Globe. Revue genevoise de géographie, tome 144 Voyage, tourisme, paysage, 2004, pp. 57-66.</note>
        <note id="25">William Gilpin, Three Essays: On Picturesque Beauty; On Picturesque Travel; And on Sketching Landscape: To Which is Added a Poem, on Landscape Painting, London, 1792 (back-translated from French).</note>
        <note id="26">The term ‘Beat’ comes from the street language of drug addicts and was used in 1948 by Kerouac to mean ‘beatific’ or ‘cool’ in the jazz beat or in the spirit of renunciation.</note>
        <note id="27">See the novel’s itinerary in the file on Jack Kerouac on the Routard.com website.</note>
        <note id="28">See John Byrum’s 1980 film Heart Beat.</note>
        <note id="29">See Allen Ginsberg’s poem Howl, with Moloch, the high-finance building.</note>
        <note id="30">Article published in the French newspaper Le Monde (Le Monde.fr) on 8 September 2008. The manuscript was found by Gabriel Anctil in the archives of various New York libraries.</note>
        <note id="31">The earliest works include John Cassavetes’s 1958 Shadows, Shirley Clarke’s 1961 The Connection, Kenneth Anger’s 1963 Scorpio Rising and films by Andy Warhol.</note>
        <note id="32">Sylvain Tesson, La géographie de l’instant, Editions Des Equateurs, 2012. p 43.</note>
        <note id="33">‘Le road movie: un genre issu d’une constellation moderne de locomotion et de médiamotion’, Walter Moser, Cinémas: Revue d'études cinématographiques/Journal of Film Studies, Volume 18, number 2-3, Spring 2008, p.7-30 http://id.erudit.org/iderudit/018415ar</note>
        <note id="34">See the two filmographies available online in the research notebook: Pascale Argod, Carnet de voyage - reportage: intermédialité, interculturalité, médiation, patrimoine, Hypotheses.org, 2012.</note>
    </notes>
</article>