<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_PDPBEG_9-47_Ls_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5068" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.5068</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="5062">
            <traducteur nom="Hoffman" prenom="Daniel" />
            Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux
        </original>
        <traduction lang="es" source="5071">El paisaje como recurso turístico de las zonas rurales</traduction>
        <traduction lang="de" source="5072">Landschaft als touristische Ressource der ländlichen Gebiete</traduction>
        <traduction lang="pt" source="5081">A paisagem como recurso turístico em áreas rurais</traduction>
        <traduction lang="it" source="5088">Il paesaggio come risorsa turistica degli spazi rurali</traduction>
        <traduction lang="ca" source="5092">El paisatge com a recurs turístic a les zones rurals</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Dérioz" prenom="Pierre">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PDPBEG_9-57_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5062" lang="fr">Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Assistant Professor, Avignon University 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Bachimon" prenom="Philippe">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PB_35-139_Ll_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1314" lang="fr">Les friches touristiques en Polynésie française – Révélateur d’une crise de la destination et forme de résistance au tourisme international</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PBFD_19-29_Au_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1172" lang="fr">A la mémoire de Rachid Amirou</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PB_5-40_De_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1652" lang="fr">Des cadres pour la recherche en tourisme</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PBJMDRK_46-47_Ee_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1336" lang="fr">Expériences touristiques et trajectoires de vie</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PDPBEG_9-57_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5062" lang="fr">Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Professor, Avignon University 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Gauché" prenom="Evelyne">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PDPBEG_9-57_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5062" lang="fr">Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Assistant Professor, University of Tours 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Landscape as a tourism resource for rural areas</titre>
    <sousTitre>South and Southeast-Asian perspectives</sousTitre>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            This issue of <em>Via@</em> aims to explore the following question: What part do rural landscapes play in tourism development in South (India, Nepal) and Southeast Asia (Laos, Vietnam and China)? This question is addressed here in six articles written by researchers of five nationalities. In this introduction we outline the questions taken up in this special issue of the journal <em>Via</em>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            The first angle of approach is to discern by whom, and for whom, the rural landscape is produced. This social co-production of the landscape is based on a complex process for take advantage of the multiple potentials offered by territories, in which the different actors cooperate, ignore each other, compete, confront one another, or negotiate. To interpret this range of interactions, it is helpful to connect two distinct but related dimensions which correspond to two different ways of understanding the expression "social production of the landscape", one, as a material process of shaping space by human actions (Lifran and Oueslaty, 2007), but another as a cultural process of “revelation” of a spatial configuration as a landscape (Toublanc, 2013, p. 108), that is as "cosmophany" (Berque, 2000; 2007).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            Standing in tension (Wylie, 2007), these two dimensions, which refer to the fundamental duality of landscapes (Poullaouec-Gonidec <em>et al.</em>, 2005, p. 34; Dérioz, 2012), together feed into relations between actors. In the north of Laos , for example, western tourists are disappointed to discover that the "jungle" marketed by tourist agencies, and through which they planned to trek through, is in fact largely exploited by peasants in slash-and-burn agriculture by peasants, or by rubber plantations encouraged by the State (Ducourtieux <em>et al.</em>, 2006). How can we analyze these discrepancies—but at times also convergences—between representations of landscapes among actors whose practices differ and whose ties to the territory may have nothing in common? How are these tensions expressed, and what questions of legitimacy do they raise? To whom, ultimately, do landscapes belong? To those who shape their features day after day; to those who own the land; to those who administer it; to those who anticipate opportunities for investment and profit; to those who perceive or invent problems, and from there draw up projects for managing or "improving" living conditions (Li, 2007); to those who contemplate and visit them; or to the local, regional, national collective that consider them common heritage? And who benefits when all or part of a banal, everyday landscape permeating individual bodies and collective landmarks—the taskscape of T. Ingold (1993)—is transformed into a market resource?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            The second angle is to approach landscape as a resource for tourism development. The authors are particularly interested in the different logics of processes of tourism development, old or very recent, which may coexist within the same territory or succeed one other over time. These logics vary from those that are rather "top-down", driven at times by tourist demand and the large operators endeavoring to meet it, and sometimes by States themselves making tourism the vehicle of public policies often with mixed objectives (regional development, poverty reduction, but also the integration and control of rural populations), to logics that are more “bottom-up”, where it is the local actors who individually or collectively attempt to develop this sector. Particular attention will be given to the ways in which populations play central roles in these processes, and how they are brought in or, on the contrary, excluded. 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            Beyond analyzing the systems of actors at work and the forms taken by tourism development, most of the articles also address the question of the true weight of these local tourism sectors and their effectiveness in terms of territorial development, as well as the role of tourism in the differentiation of spaces on various scales. Does tourism, conceived here as a vehicle for integration into a real or perceived national community or into the globalized economy, elsewhere contribute to marginalization (Déry, 2007)?
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            A third approach seeks to understand the mechanisms that construct touristic imaginaries of landscapes, bearing in mind that these imaginaries vary by society and social group (Decroly, 2015). The articles in this issue are interested in the place of landscapes as tourist attractions and, beyond this, how the contemporary evolution of clienteles influences the development of tourism in these spaces, given the segmentation of traditional clienteles and the growing importance of Asian tourists (China) and domestic tourism (Sacareau <em>et al.</em>, 2015).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            A fourth approach entails exploring the impact of the presence of tourists, more or less intense and more or less permanent, on rural populations which experience both opportunities (activities, jobs, income…), but also constraints, particularly from regulations and use restrictions arising from from heritage development (Déry, Tremblay, 2009; Dérioz, 2011; Thibault, Bénos, 2017), where the “power of exclusion” indeed can become a double-edged sword (Hall <em>et al.</em>, 2011). The functions of affected territories may be transformed, possibly to the detriment of local (agri)cultures as, for example, pressures arise on the land from other uses, and new opportunities accelerate the abandonment or reorientation of production systems (Bachimon, 2013). The articles in this issue thus address the multiple territorial changes likely to accompany tourism development, especially those which leave their mark on the landscape. It is in this sense that, in certain cases, we speak of landscape "staging" or the construction of landscapes in function of tourism, as in the case of those operated as kitsch (article of Bachimon, Gauché, and Le). The landscape effects of certain phenomena, such as urbanization or the abandonment or modernization of agriculture, may alter the landscape resource on which tourism is based, compromising its development.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            A fifth entry entails interrogating representations of landscapes, inevitably plural, and the contemporary dynamics of territories in these marginal, rural spaces which are currently undergoing profound changes due to multiple political, socio-economic, and environmental factors. We can thus see congruencies and incongruencies between the present issues faced by these territories and the representations, at times fantasized, of these same spaces. This leads us to interrogate the sources of these imaginaries (literature, cinema, photography, tourist narratives, advertising, tourism promotion, etc.) and the way they are deployed and form synergies or tensions with the social, economic and environmental realities of the territories concerned, which they ultimately transform into new socio-cultural realities. It is thus this plurality of views, endogenous as well as exogenous, that is examined here in an attempt to grasp how they intersect or even hybridize, revealing the multiple stakes that crystalize over the landscape (Gauché, 2015).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            Finally, there is the question of landscapes as sites of mediation between local cultures and the global culture conveyed by tourists, especially if these landscapes are central to local cultures (McCaskill, Kempe ed., 1997)—sometimes at the cost of folklorization, identity assignments, or the "reinvention of tradition”. This is the sixth and last approach in this issue. Local cultures, whether ethnically, religious, socio-professionally or gender-based, paradoxically are weakened by their renown and may be doomed to disappear. This phenomenon, which is widespread, can lead to a rigidification of identity or, on the contrary, to a certain renunciation. In all cases, the relationship between landscapes and identities, whether intimate or weak, static or dynamic, appears significant to the authors who seek to understand why certain local identities are considered excellent generators and managers of the landscapes they want to conserve, while other autochthonous cultures are not. How then are the more or less ecological and landscaped images of local identities forged, and how are they instrumentalized, by both external and local actors seeking, in this way, a soft-power source of visibility, capital and autonomy (Landy <em>et al.</em>, 2017)?
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Bachimon, Ph. (2013), La vacance des lieux, Belin, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (2000), Médiance, de milieux en paysages, Belin, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Berque, A. (2007), « Cosmophanie et paysage moderne », in Bergé, A., Collot, M. (dir.), Paysage et modernité(s), Ousia, Bruxelles, pp. 42-65. </reference>
        <reference>Decroly, JM. (2015), Le tourisme comme expérience. Regards interdisciplinaires sur le vécu touristique, Presse de l’Université de Québec. </reference>
        <reference>Dérioz, P. (2012), L’apparence des choses. Analyser les paysages pour comprendre les systèmes territoriaux, Habilitation à Diriger des Recherches, E.N.S. de Lyon.</reference>
        <reference>Dérioz, P. (2011), « Les ambigüités de la patrimonialisation des paysages ‘naturels’ », in Patrimoines naturels, C. Bouisset et I. Degrémont (dir.), Sud-Ouest Européen, 2010, n° 30, pp. 19-36, available at : https://soe.revues.org/1220</reference>
        <reference>Déry, S. (2007), « Les parcs nationaux en Asie du Sud-Est, une manifestation de la transformation de l’État moderne. Le cas du parc national Cat Tien au Vietnam » Géocarrefour, 82(4), pp. 219-230, available at :</reference>
        <reference>http://geocarrefour.revues.org/index3322.html </reference>
        <reference>Déry, S. et Tremblay, M. (2009), « L’implantation des aires protégées au Vietnam : quels impacts pour les populations locales ? Une étude de cas dans la province de Lâm Dông », VertigO - la revue électronique en sciences de l’environnement, Vol. 8, N. 3, mis en ligne le 15 avril 2009, available at : http://vertigo.revues.org/index8059.html, DOI : https://doi.org/10.4000/vertigo.8059, (Consulté le 30 avril 2009).</reference>
        <reference>Ducourtieux, O., Visonnavong, P., Rossard, J. (2006), “Introducing Cash Crops in Shifting Cultivation Regions – The Experience with Cardamom in Laos”, Agroforestry Systems, Vol. 66, N. 1, pp. 65-76. </reference>
        <reference>Gauché, É. (2015). « Le paysage existe-t-il dans les pays du Sud ? Pistes de recherches sur l’institutionnalisation du paysage », VertigO - la revue électronique en sciences de l’environnement, Vol. 15 N. 1, available at : http://vertigo.revues.org/16009 DOI : 10.4000/vertigo.16009 </reference>
        <reference>Hall, D., Hirsch, P., Li, T. (2011), Powers of exclusion. Land dilemmas in Southeast Asia, University of Hawaii Press, Honolulu.</reference>
        <reference>Ingold, T. (1993), "The Temporality of the Landscape", World Archaeology, Vol. 25, N. 2, pp. 152-174. </reference>
        <reference>Landy, F., Belaidi, N., Gaudry Sada, K.H., 2017, « Les espaces protégés urbains, vecteurs de justice ou d’injustice pour les populations autochtones ? Les cas de Xochimilco et des parcs nationaux de Mumbai et du Cap/Urban Protected Areas: Forces of justice or injustice for Indigenous populations? The cases of Xochimilco and the national parks of Mumbai and Cape Town” », Justice spatiale | Spatial Justice, N. 11, available at : https://www.jssj.org/article/les-espaces-proteges-urbains-vecteurs-de-justice-ou-dinjustice-pour-les-populations-autochtones-les-cas-de-xochimilco-et-des-parcs-nationaux-de-mumbai-et-du-cap/ </reference>
        <reference>Li, T. (2007), The Will to Improve. Governmentality, Development, and the Practice of Politics, Duke University Press, Durham.</reference>
        <reference>Lifran, R., Oueslati, W. (2007), « Eléments d’économie du paysage », Économie rurale, N. 297-298 | 2007, pp. 85-98 available at : </reference>
        <reference>http://journals.openedition.org/economierurale/2031</reference>
        <reference>McCaskill, D., Kampe, K. (eds.) (1997), Development of Domestication? Indigenous Peoples of Southeast Asia, Silkworm Books, Chiang Mai. </reference>
        <reference>Poulaouec-Gonidec, P., Domon, G., Paquette, S. (2005), « Le paysage, un concept en débat », in P. Poulaouec-Gonidec, G. Domon et S. Paquette (dir.), Paysages en perspective, chap. 1, coll. Paramètres, Presses de l’Université de Montréal, pp. 19-44. </reference>
        <reference>Sacareau, I., Taunay, B., Peyvel, E. (2015), La mondialisation du tourisme. Les nouvelles frontières d’une pratique, PUR, Rennes.</reference>
        <reference>Thibault, B., Bénos, R. (coord.) (2017), Paysanneries et patrimonialisation dans les Suds. Ressources, conflits, arrangements, BAGF – Géographies, N. 2017-2, pp. 185-352. </reference>
        <reference>Toublanc, M. (2013), « Ressources paysagères entre héritage et projets. Introduction », in Y., Luginbhul et D., Terrasson (coord.), Paysage et développement durable, Quae ed., pp. 101-113. </reference>
    </bibliographie>
</article>