<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_PDML_7-104_Ts_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5276" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.5276</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="5266">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            Le Mardi Himal Trek (versant sud des Annapurnas, Népal) et les évolutions récentes des pratiques de trekking
        </original>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Dérioz" prenom="Pierre" email="pierre.derioz@univ-avignon.fr">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PDPBEG_9-57_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5062" lang="fr">Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux</publication>
                <publication id="fr_TTLHPD_36-132_Lm_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5093" lang="fr">La place des espaces ruraux périphériques dans la construction par et pour le tourisme de l’identité de la région de Dalat (Vietnam)</publication>
                <publication id="fr_PDPUPBML_26-131_Du_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5552" lang="fr">Développement d’un tourisme domestique en montagne à proximité des grandes villes du Népal : versant sud de l’Annapurna et Helambu </publication>
                <publication id="fr_PDML_6-108_Lg_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5266" lang="fr">Le Mardi Himal Trek (versant sud des Annapurnas, Népal) et les évolutions récentes des pratiques de trekking</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Associate Professor HDR, Avignon Université – UMR Espace-Dev 228 IRD – 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Létang" prenom="Mauve" email="mauveletang1@gmail.com">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PDML_6-108_Lg_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5266" lang="fr">Le Mardi Himal Trek (versant sud des Annapurnas, Népal) et les évolutions récentes des pratiques de trekking</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                PhD Student in Geography, Lettres Sorbonne Université ENeC (Espaces, Natures, Cultures) et CEH (Centre d’Études Himalayennes) - 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>The Mardi Himal Trek (south face of the Annapurnas, Nepal) and recent developments in trekking practices</titre>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            (Photo P. Dérioz - 28 April 2016, 9.16 am)
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            Upper view point, 4,200 m. This is not quite the final destination of the trek, which continues as far as Mardi Himal western base camp, from which it is possible to climb to the summit proper (5,587 m), a small antesummit of the Macchapucchre, and one of the trekking peaks open to trekkers with some mountaineering experience. However, the trail beyond this view point, marked by a sign, becomes more taxing and a lot of trekkers turn back here once they have taken time to enjoy the view. From west to east (left to right on the photo), the eye is drawn into a deep rift, in the bottom of which the Modi Khola flows, and towards the very popular trail leading to Annapurna base camp, wending its way into the heart of the central cirque of the Annapurna massif from which the river emerges. Completing the cirque on the southern side are Patal Hinchuli and Annapurna South (7,219 m) (not visible on the photo), which have accompanied trekkers for the entire ascent. To the north, Annapurna I remains hidden, but the ridge line over 7,000 m which connects it in the east to Annapurna III has a series of four major summits running from Khangsar Kang (7,485 m, in the west) to Ganggapurna (7,454 m, in the east). Closer, on the same ridge line as the trekkers, the already hazy distinctive “fishtail” peak of Macchapucchre (6,997 m) hides Annapurna III. Behind them, the mid-morning cloud fills the Mardi Khola valley and obscures the view of the south face of the massif (Annapurna II and IV, and Lamjung).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">A recently developed ancient route</section>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            The Mardi Himal trek follows the huge interfluve (<em>danda</em>) separating the Modi Khola and Mardi Khola valleys. It uses an ancient network of shepherds’ trails connecting clearings used for pasture opening onto slopes in a rhododendron forest (<em>kharka</em>), which then converge on the ridge path providing access to the high-altitude meadows (<em>bugyen</em>) grazed up to a height of 4,500 m once the winter snows have melted. Trekkers meet herds of sheep and buffalo along the way, and a few yaks at the upper edge of the forest (around 3,500 m). These trails were used in the early days by a few groups of trekkers, the first of whom made camp here long before the official “opening” of this new trekking route in 2012 under the aegis of the Pokhara branch of the Trekking Agencies Association of Nepal (TAAN) and the National Trust for Nature Conservation (NTNC), an NGO responsible for the Annapurna Conservation Area Project (ACAP), which has a para-administrative role in this huge protected zone. Some lodges built in the mountains to accommodate walkers have been in existence for approximately fifteen years and therefore pre-date marketing around this trek. The first lodge, Forest Camp, at approximately 2,500 m, dates from 2008, and was followed by two more in 2010. But publicity post-2012, and the fact that agencies in Pokhara and several western tour operators have added the Mardi Himal Trek to their brochures, have led to a gradual increase in visitors, and new accommodation (lodges) and basic catering facilities (tea houses) have been built. An intermediary stage, dubbed Middle Camp (3,250 m), sprang up in 2016 between Low Camp (2,980 m) and High Camp (3,580 m), the last group of lodges before the ascent to the upper view point and Mardi Himal base camp. A trail which opened in 2018 on the left side of the Mardi Khola now connects the village of Sidhing directly to High Camp via a new stage (Rest Camp, approximately 2,600 m) and a new hotel, which also opened in 2018.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">A diverse but short high mountain trek</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            Several factors explain the relative popularity of this “new” trekking route which is perfectly aligned with the current demand from customers for a powerful experience which does not compromise their safety or take up too much time. In this respect, the Mardi Himal trek is a route which is easily accessible by bus or car, and very close to Pokhara, the second largest town in Nepal (420,000 habitants in the urban area) and the regional tourism hub. Furthermore, it is very modular – a 5-day round trip for those in a hurry, it can also be easily incorporated into a more ambitious 8-10 day circuit on the south face of the Annapurnas by connecting up, for example, with the very popular “Annapurna Balcony” trek (also known as the Poon Hill trek). Lastly, it is considered to be a trek without any major difficulties, accessible to people who are not experienced trekkers while still offering a comprehensive and varied experience of mountain landscapes: terraced paddy fields and mountain villages (Sidhing, Landruk or Lwang, depending on the choice of route) at low level, followed by forest stages which are particularly pleasant in spring when the rhododendrons are in bloom, and rounding off on the ridge path with spectacular views over very high summits, which is exposed, but not difficult except in snow. Those pursuing the trek to the end (Mardi Himal base camp, 4,500 m), have to climb even higher than the “historic” Annapurna Base Camp trek. However, unlike this trek, Mardi Himal is now described as a trek which takes you “off the beaten track” as part of an attempt to diversify and repackage the trekking offer, thus making it possible to avoid the concentration of tourists found at Poon Hill, for example, and on sections of the route relatively accessible to vehicles, but shunned by trekkers, which have often replaced the old trails on more traditional itineraries. In the case of Mardi Himal, these routes have in fact reinforced the idea of proximity: since 2014 it has been possible to end the trek at Sidhing and return directly to Pokhara by jeep. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">A route on the boundary between different tourist areas</section>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            There are many types of stakeholder engaged in tourism development here, operating different approaches on different scales, in complex relationships of cooperation and competition. Looking beyond the coordination and communication role of organising bodies such as the NTNC on the one hand, which manages permits and collects fees from operators, and TAAN Pokhara on the other, which is a key link in the chain for promoting and coordinating the circuit, it is private entrepreneurs who are the true drivers behind the system at a local level. However, their strategies and activities are still part of a complex pattern of village, ethnic and family loyalties (Dérioz et al., 2017). In this respect, the Mardi Himal Trek is at the exact interface of two very different zones from a tourism perspective. Analysed by Isabelle Sacareau (1999) in the mid-1990s, tourism development stretches back many years on the Modi Khola side (to the west), an area where the ABC (Annapurna Base Camp) Trek and now the Annapurna Balcony trek attract some of the highest concentrations of trekkers in the whole country. On the eastern side, by contrast, the Mardi Khola valley offers slightly different and later forms of tourism development. There is more collective activity, with the rollout between 2007 and 2009 of a coordinated accommodation programme in the form of homestays connected to a network of trails (the Macchapucchre Model Trek), which meets the dual aim of fostering local development and more peaceful social relations following the end of the civil war (1996-2006) (Upadhayaya, 2013; Létang et al., 2017). Competition between the two valleys has long been reflected in the reluctance of Modi Khola operators to facilitate tourists’ ascent to Mardi Himal, even though some Modi Khola entrepreneurs have eventually established themselves there (Middle Camp). Although development has consolidated its overall appeal by enhancing the offering, competition between operators has increased onsite. The opening of alternative sections, such as the route between Sidhing and High Camp via Rest Camp, is characterised by interfamily rivalry in the various forms of accommodation developed in Sidhing (a homestay and two hotels) to attract the growing stream of tourists. Differences of opinion came to light between TAAN and NTNC (2016), when NTNC undertook a programme to mark trails, as trekking agencies believed that this encouraged independent tourism to the detriment of their own business practices.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Increased visitor numbers, with Nepalese nationals matching international tourists </section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            A survey of the most recent posts and blogs by western trekkers confirms the gradual surge in popularity of the Mardi Himal Trek, which still claims to be a hidden gem, although this is no longer the case. However, it is quite difficult to measure visitor numbers accurately even though it is in the middle of the ACAP, a protected area accessible only to holders of permits which are checked at the perimeter to allow the management body to monitor flows of people entering. The number of possible departure and arrival points for treks makes it difficult to identify trekkers who have chosen this route specifically (for some trekkers, for example, the Mardi Himal Trek is an extension of the ABC trek (on their return). Furthermore, only foreign tourists require a permit and are counted, whereas nationals can move freely. Based on estimates supplied by operators of footfall in their own establishments in 2016, the total flow was of the order of 1,500 trekkers per year in 2015-2016, but the number is now significantly higher and has probably doubled. In the high season (April-May and October-November), visitors are now advised to book places at one of the three High Camp lodges (which have a total capacity of about one hundred places). While tourism is very limited during the monsoon season (notably June-July), numbers are slightly higher in winter despite the fact that the route is significantly more dangerous beyond High Camp.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            Although it is not possible to be more precise, interviews with operators (and observations in the field) highlight the fact that Nepalese tourists matched international tourists, even before the earthquake in 2015 pushed them to prominence in the strategies devised to revive tourism. The emergence of thriving domestic tourism in Nepal since the civil war ended can also be observed in high mountain areas through one of the iconic practices of international tourism. The significant majority of homestay guests in the Mardi Khola valley are Nepalese. On the photo above, one of the two groups admiring the panorama is made up of Nepalese trekkers (right). They often carry less equipment and sometimes opt for faster treks: a return trip to the upper view point or up to base camp is often fitted into a weekend by riding up to Sidhing on motorbikes and spending a single night at a High Camp lodge.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Dérioz, P., Létang, M., Bachimon, P., Upadhayaya, P.K., Loireau, M., Le Noac’h, J. (2017), « Diversification touristique, démarches innovantes et changement social en versant sud des Annapurna. Quelle place pour les femmes ? », Les Carnets du Labex ITEM, Actes du colloque international : La montagne, territoire d’innovation, Grenoble, 11-13 janvier 2017, disponible sur : https://labexitem.hypotheses.org/486#more-486</reference>
        <reference>Létang, M., Dérioz, P., Le Noac’h, J. (2017), « Développement touristique, approches patrimoniales et arrangements sociaux en versant sud des Annapurna (Népal) », BAGF – Géographies, n° 2017-2, coord. par B. Thibaud, B. and Bénos, R. Paysanneries et patrimonialisation dans les Suds. Ressources, conflits, arrangements, pp. 306-329, disponible sur : https://journals.openedition.org/bagf/1475</reference>
        <reference>Sacareau, I. (1999), « Les transformations d’une haute montagne par le tourisme : le massif des Annapurna dans l’Himalaya du Népal », Annales de Géographie, n° 605, Armand Colin, pp. 21-45</reference>
        <reference>Upadhayaya, P.K. (2013), “Peace Sensitivity in Tourism codes of Conduct at Destination in Conflict: A Case Study of Partnership Actions in Pokhara, Western Nepal”, in Wohlmuther, C. and Wintersteiner, W. (Eds.), International Handbook on Tourism and Peace, Drava, Klagenfurt, pp. 230-246, available at: http://www.uni-klu.ac.at/frieden/downloads/International_Handbook_on_Tourism_and_Peace.pdf</reference>
    </bibliographie>
</article>