<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_SVP_42-88_Te_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3427" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.3427</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>15</numero>
        <annee>2019</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <traduction lang="ca" source="3443">Termacolores: Un projecte de turisme de benestar que té en compte la riquesa dels coneixements indígenes</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Velásquez Puerta" prenom="Sandra" email="svelasquezp@unal.edu.co">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="es_SVP_42-111_Ts_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3414" lang="es">Termacolores: Un proyecto de turismo de bienestar que tiene en cuenta la riqueza de los conocimientos indígenas</publication>
                <publication id="ca_SVP_42-104_Ts_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/3443" lang="ca">Termacolores: Un projecte de turisme de benestar que té en compte la riquesa dels coneixements indígenes</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Associate Professor, Department of Human Sciences. Faculty of Administration, National University of Colombia, Manizales campus. 170001 Manizales. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Termacolores: a wellness tourism project encompassing the wealth of indigenous knowledge</titre>
    <resume>
        Traditional knowledge is a differential factor for tourism wellness projects. Tourism dynamics change if an indigenous community values tradition above economic income. The Puracé indigenous reservation in Cauca, Colombia, requested research on traditional knowledge as part of the Termacolores hot spring project. This paper emphasises the interplay with Puracé locals through the participatory action research (PAR) method. The bibliographic review, workshops, and talks highlighted key factors for Termacolores, besides natural places or health benefits of hot springs, such as locals’ familiarity with cultural traditions, local food or plants, as well as bonds between young and older generations. Results of the research include an intangible heritage inventory, multimedia content and the creation of the Traditional Knowledge Custodians group.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Can indigenous knowledge be a key factor for wellness tourism in Puracé? Can a participatory action research method help an indigenous community recognise local culture? These were the initial research questions asked by Termacolores</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> project team of the National University of Colombia, Manizales campus.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This text has resulted from working with the Kokonuco indigenous community on the Puracé reservation in southern Colombia. The community asked the project for an action plan to improve their traditional knowledge. Therefore, an interdisciplinary team of professionals</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> used the participatory action research (PAR) method to create a project with three phases: identification, training of trainers and content production. Each phase focused on six themes of indigenous cosmogony: land, food, everyday practices, cultural and artistic expressions, history, and traditional medicine.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Understanding how the research unfolded involves recognising the context, method, results and conclusions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. Recognition of place (context)</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The research project took place in the Cauca Department in southern Colombia. Ethnic groups with differing worldviews, customs and ways of interacting with their environment live in this administrative area.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> The beauty of the landscapes, the friendliness of locals and the wealth of cultural traditions in Cauca contrast with conflicts over land control and drug trafficking. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Conflicts concern Afro-descendant, indigenous and </span>peasant <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">communities fighting for the land they lay claim to as a condition for ensuring their survival, the lack of economic alternatives in a department with natural resources but hardly any industry, and military strategies to combat insurgent groups and forcibly eradicate illicit crops (United Nations Development Programme, UNDP, 2014). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Kokonuco</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> community is one of the eight indigenous communities recognised in Cauca. These peoples are present in a territory spanning 24,462 hectares across three municipalities: Popayán, El Tambo and Puracé. Their population numbers approximately 6,767 people.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Of the three reservations forming the community, only Coconuco and Puracé</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> have hot springs on their land and both have been involved in conflicts with individuals and the State over land ownership. The first case was with trader Diego Angulo and the second with the State over Puracé National Natural Park as 3,413 hectares of the park overlap the indigenous reservation area (VerdadAbierta.com and Hacemos Memoria, 2017).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Coconuco’s hot springs are a tourist attraction. When the National Park was operating, Puracé’s hot springs received an influx of visitors. However, two situations have hindered tourism: the conflict between the community and the State over National Park land that led to the closure of the service, and armed conflict in the area. The inhabitants remember the guerrilla takeover by the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia (FARC) in 2001. This was a very significant event because of the death of student Jimmy </span>Chancagana, who had dreamed of becoming the town’s mayor. He went onto the streets with the Colombian flag and a sign saying ‘Peace’ during the takeover, which spurred the population into action and resulted in the guerrillas withdrawing<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Holguín, 2012)</span>.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. Starting point, the loss of ancestral knowledge</section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although traditional knowledge has been protected by UNESCO, debate continues on its origin and effectiveness in contemporary times. At the World Conference on Science for the Twenty-first Century:</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">a New Commitment, organised by UNESCO in Budapest, traditional knowledge was specified as a cumulative body of knowledge, know-how, practices and representations that have long histories due to interaction with the natural environment. It is a cultural complex that encompasses understandings, interpretations and meanings of language systems, resource use practices, rituals, spirituality and worldview </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(UNESCO, 2002)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Despite UNESCO’s recognition, there are tensions between Western and ancestral knowledge. The former needs to be written down and the process is individual, while the latter revolves around the spoken word and learning occurs collectively with the older generation conveying their knowledge to younger people (Álvarez Echavarría, 2007).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Colombian Constitution also recognises the characteristics of indigenous communities based on their identity, their languages, legislative autonomy and the exploitation of resources on their lands. Indigenous authorities can exercise jurisdictional functions within their territory and conform to their own rules and procedures, provided they do not contradict the Constitution</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Constitutional Court and High Council of the Judiciary, 2016)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Ministry of Culture and the Ministry of Commerce, Industry and Tourism of Colombia, in line with the position of UNESCO and the Constitution, created the</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Cultural Tourism Policy </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">with the aim of promoting the country’s cultural tourism and encouraging nationals and foreigners to discover and leverage Colombia’s customs and tangible and intangible heritage to benefit communities. It also promotes the sustainability of cultural and tourism sectors (Ministry of Commerce, Industry and Tourism and Ministry of Culture, 2007). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In Colombia, traditional knowledge</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> has multiple expressions among indigenous communities, people of African descent and due to miscegenation and hybridity resulting from colonisation processes and interaction with </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">peasants</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> The knowledge processes of these population identities are constantly changing because of the relationships between them and situations outside the communities such as technology, training processes, proximity to cities and other reasons. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, conservation, activism and change in the communities depends on a vision for development. Far from Eurocentric power structures or those inspired by northern countries, development needs to be understood on the basis of Latin American or African realities, contexts where the imposed model is resisted and historical moments overlap. Arturo Escobar’s academic insights focus on contradictions arising from having an economic approach to development. In Latin American contexts, historical moments occur without the need for a linear process. This has been confirmed by theorists such as Jesús Martin Barbero, José Joaquín Brunner and Néstor García Canclini for whom historical discontinuities in Latin America include processes related to identities, cultural industries, cultural consumption, communities’ cultural practices and their relationship with technologies. According to these authors, tensions can be observed between the national identity fostered by the modern world and identities found in national territories (Martin Barbero, 2008).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">As far as indigenous communities are concerned, the concept of development is part of their worldview and forms the basis of social practice integrating political, economic, social, cultural and religious structures. That is why cooperation and communitarianism are fundamental processes and why indigenous peoples resist Western models </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Batzin, 2005, p. 7)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">For indigenous peoples, understanding development is related to the concepts of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">buen vivir</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (good living) or </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">bien vivir</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (well living). Both terms highlight resistance to the coloniality of power that has been imposed on them. </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Buen vivir</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> is a concept open to debate and dependent on populations’ everyday social practices. It involves the equality of heterogeneous and diverse individuals, reciprocity among groups and individuals, equal redistribution of resources and a tendency to form community associations</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Quijano, 2012)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Besides </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">buen vivir</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the indigenous communities use the Life Plan, a document created with the community, to analyse and plan action projects for their territory. In the case of the Kokonucos, their 2011–2013 Life Plan illustrates that a lack of external awareness of the community’s traditional knowledge is a problem, which is why they want to produce ecotourism and ethno-tourism plans and programmes (Genaro Sánchez Cabildo Association, traditional authority of the ancestral lands of the Kokonuco people, n.d.)</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourism business presents several problems where indigenous communities are concerned: conflict between interests arising from enhancing and managing heritage and their relationship with local interests; the commodification of culture, which involves reworking folkloric and ancestral traits for tourism consumption; and the inequality a tourism project can cause (Impemba, M., Maragliano, G. and Valverde, S., 2015).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A quote from Hallowell, cf. Ashley (1968) cited by Ascanio demonstrates this tension:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. Methodology</section>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Our work with the community used the participatory action research (PAR) approach.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> This method was chosen to reflect Latin American realities as it recognises people’s knowledge without distinction and allows them to actively participate in the process by contributing to the solution based on their reality and the knowledge they have of it. It differs from positivism by ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">using other strategies, paradigms and processes ... [that are] less rigid, more spontaneous and more recursive’</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Murcia Florián, 1997, p. 10)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and that create a closer link with the community, empower individuals during the research and intervention process to achieve more transformation of the cultural reality. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In PAR, the community adopts a leading role throughout the process. It is the community that has to identify the problems and their solutions while the academic researchers’ role consists of facilitating and accompanying these processes. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although the PAR may use traditional research techniques, other creative and innovative options are implemented with an emphasis on qualitative and phenomenological data such as sociocultural animation, artistic expressions and traditional games. According to Jorge Murcia Florián, the PAR ‘lays less emphasis on “scientific” knowledge and instead favours “practical” knowledge stemming from the community’ </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Murcia Florián, 1997, p. 9)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To sum up, action research allows the community to improve knowledge of its reality, create awareness of social, cultural, political and economic interrelations and stimulate organisation and solidarity to achieve a greater degree of intervention in development and structural change processes </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Murcia Florián, 1997, p. 46)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Next, we focus on working with the community, a process that was implemented in two phases. An inventory of traditional knowledge was produced in the first. Participation, feedback and validation of the information obtained were crucial in this stage. In the second phase, emphasis was placed on our intervention in the community’s cultural reality by establishing a group of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">comuneros</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> responsible for leveraging and disseminating the knowledge obtained in the first phase. Learning sessions were also held to enable them to promote their territory in the future.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The team comprised researchers, teachers from Puracé’s educational institutions, people from the community interested in participating, and traditional knowledge holders.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> The latter’s presence resulted in contribution and adjustments to the methodological process and to the work content of the traditional knowledge group.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn13" id="bodyftn13">13</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">There was a major fieldwork element to the research, which built the trust that was needed with Puracé reservation inhabitants, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">comuneros</span></em><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and the cabildo</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> authorities. This proximity allowed us to make an inventory of knowledge, generate knowledge of daily practices, leaderships and identify mechanisms for forming the group of custodians,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> the people who could be trainers and content producers.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Playful activities, oral sessions and feedback processes were crucial elements in designing and expanding the method. Work performed by cultural management, communication and tourism professionals focused on workshops and participatory training processes. The academics sought to share in the daily life of Puracé’s inhabitants to identify knowledge. Feedback meetings and fun workshops took place with children, young people and adults to facilitate access to information, promote recognition of tourism opportunities in Puracé and foster the formation of the Traditional Knowledge Custodians group.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. Process and results: document search, inventory, training and production</section>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The research began with a process of approaching the cabildo authorities and the Assembly</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn17" id="bodyftn17">17</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> to present the study’s objective and reach the first agreements. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Using the participatory method was agreed, whereby people learn by doing, prioritising experience, collective processes, recreation and the dissemination of knowledge, all characteristics of learning processes in indigenous communities </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Álvarez Echavarría, 2007, p. 121)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The documentary process to identify publications on the Kokonuco and seek similar experiences began at the same time as the fieldwork with the community. For the former, we found research by anthropologist </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Franz Xaver Faust on the worldview and architecture of the Kokonucos and Yanaconas and on ethnobotany,</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and for the latter, we found the inventory of material heritage produced by the community with the Sena (Colombian National Learning Service), which has not been published. We also studied documents that, although they are not about the Kokonucos, refer to the knowledge of indigenous communities, such as a discussion on the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">chagra </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Cabrera, 2004) or bartering (Cadena and Muñoz, 2007).</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn19" id="bodyftn19">19</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Cases of leveraging heritage were studied in the experiences: in Colombia, the Coffee Cultural Landscape and the Checua settlement in Nemocón, and in Peru, the archaeological site Huaycán Cieneguilla. The value of training and communication processes was understood at these places. In the Coffee Cultural Landscape, they worked with children through play, with young people through the use of technologies and with adults through exploring identity vis-à-vis the landscape for promotion among traders and entrepreneurs (Gómez Alzate, A., 2015). In Nemocón, publications were produced and a museum was created. ‘Checua: Our Cultural and Ecological Traveller’ was a traveller’s notebook that each child took home so that their parents, grandparents and relatives could complete the topics on the settlement and the municipality. This notebook was passed on from one family to the next in the area so that they could have the opportunity to read the information and add to it. In addition to the notebook, a magazine with two sections was published: </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Huellas de los antepasados </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Ancestors’ Footprints), which explains aspects about the landscape and ancient human groups in the region; and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Cuentan nuestros mayores </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Told by Our Elders), which relates dialogues between older and younger generations (Groot, A., 2014).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">At Huaycán Cieneguilla, the leveraging processes took the form of educational workshops and a forum cinema for children and young people. Another strategy was the Heritage Watch Group pilot programme, which was set up to protect and disseminate natural cultural heritage. Finally, the Cultural Heritage Week was held to provide information on the cultural assets of the archaeological site and Qhapaq Ñan to the inhabitants surrounding the monument (Chuquipoma Moreno, 2015).</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn20" id="bodyftn20">20</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Besides the documents consulted, the community’s role in collating traditional knowledge was established through workshops with sociocultural animation techniques. Thus, information was collected on: cultural practices, recipes, myths, stories, traditional medicine, daily life and remembrance. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Fieldwork and published information were consolidated in the traditional knowledge inventory, which is the intangible heritage of the Puracé reservation. The inventory document made it possible to identify, recognise and recover words in the Kokonuco language, to discover various versions of myths and to attach importance to daily practices lost as a result of current living conditions. One example is the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">tulpa</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (a wood stove consisting of three stones around which the community gathers to listen to the experiences and advice of its elders). This practice has been lost due to using gas and electricity for cooking.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">By exchanging knowledge within the community they rediscovered recipes made with local agricultural produce, such as </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ollucos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and links with other indigenous communities based on ancestral knowledge. Corn, an essential crop for indigenous communities in Latin America with many uses and meanings, is one example. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">People were reluctant to give information about traditional medicine at the beginning;</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn21" id="bodyftn21">21</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> however, contact with them in the field gradually built enough trust for them to share knowledge on this subject. The PAR method was key to gaining the community’s trust in this respect.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Once information on the knowledge had been obtained, an interactive exhibition was held with the schoolchildren, initially in a closed space, and then with the entire community. The events made it possible to share the information, correct it and receive new contributions. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In the second phase—training trainers and producing contents—the Traditional Knowledge Custodians group was set up with the name chosen consistent with the community’s Seed Custodians group.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn22" id="bodyftn22">22</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Rather than just being an indigenous guardian, the custodians group was created to safeguard intangible heritage in the community and tell future Puracé tourists about it.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With the Traditional Knowledge Custodians group</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn23" id="bodyftn23">23</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> training focused on learning and generating community and digital</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn24" id="bodyftn24">24</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> communication content to spread their knowledge through ICT. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The result of the community communication was a mural that gives an account of the myths, natural attractions, daily practices, moon phases and other aspects of the territory. Producing the mural was a participatory process as the community’s custodians and other members defined which elements to incorporate into it. The sketch was submitted for approval to the cabildo authorities and it was then implemented. In digital communication the custodians made a video to learn about audiovisual production and to help people discover Puracé’s culture and natural attractions. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Besides the mural and video, there was an exhibition of the profiles</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn25" id="bodyftn25">25</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of people that have worked on traditional knowledge aspects. The cabildo, the custodians and the project researchers decided who would be in the exhibition. For all of them, there was a presentation of their contributions to the community based on their leadership and their predictions for Puracé’s future. Examples of the profiles are: midwives, seed custodians and people recognised for leadership in social processes.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Two arts training workshops were also held: one on pinhole cameras</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn26" id="bodyftn26">26</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and the other on acrylic painting. The first workshop taught attendees how to build the camera, how to develop black and white photographs and took them on a tour of Puracé to photograph it. In the second workshop, the participants took inspiration from culture and landscape for their paintings. The result of both workshops will be permanently exhibited in the hot spring infrastructure that will be put into operation.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The research process of the Traditional Knowledge Area was a fundamental part of the Termacolores project. The inventory information was used for communication pieces, the marketing plan and it was also shared with the infrastructure team to study the possibility of including the cultural characteristics the community had identified into the design. The work on knowledge led to the need for training in cultural entrepreneurship so that the community could consolidate their offer of goods and services for tourists based on their traditional knowledge. Consequently, community members who perform a traditional activity such as weaving, gardening and food preparation can implement entrepreneurial ideas as part of the tourism project. This will define a community promoting its culture and offering services to visitors.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusions </section>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Problematising the loss of traditional knowledge in social groups is a research horizon that enhances diverse dialogue, ranging from individual identity to the traits that form a given territory’s collective.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The community’s knowledge, intangible heritage and hot spring wellness tourism proposal need to be valued as equally important. The traditional knowledge of the Kokonuco community is the differential factor in the Termacolores project. Besides the hot springs and the Páramo landscapes, tourism in this territory must also consider the community’s other attributes, such as traditions and rituals linked to its sacred places.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">A value proposition for cultural and heritage tourism that is community-friendly and sustainable can be based on the knowledge of Puracé’s inhabitants. Many places with hot springs offer wellness tourism, but in Puracé, it is the culture that makes the difference. Traditional knowledge can be promoted so that their own people and outsiders can understand the indigenous way of thinking in which people are part of nature.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn27" id="bodyftn27">27</a>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The indigenous community is an important asset for the Termacolores project; however, the </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">campesinos</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> living in the territory will also need to be involved. Promoting knowledge exchange between both population groups is vital.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The process of regaining traditional knowledge is not restricted to an intervention run by outsiders and the community and lasting for a limited period. It must be an ongoing process that allows the Kokonuco to experience their culture, convey it to new generations and experience it in their daily lives so that it can be known, recognised and valued by their own and other people.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The permanence of the leveraging process relies on community leadership, in other words for the Kokonucos living in Puracé to feel empowered to work for their own culture. To this end, the Traditional Knowledge Custodians are a group of people responsible for proposing, generating and leading processes to help the community discover its traditional knowledge and practices. This group needs cabildo support so it can be recognised and perform its functions.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Young Puracé people are talented and motivated. It is important for the reservation to acknowledge them and to let them participate actively in their territory. Elders in indigenous communities are those who respect and know their culture. An intergenerational dialogue is needed to tap into the experience of the traditional knowledge holders and young people’s knowledge to consolidate intangible heritage in the community.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Artistic expressions are an important educational tool for mobilising, boosting, motivating and empowering the community as far as traditional culture is concerned through learning, doing and/or artistic appreciation. The arts are a way to assertively approach a range of audiences from children to community elders and including future tourists.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Tourism in a territory impacted by conflict, as Puracé was, means that the community can recognise its culture’s potential and organise itself to create a proposal to understand the wealth of its knowledge and its position in the human-land relationship. Tourism based on this perspective contributes to bolstering the Kokonuco people and recognising indigenous communities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Research in indigenous communities involves respecting and recognising the knowledge and way of life of people whose relationship with their environment differs from that of the West. The process needs to be participatory with ongoing presentation of the results. These are communities that have often been studied but rarely receive feedback on the information they provide to academia or other sectors such as the economy or local authorities.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Álvarez, N. (2007), ‘Conocimientos indígenas y procesos de apropiación’, Revista Educación y Pedagogía, No. 49, pp. 119–128.</reference>
        <reference>Ascanio, A. (2004), ‘Las contradicciones del turismo cultural, la economía y la política’, PASOS. Revista de Turismo y Patrimonio, No. 1, 139–143. Retrieved from: http://www.redalyc.org/articulo.oa?id=88120111 (Consulted: 20 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Asociación de Cabildos Genaro Sánchez, Autoridad Tradicional de los territorios ancestrales del pueblo Kokonuco, (n.d.), ‘Plan de Salvaguarda Étnico Pueblo Indígena Kokonuco “PSEPINK” 2011–2013’, Retrieved from: http://observatorioetnicocecoin.org.co/cecoin/files/P_S%20Kokonuco.pdf (Consulted: 12 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Batzin, C. (2005), Desarrollo humano y los pueblos indígenas, CEPAL, Santiago de Chile.</reference>
        <reference>Cabrera, E. (2004), ‘El Agroecosistema “Chagra” entre los Indígenas del Amazonas’, Retrieved from: http://vip.ucaldas.edu.co/lunazul/downloads/Lunazul19_2.pdf (Consulted: 11 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Cadena, O.L. and Muñoz, M. (2007), ‘El Trueque en el Cauca: ¿Es un Sistema Alternativo Frente a las Políticas de Globalización? Hacia una mirada desde lo político–económico’, Facultad de Ciencias Contables, Económicas y Administrativas, Universidad del Cauca, Revista PorikAn, No. 12, pp. 103–122.</reference>
        <reference>Cerillos, M. (1997), ‘I Premio Somos Patrimonio. Convenio Andrés Bello’. Retrieved from: http://www.convenioandresbello.org/somos_patrimonio/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/apropiacion.pdf (Consulted: 12 December 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Chuquipoma Moreno, P. (2015), ‘Proceso de apropiación social del patrimonio: el caso del centro poblado rural Huaycán de Cieneguilla’, Repositorio institucional Ministerio de Cultura. Retrieved from: http://repositorio.cultura.gob.pe/handle/CULTURA/278 (Consulted: 6 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Corte Constitucional and Consejo Superior de la Judicatura, (2016), ‘Constitución Política de Colombia’, Centro de Documentación Judicial-CENDOJ. Biblioteca Enrique Low Murtra-BELM, Retrieved from: http://www.corteconstitucional.gov.co/inicio/Constitucion%20politica%20de%20Colombia.pdf (Consulted: 23 June 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Defensoría del Pueblo (2014), ‘Jurisdicción Especial Indígena’, Retrieved from: http://www.defensoria.gov.co/public/pdf/04/boletinNr6JurisdiccionEspecialIndigena.pdf (Consulted: 12 June 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Faust-Franz, X. (1988), Etnobotánica de Puracé, Colombia-búsqueda de sistemas clasificatorios funcionales, s.e., Popayán.</reference>
        <reference>Faust-Franz, X. (2004), ‘La Cosmovisión de los Coconucos y los Yanaconas en su Arquitectura’, Boletín de Antropología Universidad de Antioquia, Vol. 18 No. 35, pp. 350–360.</reference>
        <reference>Galeano, M. (2012), Políticas ambientales de los indígenas Kokonucos del Resguardo de Puracé, Departamento del Cauca, Desde 1974 hasta el 2011: una aproximación desde el enfoque interdisciplinario (Trabajo de grado para obtener el título de Magister en Gestión Ambiental), Bogotá, Pontificia Universidad Javeriana. </reference>
        <reference>Gómez Alzate, A. (2015), ‘Talleres comunitarios para la apropiación social del patrimonio en el Paisaje Cultural Cafetero, como estrategia para un modelo de diseño ecoeficiente’, Dearq No. 16, pp. 134–145. Retrieved from: http://dx.doi.org/10.18389/dearq16.2015.09 (Consulted: 1 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Groot, A. (2014), ‘Apropiación social del patrimonio arqueológico del municipio de Nemocón, Cundinamarca: un camino entre la ciencia, la sociedad y la política’, Boletín de historia y Antiguedades, No. 101, Retrieved from: https://dialnet.unirioja.es/servlet/articulo?codigo=5572925 (Consulted: 7 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Holguin, H. (2012), ‘Jimmy, el indígena que enfrentó a las Farc’. El Espectador. Retrieved from: https://www.elespectador.com/cronicas/jimmy-el-indigena-enfrento-farc-articulo-393267 (Consulted: 10 December 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Impemba, M., Maragliano, G., and Valverde, S. (2015), ‘Expansionismo turístico, poblaciones indígenas Mapuche y territorios en conflicto en Neuquén, Argentina’, Revista Pasos, Revista de Turismo y Patrimonio Cultural, Vol. 13 No. 2, Special Issue, pp. 395–410. Retrieved: file:///C:/Users/Usuario/Downloads/PS0213_9%20(2).pdf (Consulted: 8 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Martin Barbero, J. (1995), ‘Posmodernidad, modernidades-discursos sobre la crisis y la diferencia’, INTERCOM. Rev. BRAS. De Com. Vol. XVIII No. 2, Retrieved from: https://www.insumisos.com/lecturasinsumisas/MODERNIDAD_posmodernidad%20y%20Modernidades.pdf (Consulted: 15 March 2016).</reference>
        <reference>Ministerio de Comercio, Industria y Turismo and Ministerio de Cultura, (2007), Política de turismo cultural: Identidad y desarrollo competitivo del patrimonio. Retrieved from: https://fontur.com.co/aym_document/aym_normatividad/2007/POLITICA_DE_TURISMO_CULTURAL.pdf (Consulted: 16 June 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Ministerio del Interior, (2013). Definiciones. Cabildo. Retrieved from: https://www.mininterior.gov.co/content/cabildo-indigena (Consulted: 21 October 2019)</reference>
        <reference>Murcia Florian, L. (1997), Investigación para cambiar, un enfoque sobre la investigación acción participante, Cooperativa editorial Magisterio, Bogotá.</reference>
        <reference>Pérez Orozco, C.E. (2015), ‘Diálogo de saberes en el sistema de educación indígena propio de Colombia: hermenéutica contra inconmensurabilidad’, Revista Cuadernos de Filosofía Latinoamericana Vol. 36 No. 113, pp. 61–82. Retrieved from: http://revistas.usta.edu.co/index.php/cfla/article/view/2256/2584 (Consulted: 13 May 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Programa de Naciones Unidas, PNUD (2014), Cauca: Análisis de conflictividades y construcción de paz, Retrieved from: http://www.co.undp.org/content/colombia/es/home/library/crisis_prevention_and_recovery/cauca--analisis-de-conflictividades-y-construccion-de-paz.html (Consulted: 5 July 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Quijano, A. (2012), ‘2. Pensamientos y prácticas de(s)/coloniales. “Bien vivir”: entre el “desarrollo” y la des/colonialidad del poder’, Revista Viento Sur No. 122, pp. 46–56. Retrieved from: https://www.vientosur.info/IMG/pdf/VS122_A_Quijano_Bienvivir---.pdf (Consulted: 20 May 2017).</reference>
        <reference>Sistema Nacional de Información Cultural, (n.d.), Colombia cultural, población Cauca. Retrieved from: http://www.sinic.gov.co/SINIC/ColombiaCultural/ColCulturalBusca.aspx?AREID=3andSECID=8andIdDep=19andCOLTEM=216 (Consulted: 22 March 2017).</reference>
        <reference>UNESCO (2002), International Council for Science. Science and Traditional Knowledge: Report from the ISCU Group on Science and Traditional Knowledge, Retrieved from: https://www.academia.edu/6566405/_co-author_Science_and_Tradtional_Knowledge_Report_from_the_ICSU_Study_Group_on_Science_and_Traditional_Knowledge_2002_ (Consulted: 8 June 2017).</reference>
        <reference>VerdadAbierta.com and Hacemos Memoria (2017), Disputa en tierras de Puracé: la visión de dos mundos que no se encuentran, Retrieved from: http://www.verdadabierta.com/lucha-por-la-tierra/6851-disputa-de-tierras-en-purace-la-vision-de-dos-mundos-que-no-se-encuentran(Consulted: 5 January 2018).</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">In the National Planning Department the project title is: ‘Development of a technological environment for Termacolores on the Puracé indigenous reservation for research and innovation in the use of hot springs, mineral water and natural sulphur to boost wellness tourism in the Cauca Department’. The research was funded by the National Royalties System in Colombia. The project has been named "Termacolores" because of the variety of colors in purace´s hot springs. For further information, please consult the website www.quilliparza.com</note>
        <note id="2">The work team comprised cultural and communication managers Tatiana Grisales, Luis Miguel Hurtado and Fredy Antonio Rincón and adviser Fabiola Ortegón, a specialist in rural tourism and cultural management with an emphasis on cultural planning and policies. Sandra Velásquez, the author of this article, coordinated the research team.</note>
        <note id="3">According to the Cultural Information System of the Ministry of Culture: ‘Cauca is one of the most geographically, socially and culturally diverse departments. It has several climates, from the páramo climate of Valencia to the temperate climate of the Pacific coast or the Patía Valley. ... Its ethnic variety is also important since indigenous, black and multiracial people live here resulting in a huge diversity of artistic and cultural expressions.’ (Colombian Cultural Information System, n.d.). For further information, please consult the website http://www.sinic.gov.co/SINIC/ColombiaCultural/</note>
        <note id="4">Kokonuco is written with two ks when it refers to the people but with cs when it refers to the place Coconuco. However, it is sometimes not written as explained above in publications on the community.</note>
        <note id="5">For further information on the cultural characteristics of indigenous communities, visit the ONIC (Indigenous Organisation of Colombia) website: https://www.onic.org.co/.</note>
        <note id="6">6Coconuco and Puracé are the names of the reservations. Puracé is named after the volcano in the area.</note>
        <note id="7">The digital version of the newspaper EL ESPECTADOR of 19 December 2012 is recommended for further information.</note>
        <note id="8">Besides traditional knowledge it can also be referred to as ancestral knowledge or indigenous knowledge. </note>
        <note id="9">The three population groups, indigenous people, people of African descent and campesinos, have knowledge that connects their relationship to the territory. The 1991 reformed Constitution recognises special rights and jurisdictions for indigenous people and people of African descent in Colombia because it specifies that their cultural identity encompasses land and knowledge characteristics that help them survive as a community.</note>
        <note id="10">It is important to note that the buen vivir concept is shared by the indigenous peoples of Andean countries and the Kokonucos. For further information, see the website of the Consejo Regional Indígena del Cauca (CRIC, Indigenous Regional Council of Cauca): https://www.cric-colombia.org/portal/.</note>
        <note id="11">The participatory action research approach arose in the 1970s as a result of critical reflection on classic research methods. It was preceded by action research devised by Kurt Lewin in 1944. In Latin America, it is related to Paulo Freire’s proposals and his book Pedagogy of the Oppressed. In Colombia, Orlando Fals Borda was one of this method’s promoters and pioneers.</note>
        <note id="12">The traditional knowledge holders or community elders are people whose knowledge guides the community. The elders are respected because they have accumulated knowledge that is the result of their experience over the years.</note>
        <note id="13">The group named “Traditional Knowledge Area” refers to the research objective and it has nothing to do with a physical space, however, the group is framed in Termacolores project</note>
        <note id="14">A distinction is made between the inhabitants and the comuneros because the former may not belong to the community, such as outsider teachers, while the latter are the indigenous people who are part of the reservations. The comuneros form the community, elect the cabildo authorities and take decisions in the Assembly. Comuneros are registered as indigenous people in the cabildos.</note>
        <note id="15">“Cabildo is a public entity composed by members of an indigenous community, who are elected and recognized for a traditional socio-political organization. Their functions are: represent the community in legal terms, exercise authority and carry out the activities attributed by law. Its uses, customs and the internal regulations of each community” (Ministerio del Interior, 2013). </note>
        <note id="16">The Traditional Knowledge Custodians group was one of the methodological strategies that emerged during the research process. The cabildo authorities and stakeholders interested in the workshops formed the group of custodians to promote knowledge in the community. They chose this name because custodians care and protect. Within this group, trainers were trained in topics such as cultural management, community and digital communication and guidance.</note>
        <note id="17">The Assembly is a company of persons gathered for deliberation and legislation, the comuneros collectively decide for the whole community.</note>
        <note id="18">Consult the bibliography for further information</note>
        <note id="19">The chagra is an indigenous crop-growing area. It is a production system shared by several communities in the Andes (Chile, Colombia, Venezuela and Ecuador) that is closely linked to these cultures’ worldview. Similarly, bartering is an alternative economic system, an ancestral practice of exchanging goods and services.</note>
        <note id="20">The Qhapaq Ñan monument is the most extensive Inca construction. In Quechua its name means ‘royal road’. </note>
        <note id="21">The initial idea for this topic was a workshop method. However, it did not work because traditional medicine is related to spirituality and not all the community possesses these practices. It was during contact with researchers in other everyday spaces, such as weaving or in individual talks and during research conducted by community members that information about traditional medicine was shared.</note>
        <note id="22">The Seed Custodians group was an initiative of the cabildo authorities and the elders. The aim of this initiative is to look after seeds, pass on knowledge to children and young people and consolidate food sovereignty. The Seed Custodians group is formed by cabildo comuneros.</note>
        <note id="23">The community decided the name “Traditional Knowledge Custodians” for the group of promoters, who were trained in digital and community communication and cultural management as part of the research project. The name is similar to the seed custodians, like them, this group seeks to preserve and promote community’s knowledge. As custodians, they care and protect.</note>
        <note id="24">Digital communication takes advantage of web environments to create information and communication processes. It was decided that this form of communication was important for the project to promote the community’s knowledge beyond its territory, because this is a way to attract young people and work intergenerationally with elders.</note>
        <note id="25">Profiles are a journalistic genre that seeks to highlight people’s attributes using professional or personal traits. The exhibition represented public recognition of the leaders who have contributed to the culture of the Kokonuco community through traditional medicine, cabildo leadership and training processes.</note>
        <note id="26">The pinhole camera is an artisan system for taking photographs. Instead of using lenses it has a pinhole-sized aperture. Light enters through the aperture and the image is formed on the photographic paper inside the previously sealed box.</note>
        <note id="27">Indigenous communities are based on people’s wellbeing and their relationship with other elements of nature and the cosmos. It is a comprehensive approach to life that includes spiritual and material aspects and establishes a harmonious relationship with the land (Batzin, 2005).</note>
    </notes>
</article>