<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_SPP_28-46_Cs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4129" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.4129</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>16</numero>
        <annee>2019</annee>
    </meta>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Pakan" prenom="Sarani Pitor" email="saranipitor26@ugm.ac.id">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_SPP_28-79_Ls_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4156" lang="fr">« L’Autre » peut-il invertir le cadrage dans le champ des études touristiques ?</publication>
                <publication id="pt_SPP_28-48_Oo_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/4179" lang="pt">O "Outro" pode retornar aos estudos do turismo? </publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Gadjah Mada University, Indonesia, mail : 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Can the ‘Other’ Frame Back in Tourism Studies?</titre>
    <sousTitre>Experimenting to Respond in an Asymmetrical Dialogue</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        This essay began with the confusion and question about the very rare presence of non-Western tourist in the analysis of tourism. Then, I experimented to respond to such rarity by showcasing the photographs of Indonesian students-cum-tourists in the West. This essay is basically a reflection on my own experiment to respond to the Western-biased, Eurocentric, and colonial knowledge production in tourism studies. I found myself, who initially aimed to offer reverse South-to-North tourist/photographic framings, trapped in the question concerning whether non-Western tourism researchers are really able and need to frame back and talk back in academia. While the experiment itself might not be able to seriously challenge the Eurocentric knowledge production in tourism studies, I found it useful as a pedagogy of self-reflection through which non-Western tourism researcher, like me, can resituate her/his postcolonial being, thinking, and sensing and be an initial seed of future decolonial praxis.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">I. Setting off</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It was autumn in Wageningen, circa November 2016, when I and other students were sitting in the class of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Sustainable Development </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and watching a documentary </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Framing the Other</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Kok and Timmers, 2011). The film was made by our seniors, two alumni of MSc </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Leisure, Tourism and Environment</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> at Wageningen University, as a part of their master’s thesis. It is basically about the encounter between Mursi tribe and Western visitors in a typical tourist setting and showing how </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Dutch tourists traveled far to Ethiopia to see and photograph the ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">unusually adorned natives</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’, as Mursi women ‘</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">are known for placing large plates in their lower lips and wearing enormous, richly decorated earrings</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">’ (Synopsis, n.d.). Watching the film somehow reminded me of my late father and the place where he came from, Tana Toraja. In the context of tourism, either in commercial or academic settings, it has been long regarded as a place lived by people with an ‘exotic’ culture, especially its ‘unique’ death ceremony, valuable to be consumed by (inter)national tourists or studied by Western tourism researchers. For sure, I frequently heard the amazement of people when I told them that I have a (half) Torajan origin. “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Ah, the one with cave tombs! Will you also be buried inside the cave?</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” they often said. I hence could almost slightly imagine being the Mursi woman captured in (and off) the documentary.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The documentary can actually be representative to many other accounts that record (either critically or not) the ways Western tourists come, see, and frame non-Western places, people, and cultures. For instance, an academic article with the same title, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Framing the Other</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Snee, 2013), recounts how the overseas gap year travels of young Brits often reproduce and reinforce the already established discourse of “exotic Other”. Furthermore, by investigating photographs taken by Western students who visited various non-Western countries, Caton and Santos (2008) conclude that the taken photographs saliently reproduce the colonialist/orientalist representational discourse on ‘the Other’ as traditional, peripheral, and lazy. I slowly began wondering: where are the opposite accounts, those telling about the ways non-Western tourists come, see, and photograph Western places, people, and cultures? Are tourists always Western? If so, who am I when I tour the European cities during my study breaks?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Seemingly I found the response of my questions through Facebook, where I virtually befriend with many other Indonesians studying in the so-called Western countries (US, UK, The Netherlands, Germany, France, Australia, Sweden, Denmark, etc.). I acquainted most of them through scholarship program, university, high school, and informal courses. As such, like me, each of them is a part of a larger group of Indonesians – mostly middle class, but not necessarily – who has a chance to study abroad, either through personal funding or external scholarships. To put it short, I was leisurely scrolling my Facebook timeline when I suddenly noticed the existence of myriad of photographs taken and shared by my friends, those studying in Western universities, showing (off) a glimpse of European, American, or Australian experiences. Then, again, I was awestruck with a question in my head: what if ‘the Others’ are framing back now?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">That question perhaps would not be there if I had not studied sociology during my undergraduate study in Indonesia. It popped up due to, if I may guess, the sociological imagination I learned as a student of sociology. It was also during that time that I became academically exposed to postcolonial theories, orientalism, and the matter of ‘the Other’. Simply put, the question did not appear in vacuum. The documentary </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Framing the Other </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and my friends’ photographs on Facebook had only triggered me to sociologically reflect my own being in the West, especially in </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the land which my country shared colonial past with. Being Indonesian in The Netherlands perhaps had given me revelation. I had to become aware of my country’s colonial past, my here-and-now postcolonial being, and decolonial options I might have. This essay is the result of such complex awareness. Furthermore, as a former non-Western tourism student in a Western institution, I would also like to offer this essay as a material for reflection which naturally derived from my anxiety of being surrounded by Eurocentric theories in tourism studies.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. The problem with tourism studies</section>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">What often makes me wonder about the contemporary tourism studies is the rarity of analysis on non-Western people as tourist or traveler. Seemingly, there still exists an archaic binary of ‘Western as tourist’ and ‘non-Western as touree’ (Cohen and Cohen, 2015a). Winter (2009, pp. 23-34) points out, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Given that the paradigm of tourism has in large part been constructed around an analysis of west-to-east, north-to-south encounters, rooted in ideas of globalization as a process of westernization, our tourist has been silently conceived as white</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (and male)”. Thus, I may argue, it should be unproblematic to regard tourism studies as Eurocentric, Western-biased, and colonial (Cohen and Cohen, 2015b; Alneng, 2002; Chambers and Buzinde, 2015).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Some accounts nevertheless have provided a relieved break from such monotony. For example, Peters and Higgins-Desbiolles (2012) attempt to de-marginalize tourism research by discussing indigenous Australians as tourists, not as object of Western tourist gaze. They identify several modes of travel among indigenous Australians, such as visiting/returning to ancestral homelands and collecting remains of Aboriginal people “exhibited” in colonial museums. Furthermore, Li </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2017) explore the photography practices among Chinese tourists visiting various destinations in UK. Their research aims to de-Westernize and reconceptualize John Urry’s concept of tourist gaze by putting Chinese tourists and their photographs as foci. Still, both studies are merely tiny rebellions under the dominant discourse of tourists-are-Western. In sum, non-Western tourists are still very much ignored albeit the obvious rise of non-Western tourism, especially from Asia (Alneng, 2002).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Winter (2009, pp. 27-28) claims, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The ongoing growth of non-Western forms of travel are the empirical impetus for cultivating new approaches and perspectives</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”. Indeed, non-Western tourisms and travels are empirically abundant but theoretically poor. Tucker and Hayes (2019) assert that tourism theory remains largely rooted in the Western tourist gaze, which understandably out of relevance to not only non-Western tourists and tourisms, but also non-Western tourism students. Hence, Cohen and Cohen (2015b) call for a paradigm shift to address the problem. They suggest incorporating tourism studies into mobilities paradigm, which they claim will be free of Eurocentric assumptions. Winter (2009, p. 27) argues that pluralism should be the point of departure, and he furthermore calls for an approach which “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">geographically, </span></em><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">politically and epistemologically plural</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” and “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">a multi-centered analysis</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”. In short, he invites us to “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">seriously question the universalisms at the core of tourism studies</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">So, empirically, tourists are not always Western. Nonetheless the non-Western ones are very often silenced, ignored, overlooked, and/or forgotten. This realization is precisely where I started aiming to talk back and to showcase the framing of South-to-North tourist encounters, thanks to inspiration I took from my friends’ photographs on Facebook. As a researcher-cum-tourist from the South, I am tempted to write with “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">a certain degree of rage</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Spivak 1990, p. 62) and “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">from my very inner being</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> […] </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">from where it burns</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (del Arco 2017, p. vi) against the ignorance that has silenced the voices from the South all this time. Therefore, I locate this essay as an experiment to respond to the silence and ignorance within the Eurocentric, Western-biased, and colonial knowledge production of tourism studies.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">III. What we capture: Main themes</section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">One day, as I leisurely scrolled my Facebook timeline, I eventually realized that there were three dominant visual themes of photographs which my friends – Indonesians studying in Western countries – posted on their social media. I named these themes as: European architecture, seasonal changes, and international friendship.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">First, European architecture theme is mainly identified and defined by the element of building. As buildings are everywhere in European cities, so are they in Indonesian students’ snapshots. The presence of buildings (along with their architectural design) is salient, either as a background of self-portrait or a central photographic figure. This theme covers other elements, such as pedestrian, street, bridge, train or tram rail, statue, monument, urban park, and else. They all indicate ‘something Western’ and may represent what West is for Indonesian students. There are many kinds of building: church, house, town hall, café, shop, museum, castle, and iconic buildings (such as Eiffel Tower, Colosseum, or Dutch wind mills). What these buildings offer is a taste of Europe, as well as a glance of Western civilization. Atmaja and Budiastuti (2012), studying on the images of West among Indonesian AIESEC members, mention the importance of European building in image construction process, as it signifies Western modernity and civilization. They find that the European buildings have made Europe “worth for visiting” and “worth to be shown (off)” to other Indonesian fellows (2012, p. 24).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Second, seasonal change theme can be identified by its use of visual symbol. In the autumn, the most prominent symbol is dry brownish leaves (either with trees or on the ground). For the winter, white snow is the most obvious symbol, including its derivatives, such as snowfall, snowman, or snow mountain. Some photographs portray the frozen lake or canal as epitome of winter, too. Then, spring is expressed by the presence of flowers. Pinkish cherry blossom and colorful tulips are the strongest symbols.</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> All these seasonal symbols make it seems compulsory to take (and to share) photographs of dry leaves during autumn, snow(man) during winter, and tulips or cherry blossoms during spring. One autumn day, I was cycling to campus when I saw a group of Indonesian students taking pictures in ‘autumn setting’ – the ground full of dry leaves along with typical autumn trees. During winter, if snow falls, taking pictures of snow and making a snowman are ‘obligatory’. Then, when spring comes, Indonesian students will go ‘hunting’ the photographs of pink cherry blossoms.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Third, international friendship theme is defined by the portrayal of Indonesian student with her/his international friends. Studying abroad offers a chance to build friendship with people coming from various places – including Western countries – and eventually this human-to-human relation turns into photographic objects. Photograph of this theme contains more than one person (group picture) and hints that the persons within the frame are multinational (more than one nationality). The latter element is key to point out the international-ness of the photograph. Settings can be varied, based on place and activity. Place setting consists of classroom, campus area, park, bar/pub, city (center), kitchen, apartment room, house, café, restaurant, shop, river, sea, sports center, and else. Activity setting includes lecture/class, groupwork, study excursion, campus event, party, barbecue, drinking, eating, traveling, sightseeing, playing sports, chilling, cooking, cycling, gathering, etc. Lastly, this theme should be critically seen with an understanding that friendship with Westerners can be a valuable cultural capital for Asians (Bui </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.,</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> 2013) and, in Indonesian context, befriending Westerners indeed embodies prestige and a very high value (Atmaja and Budiastuti, 2012).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">IV. The myth behind the frame</section>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Up until here, everything seems fine. The mission to respond is arguably (half-)done. I have shown the existences of Indonesian students-cum-tourists. The photographs clearly show that </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">we</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> are there: being tourists in the West. Barthes (1981, p. 5) says, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The photograph is never anything but an antiphon of ‘Look’, ‘See’, ‘Here it is’; it points a finger at certain vis-à-vis and cannot escape this pure deictic language.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” If he is correct, the Indonesian students’ photographs then might say something like “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Look, we are here! Surrounded by European buildings</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”, or “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">See, this is Winter Wonderland</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”, or “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Here it is: the international friends of mine</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The trouble came later when I tried to understand beyond the simple photographic frame. Sontag (2005, p. 90) believes that “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">photography is advanced as a form of knowing without knowing: a way of outwitting the world, instead of making a frontal attack on it.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” I was perhaps offended being outwitted by the photographs, so, as a result, I became motivated to uncover the ‘knowing without knowing’ within the frame of photograph. Following Barthes (1972), I wanted to understand the ‘mythologies’ that lie beneath the visual themes of European architecture, seasonal change, and international friendship.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">I found that each theme has its own myths: (1) </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">European architecture</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> perpetuates the amazement toward Western civilizations, (2) </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">seasonal change</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> glorifies the West's climatic condition, and (3) </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">international friendship</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> reveals the desire for Westernized international outlook. Difference is a key here. Hollinshead (1998) regards tourism as a quintessential industry of “difference” and “otherness”. Hence, the photographs that present typical European building, snowfall, autumn leaves, spring season, and a group of multinational friends might represent the experiences of difference, i.e. experiences that one doesn’t have back home. However, postcolonially speaking, this cannot be a matter of simple difference, as there exists a hierarchical difference between the (Indonesian) home and the (Western) foreign lands captured in the photographs. It is this hierarchy which forces me to semiotically see the myths of amazement, glorification, and desire toward the West whenever I encountered the photographs of European architecture, seasonal change, and international friendship. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To go even further, I conceptualized more by putting these myths as a part of higher-level myths, namely</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Occidental fairytale </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">and </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">West as destination</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Indonesian students’ photographs, along with their thematic patterns, could silently represent (‘knowing without knowing’) that: first, being in the West is a sort of fairytale for Indonesian students-cum-tourists; second, West – with </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">all its heroic features within the photographs – is </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">our </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">only destiny</span><sup><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a></sup><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">/destination to go. While fairytale involves the almost-unbelievable experience of being (in the West), the notion of destination entails the desire and longing (for the West). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">To be sure with all these visual finding and analysis, I discussed them with some Indonesian friends in Wageningen and they, like me, found it shocking by the fact that </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">our</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> travel photographs in the West could be understood as such. They could not disagree about three dominant visual themes I found, as they also (begin to) realize them. Then, albeit hurtful, they nodded to my conceptualization on Occidental fairytale and West as destination. The idea of fairytale was even actually inspired by a friend’s comment during one particular class, where she narrated her positionality as Indonesian student who has a chance to travel to Europe through education. All in all, this demythologizing process has proven to be difficult for me, as it drained my emotion, re-situated my postcolonial being, and gave me more reflective question marks.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">V. The (im)possibility of reverse framing</section>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">I had just come back home after two-years academic/postcolonial journey in Wageningen, The Netherlands, when I corresponded with my master’s thesis supervisor through e-mail. She was particularly curious about what I think it will be like to return home after all that time away. I then replied, in part but not all, with the following passage: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The excerpt, in retrospect, was very much influenced by my project of demythologizing Indonesian, South-to-North travel photographs. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Although my initial aim is simply to respond to Eurocentric knowledge production in tourism studies, I eventually found that such epistemological/experimental response is more productive as a way to self-reflection. My voice seemed being reflected back to me and it surprised me that my own analysis has indicated something alike orientalist narrative. For instance, the visual representations I found in the Indonesian students’ photographs mythically/semiotically contain the amazement, glorification, and desire toward the West. Where am I actually heading to? This </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">confusion exemplifies the ambivalence I noticed regarding the question of ‘where do the voices really come from?’. Do they epistemologically come from within or outside the West? Who is really talking/framing? I may claim that I have voiced out Indonesian perspectives, but are they really </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">our </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">inner voices? Or, can it be just an echo of Western voices? </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">I pose these questions not to be answered, but as a device to think further about my intention to talk back and to frame back. Now I would like to reflect on that by discussing the issue of Occidentalism and a trap it may contain, namely reverse Orientalism. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">I have to admit that, at first, I imagined Occidentalism as a simple reversal of Orientalism, in which non-Western bodies finally have the possibility to talk back and project the image of West. Then, Coronil (1996) offers me a reminder that a reversal of Orientalism is impossible in the context of asymmetrical relations between Self and Other. He thus understands Occidentalism more of as a condition of Orientalism’s possibility, not as a reverse of it. Even though some scholars indeed perceive Occidentalism as a means of reversing Orientalism, later I slowly developed an understanding that the former might just be another Western project (Carrier, 1992; Venn, 2000; Ahiska, 2003). In short, Occidentalism operates within West’s discursive terms and, thus, endorses the hegemonic West’s project of modernity, through which the West articulates, defines, and represents itself as modern, developed, and greater civilization.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Thus, to clarify, my project of talking back, framing back, and/or demythologizing here cannot be a project of reversing Orientalism and, likewise, should not be called a project of Occidentalism, because whom I intend to talk back to is not Orientalism per se, but the Eurocentric, Western-biased, and often-orientalist knowledge production in tourism studies. In fact, I might not have any direct problem with Orientalism, so why bother reversing it?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Yet, now, the questions are: How about reverse framing? Is it possible? Well, I don’t have the answer, but I sense that the question (of possibility) could be wrong. Instead it should be a question of importance. Do </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">we</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> really need to reverse the North-to-South, Eurocentric framing? What for? For sleeping well, for rage (after Spivak), for revenge, or for simply provoking two-ways dialogue? Still, reverse framing is possible only if the relation and dialogue are symmetrical. If not, the best </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">we </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">can do is showing the South-to-North tourist photographic framing, to (re)claim the existence, even though such framing might also be Eurocentric, Western-biased, and unfortunately colonial. The speakers differ, the contents are alike.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">VI. To talk to power is to err</section>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It was a hot day in Jakarta, circa August 2019, when I was sitting in the commuter train and reading a monograph </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Meanings of Bandung </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Phạm and Shilliam, 2016)</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">At some point, I arrived at the following passage, written in the Chapter 16:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Perhaps I was indeed naïve to intend to talk back to the silence and ignorance I encountered in tourism studies. Since the first place, when I started aiming to talk and frame back, I imagined it as a kind of dialogue, where all this time </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">we </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">are silenced and ignored and now urging to respond. However, what I failed to imagine is whom I intend to respond to. It turns out that it is ‘power’; and when we speak to power it is very tricky because (1) the relation/dialogue is asymmetrical and unbalanced, (2) the language of the dialogue must be same, and it is the language of power, so the logics and discursive terms are only in favor to power, (3) the power perhaps never intends to listen, and (4) when the power speaks back, we realize that it is useless to even start to talk, because it is like “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">a fresh budding flower that was killed immediately</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (ibid).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Still, the point is not to remain silent. As it has occurred to me, experimenting to respond (to power) can be rewarding as a pedagogy of self-reflection. In this context, self-reflection might entail the possibility of re-situating </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">our </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">postcolonial being, thinking, and sensing. This resituated positionality, I argue, can potentially be a seed of decolonial praxis, meaning an initial stepping stone toward epistemic disobedience and delinking from Western categories of thought (after Boukhris, 2017; Mignolo, 2013), as I always believe that the first step of every revolution is to realize. To realize can only be done when we reflect, when we re-situate our position.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Furthermore, we may need to learn to not talk to power. In my humble opinion, it is way more beneficial to shy away from existential impulse to talk (back) and to respond, especially vis-à-vis power. In the meantime, we could try to re-member, re-collect, re-build, and re-phrase </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">our </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">own logics of being, thinking, and sensing. I am not calling for more silence, though, as I still believe in the importance of two-ways, symmetrical dialogue. Following Grosfoguel (2012), what I would like to propose is an inter-epistemic dialogue where any episteme can conjoin the conversation without it and its voices being dissolved, incorporated, and destabilized (after Coronil, 1996). Only if it happens to be realized, </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">we </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">can sit again in this page and frame back.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Ahiska, M. (2003), “Occidentalism: The historical fantasy of the modern”, The South Atlantic Quarterly, Vol.102 No.2, pp. 351-379.</reference>
        <reference>Alneng, V. (2002), “The modern does not cater for natives: Travel ethnography and the conventions of form”, Tourist Studies, Vol. 2 No. 2, pp. 119-142.</reference>
        <reference>Atmaja, A.S. and Budiastuti, A. (2012), “Viewing the West: A case of Occidentalism by members of AIESEC Surabaya”, Allusion, Vol.1 No.1, pp. 20-25.</reference>
        <reference>Barthes, R. (1972), Mythologies, Vintage, London.</reference>
        <reference>Barthes, R. (1981), Camera lucida: Reflections on photography, Macmillan, New York.</reference>
        <reference>Boukhris, L. (2017), “The Black Paris project: the production and reception of a counter-hegemonic tourism narrative in postcolonial Paris”, Journal of sustainable Tourism, Vol. 25 No. 5, pp. 684-702.</reference>
        <reference>Carrier, J.G. (1992), “Occidentalism: the world turned upside‐down”, American ethnologist, Vol. 19 No. 2, pp. 195-212.</reference>
        <reference>Caton, K. and Santos, C. A. (2008), “Closing the hermeneutic circle? Photographic encounters with the other”, Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 35 No. 1, pp. 7-26.</reference>
        <reference>Chambers, D. and Buzinde, C. (2015), “Tourism and decolonisation: Locating research and self”, Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 51, pp. 1-16. </reference>
        <reference>Cohen, E. and Cohen, S.A. (2015a), “A mobilities approach to tourism from emerging world regions”, Current Issues in Tourism, Vol. 18 No. 1, pp. 11-43.</reference>
        <reference>Cohen, E. and Cohen, S.A. (2015b), “Beyond Eurocentrism in tourism: A paradigm shift to mobilities”, Tourism Recreation Research, Vol. 40 No. 2, pp. 157-168.</reference>
        <reference>Coronil, F. (1996), “Beyond occidentalism: toward nonimperial geohistorical categories”, Cultural Anthropology, Vol. 11 No. 1, pp. 51-87.</reference>
        <reference>del Arco, M.P.O. (2017), South-South de/postcolonial dialogues, Master's thesis, Wageningen University.</reference>
        <reference>Grosfoguel, R. (2012), “Decolonizing Western uni-versalisms: decolonial pluri-versalism from Aimé Césaire to the Zapatistas”, Transmodernity: Journal of Peripheral Cultural Production of the Luso-Hispanic World, Vol. 1 No. 3, pp. 88-104.</reference>
        <reference>Hollinshead, K. (1998), “Tourism, hybridity, and ambiguity: The relevance of Bhabha's ‘third space’ cultures”, Journal of Leisure Research, Vol. 30 No. 1, pp. 121-156.</reference>
        <reference>Icaza, R. and Soukotta, T. (2016), “Bandung as a plurality of meanings”, in Phạm, Q.N. and Shilliam, R. (Eds.), Meanings of Bandung: Postcolonial orders and decolonial visions, Rowman &amp; Littlefield, London, pp. 185-197.</reference>
        <reference>Kok, I. and Timmers, W. (2001), Framing the Other (film), I CAMERA YOU productions, The Netherlands.</reference>
        <reference>Li, M., Sharpley, R. and Gammon, S. (2019), “Towards an understanding of Chinese tourist photography: Evidence from the UK”, Current Issues in Tourism, Vol. 22 No. 5, pp. 505-521. </reference>
        <reference>Mignolo, W. (2013), “Geopolitics of sensing and knowing: On (de)coloniality, border thinking, and epistemic disobedience”, Confero: Essays on Education, Philosophy and Politics, Vol. 1 No. 1, pp. 129-150.</reference>
        <reference>Peters, A. and Higgins-Desbiolles, F. (2012), “De-marginalising tourism research: Indigenous Australians as tourists”, Journal of Hospitality and Tourism Management, Vol. 19, pp. 1-9.</reference>
        <reference>Phạm, Q.N. and Shilliam, R. (Eds.) (2016), Meanings of Bandung: Postcolonial orders and decolonial visions, Rowman &amp; Littlefield, London.</reference>
        <reference>Snee, H. (2013), “Framing the Other: cosmopolitanism and the representation of difference in overseas gap year narratives”, The British Journal of Sociology, Vol. 64 No. 1, pp. 142-162.</reference>
        <reference>Sontag, S. (2005), On photography, RosettaBooks, New York.</reference>
        <reference>Spivak, G. (1990), “Questions of Multiculturalism (with Gunew S.)”, in Harasym, S. (Ed.), The Postcolonial Critic: Interviews, Strategies, Dialogues, Routledge, London.</reference>
        <reference>“Synopsis”, (n.d.), available at: http://framingtheother.wordpress.com/about/ (accessed 16 January 2019).</reference>
        <reference>Tucker, H. and Hayes, S (2019), “Decentring scholarship through learning with/from each ‘other’”, Tourism Geographies, DOI: 10.1080/14616688.2019.1625070, pp. 1-21.</reference>
        <reference>Venn, C. (2000), Occidentalism: Modernity and subjectivity, Sage, London.</reference>
        <reference>Winter, T. (2009), “Asian tourism and the retreat of anglo-western centrism in tourism theory”, Current Issues in Tourism, Vol. 12 No. 1, pp. 21-31.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">I observed that Indonesian students’ summer photographs doesn’t have any strong symbol. To understand this issue, one may need to pay attention to the Indonesian context. Summer is perhaps least special because Indonesia has relatively warm temperature year around. Indonesians students might not have a sound urge to express the summer-ness, hence it lacks symbolism. Thus, I deliberately exclude summer here.</note>
        <note id="2">The idea of destiny/destination here is inspired by Frantz Fanon (1952, p. 12) who writes the following sentences in Black Skin White Masks: “However painful it may be for me to accept this conclusion, I am obliged to state it: For the black man there is only one destiny. And it is white.”</note>
    </notes>
</article>