<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_SHCC_21-75_Fa_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/tourisme/2856" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/tourisme.2856</DOI>
        <revue>MondesDuTourisme</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Hürlemann" prenom="Seraina" email="Seraina.hurlemann[at]unil.ch">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="en_SH_25-59_Re_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6236" lang="en">Reinventing Representations of “Local” Identity and Culture</publication>
                <publication id="fr_SH_24-73_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6262" lang="fr">Réinventer les représentations de l'identité et de la culture « locales »</publication>
                <publication id="es_SH_68-66_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6272" lang="es">Reinventando las representaciones de identidad y cultura "locales"</publication>
                <publication id="ca_SH_24-58_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6300" lang="ca">Reinventant representacions d’identitat i cultura “locals”</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Ph.D, Cultural and Social Anthropology Research Group « Cultures et natures du tourisme » Institute for Geography and Sustainability University of Lausanne 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Clivaz" prenom="Christophe" email="Christophe.clivaz[at]unil.ch">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_MLCCHF_11-91_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5756" lang="fr">Ré-invention des territoires touristiques : quelle transition pour les stations des Alpes ?</publication>
                <publication id="fr_CCAS_39-155_Rs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/6066" lang="fr">Recul des glaciers et appréhension des changements climatiques par les acteurs touristiques locaux. Le cas de Chamonix-Mont-Blanc dans les Alpes françaises</publication>
                <publication id="fr_FDCCSNMS_27-70_As_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/tourisme/543" lang="fr">Approche interdisciplinaire du développement des stations touristiques</publication>
                <publication id="fr_CC_15-150_Cd_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/tourisme/204" lang="fr">Cédric Humair et Laurent Tissot (dir.), Le Tourisme suisse et son rayonnement international (xixe-xxe s.) : “Switzerland, the playground of the world”</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Professor, Political Sciences Research Group « Cultures et natures du tourisme » Institute for Geography and Sustainability Universtiy of Lausanne 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>From the “Other” to the “Self”: Turning Cameras Around in Lashi Hai (China)</titre>
    <resume>
        This paper explores changing tourist practices in an ethnic tourism destination in Yunnan, China. The recent trend of focusing on the “self” rather than the folkloristic representation of the “other” is related to shifting governance strategies in China allowing for increased individual freedoms in domains of leisure and consumption. The fashioning of these new “selves” and their representation in tourist photography becomes a crucial aspect in place making and the shaping of modern touristic landscapes in rural destinations. 
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">The State, Tourism and the “Self”</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lashi Hai, my case study site in northwest Yunnan, is a typical destination for what many scholars call ethnic tourism. It is somewhere the “other” </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Fabian and Bunzl 2002)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> can be gazed upon, and where this otherness is performed for visitors on the stage of tourist places </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(MacCannell 1973)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The imaginary of the “other” has been shaped and nourished by various state-led discourses related to longstanding stereotypes about borderland populations, as well as by folkloristic images of ethnic culture </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Harrell 2012)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Lashi Hai is just the sort of place that would serve the state as being illustrative of both the harmonious multi-ethnic nation-state of China </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Davis 2005; Mullaney 2011)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and its benevolent intentions towards such remote rural areas inhabited by ethnic minority groups </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Yeh 2013)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Major infrastructure projects such as new roads, railways and airports connecting these areas to urban centres are proof of such intentions. A frequent conclusion drawn from analysis of typical ethnic tourism destinations in China is thus that ethnic tourism is a performance of folkloristic cultural elements that serves as an inwardly-directed soft power instrument </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Silverman and Blumenfield 2013)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. But what happens if visitors lose interest in the state-imposed narrative and, instead of creating reproductions of the “other” with their cameras, prefer to frame other things of their own choosing? What if the tourists’ own selves are becoming the main focus of photographic reproductions, and the positioning of the “self” starts to determine novel tourist practices that could shape entirely new tourism landscapes?</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This paper analyses emerging tourist practices at a classic ethnic tourism destination in China. Considering practice an integral part of the place-making process </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Pink 2012: 12)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the paper aims to understand larger social tendencies and changes in relation to recently evolving tourist practices and hence the creation of new tourist landscapes </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Yasue and Kazuo 2012)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. It demonstrates how these “local” tourist places represent an intersection of global, national and regional flows of ideas, practices and imaginaries as well as material goods and virtual trends </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Gupta and Ferguson 1992; Massey 1994)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Here, practice (as observed by diverse actors on the stage of the local tourist place) represents the embodiment of discourses of different scales, thus demonstrating how the global is localised, and vice versa </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Low 2016: 34)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The use of social media in relation to emerging tourist practices increases the importance of considering the interconnectedness of places on various scales. Arjun Appadurai explains:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The turning around of cameras observed at tourist places in Lashi Hai is part of such self-making experiments and thus reflects an important shift in Chinese society. This change is also connected to a new central government strategy aimed at depoliticizing various aspects of social life. This approach includes granting some limited freedoms in both public and political realms, with a view to enhancing general prosperity and wealth. Further, it asserts the individual’s freedom to fashion a new modern “self” in certain domains - such as consumption, lifestyle and leisure </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Zhang 2012; Zhang and Ong 2008)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The stage of the touristic place has now become an important platform upon which to present and represent these “selves”. How this shift – and the fact that the “other” concomitantly loses importance in the touristic product – relates to changing socio-political structures forms the main substance of the discussion below. In order to understand the broader implications of this new tendency, our analysis begins with the prevalent structures that contribute to the making of tourist objects – and thus the ethnic other – in China’s ethnic tourism.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Methodology</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Data presented in this article were collected by the first author in the course of her PhD research project over several fieldwork periods, each of several months’ duration, between 2015 and 2018 at the case study site in Lashi Hai, Yunnan, China. The main methodological approach for collecting the data analysed was participant observation, alongside open and semi-directed interviews. Since this article focuses mainly on tourist practice, most of the observations were made at touristic places in Lashi Hai. Participant observation has the advantage of examining “what people </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">do </span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">as well as what they </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">say</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. It thus enables an insightful examination of any discrepancies between thoughts and deeds” </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Herbert 2000: 552, emphasis original)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In many cases, mobile methods were applied to observing both tourists and guides in their activities </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Büscher 2011)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Kusenbach suggests the “go along” approach as an appropriate ethnographic method for exploring people’s experience of a place. To examine perceived local problems in a Los Angeles neighbourhood from a phenomenological perspective, she walks around with her research participant while allowing them to talk about what is seen, felt and thought – all elements of experience </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Kusenbach 2003)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Likewise, to better grasp tourist, local service provider and resident experiences of touristic places, I both accompanied such people and conducted my own “go alongs” - on horseback, on the tour bus, over a meal, on a hike or walk, and at a photoshoot. Data was fleshed out through key informant interviews with local and regional tourism operators, marketing, development and real estate experts, as well as with scholars and professionals in cultural businesses.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Ethnic Tourism: Authenticity and the “Other”</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">“Awkward and faddish as it may sound, othering expresses the insight that the Other is never simply given, never just found or encountered, but </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">made</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Fabian 1990: 755)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Both anthropology and tourism are thus, by definition, engaged in making “others”. Urry </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(2002)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> has argued that “gazing” upon the unfamiliar, and thus in some cases the “other”, is one of the determining practices of tourists. Based on this idea, various authors describe how people derive pleasure from “taking other people as objects, subjecting them to a controlling and curious gaze” (Bruner 2004: 56, referring to Mulvey 2009: 16). The quest for authenticity, the desire to glimpse into “other” people’s everyday lives, has been identified by MacCannell</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (1973)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> as the driving factor behind modern tourism. However, according to Urry</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (2002)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the postmodern tourist appreciates touristic performances for their aesthetic or humorous value, while being well aware of their performative or “fake” nature. Similar observations have been made of Chinese domestic tourists at ethnic tourism destinations, characterising them as less critical vis-à-vis cultural performances for tourists so that, rather than searching for the authentic, they prefer to engage in the spectacle of the cultural performance and simply play along </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Oakes 1998; Walsh and Swain 2004)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">If an anthropological perspective is adopted (in which cultural identities are always situational and performative) the question of authenticity declines in significance </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Bruner 2004: 80)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Instead, Clifford suggests that we ask: “What processes rather than essences are involved in present experiences of cultural identity?” </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Clifford 1988: 275)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. From this perspective, structures that either determine the performance of culture in specific situations or shape representations of cultures in particular places or moments of interaction, become of interest. Such situations or moments might be tourist encounters at ethnic tourism destinations. It is important to understand that because multiple factor contribute to the performance and representation of ethnic culture at such a tourist encounter, the performed culture is more than just a spontaneous role assumed by the tourist or the “local” provider </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Harrell 1995; Holland et al. 2001)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The interaction often has an unwritten script that follows a touristic narrative fed by multiple sources: the destination’s marketing strategy; pre-travel imaginaries about the place and its population; all kinds of media productions; state-led discourses and the many longstanding stereotypes about ethnic minorities in China </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Bruner 2004; Harrell 1995)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Gupta and Ferguson therefore suggest focusing on: </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In this sense, in order to understand how the “other” as a touristic object is created in ethnic tourism in China, the various mechanisms that contribute to shaping the imagined places of ethnic tourism destinations must be taken into account </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Oakes 1993)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Gupta and Ferguson further propose:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Ethnic Tourism in China</section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">When it comes to literature on ethnic tourism in China, what tends to remain unsaid is that the categories of ethnic groups in China, as well as related discourses reproduced in tourism, are a highly political product. The terminology defining ethnic groups, upon which the touristic product is based, refers to fairly recently-defined ethnonyms. This was done in the course of an immense ethnic classification project initiated by the Communist Party. The government’s aim was to determine the exact names and number of ethnic groups (nationality groups) within its territory, in order to have representatives of each group at the first convention of the National People’s Congress in 1954 </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Mullaney 2011: 120)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. A great many social scientists and anthropologists were mobilised to manage and conduct this huge undertaking, and vast amounts of data were collected. The concept of </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">minzu</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (nationality group), however, was not familiar to most of the people concerned, so the number of self-ascribed ethnic categories was immense. In order to reach a manageable total and a viable systematic framework for the classification, categories were ultimately determined mainly on the basis of linguistic criteria and certain cultural aspects</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Mullaney 2011: 87)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. For each group, a set of characteristic cultural traits - such as songs, dances, clothes, festivals, language and foods - were also catalogued </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Chio 2014: 25; Oakes 1998: 36–37)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The fact that many different groups were merged into single categories </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Mullaney 2011: 124)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> meant that in many cases, those categories failed to correspond to people’s own understanding of their “ethnic” or cultural belonging. Today these categories are fixed; they are even printed on identity cards. The origins of ethnic status and this classification project are being forgotten among younger people </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Mullaney 2011: 124)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. When discussing ethnicity in China, then, it should be kept in mind that these official groups do not necessarily correspond to what anthropologists would refer to as ethnic groups, where social processes of boundary-making and self-ascription remain important aspects </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Barth 1998; Okamura 1981)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In ethnic tourism the official classification of groups and their cultural characteristics plays a significant role, as do the social processes of boundary-making. There is, however, a major discrepancy in that while cultures and related social identities are dynamic and constantly changing, in China fixed aspects of ethnic cultures are set in stone. And of course, after almost seventy years, those cultural characteristics neither continue to correspond to people’s lives, nor to their own ideas about their culture (if indeed they ever did). Nonetheless, such folkloristic typecasting of ethnic cultures is still heavily promoted in tourism. Ethnic minority groups in China have long suffered from being very negatively stereotyped as uncivilised, barbarian, backward, dirty and even dangerous </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Harrell 1995)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> – and yet another stigma arrived alongside tourism development. This emerged after the Cultural Revolution, during what Oakes has called the “Cultural Turn” in China, when ethnic culture’s value to the tourism market was recognised </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Oakes 1993: 58–62)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. At that time, a new image of colourful, cheerfully singing and dancing minority peoples evolved and were placed in immaculate natural landscapes with blue skies (a rare thing in many Chinese cities) and blooming fields of flowers as far as the eye could see. The nostalgic idea of a simple but happy life, dwelling in harmony with nature and each other, was promoted in this imaginary, which soon attracted enormous numbers of domestic travellers </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Walsh and Swain 2004: 60)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The new domestic tourism market grew at immense speed, and novel destinations developed throughout the country.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Many studies on ethnic tourism in China have shown how touristic development in areas inhabited by such ethnic groups is also strongly linked to political goals. On the one hand, a folkloristic image of popular ethnic tourism destinations is used to illustrate the idea of the harmonious multinational Chinese state </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Bruner 2004: 97; Notar 2006: 5; Oakes 1998: 39; Walsh and Swain 2004: 62)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, while on the other, as many authors contend, tourism-related economic development represents a powerful tool with which central government has been able to consolidate its power and control in the area </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Chao 2012; Davis 2005; Oakes 1998; Silverman and Blumenfield 2013; Yeh 2013)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Policies aimed at strengthening local economies via tourism development are linked to massive infrastructure projects such as roads, railways and airports. At the same time, such projects legitimate stronger presence and control through deployment of government officials in the area </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Davis 2005: 30; Oakes 1998: 132)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. A further side-effect of government-led development projects (or as Yeh terms it, this “gift of development”) is that they increase a sense of gratitude and indebtedness among local populations towards the central government, which inculcates a certain degree of loyalty as well </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Yeh 2013)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With this Cultural Turn and the establishment of a domestic tourism market in China, another important and frequently discussed phenomenon evolved: theme park fever </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Oakes 1998: 50)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. By 1990, there were already around 2,500 amusement parks showcasing ethnic folk culture in China </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Nyíri 2006: 12)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. In these parks, ethnic minority groups are represented in actual-size replicas of real houses, or in even small villages, using professional actors dressed in appropriate ethnic clothing, who “inhabit” the houses. For ethnic tourism destinations in areas where people of ethnic minority status actually live, similar development strategies and visual planning have been applied afterwards </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Chio 2014: 38–39)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. As a consequence, many of these ethnic tourism destinations appear quite theme park-like - and also resemble one another to rather a high degree </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Davis 2005: 40)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The fact that in China, places have to be “opened” for tourism implies that there is an official development agency responsible for the planning, organisation, branding, marketing, naming, and so forth, of such destinations </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Nyíri 2006: 18)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The way in which ethnic cultures are represented in these officially-developed places naturally corresponds with what is defined by the government as suitable for tourism </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Vasantkumar 2014: 58–59)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Varutti has compared this process of creating representations of ethnic cultures to what Lévi-Strauss conceptualised as miniatures, which:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">When ethnic culture is represented at an official ethnic tourism destination, it is reduced to a consumer-friendly, state-conforming version of itself, cutting out any uncomfortable or challenging features which fail to fit the state-made narrative </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Vasantkumar 2014)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. It is interesting to note, however, that this also happens in places where people of minority status actually live. Instead of looking at residents’ genuine everyday lives and homes, tourists are directed towards a fenced-off area where they can gaze at a miniature version of what is supposed to be “local culture”. This implies that residents’ actual way of life does not quite match what the government (represented through official development agencies) intends to showcase in these ethnic tourism destinations. A big advantage of the theme park strategy is that it allows the state to directly control and shape the touristic place and related experiences. Moreover, interaction with local residents is reduced to a minimum; at best they remain in fairly lowly roles as service providers. Yet for locals, this kind of development strategy has clear advantages too: as long as the visitors’ focus is directed at officially designated and designed exhibition areas, there is more room for them to shape their environments and places of everyday living in line with their own wishes and ideas. The folkloristic stereotypes related to their ethnic status remain framed and gated within touristic theme parks, so that the spaces and places of everyday life can be practised differently and attributed alternative values. When looking at newer tendencies in shaping tourism’s landscapes, however, the fact that the making of touristic objects is closely connected to political goals and governance strategies remains important.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Changing Tourist Landscapes in Lashi Hai </section>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Lashi Hai is a wetland area surrounding a lake in northwest Yunnan, China. The case study was conducted in several villages on the northern shores of the lake, at the foot of forest-covered hills that lead up into the Jade Dragon Snow Mountain range. On the other side of the hills lies the famous UNESCO World Heritage site of Lijiang Old Town. One of China’s most popular domestic tourism destinations, this is also the main source of Lashi Hai’s daytrip visitors. Most people arriving in Lashi Hai are on a prearranged package trip organised by official travel agencies. These packages include transport, meals, tea and – most importantly – a short horse trek up into the forested hills, to one of the scenic spots offering views over the lake, wetlands and villages. There is an abundance of highly-decorated reception centres designed to attract visitors, and this has recently led to some stunning inventions. Arriving for fieldwork in 2018, I found myself suddenly confronted with a huge pink plastic sculpture - several metres high -of a high heel shoe. Not quite sure as to the purpose of such an object, I started investigating this new trend of shaping touristic landscapes. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The characteristic landscapes of the area traditionally featured agricultural fields and typical Naxi houses; the Naxi are an ethnic group comprising the majority of the local population. Today, many Yi people (who used to live higher up in even more remote places), as well as Han from far and near, have moved into Lashi Hai’s villages - usually either to start a business or find jobs in the tourism sector.</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> Early tourism in the area relied mainly on horse-trekking, which was organised in village cooperatives. Over time, diverse local and external investors have initiated other business models, so that competition and overlap among different providers is now huge. Meanwhile, because Lashi Hai has not yet been officially “opened” up by a proper development agency, business happens in a rather uncontrolled and unstructured way, fully exposed to the forces of the “free” (or perhaps “socialist”) market economy. Reception centres come and go, and Lashi Hai looks different each time I return. The most recent development was a major break with the “archetypal” landscape </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Chio 2014: 12)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> the area is known for: maize crops had been replaced by roses in formerly agricultural fields, with huge plastic objects towering above them.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">I reached an understanding of the new development strategy through the interviews I conducted with Lashi Hai’s visitors and participant observation at various visitor centres. Most of the people</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> I talked to indicated that they were not interested in the local culture. According to my findings, what is most important to them is the fresh air and sharing fun experiences with their friends – mainly, what they want is just to relax and enjoy themselves. What nobody specifically mentioned in these interviews, but did strike me from my observations, is that most of these people hardly ever actually relax, because they are constantly kept busy with a practice that determines the entire visit: taking photos. I addressed this issue directly in a conversation with a young couple</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> on a shuttle bus. They explained: “We spent two full hours taking pictures. We actually wanted to have a rest, but then we saw another really nice photo subject, so we had to continue taking pictures.”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> The newly constructed reception centres with their rose gardens and gaudy plastic sculptures offer plentiful backgrounds and scenes where visitors can take pictures. There are even styling zones where visitors can get professional hairstyling or make-up. Furthermore, fancy dress costumes are available for rent. Whereas until a couple of years ago tourists still liked to dress up in colourful minority dress, there is a new trend evolving of renting “modern” outfits. Instead of photographing traditional houses and agricultural landscapes, people seem to prefer the fancy backdrops of these recently created parks. And instead of taking pictures of the “other” – that is, local ethnic minority people – the focus of the camera is now on very much trained on the “self”. The positioning of the self in the right way within the fantasy landscapes provided at these parks includes entire codes of practice that have evolved rapidly over the past few years, so that a standard set of pictures and positions that people like to take in these places is already established.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">New Selves in Tourism</section>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This behaviour is clearly not unique to Chinese domestic tourism. On the contrary, the interrelatedness of tourist practice, photography and social media has been discussed by various authors </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(See for example Crouch and Lubbren 2003; Larsen 2013; Mourtazina 2019)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The phenomenon described as “‘Backs’ to Nature” by Kohn </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(2018)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> has been observed by many others in destinations all over the world </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Lyu 2016; Dinhopl and Gretzel 2016; Souza et al. 2015)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. What I found curious in Lashi Hai’s case is the fact that visitors here are turning their backs on official touristic representations of ethnic culture and state-made discourses, rather than on nature. Zhang and Ong cite Yu Hua, who remarks: “If you want to talk about modern China, it’s not only about money. During the Cultural Revolution there was no stage for the individual. Just the government. Now there is a stage for everyone. And you can see a show every day” (Zhang and Ong 2008: 1, referring to Yu Hua in Barboza 2006).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">This increased focus on self-fashioning applies not only to visitors – it also concerns locals. People living in Lashi Hai’s villages, and even residents of Lijiang’s New Town, visit the parks in their leisure time, enjoying themselves taking pictures in front of the flowering roses and the plastic sculptures as well. From my observations, in addition to conversations in the field, it became apparent that both visitors and local residents enjoyed the new alternative to the somewhat hackneyed ethnic minority image, which looks way too similar in all of China’s ethnic tourism destinations and is performed over and over again at every official ceremony, in television shows, films and other media productions. Instead of passively gazing at these official versions of “others”, individuals may now enter the stage themselves, to perform their own social identities. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">There is also a generational issue at work. Whereas the older generation (who might have experienced turbulent political times) long for a nostalgic ideal of the past featuring romantic countryside and folkloristic cultures </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Walsh and Swain 2004)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, the “Nineties Generation”, as it is called in China, is often characterised as the generation born in a prosperous time, with a desire for modernity and economic growth, as well as a stronger focus on the self as an individual </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Zhang and Ong 2008)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. This is a generation that grew up in the one-child-policy society, where that one child received all the attention possible </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Anagnost 2018)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Parents raised their offspring with the intention of securing them the best education possible, so that they would one day be able to find well-paid jobs, and also take care of their parents in their old age. Today, however, they have also become a generation of tourists with increasing purchasing power and a strong interest in engaging in leisure activities and travel </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Lim 2009; Zhang 2012)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. This generation’s growing focus on the individual is also related to changes in policy-making and leadership techniques applied by the central government </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Hansen and Svarverud 2010)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Ong and Zhang have called this strategy “socialism from afar”, which includes the cultivation of self-governing subjects </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(cited in Yeh 2014)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The making of self-governing subjects also relates to the privatisation of property and ownership of the “self”. In order to animate these new kinds of self, the government asserts “micro freedoms” for individuals </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Zhang and Ong 2008: 7)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The typical realms of such freedoms are the domains of livelihood, commerce, consumption and lifestyle </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(See also Ren 2013; Tapp 2010)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. Tourism is clearly another important area in which to exhibit these new and modern selves. Considering Zhang and Ong’s critical standpoint on the issue, which suggests that neoliberal consumption draws attention away from political issues, including those related to ethnic minorities, in Lashi Hai’s tourism destinations this has certainly been the case. In this particular instance, however, I have found this tendency to be in line with the interests of both visitors to Lashi Hai and its residents. The focus on the self, and the growing lack of interest in official folkloristic representations of ethnic minority culture also concerns the young generation of locals. In response to my question about what she wished for Lashi Hai’s future development, my local translator and co researcher Sandy replied: “The horses should be washed and made to look pretty. If we want the tourists to be satisfied, we have to pay attention to questions of cleanness and order. Also, at the moment we do only have things based on history. Now we should also add some modern aspects. We have to develop ourselves and our own cultural characteristics (…)”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. I was told by various residents that they were proud of the new reception centre with its rose fields and plastic sculptures, as this represents something completely novel and different from the negative stereotypes discriminating against ethnic minority people as backward and dirty. The co- manager of one reception centre answered to the same question thus: “All our scenic spots there is basically only natural things. What we need is to decorate them a bit, build some man made, modern things. The landscape is to monotonous, there is only the villages, mountains and water. If I had money, I would make some kind of fun park, and add some colourful things to make the places look more interesting.”</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> The rose manor with its plastic sculptures provides exactly what she has in mind. For many residents, the park represents innovation, elegance and modernity – values both visitors and residents like to be associated with. Often, on returning from a day of field work, photos taken during the day appeared on my mobile phone the minute it reached WiFi. Sandy had already posted them on WeChat</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, presenting us and the fancy backdrop of roses and the plastic sculpture to the online community. She obviously enjoyed sharing the new look given to the surroundings of her home village with her friends from near and far. It allowed her to create a new image of herself and the place she comes from – different from the stereotypes that still dominate people’s imaginings of the place. Cameras have turned away from the stigmatized “other” as the fashioning and positioning of the “self” in those fantasy and dreamlike landscapes has become more important to both visitors and residents. It is now possible for both to focus on their individual selves and to create representations of these in the modern landscapes of Lashi Hai’s tourist destinations. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Representing New “Selves” in Depoliticized Landscapes</section>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The Cultural Turn has led to the creation of countless ethnic tourism destinations in China </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Nyíri 2006; Oakes 1998)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. While tourism in Lashi Hai has not yet been subjected to an official development project, its touristic product is nevertheless based on an officially sanctioned, folkloristic version of ethnic culture. As discussed, there is a general tendency in China to separate touristic places from everyday life by establishing ethnic theme parks in which replica ethnic minority villages can be visited. However, since the popularity of minority culture and nostalgia for a romantic rural life seems to be waning among the younger population, new trends are contributing to the shaping of touristic landscapes. Social media and “selfie culture” play a crucial role in this process. Instead of focusing on the “other” – in this case, ethnic minority people and their culture – visitors prefer to position their “selves” in the touristic landscapes and frame them in their travel photos. The lack of interest in local culture, and the shift of focus towards one’s own experiences and pleasure were very directly expressed in interviews conducted in the field. Furthermore, participant observation revealed that people spend large amounts of time taking pictures in those spaces built especially for this purpose. As at any tourism destination around the globe, these pictures are taken to be shared on social media platforms. They thus represent an important means of communicating about the “self” and demonstrating this part of one’s social identity to others </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Souza et al. 2015)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In China, this tendency reflects significant changes in society that are related to shifting political strategies. The fashioning of “self-governing subjects” represents an important part of the country’s intention to establish “socialism from afar”. This kind of system allows for “micro freedoms” in which the individual gets to animate certain domains of their self-fashioning. Tourism, photography and social media have become important means of showcasing these new “selves”. The establishment of codes of practice governing what content needs to be framed in the picture and how this should be done is sped up by modern means of communication, such as the diversity of social media channels and networks. The fact that these codes suggest turning the camera around 180 degrees to focus on the self, rather than on ethnic minorities, means turning one’s back on folkloristic representations of ethnic cultures. It also implies turning one’s back on political issues to focus on solipsistic, individual pleasures. This consequence is in line with state policies which aim to depoliticize subjects, offering consumption and commerce as substitutes for more limited freedoms in other realms. Yet at the same time, it is an alternative much appreciated by local residents and visitors alike, as it moves away from the government’s earlier strategies of “indoctritainment” </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Nyíri 2009)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, where tourism was mainly used to communicate and spread political propaganda. Of course, the argument here is that propaganda now happens at a more subtle level, by depoliticizing society and using the prospect of material prosperity and wealth to distract from certain social and political restrictions. In the case of ethnic minority cultures, this shifting of focus does however allow for new space, creating “holes in the wall” </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">(Oakes 1993)</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of rigid ethnic categories filled with stereotypes, which can now be filled with new material: individual ideas of what people themselves would like to be and how they might be represented. </span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Ann Anagnost, "Imagining Global Futures in China: The Child as a Sign of Value", Imagining Global Futures, 2018. [http://sckool.org/]</reference>
        <reference>Arjun Appadurai, Modernity at Large: Cultural Dimensions of Globalization, University of Minnesota Press, 1996.</reference>
        <reference>Fredrik Barth, Ethnic Groups and Boundaries: The Social Organization of Culture Difference, Waveland Press, 1998.</reference>
        <reference>Edward M. Bruner, Culture on Tour: Ethnographies of Travel, University Of Chicago Press, 2004.</reference>
        <reference>Monika Büscher, Mobile Methods, Routledge, 2011.</reference>
        <reference>Emily Chao, Lijiang Stories: Shamans, Taxi Drivers, and Runaway Brides in Reform-Era China, University of Washington Press, 2012.</reference>
        <reference>Jenny Chio, A Landscape of Travel: The Work of Tourism in Rural Ethnic China, University of Washington Press, 2014.</reference>
        <reference>James Clifford, The Predicament of Culture: Twentieth-Century Ethnography, Literature, and Art, Harvard University Press, 1988.</reference>
        <reference>David Crouch and Nina Lubbren, Visual Culture and Tourism, Bloomsbury Publishing PLC, 2003.</reference>
        <reference>Sara Leila Margaret Davis, Song and Silence: Ethnic Revival on China’s Southwest Borders, Columbia University Press, 2005.</reference>
        <reference>Anja Dinhopl and Ulrike Gretzel, "Selfie-Taking as Touristic Looking", Annals of Tourism Research, vol. 57, 2016. [doi: 10.1016/j.annals.2015.12.015]</reference>
        <reference>Johannes Fabian, "Presence and Representation: The Other and Anthropological Writing", Critical Inquiry, vol. 16, n° 4, 1990.</reference>
        <reference>Johannes Fabian and Matti Bunzl, Time and the Other: How Anthropology Makes Its Object, Columbia University Press, 2002.</reference>
        <reference>Akhil Gupta and James Ferguson, "Beyond “Culture”: Space, Identity, and the Politics of Difference", Cultural Anthropology, vol. 7, n° 1, 1992.</reference>
        <reference>Mette Hansen Halskov and Rune Svarverud, IChina: The Rise of the Individual in Modern Chinese Society, NIAS Press, 2010.</reference>
        <reference>Stevan Harrell, Ways of Being Ethnic in Southwest China, University of Washington Press, 2012.</reference>
        <reference>Stevan Harrell, Cultural Encounters on China’s Ethnic Frontiers, Hong Kong University Press, 1996.</reference>
        <reference>Stevan Harrell, "Introduction. Civilizing Projects and the Reaction to Them", in Cultural encounter on China’s Ethnic Frontiers, University of Washington Press, 1995.</reference>
        <reference>Steve Herbert, "For Ethnography", Progress in Human Geography, vol. 24, n° 4, 2000. [doi: 10.1191/030913200100189102]</reference>
        <reference>Dorothy Holland, William Lachicotte Jr, Debra Skinner and Carole Cain, Identity and Agency in Cultural Worlds, Harvard University Press, 2001.</reference>
        <reference>Tamara Kohn, "“Backs” to Nature: Musing on Tourist Selfies", in Tourists and Tourism: A Reader, Waveland Press, 2018.</reference>
        <reference>Margarethe Kusenbach, "Street Phenomenology: The Go-Along as Ethnographic Research Tool". Ethnography, vol. 4, n° 3, 2003. [doi: 10.1177/146613810343007]</reference>
        <reference>Jonas Larsen, Digital Snaps: The New Face of Photography, I.B. Tauris, 2013.</reference>
        <reference>Francis Khek Gee Lim, "“Donkey Friends” in China: The Internet, Civil Society, and the Emergence of the Chinese Backpacking Community", in Tim Winter, Peggy Teo and T. C. Chang (eds.), Asia on Tour: Exploring the Rise of Asian Tourism, Routledge, 2009.</reference>
        <reference>Setha M. Low, Spatializing Culture: The Ethnography of Space and Place, Routledge, 2016.</reference>
        <reference>Seong Ok Lyu, "Travel Selfies on Social Media as Objectified Self-Presentation", Tourism Management, vol. 54, 2016. [doi: 10.1016/j.tourman.2015.11.001]</reference>
        <reference>Dean MacCannell, "Staged Authenticity: Arrangements of Social Place in Tourist Setting", American Journal of Sociology, vol. 79, n° 3, 1973. </reference>
        <reference>Doreen Massey, "A Global Sense of Place", in Doreen Massey (ed.), Space, place and gender, Polity, 1994.</reference>
        <reference>Ellina Mourtazina, "Photographier Zermatt : les pratiques photographiques des touristes à l’épreuve du numérique", Mondes du Tourisme, vol. 15, 2019. [doi: 10.4000/tourisme.2148]</reference>
        <reference>Thomas S. Mullaney, Coming to Terms with the Nation: Ethnic Classification in Modern China, University of California Press, 2011.</reference>
        <reference>Beth E. Notar, Displacing Desire: Travel and Popular Culture in China, University of Hawaii Press, 2006.</reference>
        <reference>Pál Nyíri, Scenic Spots: Chinese Tourism, the State, and Cultural Authority, University of Washington Press, 2006.</reference>
        <reference>Pál Nyíri, "Between Encouragement and Control: Tourism, Modernity and Discipline in China", in Tim Winter, Peggy Teo and T.C. Chang (eds.), Asia on Tour: Exploring the Rise of Asian Tourism, Routledge, 2009.</reference>
        <reference>Timothy Oakes, Tourism and Modernity in China, Routledge, 1998.</reference>
        <reference>Timothy Oakes, "The Cultural Space of Modernity: Ethnic Tourism and Place Identity in China", Environment and Planning: Society and Space, vol. 11, n° 1, 1993. [doi: 10.1068/d110047]</reference>
        <reference>Jonathan Y. Okamura, "Situational Ethnicity", Ethnic and Racial Studies, vol. 4, n° 4, 1981. [doi: 10.1080/01419870.1981.9993351]</reference>
        <reference>Sarah Pink, Situating Everyday Life: Practices and Places, SAGE, 2012.</reference>
        <reference>Hai Ren, The Middle Class in Neoliberal China: Governing Risk, Life-Building, and Themed Spaces, Taylor and Francis, 2013.</reference>
        <reference>Helaine Silverman and Tami Blumenfield, "Cultural Heritage Politics in China: An Introduction", in Cultural Heritage Politics in China, Springer, 2013.</reference>
        <reference>Flávio Souza Diego de Las Casas, Vinícius Flores, SunBum Youn, Meeyoung Cha, Daniele Quercia and Virgílio Almeida, "Dawn of the Selfie Era: The Whos, Wheres, and Hows of Selfies on Instagram", proceedings of the 2015 ACM Conference on Online Social Networks, Palo Alto, California, Association for Computing Machinery, 2015.</reference>
        <reference>Nicholas Tapp, "The Ambiguity of “Self”: Romantics in the Marketplace", Anthropology of the Century, vol. 10, 2010.</reference>
        <reference>John Urry, The Tourist Gaze, SAGE, 2002.</reference>
        <reference>Marzia Varutti, "Miniatures of the Nation: Ethnic Minority Figurines, Mannequins and Dioramas in Chinese Museums", Museum and Society, vol. 9, n° 1, 2011.</reference>
        <reference>Christopher Vasantkumar, "Dreamworld, Shambala, Gannan: the Shangrilazation of China's "Little Tibet"", in Emily T. Yeh and Chris Coggins (eds.), Mapping Shangrila, Contested Landscapes in the Sino-Tibetan Borderlands, University of Washington Press, 2014.</reference>
        <reference>Eileen Rose Walsh and Margaret Byrne Swain, "Creating Modernity by Touring Paradise: Domestic Ethnic Tourism in Yunnan, China", Tourism Recreation Research, vol. 29, n° 2, 2004. [doi: 10.1080/02508281.2004.11081444]</reference>
        <reference>Eriko Yasue and Murakami Kazuo, "Practicing Tourist Landscapes: Photographic Performances and Consumption of Nature in Japanese Domestic Tourism", in Timothy Oakes and Claudio Minca (eds.), Real Tourism: Practice, Care, and Politics in Contemporary Travel Culture, Routledge, 2012.</reference>
        <reference>Emily T. Yeh, Taming Tibet: Landscape Transformation and the Gift of Chinese Development, Cornell University Press, 2013.</reference>
        <reference>Emily T. Yeh, "The Rise and Fall of the Green Tibetan: Contingent Collaborations and the Vicissitudes of Harmony", in Emily T. Yeh and Chris Coggins (eds.), Mapping Shangrila, Contested Landscapes in the Sino-Tibetan Borderlands, University of Washington Press, 2014.</reference>
        <reference>Li Zhang, In Search of Paradise: Middle-Class Living in a Chinese Metropolis, Cornell University Press, 2012.</reference>
        <reference>Li Zhang and Aihwa Ong, Privatizing China: Socialism from Afar, Cornell University Press, 2008.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">It is important to mention that the term “local residents” does not refer to one specific ethnic group or culture. On the contrary, this article assumes there not to be any sort of homogenous group having a distinct local identity or culture, but rather suggests conceptualizing both as being performative and situational (cf. Massey 1994; Holland et al. 2001). </note>
        <note id="2">Interviews with tourists were conducted at the reception centres in spring 2017, using a short set of standard questions. The majority of the visitors were between 20 and 40 years old and came from urban regions. There was however a wide variety of geographic origins, with visitors from all over the country. </note>
        <note id="3">A couple in their mid-twenties from a town near Chengdu in Sichuan Province.</note>
        <note id="4">Conversation quoted in field notes from 15.11.2018 in Junliang Village, Lashi Hai. </note>
        <note id="5">Interview in Lashi Hai, 08.05.2017 with Sandy (fictional name), 24 years old. As co- researcher and translator between Mandarin and the local Naxi language, Sandy contributed a great deal to my field research. She had just graduated from a university in northern China and moved back to her parents’ home in Lashi Hai, to find a job as a teacher. </note>
        <note id="6">Interview in Lashi Hai, 01.05.2017 with A Mu, 22 years old. She works as co-manager at one of the smaller, more traditional reception centres and is responsible for customer satisfaction. She grew up and lives in one of the villages in Lashi Hai. </note>
        <note id="7">WeChat is the most popular social media app in China, and combines diverse functions. Among other features it offers messaging as well as a platform on which to post pictures and other information.</note>
    </notes>
</article>