<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_TD_24-126_As_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1296" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.1296</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>1</numero>
        <annee>2012</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="1291">
            <traducteur nom="Bretagne Occidentale" prenom="Université" />
            L’authenticité par la mise en scène. Analyse dialogique des activités touristiques et culturelles de la place Jemaa El Fna et de leurs représentations
        </original>
        <traduction lang="it" source="1309">L’autenticità mediante la messa in scena. Analisi dialogica delle attività turistiche e culturali della piazza Jemaa El Fna e delle loro rappresentazioni</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Danteur" prenom="Thibault">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_TD_24-150_Ls_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/1291" lang="fr">L’authenticité par la mise en scène. Analyse dialogique des activités touristiques et culturelles de la place Jemaa El Fna et de leurs représentations</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Doctoral Student in Sociology, Université Paul Valéry, Montpellier III, LERSEM (IRSA-CRI).Thibault Danteur is currently preparing a PhD in sociology which focuses on the mass-retailing industry and its impact on the representations and the imaginary of the cultures where it develops, through food behaviours for example. His research is based on a qualitative and socio-anthropological methodology, for which he spent time in France and the United-States and took a two-year observation period in Morocco. His work is rooted in the fields of economic sociology, food, and imaginary and social representations. This present doctoral research analyses the complex interactions between globalised retailing and local environment both at economic and cultural level, leading him to address tourism as a fundamental element in the phenomenon of cultural and economic globalization in Morocco. 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Authenticity through staging. Dialogic analysis of Jemaa El Fna square’s touristic and cultural activities and representations</titre>
    <resume>
        Marrakesh’s Jemaa El Fna square is a symbol which represents the “Ochre City” as well as Morocco’s cultural identity. Its activities, which are proclaimed by UNESCO as a Masterpiece of the Intangible Heritage of Humanity, turn the square into one of the most visited sites for domestic and foreign tourists in the country. After conducting observations and interviews for several months, with the aim of following the tourists on their experience of the square, we shall present a socio-anthropological analysis of the cultural and tourist activities of this particular space, which we shall consider as a syncretic environment. It will be argued that it is necessary to take into account the dialogical relationships which bring together such elements as authenticity and its staging in an interaction which goes beyond a mere contradictory opposition.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            Nerve centre of the ancient medina, the Jemaa El Fna square has become the emblem of Marrakesh and all Morocco thanks to the traditional activities it hosts. The square is identified as the ultimate place of expression of popular and oral culture in the whole of North Africa. Artists and tourists gather there all year round, allowing us to distinguish the cultural tourism potential of the square, as an “ideal regulatory example: the ‘cultural’ ennobles the practices and destinations and allows to imagine exchanges” (Cousin, 2006a, p. 21).<br/>The present study has been conducted in the context of our doctoral research, which explores globalised industries. Focusing more specifically on examples from the large-scale distribution and food consumption habits, we have applied the “case study mosaic” (Becker, 1986), which led us to address the case of Morocco through a European exchange program with the aim of achieving a variation in geo-cultural contexts. In the perspective of analytical induction, and in order to refine our theoretical hypothesis, we have chosen to confront our observations on food consumption behaviour in volume retailing to other consumption situations in different contexts. Tourist practices, and more specifically those taking place on the Jemaa El Fna square, therefore proved particularly suitable to this variation of the cases studied, due to their obvious link with economic and cultural globalisation phenomena (Lazarotti, 2000 ; Coëffé et al., 2007 ; Gay and Violier, 2007).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            Opposing interpretations of the activities of the square, from the point of view of tourism professionals or from that of some social science researchers, present it now as an authentic and historical cultural space, now as a patrimonialised place where this authenticity would be fictitious (MacCannel, 1989) and would pertain to staging and ritual performance (Turner, 1987). Indeed, as coined by Kurzac-Souali, “the touristic areas of the old city thus represent privileged spaces of cohabitation and exchange between foreigners, tourists, residents and Moroccans” (Kurzac-Souali, 2007, p. 64). The cohabitation and co-invention of Jemaa El Fna’s cultural space<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a> being identified as a tourist spot by foreign and domestic usages, we may hope for a better understanding by taking into account the complex relationship between foreign tourism practices, domestic practices and local usage of the square. In other words, we may consider describing the relationships between syncretic practices, which result from globalisation and take the form of an actors’ performance through self-staging directed at the tourists, and the so-called traditional practices of the square other than on the basis of opposition and dualism. In the same perspective we may wonder how to articulate the various representations of the square which may first appear as contradictory.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            In the same way as in the whole of this doctoral research, we have endeavoured in this case-study to favour a pragmatic socio-anthropological approach, which mainly rests on a qualitative and inductive analysis of our field observations. We have chosen to focus more particularly on the testimony of tourists as well as managers, artists and professionals present in the square, and on the narrative reconstruction of their actions, perceptions and decisions. Our concern has therefore been predominantly centred on these testimonies and on its “overt and reconstructed practices” (Poulain, 2002) insofar as they express the imaginaries and representations of the place, of its activities and management<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            Most of our observations have been direct or participatory, and often clandestine. We accompanied tourists, went with them to various places, had conversations with their interlocutors, took the same pictures as them, in order to have direct access to the organisation and experience of the tourist flow on the square from the point of view of local and foreign visitors. These observations have then been followed up by a series of forty interviews, mainly conducted with tourists, artists or retailers from the square, and with foreign residents and the municipal agents who manage the square. These were mostly conducted informally<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn3" id="bodyftn3">3</a>, Indeed, we noticed that scheduled interviews faced important reluctance, as many of the respondents were less open and reacted with restraint<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            We have also used anthropological photography, both as a tool for a geographical survey of the square and as a fruitful source of additional information (Piette, 1996)<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a>. Moreover we followed some tourist-photographers<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn6" id="bodyftn6">6</a>, in their quest for images, thereby identifying their “photographic scripts” (Suchar, 1997). Lastly, we have established protocol for retrieval of the images photographed by the tourists with the aim of verifying the status of the Jemaa El Fna square in the visit to Marrakesh and the specific subjects photographed in the square<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">The staging of authenticity: patrimonialisation, developments and representations</section>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            The theory of the search for authenticity, as exposed by MacCannell (1989), appears to us as essential in the study of the tourism phenomenon, however disregarded it is by some authors. The authors who have been critical of this theory nevertheless appear to complement it rather than refute it. They notably underline the necessity to pay closer attention to non-western tourism practices, as well as to dialogical processes which link tourist behaviour and natives (Picard, 1992 ; Coëffé et al., 2007). However, the theory of the quest for authenticity still seems to us to represent a key to a fundamental understanding of the analysis of tourist behaviour and representations on the Jemaa El Fna square. The western tourist visiting Morocco and Marrakesh is looking to sample a way of life perceived as traditional and uncorrupted, in connection with orientalism and a perception of the exotic which is directly inherited from the nineteenth century<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a> (Staszak, 2006 ; Gauthier, 2008). It is also striking, on consulting tourist guides, reviews and websites, to note the extent to which the information available about the Jemaa El Fna square is vague from the point of view of the foreign visitor<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a>. The tourist literature broadly considers that the square is secular and that the cultural activities offered in the square draw on a unique and immemorial tradition. These descriptions of the square, through its historical, traditional and localised traits, contribute to embedding the claimed image of an authentic and preserved space which, at the same time, shows a strong potential for tourism. The Jemaa El Fna square, being patrimonialised within a localised space, has been constructed (Barthel, 2004) through a long process initiated in the 1970s, with several attempts to rigorously specify and determine the cultural heritage status of the square and of its artists, and which led to the listing of the cultural space of the place as World Intangible Heritage by UNESCO in 2001, thus launching its exploitation. In this process of patrimonialisation, a profound tension emerges through the contradiction of an ambivalent desire to protect the square while modernising it, and a simultaneous desire for transformation and preservation. Di Méo (2007) describes the stages of patrimonialisation: the “patrimonial discovery” which, in our present example, is influenced by the conferences which took place before 1991. The stage of the “actors’ part”: here, King Mohammed VI contributed to a great extent to launching the political and rhetorical game of the process of patrimonialisation through his speech in January 2001. We may also cite the strategy of the National Tourist Board, which was subsequently implemented, or the activism of the various associations which campaigned for the protection of the site. The “patrimonial selection and justification” are, in our present example, illustrated by its listing by UNESCO in 2001. The “heritage preservation, operation and development” have consisted, on the Jemaa El Fna square, of a series of developments conducted since the 1980s. We here perceive the historical nature of the process of invention of the touristic place (Raffestin, 1986).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            This protection policy has been implemented as early as the 1970s, due to several construction projects on the site whose authenticity dependability was difficult to verify, such as parking lots, buildings or fountains. Henceforth, through the positions held by the actors campaigning for its protection, the square is presented as a place for exchange, for diversity with a historical value ; they also argue for a cultural implementation of a supposedly tasteful tourism (Picard, 1992 ; Cousin, 2006b ; Simon, 2008). The geographers have rigorously described the strategy of development of the patrimonial resource which accompanies the objective of protection (Choplin and Gatin, 2010 ; Gatin, 2008). The various actions of the local authorities, such as the organisation of cultural events like the International Film Festival, a contemporary dance festival or promotional events, aim to develop the tourism potential of the square and are supported by statements that focus more particularly on the ‘promotion’ rather than the transformation. As shown by Chopin and Gatin, “the public space, as restructured by tourism, is submitted to an idealised model associated with the themes of hygiene, order, functionality and openness, which seek to break with a physionomy and spatial appropriations perceived as incompatible with the national development strategy” (2010, p. 28). These developments took place in the 1990s in various forms, always in accordance with the idea of compliance to western criteria.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            The urban facilities of the square have thus been developed over the years, with for instance a resurfaced area “in order to specifically collect greasy material (…) in the middle of the square where food stalls settle” (Choplin et Gatin, 2010, p. 27). This paving came along with the construction of localised pedestrian areas, as well as the implementation of a policy of standardisation of urban furnitures and shops. Indeed, restaurants were invited to coordinate their frontages and terraces, “in 2005, orange juice, dry fruits and snails merchants on the Jemaa El Fna square traded their old carts for new all identical structures by municipal order” (Kurzac-Souali, 2007, p. 79), in line with the aesthetic features of the horse-drawn carriages which drive through the medina.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            This tendency towards standardisation mainly characterises the second category of developments, pertaining to commercial facilities whether on or around the place. The panoramic terraces have multiplied ; restaurants have then coordinated their equipment and changed their practices. A specific control policy for quality and freshness has notably been established in order to preserve the image of the square and to reassure worried tourists, as shown by our interviews. A significant effort in development has also been focused on space management, organisation and control ever since the 1990s, and more particularly after the listing by UNESCO, in order to fight against petty crime on the square (Kurzac-Souali, 2007 ; Choplin and Gatin, 2010), which has long undermined the reputation of the Ochre City<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn10" id="bodyftn10">10</a>. Thus, “the reorganisation of the park and back streets leading to the Jemaa El Fna square has allowed the demolition of the alleys curbs used by the homeless to rest during the daytime and behind which they could sleep at night safe from the public law enforcement authorities” (Choplin and Gatin, 2010, p. 28).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <br/>The square has long had (and sometimes still has) the reputation of a dirty and anarchic place of depravity and ill-repute (Gatin, 2008 ; Gauthier, 2010) ; in order to curb such representations, mendicity in particular is handled by religious institutions, out of the space whose resources have been implemented. Complementing these measures, an effective logistical policy was introduced, with measure of aesthetic nature as well as a more rigorous organisation and control over the geographical space. The definition of areas specifically dedicated to each type of cultural and commercial activities, the allocation of name tags and licence numbers to most of the actors concerned with food retailing, and a contract concluded with an Italian firm in charge of the daily cleaning of the site have completed the series of developments which followed the patrimonialisation of the square. This whole process aimed at amending the organisation of the Jemaa El Fna square rests on a long-term narrative process<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a>, on behalf of all the participants in the “actors’ part” (Di Méo, 2007), whose goal is to justify a new operating policy for the site while promoting new representations of the square as a valuable and fragile heritage. These discourses found the dualism between preservation and economic promotion which characterises the management of the square and gives it this museified character which some deplore. Due to the fact that the square is an important tourism resource, the ambition with which it is operated encourages transformations, presented by its actors as “developments”, which take into account expectations and norms, often perceived as of western influence<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a> concerning aesthetics, logistics and safety- related comfort. “A revaluation achieved according to the needs and expectations (sometimes alleged) of the tourists (and investors)” and which, as shown by Kurzac-Souali, “distorts the relationship between the urban space and the inhabitants” (2007, p. 80). At the same time, the desire to preserve the cultural practices leads to self-staging, to play one’s own part (Staszak, 2006) for the foreign tourist in search of this exotic authenticity and who eventually discovers a mere staging, a “reconstructed authenticity” (Mac Cannell, 1989). « Une revalorisation en fonction des besoins et des attentes (parfois supposées) des touristes (et des investisseurs) » et qui, comme le montre Kurzac-Souali, « biaise le rapport de l’espace urbain à la population habitante » (2007, p. 80). Parallèlement, la volonté de préserver les pratiques culturelles conduit à la mise en scène de soi-même, à jouer son propre rôle (Staszak, 2006) pour le touriste étranger venu chercher ici cette authenticité exotique pour ne trouver finalement qu’une mise en scène, une « ethnicité reconstruite » (MacCannell, 1989).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Authenticity for sale, consumption of the square</section>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            The representations of the square as a magical place, as an ancestral space of cultural diversity partly originate in the process of patrimonialisation of the square, as comments by the official guides and tourists show. They are largely inspired by the stereotyped images perpetuated by the tourist literature and the western popular culture. Yet these representations are the driving force in the tourist economy of the square, therefore stimulating the choice of the destination as well as the content of the visits, as shown by Simon: “the image and the imaginary hold an essential place in any trip, notably in its preliminary form, namely as a plan, embodying in an image the representation of the elsewhere. (…) When turning the trip into a physical reality, the tourist searches for images (…). This range of images to be seen makes up an initial frame with which the guides must compromise. The images are so powerful that giving up their view or visit is problematic” (Simon, 2008, p. 8). The photographical image plays a particular role in the construction, support and transmission of the tourist imaginary, ever since the first package tours in the nineteenth-century England (Miossec, 1977 ; Boyer, 2002). In the present case, our observations and interviews led us at a very early stage to consider the specific role of photography in the tourist imaginary of the square as well as in the practices of the visiting tourists. The image is clearly the most consumed product (Giraud, 2002). The pictures the tourists bring back will therefore fuel the pool of stereotypes which are at the roots of the tourist imaginary and, in our present example, of representations linked to the square (Andrews, 1989 ; Urry, 1990). This is verifiable whether discussing with foreign or local tourists. The study of the tourist pictures, and of their statement regarding their practice of photography in the square, gives a comprehensive overview of the importance of the site in the city imaginary and of images in the transmission of representations of its exoticism and authenticity. Through the comments expressed by foreign and local tourists on the Jemaa El Fna square, the criterion of the “place to see” (Amirou, 1994 ; Boyer, 2002 ; Simon, 2008) stands out inasmuch as seeing is an integral part of the desire to travel. The photographic image may then take on a testimonial role, as shown by the full-length portraits including specific settings which signify and testify to the physical presence in the “place to see”. The photographic image also takes on a documentary role aimed at making one see. The tourist photography “documents the places, lists them, as in travel photo reports, and at the same time refers to a practice of testimony and appropriation, as in family pictures. (…) [It] experiences the tension between the staging of affections (it constitutes a memory and sometimes will form part of a diary) and the will to record exemplary experiences in order to turn one’s own trip into a tour which may be repeated by other tourists” (Dondero, 2008, p. 24). The visitors interviewed already have a pool of images in mind before their trip has even started, and come to the site to chase or collect the pictures that they “need”<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn13" id="bodyftn13">13</a> It is of particular interest to note that the pictures that tourists sent us often show similar content<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            Some visitors even admitted their wish to ‘reproduce’ a picture seen at a friend’s house or on the Internet. Photography therefore has a particular status in the tourist practices in the square, but it is also consubstantial with many of the activities offered on the site. As rightly pointed out by Salazar (2009) and Staszak about French Polynesia, the tourist photographic image forms part of the phenomenon of staging of the native authenticity, as it is perceived by the local population as a potential source of income. It encourages a form of “invitation for the eye” and invites one to play one’s own role and caricature, and to a staging similar to theatrical performance (Schechner, 1977 ; Turner, 1987). In this sense, the tourist photographic image affects the natives’ self far more than the tourists’ self (Bruner, 1991). This assessment is easily transferable to the Jemaa El Fna square insomuch as the practice of photography, made commonplace by the emergence of digital technology, reinforces and maintains a fictitious authenticity while encouraging architectural transformations such as the systematic implementation of panoramic terraces around the square.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            The tourist’s practice of photography in the Jemaa El Fna square has initiated changes which lead tourists to often behave as in a zoo or a safari. The western tourists mostly, some Moroccans as well, spend a lot of time seated on the panoramic terraces of the square. As shown by our interviews, the visitors appreciate and seek out these raised views, which are perceived and expressed as reassuring and allow one to capture the whole square (Leroux, 2007). Such practices have played a role in the increasing popularity of these food premises, and are also related to the rise of a new kind of harassment through the incitement to photographic consumption. “These modes of promotion,” Kurzac-Souali argues, “tend to satisfy the Other, the visitor and the new investor, rather than those who go all over and live in the medina.” (2007, p. 80) They participate in the development of staging, of a reconstruction with profitable views of an imaginary cultural identity keen on making a spectacle of itself<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            And yet, if we partly subscribe to the idea of the search for authenticity, regarding the exoticism mode in our present example (Gauthier, 2008 and 2010), we must point out, with others (Cohen, 1988 ; Giraud, 2002), the pertinence of this idea lies mainly in the study of western tourism. In considering the local tourist’s approach, the paradigmatic validity of an otherwise highly relevant theory will probably need qualifying. Indeed, many activities on the Jemaa El Fna square are presented as traditional and fundamental to the cultural aspect of the site, such as the snake-charmers, the monkey-trainers or the tooth-puller, but prove to be staged and instrumentalised ; however, this assessment of the marketing of a fictitious authenticity should not be the final point in our analysis. Taking into account the domestic inverted look (Gillespie, 2006) should allow us to put into perspective this denunciation of a form of staging, and also to further the description of the mechanisms of a complex theory of authenticity linked to Jemaa El Fna square ; in this way, we will illustrate the new rationales of the handling of domestic tourism in Morocco, as well as other non-western tourism due to its acculturating character (Cohen, 1988) or, conversely, its diffusion into a non-western culture (Doquet and Evrard, 2008). In this sense, we agree with Berriane when he describes “the present [domestic] cultural tourist practices [as] the outcome of an internal evolution in which the exogenous factors may also apply” (Berriane, 1993, p. 139).
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Authenticity through staging</section>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            The square is not exclusively used by western tourists or short-term visitors: geographically, the square is highly integrated in the urban structure of the old medina and constitutes a real “interface between the medina and the modern neighbourhoods” (Gatin, 2008, p. 8), as well as an essential crossroad for many of its inhabitants. As a result, a dichotomy is observed in the activities offered on the square. This dichotomy notably revolves around a marked temporality and a territorialisation of the various actors of the square, as well as a differentiation in the visitors to whom these activities are directed. As the day goes on, the foreign tourists, in outstanding proportion in the middle of the day, tend to disappear when, at sunset, the storytellers and fortune tellers arrive, and prefer to seat on the panoramic terraces of the restaurants overlooking the square. This temporality of the audiences of the square goes along with the temporality of its activities. In daytime, it is mainly monkey-trainers, snake-charmers, tattooists and tooth-pullers who occupy the square, activities that are clearly intended for temporary visitors. In the evening, clowns, fortune-tellers, jugglers and transvestites, who used to attract the crowds from the medina, arrive forming large circles around the artists.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            Borrowing the idea of the day-night dichotomy in regimes of the imaginary (Durand, 1998), this temporality which gives rhythm to the square, namely the Moroccan traditional recreational activities such as the moussems (Berriane, 1989) appear to us as a major element in the construction of the imaginary of the site. Besides, our interviews and the tourist literature clearly show that this evolution of the square, all through the day and evening, marks the visitors’ discourse. Many of the artists who perform at night, at the moment when the square livens up, are mostly viewed by Moroccans. Street theatre, transvestite shows, storytellers may only be understood under the condition of mastering the darija<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a> and its nuances. Even though some tourists observe, or give some change in exchange for taking a picture, they cannot access the harqua<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn17" id="bodyftn17">17</a> proper, and are excluded from the game. These activities, largely restricted to Arabic-speaking people, constitute an authentic pool of traditional activities, out of reach of foreign tourists, as opposed to gnawa<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a> shows and snake-charmers for instance. The tourists henceforth denied the access to this cultural content of the square, only perceive and consume its aesthetic aspect.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <br/>Taking into account the duality of the audiences and the activities designed for them allows us to highlight the dialogical coexistence, within this geographical space, of reconstructed activities with a touristic purpose and of traditional activities out of reach of the tourists, of which only reinterpretations are available to foreign visitors. These two types of activity may first appear opposable, but observation allows us to further our analysis of the relationship between authenticity and staging and to question the rigidity of this opposition. Considering the economic role of the tourists who elicited the reconstruction of the cultural identity of the square, and who de facto participate in the perpetuation of preserved traditional activities, we may suggest that these activities may be fulfilling within their own caricature, and that their survival at least partly depends on a tourist audience for whom they are not intended<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn19" id="bodyftn19">19</a>. The profitable and tourist-oriented activities depend in turn on these traditional activities to guarantee the image of the site and its attractiveness. This authenticity through staging defines what Morin calls a dialogic association (1990) of both contradictory and interdependent terms, in this antagonistic and reciprocally necessary relationship through which it is articulated.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Anxiety-provoking authenticity</section>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            Henceforth, this dialogism which allows us, as shown by various authors (Picard, 1992 ; Coëffé et al., 2007), to describe more appropriately the articulation between tourism implementation and its consequences for the native actors, may lead us to better understand the various representations of the square.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            Thus, the question of the search for authenticity may indeed be addressed both to the native tourist and to local residents. This attraction to the authenticity of the square, and its protection when being confronted by a supposed threat, is at the heart of the local imaginary and may be put forward in the light of some comments expressing an anxiety-provoking relationship to the square and to the evolution of its activities. The characteristics of Jemaa El Fna, on which are based its image as a cultural space, often give rise to fascination in its local or foreign visitors, but it appears that they may also evenly generate repulsion.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            In the case of local actors, it is of common knowledge that the tourist development of the square is an important resource for the city, but this tourism implementation still provokes anxiety for many actors of the medina. On the mode of ‘the invasion’, the buyout of ryads in the immediate surroundings of the square are denounced in the media<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn20" id="bodyftn20">20</a> with concerns about the gentrification of the city’s humbler neighbourhoods. Our interviews show such anxiety “to see the Europeans move in” and “renovate”, “drink alcohol”, “disrespect decency”. This fear of perversion and deculturing with a theme of invasion testifies to the anxiety-provoking relationship which some inhabitants may have towards the activities of the square. These are also perceived negatively for other reasons: Gatin and Choplin (2010) refer to the long unattractive reputation of Jemaa El Fna in the eyes of some Moroccans, who describe it as an anarchic and archaic place, a counter-model for some Moroccan urbanists.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            This anxiety-provoking relationship with the activities of the square is perceivable in the same way in foreign visitors, who refer to it as an over-touristic site and “imply that this activity has led to a total loss of authenticity, both aesthetically and in the relationship with the local population. Mass-tourism would be a corrupting factor for this population, which it would have contaminated” (Leroux, 2007, p. 11). Many interviews pointed out this fascination-repulsion relationship<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn21" id="bodyftn21">21</a>, in the western tourists who mention a dirty square and the discomfort provoked by promiscuity in the nightly activities. The harassment of tourists by child beggars or by ‘pointeurs’¬, men who take advantage of the crowd to rub up against the backs of young men or women, the fear of pick-pockets are all cited in explanation this anxiety shared and expressed by many subjects from their experiences. The worries about to food quality, particularly in food stalls, come next ; the fear of water and fruit juice quality, of diseases and hygiene are also often expressed. The tourist literature does not often refer to Gauthier (2010) to preserve the brand image of Jemaa El Fna, though his works have allowed us to note the lasting nature of this anxiety-provoking aspect ever since the first travellers of the nineteenth century, despite the development of the square. Gauthier (2010) shows that the western travellers, like some modern tourists, already referred to the oppressive and dangerous character of the square, while associating these terms with values of exoticism presented as positive. We may therefore argue that repulsion as well as fascination justify the choice of the destination, and that the tourists seek to some extent to verify what will provoke anxiety or comfort them in their feeling of superiority (Boyer, 2002 ; Leroux, 2007). The relationship between fascination and repulsion henceforth appear to us as exceeding the mere opposition, insofar as the two terms seem both opposable and complementary in constructing the imaginary of authenticity and exoticism in a dialogic and complex relationship.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            Our observations on the cultural and touristic activities of the Jemaa El Fna square, on its usage both by foreign visitors and native actors, as well as our interviews and conversations with all of them, have allowed us to put forward several phenomena which pertain to the modalities of its tourism implementation, its consequences at local level and the representations associated to it.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            First, about the activities on the square, it appears to us that it should be considered other than only as a place of staging of a fictitious authenticity (MacCannell, 1989). Indeed, in the light of some assessments such as the day-night dichotomy which characterises the distribution of the activities, the numerous developments pertaining to “neo-traditionalism” (Graburn, 1983) or the internalisation by the natives of the photographical touristic collection ; and following Picard (1992) or Coëffé (2007, 2008), it appears that its functioning is far better described with the help of a dialogical approach. The latter thus allows us to understand the performances of the actors such as the Gnawas, the snake-charmers or the tooth pullers as a syncretic reinterpretation of a fantasized tradition by the western perception, notably, thus made available to an audience of foreign tourists. Moreover, it appears after observation that numerous traditional cultural activities like storytelling derive benefits and protection from the tourism activity and the stagings it brings about. However, this assessment must be qualified as regards the storytellers in particular. Indeed, despite the desire of UNESCO to preserve this heritage, notably through the organisation and the funding of pedagogical activities at school, the storytellers on Jemaa El Fna square are ever less present over the years. They must face up to the problem of arousing new vocations for an occupation which is transmitted orally, and the competition from television and new technologies which capture a large part of their traditional audience. However, they strive to perpetuate their art on the square or at the occasion of some cultural exhibitions dedicated to storytelling under the impulse of UNESCO and other organisations such as the French Institute of Marrakesh<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn22" id="bodyftn22">22</a>.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            The cultural activities on the square are thus characterised by the dialogic aspect of their physical and administrative organisation, clientele and temporality. We therefore argue that if the square is the site of the staging of a reconstructed ‘fake identity’, marketed and instrumentalised, it also represents a space for a tangible tradition, made available to the majority of foreigners through this reinterpretation in the form of a theatrical performance, and depending on the tourists’ presence ; an authenticity and its staging, which all in all nurture one another in order to generate new syncretic practices. The complex perspective thus allows us to go past a simplifying vision of tourist anthropology polarised around its traditional dualisms of the oppositions between visitors and hosts or between authenticity and staging. At the same time, this complex and dialogic perspective provides a better understanding of the representations associated with the square, and of coherently articulated imaginaries which could at first seem to be in stark opposition. Therefore, rather than consider the images linked to some aspects perceived as repulsive and described in the travel literature of the nineteenth century or in the contemporary tourists’ comments, in the mode of negative representation ; conversely, the comments showed some fascination for the traditional character of the square in the positive mode. Observation allows us to understand these two types of representations within the complex link which articulates the fascination and repulsion categories in a dialogic relationship largely participating in the renewed attractiveness of the square and in the force of its representation in the tourist imaginary. Finally, the complex understanding of the tourism implementation in the Jemaa El Fna site allows us to develop an analysis of globalisation which goes past the mere denunciation of its standardising aspects (Brunel, 2006). Henceforth, we shall prefer a description of globalised industries, such as that of tourism, as forces of cultural differentiation (Warnier, 1999) and hybridisation (Coëffé et al., 2007), in that they alter, standardise, museify and stage some cultural practices as much as they preserve, nurture, modify or generate new ones. “From this point of view, tourism may first appear as a hybridisation agent. Not only are the actors of the tourism sphere capable of updating, reformulating and combining the elements by giving them a new form which often allows the survival of moribund cultural elements, they may also make the diversification of spacetimes possible in the social organisation of ‘local societies’” (Coëffé, 2007, p. 95). Thus agreeing with food socio-anthropologists (Fischler, 1990 ; Poulain, 2002), Coëffé and Violier use the example of McDonald’s as an illustration of “the dialogism of uniformisation and of differentiation which affects globalisation” (Coëffé and Violier, 2008, p. 10). This convergence between tourism studies and food sociology allows us to draw the coherence of our various grounds for the application of the comparative methodology of diverse case studies. Besides, following Castoriadis (1975) as regards the imaginary, Fischler (1990), Poulain (2002) concerning nourishment, or Picard (1992) and Coëffé (et al., 2007) about tourism, and whether considering cultural practices or representations, the Jemaa El Fna griots or the Moroccan culinary techniques and habits, it seems that the phenomena generated by their confrontation with globalised industries, such as cultural tourism or mass-retailing, always deserve to be analysed and described from a dialogic perspective which does not evade the natural complexities of human cultures and moves away from reductive simplifications (Morin, 1990).
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Amirou R., 1994, « Le tourisme comme objet transitionnel », Espaces et Sociétés, n° 76, 149-164.</reference>
        <reference>Amirou R., 2000, Imaginaire du tourisme culturel, Paris, PUF.</reference>
        <reference>Amirou R., 2008, « Le Paradis, c’est les autres. Isolat relationnel et expérience du paradis: une entrée par le tourisme », Articulo – Journal of Urban Research, n° 4, http://articulo.revues.org/179.</reference>
        <reference>Andrews M., 1989, The Search of the Picturesque. Landscape and Tourism in Britain, 1760-1800, Stanford , Stanford University Press.</reference>
        <reference>Arrif A., 2006, « Place publique pour une parole publique: Jama‘ Lafna, ou le territoire du malentendu », La pensée de midi, 1er trimestre, n° 17, 144-149.</reference>
        <reference>Barthel P.-A., 2004, « Enchanter les touristes en médina: mises en scène et construction de lieux orientalisants. Les cas de Tunis et de Yasmine Hammamet (Tunisie) », atelier « Enchantement, réenchantement des territoires ? » (sous la direction de F. Bruyas et G. Gillot), Afemam.</reference>
        <reference>Becker H. S., 1985, Outsiders: étude de sociologie de la déviance, Paris , Éditions A.M. Metailé.</reference>
        <reference>Becker H. S., 1986, « Biographie et mosaïque scientifique », Actes de la recherche en sciences sociales, vol. 62-63, juin, 105-110.</reference>
        <reference>Bennani-Chraïbi M., 1997, « Jeunes Égyptiens et jeunes Marocains face à l’Occident », Égypte/Monde arabe, Première série, 30-31.</reference>
        <reference>Berriane M., 1989, Tourisme national et migrations de loisirs au Maroc, thèse de doctorat de géographie, Université de Tours.</reference>
        <reference>Berriane M., 1993, « Le tourisme des nationaux au Maroc. Une nouvelle approche du tourisme dans les pays en développement », Annales de Géographie, n° 570, 131-161.</reference>
        <reference>Bertrand M.-J., 1984, « Une approche de la forme urbaine et de la centralité. Des indices de localisation et d’affinités d’équipements publics », Annales de Géographie, n° 520, 666-686.</reference>
        <reference>Blanchet A., 1989, « Les relances de l’interviewer dans l’entretien de recherche: leurs effets sur la modalisation et la déictisation du discours de l’interviewé », L’année psychologique, vol. 89, n° 3, 367-391.</reference>
        <reference>Bonard Y. &amp; Felli R., 2008, « Patrimoine et tourisme urbain. La valorisation de l’authenticité à Lyon et Pékin », Articulo – Journal of Urban Research, 4, http://articulo.revues.org/719.</reference>
        <reference>Boujrouf S., 2001, « Acteurs et territoires touristiques de Marrakech », Géocarrefour, Le tourisme et la ville, vol. 76 n° 2, 91-97.</reference>
        <reference>Bourdieu P., Boltanski L., Castel R. &amp; Chamboredon J.C., 1965, Un art moyen,Essai sur les usages sociaux de la photographie, Paris, Éditions de Minuit.</reference>
        <reference>Boyer M., 2002, « Comment étudier le tourisme ? », Ethnologie française, 3ème trimestre, vol. 32, 393-404.</reference>
        <reference>Brunel S., 2006, La Planète disneylandisée, Paris, Sciences Humaines.</reference>
        <reference>Bruner E., 1991, « Transformation of self in tourism », Annals of Tourism Research, vol. 18, n° 2, 238-250.</reference>
        <reference>Bruneteaux P. et Lanzarini C., 1998, « Les entretiens informels », Sociétés Contemporaines, n° 30, 157-180.</reference>
        <reference>Castoriadis C., 1975, L’institution imaginaire de la société, Paris, Éditions du Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Cattedra, R., 2002, « Les métamorphoses de la ville. Urbanités, territorialités et espaces publics au Maroc », Géocarrefour, vol. 77, n° 3, 255-266.</reference>
        <reference>Chalfen R. M., 1979, « Photography’s role in tourism: some unexplored relationships », Annals of Tourism Research, vol. 6, n° 4, 435-437.</reference>
        <reference>Chamboredon H, Pavis F., Surdez M. et Willemez L., 1994, « S’imposer aux imposants. À propos de quelques obstacles rencontrés par des sociologues débutants dans la pratique et l’usage de l’entretien », Genèses, 16, 114- 132.</reference>
        <reference>Choplin M.-A. et Gatin, V., 2010, « L’espace public comme vitrine de la ville marocaine: conceptions et appropriations des places Jemaa El Fna à Marrakech, Boujloud à Fès et Al Mouahidine à Ouarzazate », Norois, 214.</reference>
        <reference>Cochoy, F., 2005, « L’hypermarché: jardin d’un autre type aux portes des villes », Ethnologie française, vol. 35, n° 1, pp. 81-91.</reference>
        <reference>Coëffé V., Pébarthe, H. et Violier, P., 2007, « Mondialisations et mondes touristiques » , L’Information géographique, n° 2 vol. 71, p. 83-96.</reference>
        <reference>Coëffé, V. et Violier, P., 2008, « Les lieux du tourisme: de quel(s) paradis parle-t-on ? Variations sur le thème de l’urbanité touristique », Articulo – Journal of Urban Research, vol. 4.</reference>
        <reference>Cohen E., 1988, « Traditions in the qualitative sociology of tourism », Annals of Tourism Research, vol. 15, 29-46.</reference>
        <reference>Conord S., 2002, « Le choix de l’image en anthropologie: qu’est-ce qu’une ” bonne ” photographie ? », ethnographiques.org, n° 2.</reference>
        <reference>Cousin S., 2006a, « De l’UNESCO aux villages de Touraine: les enjeux politiques, institutionnels et identitaires du tourisme culturel », Autrepart, n° 40, 15-30.</reference>
        <reference>Cousin S., 2006b, « Le “tourisme culturel”, un lieu commun ambivalent », Anthropologie et Sociétés, vol. 30, n° 2, 153-173.</reference>
        <reference>Demazière D., 2008, « L’entretien biographique comme interaction négociations, contre-interprétations, ajustements de sens », Langage &amp; société, vol. 1, n° 123, 15-35.</reference>
        <reference>Di Méo G., 2007, « Processus de patrimonialisation et construction des territoires », in Regards sur le patrimoine industriel, Actes du colloque de Poitiers Patrimoine et industrie en Poitou-Charentes: connaître pour valoriser, 12-14 septembre 2007, Poitiers-Châtellerault.</reference>
        <reference>Doquet A. &amp; Evrard O., 2008, « Introduction », Civilisations, vol. 57, 9-22.</reference>
        <reference>Dondero M. J., 2007, « Les pratiques photographiques du touriste entre construction d’identités et documentation », Communication et langages, n° 151, 21-37.</reference>
        <reference>Duchesne S., 1996, « Entretien non-préstructuré, stratégie de recherche et étude des représentations. Peut-on déjà faire l’économie de l’entretien non-directif en sociologie ? », Politix, vol. 9, n° 35, 189-206.</reference>
        <reference>Dujarier M.-A., 2008, Le travail du consommateur. De Mcdo à Ebay: comment nous coproduisons ce que nous achetons, Paris, La Découverte.</reference>
        <reference>Durand G., 1998, L’imagination symbolique, Paris, PUF.</reference>
        <reference>Équipe MIT, 2002, Tourismes 1. Lieux communs, Paris, Belin.</reference>
        <reference>Équipe MIT, 2005, Tourismes 2. Moments de lieux, Paris, Belin.</reference>
        <reference>Fine E.C. &amp; Haskell Speer J., 1985, « Tour guide performances as sight sacralization », Annals of Tourism Research, vol. 12, n° 1, 73-95.</reference>
        <reference>Fischler C., 2001, L’Homnivore, Paris, Odile Jacob.Forum Marocain du Tourisme (FMDT, Rapport d’évaluation du tourisme marocain 2000-2009, février 2010.</reference>
        <reference>Gatin V., 2008, « L’art populaire et le développement local sous le prisme de l’idéologie: au sujet de la place Jemaa el Fna à Marrakech », Actes du colloque: Arts et territoires. Vers une nouvelle économie culturelle, 76e Congrès de l’ACFAS, Québec, 6 et 7 mai 2008.</reference>
        <reference>Gauthier L., 2008, « L’Occident peut-il être exotique ? De la possibilité d’un exotisme inverse », Le Globe, Genève.</reference>
        <reference>Gauthier L., 2010, « Jemaa El Fna ou l’exotisme durable », Géographie et Cultures, n° 72, 117-136.</reference>
        <reference>Gay J.-C. &amp; Violier P., 2007, « Tous touristes ! Le Monde comme espace touristique », in Retaillé D. (dir.), La mondialisation, Paris, Nathan, 257-272.</reference>
        <reference>Gillespie A., 2006, « Tourist photography and the reverse gaze », Ethos, vol. 34, n° 3, 343-366.</reference>
        <reference>Giraud M.O., 2002, « Esthétiques de l’authenticité. Tourisme et touristes chez les Hmong de Guyane française », Ethnologie française, vol. 32, n° 3, 447-459.</reference>
        <reference>Goytisolo J., 1997, « Un espace magique de sociabilité. Jemâa-el-fna, patrimoine oral de l’humanité », Le Monde diplomatique, juin, 9-13.</reference>
        <reference>Goytisolo J., 1999, « Jemâa El Fna, l’univers des diseurs d’histoires », Sources, n° 113, juin, 15.</reference>
        <reference>Goytisolo J., 2000, « Les mille et une nuit de la place », Le Courrier de l’UNESCO, Décembre, , 34-36.</reference>
        <reference>Graburn N., 1983, « Anthropology of Tourism », Annals of Tourism Research, n° 10, 9-34.</reference>
        <reference>Harper D., 2002, « Talking about pictures: a case for photo elicitation », Visual Studies, vol. 17, n° 1, 13-26.</reference>
        <reference>Hauteserre (d’) A.M., 2009, « L’altérité et le tourisme: construction du soi et d’une identité sociale », Espace populations sociétés, n° 2, 279-291.</reference>
        <reference>Hillali M., 2007, « Du tourisme et de la géopolitique au Maghreb: le cas du Maroc », Hérodote, vol. 4, n° 127, 47-63.</reference>
        <reference>Knafou R., 1991, « L’invention du lieu touristique: la passation d’un contrat et le surgissement simultané d’un nouveau territoire », Revue de géographie alpine, vol. 79, n° 4. 11-19.</reference>
        <reference>Knafou R., 1996, « Introduction. La transformation des lieux anciennement touristiques », Méditerranée, vol. 84, n° 3, 3-4.</reference>
        <reference>Kurzac-Souali A.-C., 2007, « Rumeurs et cohabitation en médina de Marrakech: l’étranger où on ne l’attendait pas », Hérodote, 4.</reference>
        <reference>Lahire B., 2001, L’homme pluriel. Les ressorts de l’action, Paris, Armand Colin.</reference>
        <reference>Latouche S., 1989, L’occidentalisation du monde, Paris, La Découverte.</reference>
        <reference>Lazarotti O., 2000, « Patrimoine et tourisme: un couple de la mondialisation », Mappemonde, n° 57, 12-16.</reference>
        <reference>L’économiste, « Touristes à Marrakech: harcèlement, coups de poing et indifférence », édition n° 227 du 25/04/1996.</reference>
        <reference>L’économiste, « Marrakech renoue avec ses touristes », édition n° 253 du 07/11/1996.</reference>
        <reference>L’économiste, « Tapis marocains: opération de charme sur la place Jamaâ el Fna », édition n° 514 du 25/05/1999.</reference>
        <reference>L’économiste, « Les chasseurs de ryads s’activent à Marrakech », édition n° 985 du 29/03/2001.</reference>
        <reference>L’économiste, « Marrakech: ruée des investisseurs dans l’ancienne médina », édition n° 997 du 16/04/2001.</reference>
        <reference>L’économiste, « Marrakech: le devenir de Jamaa El fna inquiète ses défenseurs », édition n° 1875 du 14/10/2004.</reference>
        <reference>Le Velly R., 2007, « Les démonstrateurs de foire. Des professionnels de l’interaction symbolique », Ethnologie française, vol. 37, 143-151.</reference>
        <reference>Le Monde, « Pour les djihadistes salafistes, Marrakech est symbole de débauche: entretien avec Lhoussain Azergui », Édition en ligne du 29/04/11.</reference>
        <reference>Leroux S., 2007, « Les temporalités des touristes itinérants dans le Sud marocain ou la quête de liberté », Espace populations sociétés, n° 3, 273-284.</reference>
        <reference>MacCannell D., 1989, The Tourist, A New Theory of the Leisure Class, New-York, Shocken Books, deuxième édition.</reference>
        <reference>Michelat G., 1975, « Sur l’utilisation de l’entretien non directif en sociologie », Revue française de sociologie, vol. 16,n° 2, 229- 247.</reference>
        <reference>Miossec J.-M., 1977, « L’image touristique comme introduction à la géographie du tourisme », Annales de Géographie, n° 473, 55-70.</reference>
        <reference>Morin E., 1990, Introduction à la pensée complexe, Paris, ESF éditeur.</reference>
        <reference>Morin E., 1973, Le paradigme perdu: la nature humaine, Paris, Éditions du Seuil.</reference>
        <reference>Olivier de Sardan J.-P., 1995, « La politique du terrain. Sur la production des données en anthropologie », Enquête, n° 1, 71-109.</reference>
        <reference>Petonnet C., 1982, « L’observation flottante. L’exemple d’un cimetière parisien. », L’Homme, vol. 22, 37-47.</reference>
        <reference>Picard M., 1992, Bali. Tourisme culturel et culture touristique, Paris, L’Harmattan.</reference>
        <reference>Picard D. &amp; Robinson P. (ed.), 2009, The Framed World: Tourism, Tourists and photography, Londres, Ashgate.</reference>
        <reference>Picon A., 2001, « Espaces publics: espaces dangereux », Géocarrefour, vol. 76, n° 1, 23-26.</reference>
        <reference>Piette, A., 1996, Ethnographie de l’action, L’observation des détails, Paris, Métailié.</reference>
        <reference>Pinçon M. &amp; Pinçon-Charlot M., 1991, « Pratiques d’enquête dans l’aristocratie et la grande bourgeoisie: distance sociale et conditions spécifiques de l’entretien semi-directif », Genèses, 3, 120-133.</reference>
        <reference>Poulain J.-P., 2002, Sociologie de l’alimentation, Paris, PUF.</reference>
        <reference>Raffestin C., 1986, « Nature et culture du lieu touristique », Méditerranée, Troisième série, vol. 58, 11-17.</reference>
        <reference>Roussillon A., 2010, « À propos de quelques paradoxes de l’appropriation identitaire du patrimoine », in Cattedra R., Garret P., Miller C. et Volait M. (dir.), Patrimoines en situation. Constructions et usages en différents contextes urbains, Beyrouth / Rabat, Presses de l’Ifpo / Centre Jacques Berque (« Études contemporaines »).</reference>
        <reference>Salazar N. B., 2009, « Imaged or imagined ? Cultural representations and the « tourismification » of peoples and places », Cahiers d’études africaines, n° 193-194, 49-72.Schechner R., 1977, Essays on Performance Theory (1970-1976), New York, Drama Book Specialists.</reference>
        <reference>Schmitt T. M., 2005, « Jemaa el Fna Square in Marrakech: changes to a social space and to a UNESCO Masterpiece of the Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity as a result of global influences », The Arab world geographer, vol. 8, n° 4, 173-195.</reference>
        <reference>Simon G., 2008, « La puissance prescriptive des guides à Paris », Articulo – Journal of Urban Research, n° 4, http://articulo.revues.org/279.</reference>
        <reference>Skounti A. et Tebbaa O., 2005, La place Jemaa El Fna: patrimoine culturel immatériel de Marrakech, du Maroc et de l’Humanité, Éditions de l’UNESCO.</reference>
        <reference>Smith V. L., 1989, Hosts and Guests: The Anthropology of Tourism, Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Press.</reference>
        <reference>Sontag S., 1978, On Photography, New York, Farrar, Straus and Giroux.</reference>
        <reference>Staszak J.-F., 2006, « Voyage et circulation des images… », S. &amp; R., n° 21, 79-99.</reference>
        <reference>Suchar C. S., 1997, « Grounding Visual Sociology Research In Shooting Scripts », Qualitative Sociology, vol. 20, n° 1.</reference>
        <reference>Tabassir S.-A., 1994, « Jama’ el-Fna. Place complexe », Horizons Maghrébins, n° 23/24, 93-99.</reference>
        <reference>Toufiq A., 2001, Place Jama’ L-Fna, Marrakech-Maroc: patrimoine de l’humanité, Ministère de la culture et de la communication, Maroc.</reference>
        <reference>Turner V., 1987, The Anthropology of Perfomance, New York , PAJ Publications.</reference>
        <reference>Urry J., 1990, The Tourist Gaze, Leisure and Travel in Contemporaries Societies, Londres, Sage.</reference>
        <reference>Vacher H., 2010, « La planification de la sauvegarde et le détour marocain (1912-1925) », in Cattedra R., Garret P., Miller C. &amp; Volait M. (dir.), Patrimoines en situation. Constructions et usages en différents contextes urbains, Beyrouth / Rabat, Presses de l’Ifpo / Centre Jacques Berque (« Études contemporaines »).</reference>
        <reference>Vialles N., 1987, Le sang et la chair. Les abattoirs du pays de l’Adour, Paris, Maison des sciences de l’Homme.</reference>
        <reference>Vision 2010, 2001, Accord cadre, Marrakech.</reference>
        <reference>Vision 2010, 2001, Accord d’application de l’accord cadre, Agadir.</reference>
        <reference>Wacquant L., 2000, Corps et âme: Carnets ethnographiques d’un apprenti boxeur, Paris, Agone.</reference>
        <reference>Warnier J.-P., 1999, La mondialisation de la culture, Paris, Éditions La découverte.</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">The researchers in social sciences agree on the fact that the cultural place is a construction (Raffestin, 1986; Knafou, 1991; Coëffé et Violier, 2008). Thus, if “the invention of the touristic place is initiated through a diversion of the traditional purpose of the territory which (…) meaning changes” (Knafou, 1991, p.16), it simultaneously requires “an unspoken contract between the local society and the global society” (Ibid., p.19) to be concluded, which henceforth allows to evoke a co-invention process.</note>
        <note id="2">We thus use some contentions of the non-directive interview methodology (Michelat, 1975; Duchesne, 1996).</note>
        <note id="3">About participatory and clandestine observations, see Becker (1985) in particular. Besides, Wacquant’s works (2000) remain in our opinion a crucial influence. As regards informal interviews, we shall quote Pétonnet’s (1982) methodological plea, Olivier de Sardan’s guidelines (1995) who regards it as a tool of immersion, or Bruneteaux and Lanzarini’s researches. More recently, Le Velly (2007) resorted to informal interviews during an investigation on fair demonstrators. We may also quote Dujarier’s example who mentions the idea of «conversing observation» (2008: 18).</note>
        <note id="4">As regards the interview situation, as well as the possible strategies to get around them, see Blanchet, 1989; Pinçon and Pinçon-Charlot, 1991; Chamboredon et al.,1994; Demazière, 2008.</note>
        <note id="5">Photography, in the context of socio-anthropological context, is an efficient complement to note-taking and limits the “loss of details” related to the simplifications which occur during the process of scientific writing of the description (Piette, 1996). It is however obvious that photography does not eliminate the “loss of details” as the “technical, cultural, social and aesthetic” (Conord, 2002) choices similarly lead to make a selection in the representation of reality.</note>
        <note id="6">The relationship between tourism practices and the production of images has been thoroughly investigated by authors, whether analysing the way in which travel practices and types of tourist photography converge (Dondero, 2007), pointing out the close link between tourist photography and family pictures (Bourdieu et al., 1965), understanding tourist photography as a tool for recording through the capture of images (Picard et Robinson, 2009), as a way of memorizing and witnessing presence (Sontag, 1978), as a production of stereotyped material fuelling a closed-circuit of representations (Urry, 1990). It has eventually been closely studied through questioning the local impact of the practice of photography (Staszak, 2006; Salazar, 2009) and reciprocally the influence of the indigenous look on this practice (Chalfen, 1979; Gillespie, 2006).</note>
        <note id="7">The request to the tourists interviewed rested on a “selection of snapshots illustrating the visit OF Marrakesh and what had impressed them”. We received a total of 52 pictures, among which 23 had a direct link with the square. The 19 respondents supplied at least one picture of the square or mentioned it in their comments. This methodology largely draws from “photo elicitation”, albeit partially.</note>
        <note id="8">In this context, the search for alterity as a justification for the trip is rooted in a feeling of nostalgia (Raffestin, 1986, p.12).</note>
        <note id="9">The historical facts upon which marketing communication concerning the Jemaa El Fna square rest have never been clearly established. “The origins of the Jemaa El Fna square are obscure and date back to a remote time, thus merging with the history of the city. The historical texts have referred to it, though indirectly, ever since the creation of Marrakesh.” (Skounti et Tebbaa, 2006, p. 25). The most commonly accepted translation of the name ‘Jemaa El Fna’ is ‘the square of the assembly of the dead’, as a reference to the executions which used to take place there, although other translations are often suggested. In this regards, see in particular Gauthier, 2010.</note>
        <note id="10">The analysis of the Moroccan economic press reflects problems related to security and harassment of tourists (The Economist, edition n° 227, 25/04/1996, « Touristes à Marrakech: harcèlement, coups de poing et indifférence » [Tourists in Marrakesh: harassment, fighting and indifference] and edition n° 253, 07/11/1996, « Marrakech renoue avec ses touristes » [Marrakesh makes up with its tourists]). Gatin argues: “As far as the local authorities are concerned, it has progressively become inconceivable to offer visitors and media from around the world an image of poverty and insecurity. As a result, numerous police officers (in uniform or plain clothes) patrol day and night to provide security to the tourists. The selling behaviours have also been regulated in order to minimise nuisances to the tourists. Consequently, the Jemaa El Fna square which appeared to the cultural actors as a space of freedom has gradually become a supervised and highly controlled space (Gatin, 2008, p. 13). In this sense, many developments in the square after its listing by UNESCO form part of a rationale of “tourism re-implementation” (Knafou, 1996, p.4).</note>
        <note id="11">Fine and Haskell Speer (1985) underline this narrative process which accompanies the stages of the “sacralisation of the place” (MacCannell, 1989) by focalising on the narrative and rhetorical performance of the tourist guides.</note>
        <note id="12">This westernisation is denounced by one part of the population and by some extremist movements (Le Monde, « Pour les djihadistes salafistes, Marrakech est symbole de débauche: entretien avec Lhoussain Azergui » [According to the Salafist djihadists, Marrakesh is a symbol of depravity: an interview with Lhoussain Azergui], online publication, 29th April 2011).</note>
        <note id="13">Staszak describes the extent to which the representations of Tahiti are linked to stereotyped images and adds: “the prodution of images on site does not operate without mediation: the photographer and painter choose and compose their scenes according to the images they already have in their eyes or mind” (Staszak, 2006, p. 91). See also Urry, 1990 ou Boyer, 2002.</note>
        <note id="14">The selections indeed presented important subjects and framing redundancy which confirm some authors’ statements on the predetermined and stereotyped character of some of the tourists’ shootings (Urry, 1990; Boyer, 2002; Staszak, 2006; Simon, 2008).</note>
        <note id="15">As an example, it is worth mentioning the tooth-puller who exposes his tools and dental harvest. The sale of souvenir pictures represents the essential part of his income; he clearly explains that his goal is to exploit the tourist’s search for images (Arrif, 2006), one of an authenticity and exoticism perceived in a downgrading way and intermingling with much attraction, fascination, disgust and repulsion.</note>
        <note id="16">The darija is the Arabic dialect almost exclusively used in oral communication in Morocco.</note>
        <note id="17">The term harqua designates the cercle of spectators which forms around the storyteller and actively and financially participates in the evolution of the story being told. See Berriane, 1989.</note>
        <note id="18">The Gnawas are the members of a brotherhood which rites include songs and trances. These repertoires are being re-interpreted in the square in syncretic versions intented for foreign and Moroccan tourists. This phenomenon may be compared to those described by Picard (1992) or Coëffé (2007) in Bali and Hawaï. “The dance staged in the universe of tourism is irreductible to the whole of the local repertoire (…). For all that, it is not a fool’s bargain as the time of the tourism experience, by definition short, does not allow the tourists to integrate the most sophisticated codes which make the reading and also the understanding of local ‘nuances’ possible» (Coëffé et Violier, 2008, p.9).</note>
        <note id="19">With this idea of an authencity nurtured by its own staging, we agree with Coëffé who presents the tourism space as an “incubating refuge” for some forms of new cultural and syncretic practices (2007, p.93). Even more so, we subscibe to the vision of a touristic space which ensures some protection to practices which “would no doubt have disappeared if they had not been reactivated” (2008, p.9).</note>
        <note id="20">It is noticeable that once “once disparaged by the Protectorate then by the local elites, the medinas are now coveted and reinvested by western people who are fascinated by these exotic settings” (Kurzac-Souali, 2008, p.65) . See also The Economist, n°985, 29th March 2001, « Les chasseurs de ryads s’activent à Marrakech » [Ryads chasers are at work in Marrakesh]; The Economist, n°997, 16th April 2001, « Marrakech: ruée des investisseurs dans l’ancienne médina » [Marrakesh: investors rush into the medina]. On this phenomenon and its analysis through the concept of moment of place, see also MIT Team, 2005.</note>
        <note id="21">Bennani-Chraïbi well describes this fascination-repulsion relationship concerning young Moroccans and Egyptians in contact with tourist populations (Bennani Chraïbi, 2008). Boyer also insists on this search for the spectacle of peoples “which physical appearance, habits and practices are subject to both attractiveness and repulsion” (2002, p. 400).</note>
        <note id="22">According to a griot we met, there would only be about six storytellers left acting more or less frequently on the square today, whereas they were about twenty in the 1970s who used to perform daily in the morning and in the evening.</note>
    </notes>
</article>