<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_TTLHPD_34-125_Tm_0" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5127" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.5127</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>17</numero>
        <annee>2020</annee>
    </meta>
    <traductions>
        <original lang="fr" source="5093">
            <traducteur nom="Kassouha" prenom="Zeid A." />
            La place des espaces ruraux périphériques dans la construction par et pour le tourisme de l’identité de la région de Dalat (Vietnam)
        </original>
        <traduction lang="it" source="5186">L’importanza delle aree rurali periferiche nella costruzione da parte e per il turismo dell’identità della regione di Dalat (Vietnam)</traduction>
    </traductions>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Thi Lan Huong" prenom="Truong">
            <description>
                Faculté du Tourisme, Dalat University, Vietnam 
            </description>
        </auteur>
        <auteur nom="Dérioz" prenom="Pierre">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_PDPBEG_9-57_Lx_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5062" lang="fr">Le paysage comme ressource touristique des espaces ruraux</publication>
                <publication id="fr_TTLHPD_36-132_Lm_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/5093" lang="fr">La place des espaces ruraux périphériques dans la construction par et pour le tourisme de l’identité de la région de Dalat (Vietnam)</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                UMR 228 Espace-Dev, Avignon University 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>The place of peripheral rural areas in the construction, by and for tourism, of the identity of the region of Dalat (Vietnam)</titre>
    <sousTitre>Peer-reviewed article</sousTitre>
    <resume>
        The objective of this article is to understand the place that peripheral spaces and landscapes hold in matters of tourism development, both in the tourist offer and in the construction of the local identity of a region where main center attractor is the city of Dalat, a recognized tourist destination in the Highlands of Vietnam. This study analyzes the way in which the components of these spaces (physical elements, activities and image) contribute to the identity of the Dalat region, based on the in-situ study, official documents, photographs, maps and semi-structured interviews with different local stakeholders. The results show that peripheral spaces have occupied and still occupy an important place in the tourist development of the city and in its image as a destination. But there is for the moment no or very few interactions between these peripheral zones, of which absolute dependence on the center restricts their dynamism and their possibilities of opening.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            Peripheral spaces have always been perceived as a problematic socio-spatial category not only in sociology, spatial planning or geography (Steinführer et al. 2016) but also in tourism, since the periphery has often remained outside the scope of tourism development (Miternique and Marcotte, 2014). Their marginalization in relation to tourist routes is often the result of "<em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">several shortcomings: lack of accessibility, inland transport, information, major attractions, specialized labor, political and economic power</span></em>" (Müller and Jansson, 2007; Hall, 2007, cited in Miternique and Marcotte, 2014). However, outlying areas can also attract travelers "<em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">in search of the original and mythical essence of travel, or in search of areas that are not very crowded and not much transformed by the tourism industry [...]</span></em>" (Hiernaux, 1996, quoted in Miternique and Marcotte, 2014), to whom peripheral rural areas offer “<em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">calm and natural landscape conducive to their activities</span></em>” (Hall, 2007, quoted in Miternique and Marcotte, 2014) especially for the contemporary forms of alternative and experiential tourism.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            The very notion of peripheral space, which implicitly refers to a position of remoteness but also to a relationship of dependence towards a central space (Reynaud, 1992), can be understood at very different scales. Applied to tourism on a global scale, it can refer to areas which appear to be far from the major flows of international tourism, at the risk of ignoring the extent of the tourist industry in countries such as Vietnam, where this tourism is predominantly domestic (Peyvel, 2017). Taken on the scale of a country, it may designate more or less marginalized rural regions, as opposed to metropolitan areas which concentrate economic activity, wealth and power. On a larger scale, it simply corresponds to the rural or even peri-urban spaces which surround an urban center, depend on it, and participate more or less actively in its development, possibly including tourism. Although tourism appears to be "<em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">primarily an urban phenomenon, both in terms of the origin of the majority of visitors and their destination</span></em>" (Ibanescu, 2012 referring to Duhamel and Sacareau, 1998, p. 44), the development of new forms of tourism in peripheral spaces can also contribute to the promotion of the territorial identity of the whole destination organized around a city, through local development initiatives aimed at building representations of the place (Kneafsey, 2000). 
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            The term “<em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">place identity</span></em>” can be understood in different ways in different disciplines. In spatial planning, place identity refers to the distinctiveness or uniqueness of a place, and results from the interaction between its physical characteristics and its users (Kaymaz, 2013). But in environmental psychology, place identity refers to the cognitive integration of the parameters of the familiar physical environment within the conscious or unconscious psychic self-regulation processes of individuals (Korpela, 1989). The notion of place identity can thus be approached both through the social interpretation of the physical and functional characteristics of place, and from the emotional aspects of environmental experience.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            Adapted from the work of Montgomery (1998) and Ujang (2012), our study, based on a doctoral thesis focusing on the issues of local typicity and authenticity in the tourist experience (Truong 2019), identifies three articulated components in the construction of local identity: (1) physical elements, (2) activities and (3) image (see Document 1). The first component encompasses natural environmental features (relief elements, watercourses, forests, etc.) or artificial features (such as infrastructures or buildings) and contributes for individuals to the cognition of places in terms of form and function (Ujang, 2012). Activities include all forms of interactions and social practices induced by tourism. The images, finally, are those projected, perceived and manipulated by the various actors involved in the field of tourism (Truong, 2019, pp. 79-80). These images convey meaning and symbols (Relph, 1976) and can mobilize history, stories, legends or even toponymy (Stephenson 2008).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">While the question of identity is often addressed in urban spaces in connection with attachment to the urban place (Ujang, 2012), the identity of the urban landscape (Kaymaz, 2013) or its cultural dimension (Ziyaee, 2017), this work is less concerned with marginalized spaces and peripheral areas, and even less with the articulation between urban spaces and rural peripheries. The latter, however, are likely to host the development of alternative forms of tourism, which sometimes represent new economic options and/or allow a better distribution of the flows affecting highly concentrated urban areas (Miternique and Marcotte, 2014). Considered as a complement or counterpoint to the forms of tourism which characterize the central areas, the tourist phenomena that appear in peripheral rural areas can thus become important drivers of change by promoting, in these areas, proactive conservation and landscape planning, active citizenship and a dynamic tourist economy (Salvatore </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2018). They may also have a role to play in improving the living conditions and social situation of marginalized or minority groups at the scale of the destination as a whole. The reconsideration of the tourism potential and function of peripheral areas in the planning and management of tourism supply within the overall territorial system, leads then in some cases to the activation of local elements (landscape, natural, historical or cultural heritage...), and their incorporation into the definition of the territorial identity (Salvatore </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2018). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The objective of this paper is to understand the role of peripheral spaces and landscapes, in terms of tourism development, in the construction of the local identity of a region whose main attracting center is the city of Dalat (229,614 inhabitants)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, a renowned tourist resort in Vietnam’s Central Highlands. The research focuses in particular on the way in which peripheral spaces of different natures, whether rural (terroirs, cultivated and villages, cf. Ducourtieux et al. 2017) or natural (national park, cf. Déry and Tremblay 2008), are integrated into the overall tourist offer of the Dalat "destination" and are articulated (or not) with its more urban components. Particular attention is paid here to the valorization of the different landscape atmospheres as well as to the forms taken by the tourist promotion of the cultural heritage of the minority ethnic groups of the region. The aim here is to evaluate both the tourism developed part of the peripheral areas themselves (material dimension), and the symbolic place attributed to them in the system of representations which underlies the identity of this destination (representational dimension).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Created ex nihilo in 1893, on the basis of a predefined plan, as a French resort in Indochina, Dalat soon became a well-known tourist town in Vietnam, with a strong local identity, even if historical events have led to different forms of visits according to the considered periods. Although the resort originally appeared in a "peripheral" region on the scale of what was then Indochina, it very quickly established itself, in a few decades, as a major tourist center. The analysis of the position of its peripheral areas, must therefore also take into account the legacies of this history, even though contemporary strategies envisage a continuation of the very rapid tourist development of recent years (cf. document 3), with the strengthening of the recent opening to the international tourist market. This analysis raises from the outset the question of the definition of these spaces - nature, degree of remoteness and mode of contact with the central city, extension and spatial depth. The city of Dalat, capital of Lam Dong province, currently consists of 12 wards and 4 communes, but the latest development plan approved by the State for the period 2030 to 2050 should lead to an enlargement, both spatial (from 39,440 ha to 335,930 ha) and demographic (640,000 to 680,000 inhabitants envisaged for 2030)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> of Dalat, which will then integrate parts of the four other outlying districts (Duc Trong, Don Duong, Lac Duong and Lam Ha). In this study, the rural peripheral areas will include the above-mentioned districts, the four communes (Ta Nung, Xuan Tho, Xuan Truong and Tram Hanh), and a part of Wards 3, 4, 7, 8, 12 which are located outside a radius of 10 km from the current Dalat city center (See Document 2).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Applying the model of place identity proposed above, this study sought to identify the components of Dalat identity, based on fieldwork, available bibliography and analysis of official documents and plans of strategic orientation and planning, attempting to distinguish the role and contribution of peripheral spaces. The research is also based on semi-directive interviews with thirty local experts (managers, suppliers, researchers), focusing on the components of Dalat identity, which also shed nuanced light on the place of peripheral spaces. Data collection was carried out between December 2016 and July 2018.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">I. From a mountain margin to a large urban tourist center: historical analysis of the place of peripheral areas in Dalat region </section>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">First developed in the 1920s as a sanatorium, a high-altitude tourist resort and the political center of the Indochinese Union (Tessier </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013), the colonial town was originally thought of as a holiday and open-air leisure resort for the French colonists, whose attraction rested above all on the temperate climate and the surrounding pine forests. From the very beginning, these forests were used for walking and driving excursions as well as various sports activities (Jennings and Larcher-Goscha (Trad.) 2013). Several places, including the Dankia and Tuyen Lam areas in the Langbiang mountains, have also been frequented by hunters. Dalat’s coat of arms featured back then the Langbiang mountain, a K’ho couple and the silhouette of a tiger (Document 4). These images are often used in Dalat tourism promotion materials such as the "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Petit guide illustré</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" (Little Illustrated Guide) (Document 4).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The first hunting guide dedicated to the Langbiang plateau was published in 1912 (Tessier et al., 2013), forms of agritourism can be observed with farms producing, for example, salads or strawberries, as well as bourbon coffee plantations (Don Duong, across the Dran pass). These activities then correspond mainly to one-day excursions. The estimated number of tourists increased from 1,165 in 1933-1934 to 4,945 in 1937-1938, mostly French and members of the Indochinese elite (Jennings and Larcher-Goscha, 2013).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Document no. 5 clearly shows that a large part of the tourist activities in the Dalat region take place in peripheral areas which offer many possibilities for excursions, ranging from discovering the local cultures of the K’ho ethnic groups at the foot of the Langbiang mountain, to visiting natural sites (waterfalls, forests) or hunting, regarded as a typical tourist product of the region. The resort of Dalat itself is reserved for vacationing, accommodation or leisure activities such as golf. From the beginning of development, the peripheral area thus plays a role as a tourist attraction, while the urban center provides basic travel services such as accommodation, catering or entertainment. The relationship between the central and peripheral areas is essential for the tourist development of the city. Even the images which symbolize Dalat in tourism promotion documents mobilize pictures of the periphery. These peripheral activities are important for the attractiveness of the city, but they are not taken into account in the planning of the city itself, even though they are gradually giving rise to the development of sites and itineraries.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">During the period 1945-1975, despite the war, this initial model of European elite tourism was extended to the elites of South Vietnam. "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The resort had something to offer for everyone, including lovers</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" (Jennings and Larcher-Goscha (Trad.), 2013, p. 237). The city, whose population grew from 5,200 in 1946 to 83,800 in 1975, became "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">the major destination in South Vietnam</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" with activities, which continued to combine excursions or hunting in the outskirts and resorting in the urban center (See Document 6) (Truong, 2019). The demographic increase and a strategy mobilizing education gave the city a more varied cultural life (schools, libraries, music, cinemas, cafés, tea rooms, etc.), contributing to the emergence of new intellectual and civilized values, “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">European-styled</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”, and reinforcing Dalat’s identity as a "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">city of knowledge, culture and tourism</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" (Truong, 2019). However, this tourist development occurs mainly in the urban areas, as the city gradually expands to integrate new tourist facilities (Lien Khuong Airport, Prenn Falls, Love Valley). The peripheral areas only serve as a landscape background, mobilized in the service of the city’s image. Thus, the communication efforts made by the Diem government to promote the romantic Dalat, nicknamed the "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">city of dreams</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" as of 1950 (Tessier </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">., 2013), also rely heavily on peripheral natural components made more accessible by new developments. Document no 7 demonstrates the prominence in the 1960s of images of mountains, pine forests and streams on tourist promotion posters or in the illustrations of guides, depicting hunting activities or landscape visits in the surroundings of Dalat.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            After the country’s reunification in 1975, Dalat maintained its role as the country’s tourist centre receiving groups of Vietnamese officials and experts from the Soviet Union, then a new wave of international tourists starting from the implementation of the "<em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Doi moi</span></em>" renovation policy (1986 - Đổi mới) between 1986 and 1991. In 1992, Dalat received 261,305 tourists (among whom only 29,874 were foreigners), which was then twice the population of the city
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The creation of the lakes in the vicinity of Dalat, which was primarily for agricultural purposes, embellishes the landscape and reinforces its romantic character. Even if this period marked a certain decline in their visits (Document 8), and although they were hardly taken into consideration in the spatial plans and the tourism development policies of the city at that time, the peripheral areas still occupied an important symbolic place in the identity of Dalat. Document no 9 shows a handicraft picture featuring the symbols of Dalat’s city centre (Thuy Ta restaurant at Xuan Huong lake) and its outskirts (the pine forests, animals) made of sawn pine wood, a popular handicraft at the time producing souvenirs for tourists and for export.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The identity of Dalat from the end of the 20th century appears to be equally influenced by its colonial relics and landmarks as by the contemporary efforts of the authorities to develop a poetic and romantic image of the city (Jennings and Larcher-Goscha, 2013). The colonial myth, the successive transformations of the city, the imagination produced in connection with its tourist development, its reputation as an innovative city with "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">authentic</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" landscapes, have forged Dalat’s own identity. Beyond its original composite image of a “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">landscape-city</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">” (Tessier </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2013), the systematic inventory of the various physical or human elements that shape the identity of the Dalat region in official documents, studies and interviews with local experts (Table 1), shows that sites and images referring to peripheral spaces also played an important role, from the outset. This observation probably conceals the fact that the very idea of the creation of the city in the 19th century was born out of the recognition of the virtues of the pre-existing geographical environment in what was then a peripheral space. These characteristics were incorporated into the image of the city from the outset.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Table 1 attempts to give an account of the constituent elements of this identity (Truong et al. 2018), by distinguishing those which characterize the region as a whole from those which appear specifically urban, or which, on the contrary, belong to peripheral spaces. The characteristics of Dalat and its environs listed in the table result from systematic content analysis of official documents</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn4" id="bodyftn4">4</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> (Dalat monographs, studies on Dalat commissioned by the Lam Dong Department of Science and Technology) and interviews in which local experts evoke the constitutive elements of place identity (physical elements, human activities, images/representations). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Social activities and practices turn out to be quite diverse, as this region is a place of multi-ethnic and multi-origin cohabitation, a reflection of the city’s history. This mix of populations contributes to the specificity of the identity of the city not only in terms of the landscape but also through the lifestyle or even the nicknames of the city.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">As far as the physical elements are concerned, it is clear that the peripheral areas contribute greatly to Dalat’s identity as a landscape-city with mountains (mainly Langbiang and Bidoup mountains at Lac Duong), forests (Bidoup-Nuiba National Park), waterfalls, lakes (in Wards 3, 8 and in the districts of Lac Duong, Duc Trong, Lam Ha) and agricultural areas in the vicinity of Dalat. Traditional anthropogenic elements such as the K’Ho longhouses or the gong culture also refer above all to the peripheral areas (Lac Duong and Don Duong). In tourism, natural attractions and mountain resorts take advantage of the natural environment of the periphery to become the typical tourist products of the city (Truong, 2019).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">With regard to the human activities involved in the construction of the Dalat identity in the peripheral areas, the indigenous ethnic groups with their customs, architecture and rituals represent, in appearance, important inherited values, related to the "authentic" part of Dalat. The Langbiang mountain with its imposing silhouette and its legend</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn5" id="bodyftn5">5</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> at Lac Duong was and still is a significant symbolic landmark in the overall image of Dalat (see Document 10). Less explicitly, finally, the nicknames of the city such as "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">city of dreams</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">", "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">city of fog</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">", which suggest particular atmospheres, depend to a great extent on physical elements of a rather regional scale (climate). Thus, in one way or another, the peripheries always seem to participate in the construction of the identity of the Dalat region.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">II. The role of peripheral spaces for contemporary Dalat: artificialization and integration into an expanding urban tourist system </section>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Rather neglected between 1975 and 1993, when tourism seemed to be limited to the relaxation reserved for Vietnamese officials and centered on the "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">romantic</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" city, peripheral rural areas regained importance in 1996 with the master plan approved in 1993, then the tourism development project for the city and the province on the horizon of 2010. Mostly domestic, tourist numbers are on the rise, they increased from 1.069 million in 2005</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn7" id="bodyftn7">7</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> to 6.5 million (of which 92.5% are nationals) in 2018</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn8" id="bodyftn8">8</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, and various facilities and infrastructures are then built to accompany this growth. Several peripheral sites, often highly equipped, became a sort of satellite extensions of the tourist city: Thien Vien Truc Lam meditation pagoda (completed in 1997) and its cable car, staged gong evenings at the Lat village, the reconstructed "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ethnic</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" village of Cu Lan at Lac Duong, a tunnel for clay sculpture and a scenery for the "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">honeymoons</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" of Tuyen Lam lake... The Langbiang mountain (2124 m), 12 km from the city center, remains a popular excursion spot. This site received about 590,000 tourists in 2016</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn9" id="bodyftn9">9</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. All the waterfalls (Prenn, Datanla, Tiger, Elephant...) have become tourist attractions, sometimes strongly artificialized, attracting a large number of tourists every year (see table 2).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Several fruit-picking farms (strawberry) are located on the outer belt of the city and participate directly in the construction of the city’s identity. Created about twenty years ago, the "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Dalat countryside tour</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">"</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn11" id="bodyftn11">11</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, one of the best known tourist circuits in Dalat, combines the city center, Van Thanh Flower Village (Ward 5), the Ta Nung pass and other developed sites on the outskirts, by articulating farms (coffee, silk production, cricket, rice alcohol) at 19.4-27 km from Dalat, Elephant waterfall (28 km from Dalat), Happy Buddha pagoda (28 km), Nam Ban market (Lam Ha District) (Document 11). There are several versions of this tour, in groups or tailor-made, offered by local travel agencies and by "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">easy-riders</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" (motorbike guides)</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn12" id="bodyftn12">12</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. For example, Dalattrip, a local travel agency, offers this tour at a price of 15 to 30 USD per tourist depending on the number of people in the group. Their tour combines cultural sites (Dalat railway station, market, Happy Buddha Pagoda) and natural, rural sites (farms, waterfall, coffee fields). The original version with groups of 15-25 people only attracts about 6,000 international tourists per year, while the more personalized versions with small groups with "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">easy-riders</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" are currently chosen by most foreign tourists. The Cuong Hoan silk production factory, one of the main attractions of this tour welcomes annually about 30.000 tourists, 80% of which are international (Interview with the Director of the Cuong Hoan company on 13/03/2018 / Document 11).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The websites and brochures of travel agencies display as well a range of tourist products (tours, sites, events) in the peripheral areas of Dalat, mainly centered on the Lac Duong district. The development of tourism started early in this area with the discovery of the local culture in the Lat village and the hunting during the French colonization, and then adventure tourism in the early 1990s. The activities suggested nowadays are mostly (short) visits to farms, cultural exchanges with ethnic minorities and outdoor activities (team building, kayaking, trekking, paragliding, ...). For a few years now, cultural (Pink Grass Festival, see Document 12) and sporting events (Dalat Ultra Trail) attract also the attention of tourists.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">"</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Paradise of honeymoons</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">", "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">city of flowers</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">", Dalat thus continues to rely on the mildness of its climate and on its picturesque scenery, but most of the sites situated on the periphery, by their facilities, their better accessibility and their massive number of visitors, appear today to be very much integrated into the dominant tourist model. Beyond this "first circle", there is no real emergence of new sectors more remote and more confidential. The Tuyen Lam</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn14" id="bodyftn14">14</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> and Dankia areas are two important tourist hubs, identified in the provincial and national tourism development planning as major attractions in the Highlands region. </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Concerning the tourist activities in the peripheral areas of Dalat, Document no 13 clearly shows that the sites are mainly strung out along the national roads No. 20 towards Bao Loc - Ho Chi Minh City and Ninh Thuan, No. 27 towards Dak Lak, regional road No. 723 towards Nha Trang and a few provincial roads towards the nearby districts of Lam Ha, Lac Duong and Don Duong. All the current routes start from the city center of Dalat and radiate out to the surrounding communes and districts following a star-shaped pattern that reflects the central role of the urban area in contrast to the relatively dull role of the surrounding areas in the overall tourism development strategy of the city.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">On the other hand, the (slightly) less organized and more sporting activities, which are more similar to adventure tourism and lean on less densely frequented areas, involve international tourists, whether it concerns forest trekking in the national park of Bidoup-Nuiba or motorbike excursions (easy rider tours). Over the past few years in particular, community-based ecotourism</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn15" id="bodyftn15">15</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> has seen some development with the efforts of the national park of Bidoup-Nuiba in collaboration with JICA, the Japanese development agency. The number of tourists engaged in "sustainable" tourism activities in the national park of Bidoup-Nuiba has increased in recent years from 2,132 in 2012 to 10,092 tourists (including 3,208 foreigners) in 2018</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn16" id="bodyftn16">16</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. However, the number of visitors on one hand, and the nature of these visits on the other, clearly indicate that these are marginal components of the tourist system, concerning a protected natural area relatively far from Dalat.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">But at the moment there is little to no interaction between these different peripheral areas, whose dependence on the center restrains the dynamism and the opening possibilities. It should also be noted that tourist activities remain very close to the center, within a radius of 30-35 km, which raises the question of the role of the remote peripheries, still further behind in terms of tourist development.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            Recently, in order to reduce the burden on the urban area, the efforts of the local authorities in the modernization of the road network from Dalat to Don Duong through the communes of Xuan Tho, Xuan Truong and Tram Hanh, as well as the organization of fam trips for travel agencies in order to create new itineraries connecting the tourist sites in the districts of Lac Duong, Don Duong and Duc Trong, are starting to show positive results (see Table 3).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The successive maps presented above clearly illustrate the evolution of the place of the peripheries in the tourist development of the city and in the strengthening of its identity as a nostalgic holiday resort in the middle of the forests. However, according to some of the local experts</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn18" id="bodyftn18">18</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, despite their importance in terms of surface area, potential and planning, tourism development in the vicinity of Dalat remains modest and undiversified. In fact, there are few connections between the tourist roads towards the districts around Dalat, which results in the observation that the peripheries participate in the tourist offer mainly as resources. As far as activities are concerned, the peripheries play only an auxiliary role, which then leads to a rather blurred image in the overall identity of the city, even though the image of the surrounding areas (forests, lakes, farms, mountains, etc.) is often used in tourist advertisements (see Document 12). Efforts aiming to promote the development of tourism in the vicinity of the city of Dalat have been encouraged over the past two years with fam trips for the media and travel</span><em><strong><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> </span></strong></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">agencies in order to present new tourist products. For example, we took part in a fam trip organized by the Department of Culture, Sports and Tourism of Lam Dong in collaboration with the Don Duong People’s Committee in July 2018 to promote agritourism experiences in Duc Trong (vegetable and fruit farms, factories of Vinamilk, Dalatmilk and Ladophar) and cultural experiences in Don Duong (church of Kadon, toasted pancake villages). A new tourist road linking Dalat, Don Duong and Duc Trong has been created to encourage agritourism and community-based tourism in the peripheries. However, the number of tourists who come to visit these communes remains modest compared to the figures in Dalat or Lac Duong, where tourism already has a long history (see Table 3).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It should also be highlighted that the peripheral agricultural areas, where these tourist circuits are deployed, largely correspond to sectors in which the landscape is undergoing a major transformation, due to the development of intensive vegetable and flower crops, very often under greenhouses, pushing coffee plantations outwards to the detriment of the initial forest setting (Ducourtieux </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">, 2017). This decline of the forest (see Table 4) tends to locally weaken one of the major elements of the landscape framework that made the reputation of Dalat.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The current situation therefore appears to be quite far from the more balanced prospects outlined by the planning for 2030, vision for 2050, which envisions Dalat counting on the protection and enhancement of its remarkable landscape features (forests, lakes, architectural heritage) and on the exceptionality of its horticultural, floricultural and agricultural activities. As shown in the map of the tourism development planning for the extended Dalat region up to 2030, vision for 2050 (Document 14), the role of peripheral areas has been taken into account, and the role of the tourist road linking the areas around Dalat is well emphasized. Thus, the project of the local authorities has clearly oriented tourist development towards surrounding areas, where priority types of tourism have also been identified for each district, such as Lac Duong with ecotourism, adventure tourism and community based tourism; Lam Ha with adventure tourism and agritourism; Don Duong with agritourism and community based tourism; and finally Duc Trong with agritourism, business tourism and basic services (accommodation, catering, airport, etc.).</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">However, these forms of tourism require a fine strategic approach to preserve sensitive tourist resources: the offer linked to the tourist development of certain elements of the culture of the local communities of the peripheral areas thus raises particularly the complex question of "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">authenticity</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">", as demonstrated by the example of the Gong shows on the Langbiang plateau, an unavoidable component of tourist stays in Dalat. This representation of Gong culture, recognized as Intangible Cultural Heritage of Humanity by UNESCO in 2008, at the Lat village with the K’Ho community, at Lac Duong, which was initially considered as an auxiliary night-time leisure activity for the tours organized in Dalat since 2006, has seen remarkable growth recently attracting around 800,000 spectators per year</span><a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn20" id="bodyftn20">20</a><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">. The massive development of the gong evenings is boosting social life in the Lat village and helping to promote traditional handicrafts such as brocade weaving. Despite some criticism regarding the authenticity of the gong performances (Truong, 2019), this activity is developing in the Dalat area, especially in Lac Duong with the K’ho ethnic group and in Don Duong with the Churu ethnic group, as a typical experience in the peripheries. Some tourist sites, such as Dream Hill situated directly in the city of Dalat, also offer gong performances, reflecting the incorporation of a traditional practice into the offer of an increasingly urban destination. According to the tourism development planning for the extended Dalat region up to 2030, vision for 2050 (Ngô and Phân viện Quy hoạch Đô thị - Nông thôn Miền Nam 2014), the prominent place of gong performances is confirmed as a typical cultural activity of Lac Duong and Don Duong, where most of the K’ho and Churu communities live.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusion</section>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">The evolution of gong shows demonstrates a process of assimilation and incorporation of elements coming from peripheral areas into the tourist offer of Dalat, while this form of cultural tourism refers to the question of preservation of the identity of minority ethnic groups, most of whom live in rural and peripheral areas. The identity of the Dalat region is thus constructed over time by mobilizing peripheral components, whether physical or imaginary. This gives the impression of a historical continuity from the creation of Dalat to the present day, to which three corrections should be made: (1) the region’s clientele has increased considerably, passing from a majority of international tourists (Europeans and Indochinese) during the first period to a majority of Vietnamese, or even South Vietnamese, with more than 90% of the total number of arrivals in the current period, national tourists whose expectations are no longer those of the initial tourists; (2) Dalat has meanwhile become a large city, which has expanded and will continue to expand, with its own attractiveness (atmosphere, flower festival); (3) the peripheries themselves have changed, particularly because of its belt of greenhouse farming, which pushes the forest and the traditional rural landscape further away (Ducourtieux </span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">et al.</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en"> , 2017). </span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">In this context, the peripheries are constantly mobilized, but in an often highly artificial manner, almost “</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">urbanized</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">”, one could say, as a set of attractions in the vicinity of the city and under its close control:</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Artificialization of natural sites (Dantala or Prenn waterfalls transformed into quasi-amusement parks, Langbiang mountain highly landscaped) or both natural and man-made (Tuyen Lam lake as a holiday and honeymoon photo setting). The truly natural sites, in which international clientele becomes again the majority, are not much visited. There we find a very different segment of clientele, almost marginal compared to the dominant tourist system of Dalat.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Visiting the greenhouses (which are part of an industrial and urban agriculture), especially the panoramic view of their lights at night, but not visiting the traditional rural areas.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe>
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">Urban reappropriation of the "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">ethnic</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" character, leading sometimes to the diversion and take-over of this cultural heritage, as with the fake ethnic village of Cu Lan (a reconstruction both architectural (with buildings from all over Vietnam) and historical (invention of a legend that leaves the local ethnic groups largely in the shadows)), or with the Gongs Shows that take place in the city, representing a very "</span><em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">modernized</span></em><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">" tradition.</span>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            <span lang="en" xml:lang="en">It should also be noted that in the case of Dalat, this periphery is in fact very near, and enables these cultural shows, visits to natural areas and urban activities to be easily combined during the visitors’ stays. Although the peripheral spaces have indeed played an important role in the construction of the city’s identity by and for tourism throughout its development, their tourist offer, punctual, irregular, is complementary and subordinate to that of the central city, to which they provide both a kind of setting - mountain climatic atmosphere, forest and lake environment - and a stock of activities. When reading the longer-term tourism planning documents, two questions seem to arise. The first is that of the spatial depth of the penetration of tourist activities within the peripheral areas: while the activities have become denser and more diversified since the creation of the resort, and the city has expanded considerably, ultimately the extension of this "tourist periphery" has not changed much, although it has taken advantage of the improvement of the road network to strengthen its southern side, as well as its north-eastern side with the creation of Route 723 towards Nha Trang (2007) and that of the Bidoup-Nuiba National Park (2004) (cf. Document 13). In spite of this, beyond some 30 km from Dalat, the offer is still very limited, and one wonders to what extent this halo is likely to expand. This question must therefore be linked to the second, which concerns sustainable and experiential forms of tourism such as agritourism or rural tourism, ecotourism, community-based tourism, and the role given they play in the tourist offer and the identity of the destination according to these planning documents. This alternative offer, which is characteristic of peripheral areas, is still modest and will represent an important challenge for the management of the destination and for the future efforts of coordination and territorial governance. Even if the night seeing of the blanket of electric light formed by the continuously illuminated greenhouses has today become a tourist attraction on its own, it is also necessary to question the threats looming over the city’s landscape setting: as an important component of its identity through its pine forests, it appears in fact strongly threatened both by urban expansion and by the peripheral deployment of vegetable crops and of greenhouses, and, beyond that, of coffee </span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">plantations</span><span lang="en" xml:lang="en">.</span>
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Bon, A. (1930), Petit Guide illustré de Dalat, Indochine française. 1930, Imprimerie d’Extrême-Orient, Hanoi.</reference>
        <reference>Déry, S. and Tremblay, M. (2008), "L’implantation des aires protégées au Vietnam : quels impacts pour les populations locales? Une étude de cas dans la province de Lâm Đồng", VertigO, Vol.8 No.3, pp. 1-17. </reference>
        <reference>Đỗ, T. H. (2014), "Cao nguyên LangBiang : Những giá trị độc đáo về đa dạng sinh học", Tạp chí Môi trường, Vol. 12, Available at: http://tapchimoitruong.vn/pages/article.aspx?item=Cao-nguy%C3%AAn-LangBiang:-Nh%E1%BB%AFng-gi%C3%A1-tr%E1%BB%8B-%C4%91%E1%BB%99c-%C4%91%C3%A1o-v%E1%BB%81-%C4%91a-d%E1%BA%A1ng-sinh-h%E1%BB%8Dc-38743 (Accessed: 20 July 2019).</reference>
        <reference>Ducourtieux, O., Delry, S., Nguyen, N. T., and Mounayar, M. (2017), "Dynamiques touristiques et révolutions paysagères dans les montagnes du Lam Dong (Vietnam)", in La montagne, territoire d’innovation. LabEx ITEM (Innovation et Territoires de montagne) Jan 2017, Grenoble, France. </reference>
        <reference>Duhamel, P. and Sacareau, I. (1998), Le tourisme dans le monde, Armand Colin, Paris.</reference>
        <reference>Ibanescu, B. (2012), Les conditions de la mise en tourisme d’un espace rural périphérique de l’Union Européenne : la province de Moldavie en Roumanie, Université Michel de Montaigne - Bordeaux III.</reference>
        <reference>Jennings, E. T. and Larcher-Goscha (Trad.), A. (2013), La ville de l’éternel printemps. Comment Dalat a permis l’Indochine française, Payot, Paris. </reference>
        <reference>Kaymaz, I. (2013), "Urban Landscapes and Identity", in Ozyavuz, M. (Ed.), Advances in Landscape Architecture. Intechopen, pp. 739-760.</reference>
        <reference>Kneafsey, M. (2000), "Tourism, Place Identities and Social Relations in the Urban Rural Periphery", European Urban and Regional Studies, Vol. 7 No.1, pp. 35-50. </reference>
        <reference>Korpela, K. M. (1989), "Place-identity as a product of environmental self-regulation", Journal of Environmental Psychology, Vol. 9 No.3, pp. 241-256. </reference>
        <reference>Miternique, H. C. and Marcotte, P. (2014), "Marges et périphéries : un espace pour des pratiques non touristiques", Téoros. Revue de recherche en tourisme, Vol. 33 No.2, Available at: http://journals.openedition.org/teoros/2684 (Accessed: 25 December 2015).</reference>
        <reference>Montgomery, J. (1998), "Making a city: Urbanity, vitality and urban design", Journal of Urban Design, Vol. 3 No.1, pp. 93-116.</reference>
        <reference>Ngô, Q. H. and Phân viện Quy hoạch Đô thị - Nông thôn Miền Nam (2014), Thuyết minh tổng hợp điều chỉnh quy hoạch chung thành phố Đà Lạt và vùng phụ cận đến năm 2030 và tầm nhìn đến năm 2050.</reference>
        <reference>Peyvel, E. (2017), "Sortir de l’ornière. Périphérisme et invisibilité touristique", in Bernard, N., Blondy, C., and Duhamel, P. (eds), Tourisme et périphéries. La centralité des lieux en question, Presses universitaires de Rennes, pp. 291-312.</reference>
        <reference>Reimer, J. K. K. and Walter, P. (2013), "How do you know it when you see it ? Community-based ecotourism in the Cardamom Mountains of southwestern Cambodia", Tourism Management. Vol. 34, pp. 122132. </reference>
        <reference>Relph, E. C. (1976), Place and placelessness, Pion Limited (Research in Planning and Design Series). </reference>
        <reference>Reynaud, A. (1992), "Centre et périphérie", in Bailly, A., Ferras, R., and Pumain, D. (eds) Encyclopédie de géographie, Economica, Paris, pp. 599-615.</reference>
        <reference>Salvatore, R., Chiodo, E. and Fantini, A. (2018), "Tourism transition in peripheral rural areas: Theories, issues and strategies", Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 68, pp. 41–51. </reference>
        <reference>Steinführer, A., Reichert-schick, A., Mose, I. and Grabski-kieron, U. (2016), "European rural peripheries revalued ? Introduction to this volume", European Rural Peripheries Revalued: Governance, Actors, Impacts, 1 (Rural areas: Issues of local and regional development), pp. 2-27.</reference>
        <reference>Stephenson, J. (2008), "The Cultural Values Model: An integrated approach to values in landscapes", Landscape and Urban Planning, Vol. 84 No.2, pp. 127-139.</reference>
        <reference>Tessier, O., Bourdeaux, P. and École française d’Extrême-Orient (2013), Đà Lạt et la carte créa la ville... bản đồ sáng lập thành phố... and the map created the city..., Nhà Xuất Bản Tri Thú̉c École Française d’Extrême-Orient, Hanoi.</reference>
        <reference>Truong, T. L. H. (2019), Quelle place pour la typicité locale et l’authenticité dans l’expérience touristique : le cas de Dalat, station de montagne au Vietnam. Géographie, Université d’Avignon, École doctorale 537 "Culture et patrimoine", Avignon.</reference>
        <reference>Truong, T. L. H., Lenglet, F. and Mothe, C. (2018), "Destination distinctiveness: Concept, measurement, and impact on tourist satisfaction", Journal of Destination Marketing and Management, Vol. 8, pp. 214-231.</reference>
        <reference>Ujang, N. (2012), "Place Attachment and Continuity of Urban Place Identity", Procedia - Social and Behavioral Sciences, Vol. 49, pp. 156-167.</reference>
        <reference>Ziyaee, M. (2017), "Assessment of urban identity through a matrix of cultural landscapes", Cities, Vol. 74, pp. 21–31. </reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">Cục Thong ke Lam Dong (Lam Dong Statistics Office). (2019). Nien Giam Thong Ke Lam Dong 2018 (Lam Dong Statistics Yearbook 2018). Hanoi: NXB Thong Ke</note>
        <note id="2">Prime Minister of Vietnam. Decision No 704/QĐ-TTg concerning the Adjustment of the Master Plan of Dalat city and its vicinity up to 2030, vision of 2050, on 12/05/2014.</note>
        <note id="3">Data collected from the Department of Culture, Sports and Tourism of Lam Dong in 2019</note>
        <note id="4">Documents about Lam Dong, official website of the province of Lam Dong, Source: http://w3.lamdong.gov.vn/vi-VN/a/book/Pages/default.aspx</note>
        <note id="5">The legend of Langbiang: It is an impossible love story between K'Lang, son of the chief of the Lat tribe and H'Biang, daughter of the chief of the Chil tribe. Because of the curse between the two tribes, they were not allowed to become husband and wife. The two lovers decided to die together to show their love, and their opposition to traditions. After their death, the two fathers decided to reunite the different tribes Lat, Chil and Sré to constitute the K'ho group. The mountain in the hamlet of La Ngu Thuong, where the young couple died, was named LangBiang in memory of their love. The legend is considered to be a Vietnamese love story similar to that of Romeo and Juliet.</note>
        <note id="6">Dalat in 1967-1971, photo by Ken Thompson (Source :https://www.flickriver.com/photos/13476480@N07/31296977864/) ; Dalat in 2007, photo by NguyenVan Giau (Source : https://www.facebook.com/notes/i-love-dalat/h%C3%A3y-c%E1%BB%A9ul%E1%BA%A5y-dalat-ti%E1%BA%BFp-theo-v%C3%A0-h%E1%BA%BFt-/405373346169251/) and Dalat in 2019 (Source: http://www.dalat-info.vn/vn/du-lich/da-lat-duoc-ket-nap-la-thanh-vien-to-chuc-xuc-tien-du-lich-cac-thanh-pho-chau-a--x2d--thai-binh-duong-tpo-39241.phtml) </note>
        <note id="7">Department of Statistics of Lam Dong. Lam Dong Statistical Yearbook 2006. http://www.lamdong.gov.vn/vi-VN/congdan/thong-tin-can-biet/NGTK2006/Pages/index.htm</note>
        <note id="8">Department of Culture, Sports and Tourism of Lam Dong. (2018). Report of cultural, sports and tourism activities in 2018, directions and tasks in 2019, Report 125/BC-SVHTTDL, 05/11/2018. </note>
        <note id="9">Data collected from the Direction of the Langbiang tourist site in 08/2017. </note>
        <note id="10">Data collected from the Department of Culture, Sports and Tourism of Lam Dong in 07/2018</note>
        <note id="11">Cf. https://www.dalattrip.com/dalat-countryside-tour/ </note>
        <note id="12">Cf. http://dalat-easyriders.com/ The "easy-riders" are also a typical tourist product of Dalat, often recommended in the guidebooks.</note>
        <note id="13">Pictures taken in 2017, 2018; brochure of the Langbiang website, brochure of the Pink Grass Festival 2017 and website of Phattire Ventures, an online Dalat travel agency. </note>
        <note id="14">Tuyen Lam lake (2,900 ha) was officially recognized as the first National Tourism Zone in 2017, cf.</note>
        <note id="0">ttp://www.vietnamtourism.com/fn/index.php/news/items/12855</note>
        <note id="15">Community-based Ecotourism refers to a particular variant of ecotourism that embodies a mutually reinforcing relationship between environmental conservation, local economic livelihoods and cultural preservation - a kind of symbiotic mutualistic relationship that benefits to all three. (Reimer and Walter 2013)</note>
        <note id="16">Data collected from the Centre for Ecotourism and Environmental Education of the national park of Bidoup-Nuiba in 01/2019.</note>
        <note id="17">Partial figures: January to September 2018.</note>
        <note id="18">Notably Mrs. Nguyen Thi Thanh Ngan, associate professor and researcher in tourism at Dalat University (Interview on 11/11/2018), or Mr. Minh Lan, journalist specialized in tourism at Lam Dong Radio-Television (Interview on 12/11/2018).</note>
        <note id="19">Cục Thống kê Lâm Đồng (Lam Dong Statistics Office). (2016). Niên Giám Thống Kê Lâm Đồng 2015 (Lam Dong Statistical Yearbook 2015). Hanoi: NXB Thống Kê.</note>
        <note id="20">Data estimated by the Department of Culture, Sports and Tourism of Lam Dong in 2018. </note>
    </notes>
</article>