<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="en_YS_51-79_We_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/745" lang="en">
    <meta>
        <extraction>2021-05-26</extraction>
        <DOI>https://doi.org/10.4000/viatourism.745</DOI>
        <revue>Viatourism</revue>
        <numero>6</numero>
        <annee>2014</annee>
    </meta>
    <auteurs>
        <auteur nom="Shioji" prenom="Yuko">
            <oeuvres>
                <publication id="fr_YS_50-96_Qs_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/752" lang="fr">Qui porte le mythe de la "Vieille Angleterre" ? - Tourisme et migration dans la campagne anglais</publication>
                <publication id="it_YS_51-106_Ce_1" source="https://journals.openedition.org/viatourism/759" lang="it">Chi conserva l’immagine della “Vecchia Inghilterra”? - Turismo e fenomeni migratori nella campagna inglese</publication>
            </oeuvres>
            <description>
                Professor (Cultural anthropology), Hannan University, Faculty of International Tourism, Department of International Tourism" 
            </description>
        </auteur>
    </auteurs>
    <titre>Who Maintains “Old England”? - Tourism and Migration in the English Countryside</titre>
    <resume>
        The imaginary world of “Old England” has attracted tourists and incomers to the English countryside since the 19th century. This has had a great impact on the local community. This paper is a case study of a country town in the Cotswolds. It describes the local community and their reactions to tourism and migration, and highlights the prominent role played by incomers in maintaining the imaginary world which drew them to the town. This paper also looks at how local people have worked to uphold the legacy of their ancestors.
    </resume>
    <corps>
        <section niveau="h1">Introduction</section>
        <paragraphe num="1">
            The imaginary world of “Old England”, which has attracted many tourists, contains with historic buildings, beautiful landscapes of countryside and quiet village life. Images of “Old England” have been produced in the English countryside since the end of the 19th century by guidebooks, tourist brochures, mass media and the tourism policies of the British Tourist Authority and now Visit Britain. Urry discusses that people come to preserve and visit the countryside because the landscape and customs of countryside are settled as symbols of “Old England” (Urry 1990 : 96-99). Such images have been attracting not only tourists but also incomers who moved from other areas in Britain. Some tourists love the area so much that they came to live there. This study, based on the anthropological participatory fieldwork carried out from 1996 to 2010<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn1" id="bodyftn1">1</a>, takes a country town in the Cotswolds as a case study to demonstrate how the imaginary world affects the living community and what feed back the community gives from 1990s to 2010.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="2">
            In the discussion of anthropological studies of tourism, it has been pointed out that the people in host societies, who are ethnic, political, economic or even cultural minority in many cases, have negative impacts by tourists and tourism development such as selling their traditions and lands as touristic commodities (Smith 1989 ; Boissevain (ed.) 1996). Conversely, it has been claimed that new traditions are formed or that disappearing traditions are reconstructed in cultures of host societies as a result of making use of tourism (McDonald 1987 ; Boissevain (ed.) 1996 ; Yamashita 1999).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="3">
            There has been a kind of exaggerated presupposition that hosts and guests are living in different worlds such as between wealthy “north” and poor “south” or majority and minority or the strong and the weak in tourism studies<a class="footnotecall" href="#ftn2" id="bodyftn2">2</a>. However, in the English countryside, there are guests who moved to live in host societies and now are part of host community. As reported by Fees, a place myth brought in by those incomers, who tend to be retired, wealthy, middle-class people, can influence the politics and social relations of a country town (Fees 1996) ; incomers have similar images to tourists, but they can give more serious impacts on the local community by becoming permanent residents. In this study, the local reactions to tourism and migration are discussed in order to consider who and what maintains the imaginary world of “Old England”. 
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">English Countryside and Tourism</section>
        <section niveau="h2">English Countryside as an Ideal Area</section>
        <paragraphe num="4">
            English countryside has been an ideal area. Since the Industrial Revolution, Britain as a “World Factory” experienced a rapid urbanization and dense population in cities, and lost historical buildings and natural environment one after another by development. A total of 200,000 hectares of farmlands and forestlands in Britain disappeared in 15 years between 19th century and the early 20th century. In addition of such rapid social change within the country, the social change outside the country as expansion of the Empire also happened in the 19th century. During that time, people looked for their belongingness to the English countryside.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="5">
            Many of the descriptions of countryside in literary works tend to emphasize old England, rural virtue and rural landscape. Rural landscape was drawn symbolically in landscape paintings so that countryside came to be focused on as a motif in the works of art, too (Pevsner 1956 : 167). As Williams points out, for the British who went to work in colonies in the era of British Empire, the idea which regards England as ‘home’ came to stay (Williams 1973 : 281). Many of the images of this ‘home’ are of an idea of rural England. The reward for hard service in British colonies was “a return to a rural place within this urban and industrial England” (Williams 1973 : 282). In short, after Empire era, countryside became a place to retire to (Williams 1973 : 282).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="6">
            The Country Life, has been published over hundred years since it was launched in 1890s, has always articles and advertisements of houses in towns and villages of the countryside. Thus, the rapid changes in and outside the country in the 19th century made the English countryside as an imaginary place to belong to and developed more realistically as an ideal residential area throughout the 20th century.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Tourism and Tourist Images in the English Countryside</section>
        <paragraphe num="7">
            In the 20th century, countryside became a kind of representation of Englishness. For instance, in the recession of 1930s, BBC radio lecture programs emphasized the life of traditional English countryside, and Longman’s English Heritage series and Batsford’s English Life series were published one after another (Wiener 1981 : 73). In those days, guidebooks and travel writings described English countryside esthetically for middle class people in cities who were seeking the beauty of English landscape (Potts 1989 : 172-173).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="8">
            Improvement in transportation and nation’s leisure boom made countryside an attractive tourist destination easy to access. This promoted much more people to visit there. By the spread of motorcars after the World War II, people’s travel patterns changed enormously. New Aims of travel to the countryside appeared such as sports and country walks. From the late 1980s to the 1990s, a new form of leisure in the countryside which limits impacts of tourism on environment was shown by the Countryside Commission (Countryside Commission 1987 ; 1991ab ; 1992).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="9">
            English countryside in present day has a lot of natural and cultural heritage because of its long history of preservation. It is an area of high consciousness about protection of the environment. There are many areas which aim at revitalization by tourism using these natural and cultural resources. Historical buildings are not only opened to the public, but also used as accommodations. For example, 45 % of total accommodations in Gloucestershire, where the Cotswolds is mainly included, are historical buildings (BTA/ETB 1996 : 15). British Tourist Authority (BTA) promoted “countryside”, “heritage” and “culture” as the most important characteristics of Britain. Two thirds of foreign visitors gave these as a reason to visit Britain (Shioji 1997 ; 2003 : 96-98).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="10">
            Since the latter half of the 20th century, the images of English countryside have been used for tourism by national and regional governments, and tourism industry. We can clearly see these images in national, regional and local tourist brochures (Shioji 2003 : 98-122). For instance, the images in the “England” section of national tourist brochures from 1992 to 1997 reveal the importance of its landscape combining historic buildings with nature such as green fields, lakes and the sea. Historic buildings are “magnificent”, “splendid” and “grand” buildings such as country houses, castles and cathedrals and also “picturesque”, “romantic” and “poetic” buildings such as wooden houses, stone cottages and ruins of castle. Small thatched cottages, stone houses and wooden houses are always contained in the “England” section of tourist brochures as if they were idealized houses in England.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="11">
            “Countryside” is often used for the introduction of “England” section and it is explained as “picturesque”, “breathtaking”, “beautiful”, “delightful”, “green” and “rolling”. Such images of countryside do not include tractors cultivating grounds and tracks carrying corns, and muddy agricultural laborers. The tourist brochures tend not to describe the real lives in the countryside where sounds and smells of agriculture and farming exist. “Central England” is especially described as “essential England” including culture, history, the idealized English historic houses, and the conceptualized countryside. These images are basically repeated in the regional and local tourist brochures produced by regional and local administrations aiming to revitalize the area by tourism.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">A Community in the English Countryside</section>
        <section niveau="h2">Chipping Campden in the Cotswolds</section>
        <paragraphe num="12">
            The Cotswolds is the hilly area situated in the south-west of England, and it covers mainly
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="13">
            Gloucestershire and four other counties. It has about 145 small towns and villages and population of the area is about 80,000. From the end of the 19th century to the beginning of the 20th century, environmental movements became active across the country and the environmentalists and benefactors have repaired old houses and conserved townscape and natural environment in the Cotswolds. The area is now Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty (AONB), which is an area of countryside considered to have significant landscape value specially designated on behalf of the British government. Its natural and cultural resources attract about 3,000,000 people a year. This paper looks at the north Cotswold town, Chipping Campden, population of 2,000.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="14">
            This town was a market town in the Middle Ages, and from the 5th to 10th century it was the political centre in the area. It flourished by wool trade and the wealthy wool merchants built St. James church, almshouses and market hall. The town was left from the Industrial Revolution and had been a remote country town with the dilapidated houses from which owners moved out to cities after the 1870s agricultural depression. However, since the architect, C.R. Ashbee and his Guild of Handicraft moved from London in 1902 to achieve ideal of the Arts and Crafts Movement, the town had been revived culturally, socially and economically. Since Ashbee, wealthy incomers to the town had been gradually increased. Not only middle class artists, but also service persons from colonies and the successful businessmen from cities came to live in the town for their retirement lives (Figure 1.1, 1.2).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="15">
            Chipping Campden has now the second most dense listed buildings of the country and it is a conservation area as well as an AONB. It also has cultural heritage such as morris dancing (which is an English folk dance), the May Day festivity and the Cotswold Olimpick Games (that is the sport festival originated from the 17th century). Not only the tangible heritage like historical buildings and landscape, but also the intangible local heritage, handed down by the people in the town, also attracts people from outside the town.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Tourism and the Local Reactions in Chipping Campden</section>
        <paragraphe num="16">
            Tourism is the major industry of Chipping Campden. In the high seasons, from June to September, there are over 250 visitors coming into the tourist information centre of the town centre in a day. This town is situated in 20 minutes drive from Shakespeare’s birthplace, Stratford-upon-Avon and the Cotswolds is surrounded by Oxford and Bath so that it is one of the famous touring spots in the area (Figure 2.1, 2.2).
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="17">
            There are enough facilities for tourism such as hotels, bed and breakfasts, restaurants, tearooms and antique shops in the high street, which also has the necessary shops for community life such as post office, banks, bakery, butcher, greengrocer, chemist and co-op shop. People are living in more than 40 % of the buildings in the high street (Shioji 2003 : 69). The town has 2 elementary schools and one comprehensive school and also 3 churches of Anglican, Baptist and Roman Catholic. It is a living community as well as a famous tourist destination, which causes the complex problems of the “inside” and “outside” the town such as the issue of promoting tourism and protecting residents’ daily lives. The impacts of the “outside” the town is not only tourism, but also the gaze from “outside” to seek old England also results in the conflicts between local people and incomers discussed in the following sections.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="18">
            Majority of the residents, who are not directly depending on tourism, are generally not willing to promote tourism in the town. It can be seen in the fact that the local clubs and Women’s Institute opposed to set up the tourist information centre inside the town hall in 1997. They claims that the activities of clubs and Women’s Institute at the town hall are for the residents, but that the tourist information centre is for outsiders and is not suitable for the aims of the town hall. Although the town council gave grants to set up the tourist information centre for first 2 years as they admitted the benefit of tourism to the town, they took a decision to put the highest priority on the residents’ convenience. Most of the residents understand more or less that tourism is essential for their daily life to maintain a variety of shops and facilities in the town. They can easily imagine that the town will lose the liveliness and these shops will disappear if tourists do not come to the town. However, there is still a negative opinion that they do not have direct benefit from tourism. There are very few people who do not mind strangers with cameras gazing long at their gardens and houses.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="19">
            However, the imaginary world of the “Old England” created by the gaze from outside of the town attracts tourists continuously. Tourist images of the English countryside, mentioned before, are used practically in Chipping Campden. Hotels and shops using historic buildings are making use of the tourist images of the historic town. 5 hotels in high street are the biggest tourism industry benefitting form guests and customers to the restaurants in the town. These hotels emphasizes the oldness of the buildings and the long history as hotels by showing wooden beams in ceiling, setting fireplaces with logs and antique interiors, and prepared four-poster beds in guests rooms. Antique shops in high street are the typical example of making good use of the oldness of the buildings. Most of the antiques sold in the shops are not originated from Chipping Campden, but collected from all over the country.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="20">
            Not only hotels and shops, but also a trust focusing on preservation of the cultural heritage in the town makes use of the tourist images. The Court Barn Museum, opened and managed by the Guild of Handicraft Trust in 2007, gives instructions to visitors to the shops and workshops where they can buy local handicrafts. The museum is exhibiting the history and art works of the Arts and Crafts Movement and it cooperates with local art workshops, galleries, and tourist information centre. One of such workshops is the 17th century Old Silk Mill where C. R. Ashbee and his guildsmen used as workshop building in the beginning of the 20th century. There is still a silversmith workshop in the Old Silk Mill where visitors can watch silversmiths making silverworks and buy them. In the showcase, there are original accessories based on the Ashbee’s designs, framed as the main historic buildings in the town such as Market Hall.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="21">
            The group promoting tourism in the town has consisted of the accommodation providers in and around the town and the members of the Chamber of Trade such as shopkeepers in high street. Especially, the people, running bed and breakfasts in the local area, had set up and managed the tourist information centre in the town since 1995. They had some merits such as getting their guests regularly by making pre-bookings of accommodations for tourists in the tourist information centre. However, since the website became popular to find and reserve the accommodations, the accommodation providers gradually withdrew from organizing the tourist information centre. Instead, as the recent tendency, there are some local volunteers who are retired and not necessarily related to tourism started to help organizing it. They seem to enjoy helping there and talking to visitors. One of the main organizers and the manager of the tourist information centre in 2010 is a retired local bank manager. He is also a folk musician and a leader of the local morris dance team so that he has a good local network. He is eager to attract tourists to the town and inform them about the heritage of the town such as historical festivals and morris dance.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="22">
            There are also some residents who actively teach visitors about the history of the town. They are the members of the Cotswold Volunteer Warden and organized guided tours and country walks. Each guided tour of Chipping Campden takes about 10 tourists and walks around the town by explaining the historic buildings in the town such as the time and aims of construction and restoration, and the stories of the past owners and present owners. Such residents tend to live in historic houses themselves and appreciate the old atmosphere and natural environment of the town so that they want tourists to understand the heritage of the town and to think about the preservation. They aim to educate and guide visitors appropriately, therefore they insist the necessity of a tourist information centre.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">The Social and Cultural Changes by Incomers</section>
        <paragraphe num="23">
            Chipping Campden used to be an ordinary English country town which depended on agriculture and farming. However, since the late 19th century, the number of tourists has increased. The mechanization of agriculture in the 20th century reduced employment of the town and led young population drain. Furthermore, the number of incomers increased enormously after the late 1980s when the house price of cities went up, and instead, the houses in the countryside became easy to obtain and popular for the city people. Therefore, the population of the town has been aging, and 37 % of the population is over retired age people and households of pensioner occupy 23 % of all households.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="24">
            The incomers, who moved to the town, made the English ideal of “spending retirement life in the countryside” come true. Most of the incomers, I interviewed, have the experiences of visiting the Cotswolds or Chipping Campden as tourists. Some of them were familiar to the Cotswolds since they had visited the area often in their childhood, so that they have even a nostalgic feeling for the place. Others certainly love the place and decided to move to when they visited the area.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="25">
            However, the conflicts and difficulties, discussed in the next section, were occurred between “Campdonians” born and bred in the town and wealthy incomers from cities. Both of the words, “incomer” and “Campdonian”, are used by the people living in the town when they talk about themselves. Most Campdonians are working class people who are living on the local industry. Incomers, in many cases, are retired middle class people who were successful in cities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="26">
            The flow of incomers into the town made social and cultural changes in the town. Firstly, a rise in house prices, resulted from setting them higher for the city people, made the local young people not be able to afford buying the houses in the town. This changed the social structure of the town.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="27">
            According to my analysis based on the census data and the identification by some residents who know both Campdonians and incomers well in the late 1990s, incomers live in high street lined with historic listed buildings and also live in the block of thatched cottages. That is, they live in the “centre” of culture and landscape in the town. On the contrary, Campdonians live in the “periphery” such as council houses and collective housing built in back streets or outskirt of the town in the 20th century (Shioji 2003). After more than 10 years passed since my analysis, a few old Campdonians died and young Campdonians went out the town to live and work in bigger towns and cities so that the number of Campdonians has continued to decrease.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="28">
            Secondly, incomers started to control the town culturally, socially and politically. Incomers had good experiences of business or professional jobs, and they are good at debating and organizing things. They set up some conservation societies and trusts in the 1980s to keep “their” town’s beauty and they also became the town councilors. They gradually came to control the outlook of the town by their point of views.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="29">
            For example, one of such societies and also the biggest non-profitable organization in the town is the Campden Society (CS). It is originally formed in 1924 and reformed in 1970 by incomers. This movement began at the time of the arrival of incomers in relation with the narrative of Old England. Reformed CS aims at protecting Campden’s own beauty and history in cooperation through managing buildings. It has about 350 members, but most of them are incomers who are retired and over 60 years old. Activities of the CS include lectures and study tours, which many members can participate in, and also has the special role by the planning sub-committee. The latter is to examine the planning applications of housing in the town sent from the local government each month, and submit opinions about rebuilding, extension, new construction and restoration of the buildings of the town to the local government. In this sense, CS has the role of an advisory body for the local government and its opinions are referred as the voices of “Campden residents” apart from the decision of the town council.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="30">
            CS’s opinions gradually came to make an impact on the discussion in the small country town. Especially, incomers started to join the politics of the town as town councilors and they occupied more than half of the seats of town council in 1980s. Incomer councilors are convinced of CS’s opinions which also have incomers’ point of views, so that CS’s opinions about planning applications easily are reflected in the town council. Under such situation, an opinion of “outsiders rule the town’s landscape” grew among Campdonians and CS provoked Campdonians antipathy as a representative of incomers who have control of the town.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="31">
            Thus, the incomers helped to maintain an Old England landscape which had attracted themselves to the place. Although Chipping Campden is situated in a politically and economically “periphery” from cities, mythical images, created since Ashbee and the Guild of Handicraft, have attracted incomers from “centre” who came to control the town by societies and trusts (Fees 1996 : 129-138). Campdonians had hardly joined such social organizations. Most of them, I interviewed, said, “Campdonians do not join the CS.” Their reasons are, “the society is consisted of outsiders”, “we are too busy living to have time to discuss” and “want to support more ‘important’ charity helping old people in the town than joining the CS.” Some of them join the limited social groups such as cricket club and local Women’s Institute. Most of Campdonians are not interested in conservation, but in modern and convenient life.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Conflicts between Campdonians and Incomers</section>
        <paragraphe num="32">
            There are the conflicts and difficulties between Campdonians and incomers based on the economic gap and difference of life styles and sense of value. Especially, from 1980s till 1990s when the number of incomers increased rapidly, the conflict among the residents became prominent. For example, in 1988, the incomers insisted that large lorries running through the centre of the town spoiled the landscape. In response to the incomers appeal, the town council suggested the plan of weight restriction of lorries running through the town so that Campdonians’ anger explodes towards incomers.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="33">
            The county council had drawn up a draft proposal for the restriction on the road after the town council suggested the idea. When the town council called local companies which use trucks for business in order to have a hearing of their opinions, a representative of a company supplying dairy products for the local area claimed as follows : <em>“This proposal is typical of the wrinkly yuppies who are destroying this town.<br/>The reason they all move to Campden is because people whose families have been here for hundreds of years have made it so pretty. But because of the newcomers, trade suddenly is not a concern. They are turning Campden into a wrinkly paradise. What are they trying to do to this town ? ··· Townies are coming into Campden in their droves and we are expected to convert to their lifestyles. We are just trying to earn a living.” (Evesham Journal 1988. 6. 2 :1)</em>
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="34">
            “Wrinkly yuppies”, “townies” and “newcomers” described by the representative are referred to the middle class incomers moved from cities after retirement. Compared with the retired wealthy incomers, Campdonians, in many cases, are few working age people supporting their family. When incomers force Campdonians to change their lives by incomers’ sense of value, Campdonians’ anger exploded like this. Such conflict between incomers and Campdonian did not come up to the surface in the late 1990s when I was carrying out my fieldwork, but a few residents explained to me their different ways of thinking and attitudes. There are potential conflicts within the community.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">A New Change of the Community</section>
        <paragraphe num="35">
            However, around the year 2000, some Campdonians started to participate in several social organizations set up and occupied by incomers such as the historical society and a care group for the elderly people. In this section, the recent change of the historical society of the town is discussed.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">The Historical Society</section>
        <paragraphe num="36">
            The historical society in the town is Campden and District Historical and Archaeological Society, called CADHAS in short. CADHAS was formed in 1984 by incomers’ appeal for establishment of historical society. At that time, the incomers, who are historians and intellectuals including the proposer who is an ex-surveyor, formed a committee and made regulations. 60 people came up in the first meeting, but there was few Campdonians committed in its formation. In 1987, the number of its members increased to 150 people and it has a broader range of activities such as lectures, exhibitions, research, study tours and publication same as the present activity. In the first five years, CADHAS published books about local people and artists committed in Arts and Crafts Movement. After that, in 1990s, it published some books such as “Memories of a Campdonian” written by an old Campdonian who thought back to his life and the people and life in the town.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="37">
            CADHAS has been extremely active in digging up the local history, opening exhibitions, presentations and lectures to the public, and producing publications. According to my research in the mid 1990s, although the number of its member became over 200 people, CADHAS has very few Campdonian members, and several Campdonians such as the author of the book were invited and treated as living witnesses of the history in its regular meetings.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Community Archives in 2001 : Volunteers are Campdonian</section>
        <paragraphe num="38">
            CADHAS, however, started to change gradually after 2000. In 2000, the archives and photographs owned by CADHAS and kept in a member’s house were moved to the public library in the town, and put into computer as a digital data. This was called “the Community Archives Plan” which made them accessible for the public use. Then, CADHAS rented a room in the building of town centre to keep and consult these archives in 2001, which opened the opportunity of history research to the other members. The history research had been limited to several members. This was the beginning of a change of CADHAS. The Campdonians in their 60s, who had not shown any interest in CADHAS activity, started to meet in the archives room. They had just retired from their work and came to help input of archives and photographs to the computer as volunteers. Gradually the other Campdonians started to come to research their ancestors records of marriage, birth and death to the archives room. CADHAS obtained the fund of 25,000 pounds for three years from Heritage Lottery Fund in 2002 so that the activity of the archives room was established as the regular activity in CADHAS.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="39">
            There are four Campdonians in their 60s who got involved in the archives room since it was opened. Among them, G has been living in Campden since he was born and so, he knows old residents and changes of the town. He told that he got an interest in the history of the town which he did not know before he started to identify the old photographs of the end of 19th century. He went to see the elderly Campdonians in order to identify and borrow some old photographs. By this kind of volunteer’s activity, Campdonians who had not known the existence of community archives, came to have an interest in CADHAS.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="40">
            V is in her early 60s. She worked as a nurse and married to a Greek doctor. She had lived in Greece for over 10 years and came back to the area for her husband illness. She had lived a big town near Campden to bring up her children for 10 years after her husband’s death and then, she bought a small house in Campden several years ago when her children were grown up. She is, so called, U-turn Campdonian from abroad. I define them as “U-turn Campdonians”, who came back to Campden to retire, very few people in comparison with incomers. V is glad to come back to the town where her sister and relatives live. She is also doing volunteer work with G to help the elderly people in the town. The Campdonians in their 60s of the voluntary help group with her are the people who went to the same school and so they have good conversations and discuss the pension and retirement life. She is interested in history and joined CADHAS as a volunteer by other Campdonian’s recommendation.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="41">
            E is in her late 60s and the present president of CADHAS. She left Campden at the age of 18 and worked outside Britain. After her divorce, she came back to live in Campden in 2001. She is also U-turn Campdonian. The reason for joining CADHAS was to research her family history. She found out that her paternal ancestor existed in Campden in the middle of 16th century, and then she became enthusiastic about the research of the town’s history. She was surprised that there had been very few Campdonians participating in CADHAS activity and thinks that Campdonian should participate in its activity. Her 96 year-old mother is also living in the town and has a strong interest in recording the history of the town. Her mother is one of the few old Campdonians who positively takes part in its activity ; she gave a lecture about the town in old days at an informal meeting of CADHAS in 2009 and wrote an essay for the CADHAS newsletter. After E came back to her hometown, she met her old friends at her age and built up her Campdonian network again through her mother’s local networks and her own CADHAS activity.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="42">
            As E asked some Campdonians in her age to carry on the history research, the other Campdonians came to show their interest in CADHAS activity and CADHAS could have a tie with the existing community. CADHAS has also many inquires about looking for family roots from outside the town. As the archives room became a counter to answer the inquiries, the network of the society was broadened towards outside the town. The volunteer people of the archive room fully enjoyed the discovery of unexpected links with distant places by following the relatives in old photographs.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="43">
            However, E explained that the executive committee of CADHAS originally did not agree with the community archives activity in the room. The society is the “elite” organization consisted of many intellectual incomers and they are proud of its researches and lectures so that they did not like the ordinary residents, who are not historians, joining the research of the society. When E was recommended to the president of the society several years ago, the people of the top of the society such as the president at that time objected for the reason that she was “not a historian”. This moved her to take a history course at university after which she became president of the society in 2009.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h2">Photo Exhibition in 2010 : Contacting Point between Incomers and Campdonians</section>
        <paragraphe num="44">
            CADHAS held the photograph exhibition of “Old and New Campden” at the town hall for 2 days in January 2010. These photographs were taken from 1896 to 1938 by a photographer who lived in Campden during that time. They were important for the town history and they were exhibited parallel with the photographs of the present town. The sections for slide show and computer with photographs and music were also set.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="45">
            Before the exhibition, the president E held an informal slide show of CADHAS’s unidentified old photographs of the people and landscape of the town since the beginning of the 20th century. 15 Campdonians over 70s including E’s mother came to the meeting place. They told the names of the people and the time of landscape and festivals in the photographs each other, which showed the old Campdonian’s feeling to leave a record of the history of local people who are becoming the minority in the town. Most of them are not CADHAS member.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="46">
            450 people visited the photo exhibition in total. Among them, there were many non-members pointing at old photographs with nostalgia. Moreover, both old and new residents were talking by looking photographs and slides (See Figure 4.1, 4.2). Such scene could not have been seen in CADHAS activities so far. As it was very successful, CADHAS is planning to hold the similar exhibition again.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="47">
            Thus, activities of CADHAS have attracted the old residents of the community since 2000. It was the time when the local generation who had experienced to work and live outside the town came back to retire. They have broader views and similar feelings with the landscape as incomers, and so they can mix with incomers. Once the local people in their 60s joined the historical society, their parents’ generation also got involved the activities by using their knowledge of the past. They are now willing to hand down the local past by joining the incomers’ society.
        </paragraphe>
        <section niveau="h1">Conclusions</section>
        <paragraphe num="48">
            The imaginary world of “Old England” had social, cultural, political and economic impacts on a country town through attracting people from outside the town in the form of tourists and incomers. Tourists indirectly maintain the town as a living town by visiting and consuming the “Old England” in the town. There are local people who guide and welcome tourists by running the tourist information centre, organizing guided tours around the town and providing tourist facilities.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="49">
            Tourism can be effective to make people move to live in their tourist destinations. In fact, incomers are the most influential people in turning their imaginary world into reality. They are preserving historic houses and thatched cottages by actually living there. These houses characterize the landscape of the town. They control the landscape of the town by a conservation society and the town council. They also do voluntary work in the tourist information centre and guided tours as local wardens.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="50">
            Campdonians have been accepting incomers to come to live in the town, which makes the local community keep changing. The gaps between incomers and Campdonians such as the difference of classes, economic power, lifestyles and sense of value are unchangeable so that the conflicts between them potentially exist within the community. Campdonians have hardly joined the societies and trusts which incomers formed and occupy. However, around the year 2000, the generation, who had experience of outside the town and the country, came back to the town to retire. They can understand incomers’ viewpoints and communicate with them. They participated in incomers’ society and joined their activities to keep the imaginary world, but what they aim at is to leave the record of the local history of Campdonians, who are now becoming the minority in the town.
        </paragraphe>
        <paragraphe num="51">
            Unlike the major tendency of the anthropological studies of tourism, the people in the host community are not always “the weak” in this case study. They have incomers within the community who have similar viewpoints to tourists, which is strong pulling force to maintain the “Old England” landscape in the town. In comparison with incomers as outsiders, Campdonians are not always “the weak”, but can be equal to incomers by making use of their activities. They are not doing the conspicuous activities to maintain the “Old England”, but are quietly trying to strengthen the foundations of the “Old England” of their ancestors.
        </paragraphe>
    </corps>
    <bibliographie>
        <reference>Boissevain, J. (ed.), 1992, Rivitalizing European Rituals, London : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Boissevain, J., 1996, Coping with tourists : European Reactions to Mass Tourism, Oxford : Berghahn Books.</reference>
        <reference>British Tourist Authority and English Tourist Board (BTA/ETB), 1996, English Heritage Monitor, London.</reference>
        <reference>Countryside Commission, 1987, Policies for Enjoying the Countryside.</reference>
        <reference>Countryside Commission, 1991a, Visitors to the Countryside.</reference>
        <reference>Countryside Commission, 1991b, Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty : Policy Statement 1991.</reference>
        <reference>Countryside Commission, 1992, Enjoying the countryside : Policies for People.</reference>
        <reference>Fees C., 1996, “Tourism and the Politics of Authenticity in a North Cotswold Town.” In T. Selwyn (ed.), The Tourist Image : Myths and Myth Making in Tourism, Chichester : John Wiley and Sons, pp. 121-146.</reference>
        <reference>Hall D., Richards G. (eds.), 2003, Tourism and Sustainable Community Development, London : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>McDonald M., 1987, “Tourism : Chasing Culture and Tradition in Brittany.” In M. Bouquet and M. Winter (eds.), Who from Their Labours Rest ? : Conflict and Practice in Rural Tourism, Alershot : Avebury, pp. 120-134.</reference>
        <reference>Moscardo G. (ed), 2008, Building Community Capacity for Tourism Development, Wallingford : CABI.</reference>
        <reference>Pevsner N., 1956, The Englishness of English Art, London : The Architectural Press.</reference>
        <reference>Potts A., 1989, “Constable Country” between the Wars.” In R. Samuel (ed.), Patriotism : The Making and Unmaking of British National Identity, vol. III., National Fictions, London : Routledge, pp. 172-173.</reference>
        <reference>Shioji Y., 1997, Myths of the English countryside : An Interpretation of the Language and Images of Tourist Brochures, Language and Culture 8 : 183-200.</reference>
        <reference>Shioji Y., 2003, The Creating Englishness : Sensing boundaries and the Preservation of Cultural Heritage in the Cotswolds of England, Tokyo : Akashi Shoten.</reference>
        <reference>Singh S., Timothy D., Dowling R. (eds), 2003, Tourism in Destination Communities, Wallingford : CABI Publishing.</reference>
        <reference>Smith V. (ed), 1989, Hosts and Guests : The Anthropology of Tourism, Philadelphia : University of Pennsylvania Press.</reference>
        <reference>Urry J., 1990, The Tourist Gaze, London : Routledge.</reference>
        <reference>Wiener M., 1981, English Culture and the Decline of the Industrial Spirit 1850-1980, Harmondsworth : Penguin.</reference>
        <reference>Williams R., 1973, The Country and the City, London : Chatto and Windus.</reference>
        <reference>World Tourist Organization, 2009, Tourism and Community Development – Asian Practices, Madrid : World Tourism Organization.</reference>
        <reference>Yamashita S., 1999, Bali : What Can We Learn from the Anthropology of Tourism ? Tokyo : University of Tokyo Press</reference>
    </bibliographie>
    <notes>
        <note id="1">Fieldwork in Chipping Campden, a town of the Cotswolds, was conducted in several stages from 1996 to 2010. I carried out the participatory long-term fieldwork in 18 months from April 1996 to October 1997 and in 12 months from April 2009 to March 2010. In both periods, I was living in the town to research how the residents have hold balance between preserving heritage and developing tourism as well as how social groups of the town have worked and connected in the community. Between the two long-term fieldworks, from 1997 to 2009, I carried out short-term fieldworks in the same town almost every year. I wish to thank all the people in Chipping Campden who supported my research during these 15 years.</note>
        <note id="2">Some recent works relativise this point of view by discussing the possibilities of community-based tourism or community development as well as tourism, which needs a partnership with local community (Hall and Richards (eds.) 2003; Singh, Timothy and Dowling (eds.) 2003; Moscardo (ed.) 2008; World Tourism Organization 2009).</note>
    </notes>
</article>